<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1958">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1958</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:150</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Sprachpragmatische Aspekte der Negationsverarbeitung: Bestätigen und Zurückweisen mit negativen Sätzen</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Pragmatic aspects of negation comprehension: Confirming and rejecting with negative sentences</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lüdtke, Jana</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:150</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Arbeit beschäftigte sich mit der Kontextabhängigkeit der Verarbeitung negativer Sätze. Ausgangspunkt waren Annahmen der pragmatisch kommunikativ orientierten Ansätze der Negationsforschung, nach denen die Verwendung von Negation bestimmten Beschränkungen unterliegt. In der Regel werden negative Sätze benutzt, um Aussagen oder Annahmen von Kommunikationspartnern zurückzuweisen (Givón, 1978; Schmidt, 1973;Wason, 1965). Folglich können negative Sätze nur dann angemessen verwendet werden, wenn eine Annahme bzw. Erwartung besteht, die sie zurückweisen können. Aus diesen Verwendungsbeschränkungen ist die Hypothese abgeleitet worden, dass die Verarbeitung negativer Sätze vereinfacht ist, wenn sie entsprechend eben dieser Verwendungsbeschränkungen verwendet werden (Wason, 1965; Glenberg, Robertson, Jansen &amp; Johnson-Glenberg, 1999). Werden negative Sätze hingegen außerhalb eines legitimierenden Kontextes angewendet, sollten längere Verarbeitungszeiten auftreten. Diese exceptionality hypothesis (Wason, 1965) ist in mehreren experimentellen Arbeiten (Satzlesezeiten) untersucht worden (Glenberg et al, 1999; Lüdtke &amp; Kaup, 2006; Schindele Lüdtke, Kaup, 2008a, 2008b; Wason, 1965). Diese Arbeiten lieferten Evidenz dafür, dass negative Sätze dann leichter verarbeitet bzw. schneller gelesen werden können, wenn der vorangegangene Kontext eine Erwartung für das nahe legte, was durch den negativen Satz zurückgewiesen wurde. Demnach kann ein negativer Satz wie (1) dann relativ schnell gelesen werden, wenn der vorangegangene Kontext nahe legt, dass die Vase zerbrochen sein sollte. (1) Die Vase ist nicht zerbrochen. Diese Befunde aus der Negationsforschung wurden mit Ergebnissen von Lesezeitstudien aus der Inferenzforschung kontrastiert, die sich ebenfalls mit der Verarbeitung von Sätzen in Abhängigkeit von nahe gelegten Erwartungen beschäftigten. In diesen Lesezeitstudien wurde festgestellt, dass Inferenzen die Verarbeitung von nachfolgenden affirmativen Sätzen vereinfachen, sofern sich diese Sätze auf die nahe gelegten Informationen beziehen und diese bestätigen. Affirmative Sätze, die nahe gelegte Erwartungen zurückweisen, wurden hingegen vergleichsweise langsam gelesen (vgl. Calvo &amp; Castillo, 1998; Campion, 2004; Duffy, 1986; Klin, Guzán &amp; Levine, 1999; Linderholm, 2002; Peracchi &amp; O'Brien, 2004). Diese Befunde wurden unter anderem auf Basis des Verarbeitungsaufwandes erklärt, der notwendig ist, um den Satz in den vorangegangenen Kontext zu integrieren. Weißt ein Satz eine nahe gelegte Erwartung zurück, ist ein hoher Integrationsaufwand notwendig, bestätigt ein Satz hingegen eine Erwartung, ist der Integrationsaufwand geringer (Duffy, 1989; Calvo &amp; Castillo, 1998). Aus der Verknüpfung der Negationsforschung und der Inferenzforschung wurden unterschiedliche Annahmen in Bezug auf die Verarbeitung negativer Sätze abgeleitet, z.B. dass die Verarbeitung negativ zurückweisender Sätze ähnlich wie die Verarbeitung affirmativ bestätigender Sätze von einer nahe gelegten Erwartung profitieren sollten. Diese Vorhersage wurde auf die Unterschiede in der Verarbeitung affirmativer und negativer Sätze zurückgeführt. Die Rolle der unterschiedlichen kommunikativen Funktion des Bestätigens und Zurückweisens wurde ebenfalls experimentell untersucht. Es wird über vier Experimente berichtet, in denen die Lesezeiten negativer Sätze im Rahmen von prädiktiven Inferenzen und in Bezug auf die kommunikativen Funktionen des Bestätigens und Zurückweisens untersucht wurden. Zusammengenommen bestätigen die Ergebnisse der vier Experimente die Annahmen der kommunikativ orientierte Ansätze der Negationsforschung, nach denen negative Sätze dann angewandt und relativ leicht verarbeitet werden können, wenn der vorangegangen Kontext eine Erwartung für das nahe legt, was durch den negativen Satz zurückgewiesen wird. Zusätzlich zeigen die Ergebnisse der Experimente aber auch, dass die Lesezeiten negativer Sätze von einem zweiten Faktor beeinflusst werden, der bisher in der Negationsforschung nur wenig berücksichtigt wurde. So legten die Ergebnisse der Experimente nahe, dass die Verarbeitung negativer Sätze nicht in jedem Falle erleichtert ist, wenn eine Erwartung für das besteht, was durch den Satz negiert wurde. Die Lesezeiten negativer Sätze scheinen ähnlich wie die Lesezeiten affirmativer Sätze auch von dem Aufwand für Integration der Satzaussage in den vorangegangenen Kontext abhängig zu sein. In Bezug auf einen negativen Satz wie (1) bedeutet das, dass dieser nur dann relativ schnell gelesen werden kann, wenn sich die aus diesem Satz ableitbare Annahme einer heilen Vase leicht in den vorangegangenen Kontext integrieren lässt. Ist dies nicht der Fall, kann es trotz einer im Sinne der pragmatisch kommunikativ orientierten Ansätze angemessenen Verwendung zu relativ langen Lesezeiten kommen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This thesis investigates how the processing of a negative sentence is influenced by its context. According to the assumptions of pragmatic communicative-orientated approaches to negation, the natural use of negation is subject to specific limitations. Given that negation is typically used to reject an assumption or statement of a discourse partner (Givón, 1978; Schmidt, 1973; Wason, 1965), the appropriate use of negative sentences implies a contextual expectation that they reject. Accordingly, the processing of negative sentences should be facilitated if they are used according to these limitations (Glenberg, Robertson, Jansen &amp; Johnson-Glenberg, 1999; Wason, 1965). On the other hand, the use of negative sentence outside an appropriate context should lead to longer comprehension times. These assumptions (the exceptionality hypothesis; Wason, 1965) were tested in several empirical studies (e.g., by measuring sentence reading times). The studies proved that the comprehension of negative sentences is easier when the preceding context establishes an expectation regarding to the state of affairs that is being negated (Glenberg et al, 1999; Lüdtke &amp; Kaup, 2006; Schindele, Lüdtke, &amp; Kaup, 2008a, 2008b; Wason, 1965). Thus, the reading time of a negative sentence like (1) should be relatively short when the preceding context contains an expectation of a broken vase. (1) The vase is not broken. These findings seem to differ from results reported in the field of inference research. This domain also analysed the dependence of sentence comprehension on expectations established by the preceding context. In the inference studies, elaborative inferences seemed to facilitate the comprehension of affirmative sentences if the inferred state of affairs and the affirmative sentences followed each other quite consecutively. However, if an affirmative sentence rejected the expectation, relatively long reading times were observed (cf. Calvo &amp; Castillo, 1998; Campion, 2004; Duffy, 1986; Klin, Guzán, &amp; Levine, 1999; Linderholm, 2002; Peracchi &amp; O'Brien, 2004). These results were explained by the comprehension costs necessary for integration of the meaning of the sentence in the mental representation of the preceding context. For a sentence that rejects the expectation, the integration into the preceding context will be difficult, resulting in high integration costs. Sentences that confirm an expectation, on the other hand, can be integrated easily into the preceding context, resulting in low integration costs (Duffy, 1989; Calvo &amp; Castillo, 1998). The present thesis combines the approaches of negation and inference research to make further predictions about the comprehension of negative sentences. It is assumed that the comprehension of rejecting negative sentences should be facilitated by previous expectations just as the comprehension of confirming affirmative sentences is. This was expected due to hypothesized differences in comprehension processes for affirmative and negative sentences. Additionally, differences between the communicative functions of confirmation and rejection were expected and also analysed. Four reading-time experiments compared the reading times of negative sentences with the reading times of affirmative sentences. Whether and to what extent the preceding context elicited predictive inferences (Experiments 1 and 2) or other elaborative inferences (Experiments 3 and 4) was manipulated. Furthermore, the critical affirmative and negative sentences could either confirm or reject the inferences. The results of the experiments support the pragmatic communicative-orientated approaches of negation research. They are in line with the assumption that the comprehension of negative sentences will be easier in a context that elicits an expectation of the state of affairs that is negated. In addition, the results showed that the reading times of negative sentences are influenced by a second factor, namely the costs for integration of sentence meaning into the mental representation of the preceding context. Therefore, expectations regarding the state of affairs that is negated did not always lead to shorter reading times. A negative sentence like (1) is only read relatively fast, when the implied sentence meaning of an unbroken and therefore intact vase is easily integrated in the mental representation of the preceding context. If this is not the case, reading times of negative sentences will be relatively long, despite an appropriate usage in terms of the pragmatic communicative-orientated approach.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-10-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1958</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20532</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20532</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1958/luedtke_jana.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
