<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2870">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2870</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:150</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Trainings in Mensch-Maschine-Systemen. Strategien zur Unterstützung des Erwerbs mentaler Kausalmodelle</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Trainings in human factors. Strategies supporting the development of causal models</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Klostermann, Anne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:150</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Durch die technische Weiterentwicklung von Arbeitssystemen entsteht ein Bedarf an neuen Trainings- und Ausbildungskonzepten, in deren Fokus die Qualifizierung für die veränderten Aufgaben stehen sollte, die mit einer zunehmenden Automatisierung einhergehen. Neben traditionellen Lehr- und Lernmethoden bieten neue Ansätze, wie computerbasierte Trainingsmethoden, eine zusätzliche Möglichkeit, spezifische Wissensinhalte zu trainieren. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurden Möglichkeiten zur Gestaltung von computerbasierten Trainingsstrategien für Aufgaben in komplexen Mensch-Maschine-Systemen entwickelt und einer empirischen Überprüfung unterzogen. Der theoretische Beitrag der Arbeit zur Erfor-schung der Mensch-Technik-Interaktion liegt in der Formulierung eines Rahmenmodells zum Erwerb mentaler Kausalmodelle, in dem verschiedene Ansätze zu mentalen Modelltheorien integriert und auf den Kontext des Wissenserwerbs in komplexen Mensch-Maschine-System übertragen werden. Auf der Grundlage des Rahmenmodells wurde ein Trainingskonzept für komplexe Systeme entwickelt. Der empirische Beitrag der Arbeit liegt im experimentellen Nachweis der Potenziale des Rahmenmodells als Grundlage für die Untersuchung von Trainingsstrategien. In der Praxis kann das entwickelte Rahmenmodell als Grundlage für die Gestaltung von Trainings eingesetzt werden und für jede Ebene des Wissenserwerbspro-zesses Ansatzpunkte zur Gestaltung von Trainingseinheiten liefern. Gerade in frühen Phasen der Entwicklung oder Umgestaltung von Anlagenkomponenten und Automationskonzepten trägt ein Vorgehen in enger Orientierung an dem Rahmenmodell und dem Trainingskonzept dazu bei, die relevanten Informationen, die es zu vermitteln gilt, zu bestimmen und zu struk-turieren und es dem Operateur zu ermöglichen, ein gutes mentales Kausalmodell über das zu bedienende System zu erwerben. In Anlehnung an das Trainingskonzept ließen sich bei-spielsweise die Trainingsinhalte dahingehend strukturieren, welche Wissensinhalte am besten durch eine Visualisierung der Ursache-Wirkungs-Beziehungen dargestellt werden können, für welche Aufgaben sich Phasen der Interaktion eignen oder für welche Wissensinhalte eine Anleitung von Envisioning-Prozessen sinnvoll ist. Insgesamt liefern die Erkenntnisse der vorliegenden Arbeit einen wichtigen Ansatzpunkt zur Beschreibung der Wissensanforderungen und Trainingsinhalte für die neuen Aufgaben und damit einen praktischen Ausgangspunkt für die prospektive Gestaltung von computerbasierten Trainingskonzepten für die Ausbildung von Operateuren in komplexen Mensch-Maschine-Systemen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The present work deals with the theoretical development of assumptions concerning the acquisition of mental causal models of complex systems and the empirical testing of computer-based training strategies for the enhancement of mental causal model acquisition. Complex technical systems have a high degree of automation, and integration of system components; they are highly dynamic and non-transparent. This implies high requirements for the cognitive performance of the operators working in these systems. Accordingly, operator trainings and development play an important role, and a wide variety of training approaches exist in practice. Beside traditional operator trainings, computerbased trainings are applied increasingly. They are especially useful for the training of specific knowledge contents, e.g. knowledge about cause-and effect relations of subprocesses. When developing training systems, a first requirement is that insights about human knowledge acquisition and information processing should be considered, in order to guarantee an optimal qualification of operators for the cognitively varying tasks. As a second requirement, the didactic format of the training material should rely on theories of multimodal learning. The aim of the present work is to provide a contribution to these requirements. Based on theories of causal knowledge acquisition, a framework for mental causal model acquisition of complex technical systems was developed. This framework forms the basis for the examination of relevant multimedia design principles. In close dependence on the framework, didactic strategies for computer-based knowledge transfer and multimedia psychology principles are presented and discussed. These strategies and the framework provide the basis for the deduction of a training concept for the enhancement of causal mental model acquisition. In three empirical studies different training strategies have been developed and tested. The focus was on the effects of the training strategies on the performance in system interaction and in knowledge tests, both forming indicators for the quality of the mental causal model. The simulation of a technical system served as experimental platform. The first empirical study investigated holistic, gradual and text-based training strategies, combined with a varying degree of learner participation. The results concerning system knowledge show a slight advantage of the holistic and gradual trainings over the text-based training, although there could be shown no differences concerning the cause-and-effect knowledge and the system performance. In the second empirical study, the presentation of the gradual training strategy was optimised and compared to a text-based training. As a second factor, the system interaction was varied. Results show that a combination of gradual visualisation and system interaction has a positive influence on both knowledge acquisition and performance in system interaction. The third empirical study aimed at investigating the influence of guided mental simulation (envisioning) compared to unguided system interaction. Results show that guided mental simulation is beneficial for the causal knowledge acquisition, yet there is no provided evidence for advantages for the performance in system interaction. The results of this thesis can be recapitulated regarding three aspects. The first one concerns the theoretical contribution. In the theoretical part of the thesis, various mental model theories have been integrated into a framework for mental causal model acquisition. This framework serves as the basis for the development of a training concept. The second aspect concerns the experimental examination of training strategies referring to the framework, in the course of which the potentials of the framework and the training concept could be demonstrated. The third aspect relates to both the practical and the epistemological contribution. The framework can be seen as the basis for a holistic training concept, since it offers starting points for the design of training units for every level of the knowledge acquisition process. This procedure was demonstrated exemplary for parts of the training concept; an examination of the further components of the training concept thus seems very promising.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2870</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30278</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30278</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2870/klostermann_anne.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
