<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:34Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3750">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3750</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Kommunikation und Handeln lokaler Akteure des Wohnungsmarktes nach der Komplettveräußerung kommunaler Wohnungsbestände</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Communication and actions of local actors on the housing market following complete disposal of municipal housing stocks</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kaufmann, Kristin Klaudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Spätestens seit Ende der 1990er Jahre erreichten Liberalisierungsbestrebungen und kommunale Entschuldungsüberlegungen auch die kommunale Wohnungswirtschaft. Um ihre Handlungsfähigkeit abzusichern, Schulden zu senken und Haushalte zu sanieren, wurden deshalb durch kommunale Anteilseigner teilweise komplette Wohnungsunternehmen an institutionelle Investoren veräußert. In Zeiten der Marktentspannung schien das teils mit hohem Modernisierungs- und Umbaubedarf versehene Wohneigentum, die Chance auf einen kommunalen Schuldenabbau sowie auf professionellere wohnungswirtschaftliche Strategien für den kommunalen Wohnungsmarkt zu eröffnen. Die mit dem Verkauf an "neue Investoren" verbundenen Risiken stellten sich beim Erstverkauf als gering dar. Eine kommunale Einflussnahme auf Stadt- und Quartiersentwicklung sowie soziale Wohnraumversorgung sicherten teils zeitlich begrenzt Verträge ab. Spätestens mit dem Zweitverkauf des einst kommunalen Wohnungsunternehmens wurde klar, dass sich wohnungswirtschaftliche Schwerpunktsetzungen durch die stark renditeorientierten Erwerber wandelten. Kommunen sahen sich nun einer wachsenden und in ihren Verwertungsinteressen zunehmend differenzierten Akteurvielfalt gegenüber. Die Dissertation erforscht deshalb das Handeln und die Kommunikation zwischen wohnungswirtschaftlichen Akteuren und der Kommune nach dem Komplettverkauf kommunalen Wohneigentums. Am Beispiel der Städte Kiel, Osnabrück und Wilhelmshaven werden mögliche Auswirkungen des Markteintritts internationaler strategischer und Finanzinvestoren auf Prozesse der Stadtentwicklung, des Wohnungsmarktes sowie auf lokale Kooperationsprozesse untersucht. Diese Aspekte wurden bisher in der raumwissenschaftlichen Forschung nur in Ansätzen betrachtet. Diese Forschungslücke soll mit der vorliegenden Arbeit geschlossen werden. Mit Hilfe von handlungs- und governancetheoretischen Ansätzen der Wohnungsmarkt- und Stadtforschung werden auf der Basis von Experteninterviews, qualitativer Inhaltsanalyse, Dokumentenanalysen und sekundärstatistischen Auswertungen Veränderungen zwischen 1999 und 2009 systematisch analysiert und interpretiert. Im Rahmen eines systematischen Vergleichs werden einerseits der Einsatz kommunaler Instrumente zum Erreichen von stadtentwicklungs- und wohnungspolitischen Zielsetzungen, andererseits neue kommunale Handlungserfordernisse und Handlungsansätze sowie Verhandlungspositionen im Zusammenhang mit dem Markteintritt neuer Investoren untersucht. Ziel ist es, die Auswirkungen des Markteintritts ‚"neuer Akteure" auf Prozesse der Stadtentwicklung, des Wohnungsmarktes sowie für die Absicherung kommunaler Kernaufgaben herauszuarbeiten. Es zeigt sich, dass nicht zu allererst der Markteintritt "neuer Investoren", sondern die Auswirkungen des Strukturwandels das strategische – kollektive wie kompetitive – Agieren der Akteure intensiv beeinflusst haben. In allen Kommunen wurde das Entschuldungsziel verfehlt. Die Abhängigkeit der Kommune vom Kooperationswillen privatwirtschaftlicher Akteure steigt. Ein kommunales Durchsetzen integrativer Ansätze der Stadtentwicklung sowie wohnungspolitische Gestaltungsansätze auf Bestandswohnungsmärkten werden schwieriger. Eine unmittelbare Neuorientierung des kommunalen sowie des wohnungswirtschaftlichen Handelns durch den Markteintritt "neuer Investoren" war jedoch nicht nachweisbar. Die langfristigen Folgen der einzelnen Verkaufsentscheidungen deuten sich bereits heute in den untersuchten Städten an. Dies betrifft die Wohnsituationen und Wohnraumversorgung einkommensschwächerer Haushalte genauso wie Belange einer nachhaltigen Stadt- und Quartiersentwicklung. Dabei ist es zweitrangig, ob sich Entwicklungsprozesse auf schrumpfenden, stagnierenden oder wachsenden Märkten ereignen. Das jahrzehntelang unausgesprochene lokale Bestandsinteresse wohnungswirtschaftlicher Akteure mit tendenziell langfristiger Verantwortungsbindung ist professionellen Verwertungsinteressen gewichen. Kommunale Interventionsstrategien sind für diese, teils massiv auftretenden, neuen Situationen und Konflikte nicht vorhanden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Communication and actions of local actors on the housing market following complete disposal of municipal housing stocks Since the end of the 1990s at the latest, efforts at liberalisation and municipal debt reduction considerations also began to affect the housing market. As a consequence, in order to secure their freedom of action, reduce debt and balance budgets municipal shareholders in some cases sold entire housing companies to institutional investors. In times of easing of the market the housing stock, some of which required significant modernisation and conversion investment, appeared to offer an opportunity for municipal debt reduction and more professional housing strategies for the municipal housing market. The risks associated with sale to "new investors" appeared slight for the initial sale. Municipal influence on the development of urban districts and the supply of social housing was secured via contracts, some of which were for limited periods. At the latest with the second disposal of the formerly municipal housing company it became evident that the focal points of housing considerations were shifting as a consequence of the strongly profit-oriented purchasers. Municipalities now saw themselves faced with a growing range of actors, differentiating increasingly with regard to their financial interests. The dissertation subsequently investigates the actions and communication between housing industry actors and the municipalities following the complete sale of municipal housing stock. Using the example of the cities of Kiel, Osnabrück and Wilhelmshaven possible effects of the market entry of international strategic and financial investors on processes of urban development, the housing market and local co-operation processes are investigated. These aspects have only been partially considered thus far in the field of spatial research. This dissertation aims to close this research gap. With the aid of action and governance theory approaches of housing market and urban research the changes that occurred between 1999 and 2009 are systematically analysed and interpreted on the basis of interviews with experts, qualitative analysis of content, document analysis and the evaluation of secondary statistics. In the scope of a systematic comparison on the one side the use of municipal instruments to achieve urban development and housing policy objectives was investigated, on the other new municipal action requirements and approaches, together with negotiating positions in relation to the market entry of new investors. The objective is to determine the effects of the market entry of 'new actors' on urban development processes, the housing market and the securing of core municipal tasks. It is apparent that it is not primarily the market entry of "new investors" that has had the most intensive influence on the strategic - collective and competitive - actions of the actors, but the effects of structural transition. The goal of debt clearance failed to be met in all of the municipalities. The dependence of the municipalities upon the willingness of private sector actors to co-operate is increasing. The municipal implementation of integrative approaches to urban development and housing policy angles on existing housing markets is becoming increasingly difficult. A direct realignment of the municipal and housing policy activity as a result of the market entry of "new investors" was not discernible, however. The long-term consequences of the individual sale decisions are already becoming evident in the cities investigated. This concerns the housing situation and supply of housing to lower-income households as well as issues such as the sustainable development of cities and districts. In this it is of secondary importance whether the development processes occur in shrinking, stagnating or growing markets. The unspoken, decades-long interest of housing policy actors in local stock with longer-term responsibility has given way to professional asset maximisation interests. Municipal intervention strategies do not exist for these new situations and conflicts, some of which are highly significant in their extent.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-06-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3750</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-39832</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-39832</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3750/kaufmann_kristin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
