<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2502">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2502</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ablaufplanung von Entsorgungsstrategien zur Steigerung der ökologischen Sinnhaftigkeit</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Sequence planning of disposal strategies for increasing the ecological meaningfulness</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lee, Jae Moon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die produktabhängige Gestaltung und die integrierte Bewertung von Entsorgungsstrategien sind die beiden grundlegenden Aspekte der für komplexe Produkte entwickelten Methodik für die Ablaufplanung von Entsorgungsstrategien zur Steigerung der ökologischen Sinnhaftigkeit. Als Resultat der entwickelten Methodik werden im ersten Schritte die technisch möglichen Entsorgungsstrategien produktabhängig gestaltet. Im zweiten Schritt wird durch die Bewertung ausgewählter Umweltwirkungen aus den technisch möglichen Optionen die ökologisch sinnvollste ermittelt. Die produktabhängige Gestaltung der technisch möglichen Entsorgungsstrategien erfolgt auf Basis der Modellierung der Produktcharakteristik. Für die systematische Darstellung sämtlicher Produktparameter sowie die Bestimmungskriterien werden die Blockdiagramme konzipiert. Die resultierenden produktabhängig gestalteten Entsorgungsstrategien werden anschließend bezüglich des Potentials zur Steigerung der ökologischen Sinnhaftigkeit bewertet. Die für diese Arbeit spezifizierten Bilanzkennzahlen umfassen dabei vier ausgewählte Wirkungskategorien: Ressourcenverbrauch, Treibhauseffekt, Humantoxizität und Ökotoxizität. Für die Beurteilung der ökologischen Sinnhaftigkeit wurde der Sinnhaftigkeitsfaktor (SF) eingeführt. Er wurde als Verhältnis der ökologischen Aufwendungen und der ökologischen Einsparungen der Entsorgungsstrategien definiert. Durch die Gegenüberstellung der Sinnhaftigkeitsfaktoren können ökologisch vorteilhafte Entsorgungsstrategien für komplexe Produkte ermittelt werden. Die Anwendbarkeit der entwickelten Methodik wird anhand repräsentativer Beispielprodukte, „Smart junction box“ und Zentralsteuergerät für die Anwendung in Automobilen nachgewiesen. Durch die Modellierung der Produktcharakteristik wurden Behandlungsziele für die untersuchten Produkte bestimmt und die dafür erforderlichen Behandlungsprozesse identifiziert. Dabei reduziert sich der Untersuchungsaufwand zur Gestaltung durch die Aufteilung der Modellierungsebenen – Produkt- und Produktteilebene erheblich, weil statt der Untersuchung aller Produktteile eine Fokussierung auf die identifizierten Zielteile erfolgt, für die als Behandlungsziele gezielt Behandlungsprozesse erforderlich sind. Bei der „Smart junction box“ wurden vier technisch mögliche Entsorgungsstrategien identifiziert. Bei der Beurteilung der ökologischen Sinnhaftigkeit wurde dann die Entsorgungsstrategie mit der Demontage und Aufbereitung der Leiterplatten (Strategie 3) als ökologisch sinnvollste bestimmt (SF im Bereich von 0,12 bis 0,35).</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The product-related constitution and integrated assessment of disposal strategies for complex products are the two fundamental aspects of the methodology developed for complex products concerning sequence planning for increasing the ecological meaningfulness. As a result of the developed methodology are determined technically possible disposal strategies in the first steps. In the second step is determined the ecologically meaningful disposal strategy of the technically possible options by the assessment of selected environmental effects. The product-related constitution of technically possible disposal strategies is based on the modeling of product characteristics. For the representation of all the product parameters and the determination criteria were drawn the block diagrams. The resulting product-related disposal strategies are then analyzed regarding the potential for increasing the ecological meaningfulness. For this purpose, the balance indicators specified for this thesis assess four selected impact categories: Resource Depletion Potential, Global Warming Potential, Human Toxicity Potential, and Eco Toxicity Potential. For the evaluation of the ecological meaningfulness was used the meaningfulness factor (Sinnhaftigkeitsfaktor; SF). It was defined as the ratio of environmental expenditure and environmental savings of disposal strategies. By comparison in the meaningfulness factor can ecologically meaningful disposal strategies for complex products are identified. The applicability of the developed methodology is demonstrated on a representative sample products, smart junction box and central control unit for use in automobiles. By modeling the product characteristics were identified treatment goals for the investigated product determined and for them required treatment processes. Thereby is the effort of the investigation reduced considerably by division of modeling levels, because instead of investigation all parts of the product occurs a focus on the identified target parts, for which as goals of treatment are treatment processes required. In case of the "smart junction box" have been identified four technically possible management strategies. In assessing the ecological meaningfulness was then the disposal strategy with disassembly and treatment of the printed circuit board (strategy 3) as the ecologically meaningful disposal strategy determined (SF in the range of 0.12 to 0.35).</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-04-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2502</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25879</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25879</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2502/lee_jaemoon.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
