<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:12Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2578">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2578</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Verfahren für die Systembewertung und Ableitung der Optimierungspotenziale für Entsorgungssysteme am Beispiel eines polnischen Zweckverbandes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Special assessment methodology and derivation of optimization potentials for waste disposal systems on the example of a Polish Association of Local Authorities</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kapsa, Karolina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die abfallwirtschaftliche Situation in Polen ist nach dem EU-Beitritt im Jahr 2004 von mehreren Faktoren geprägt. Durch die notwendige Systemumstellung von kommunalen Entsorgungssystemen, durch Mitfinanzierungsmöglichkeiten abfallwirtschaftlicher Anlagen über EU-Fördermittel, sowie durch von der EU auferlegte Beitrittsverpflichtungen sind polnische Kommunen gezwungen, die kommunale Abfallwirtschaft nach europäischen Standards in Bezug auf quantitative und qualitative Zielvorgaben zu reformieren. Damit stellt sich auch die Frage, wie die Entsorgungssysteme unter dem Gesichtspunkt der Nachhaltigkeit langfristig optimiert werden können. Das Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, ein Bewertung- und Entscheidungsunterstützungsinstrument für die Bewertung von Entsorgungssystemen von Haushaltsabfällen für kommunale Entscheidungsträger zu schaffen. Dafür werden Bewertungsmethoden ausgewählt und in einem Bewertungsverfahren zusammengeführt. Die Kommunen können darauf aufbauend Optimierungspotenziale für ihre Abfallwirtschaftssysteme ableiten. Die entwickelte Methodik des Bewertungsverfahrens wird am Beispiel des kommunalen Zweckverbandes Dolina in Polen dargelegt. Hierzu wurden umfangreiche theoretische Abhandlungen zu Bewertung und Bewertungsmethoden mit den - aus Feldrecherchen gewonnenen - spezifischen Anforderungen und Wünschen aus der Praxis in Beziehung gesetzt. Um ein beispielhaftes Entsorgungssystem zu bewerten, wird ein Modell erstellt, das die Entsorgungsteilnehmer und Entsorgungsprozesse abbildet, sowie die Darstellung von Entsorgungsalternativen erlaubt. Als Entsorgungsteilnehmer werden die Kommune, Haushalte, Sammelunternehmen, sowie Betreiber der Abfallbehandlungsanlagen identifiziert. Die berücksichtigten Entsorgungsprozesse umfassen die Schritte von der Abfallentstehung bis hin zur -verwertung bzw. -beseitigung. Die Entsorgungsalternativen stellen quantitative Entwicklungsszenarien der kommunalen Abfallwirtschaft im Entsorgungssystem dar. Das erstellte Bewertungsverfahren umfasst die Bereiche Ökonomie, Ökologie und Soziales (als den drei Säulen der Nachhaltigkeit), sowie den Bereich der Technik. Für die Ermittlung der Ergebnisse innerhalb dieser Bereiche werden drei maßgebliche Bewertungsmethoden eingesetzt: die Kosten-Nutzen-Analyse, die Ökobilanzmethode und die Nutzwertanalyse. Im ökonomischen Bereich wird die Wirtschaftlichkeit kommunaler Abfallwirtschaft mittels der Kosten-Nutzen-Analyse dargestellt. Die Wirtschaftlichkeit wird durch die Gegenüberstellung von Einnahmen und Systemkosten unter Vorbehalt von volkswirtschaftlichen Aspekten quantitativ ermittelt. Im Bereich Ökologie werden potenzielle Umweltwirkungen der Entsorgungsalternativen mithilfe der Ökobilanzmethode quantitativ erzielt. Als die in Verbindung mit Entsorgungssystemen besonders relevanten Umweltwirkungen werden Klimawirksamkeit, Toxizität und Ressourcenverbrauch ausgewählt und gemessen. In Bezug auf die sozialen Aspekte werden Akzeptanz und Einstellung der Bevölkerung untersucht. Bei den technischen Aspekten werden anlagenbezogene und für die Abfallsammlung spezifische Rahmenbedingungen erfasst. Für die Analyse und Messung dieser Aspekte wurden Fragebögen für Entsorgungsteilnehmer entwickelt und an diese Entsorgungsteilnehmer verteilt. Die Berechnung der Ergebnisse erfolgte mithilfe der Nutzwertanalyse. Für eine umfassende Bewertung der betrachteten Entsorgungsalternativen werden die mit den drei angewandten Bewertungsmethoden erhaltenen Ergebnisse zu einem Gesamtergebnis mit der sog. multikriteriellen Entscheidungsanalyse - Promethee Methode I und II - zusammengeführt. Weiterhin wird ein Ansatz zur Beschreibung der Optimierungspotenziale im Bereich der kommunalen Abfallwirtschaft entwickelt. Dieser Ansatz umfasst die Auswertung der Fragebögen, den Vergleich des Ist-Zustands mit dem Soll-Zustand, beschrieben durch quantitative und qualitative Abfallwirtschaftsziele der EU, sowie die Analyse der Ergebnisse von Sensitivitätsanalysen. Im betrachteten kommunalen Zweckverband Dolina werden neben dem Ausgangsszenario (Deponierung) zusätzlich drei andere Entsorgungsszenarien (getrennte Sammlung von Wertstoffen und Bioabfall und: Deponierung, MBA und MVA) modelliert. Innerhalb der durchgeführten Bewertungsmethoden ergibt sich als günstigstes Szenario die Entsorgungsalternative mit einer Müllverbrennungsanlage. Außerdem bieten das hier vorgestellte Bewertungsverfahren und die damit gewonnenen Erkenntnisse Möglichkeiten zur Verbesserung des Umweltbewusstseins, zur Erhöhung gesellschaftlicher Akzeptanz spezieller Entsorgungsalternativen, sowie Anreize zur Förderung einer konsequenten Einführung von getrennter Sammlung. Eine Realisierung von Entsorgungsinvestitionen, die durch EU-Gelder unterstützt wird, wird nicht nur eine Chance zur Verbesserung des Umweltzustands bieten, sondern auch die Entsorgungssicherheit erhalten und die Ziele der Abfallwirtschaft langfristig erfüllen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Following accession to the EU in 2004, the situation of waste management in Poland has been marked by several factors. The necessity to change the system of municipal waste management systems along with the possibility of co-financing waste management facilities with EU funds, as well as the obligations imposed by accession to the EU has forced Polish municipalities to reform their management of waste disposal so that it complies with European standards with regard to qualitative and quantitative targets. With this question also arises as to how waste management systems can be optimised in the long term with regard to sustainability. The aim of this study is to develop an instrument for municipal decision makers with which they can assess household waste management systems and which will facilitate decision making. Assessment methods will be selected and merged into a single assessment. Based on these results, the municipalities will be able to derive optimisation potentials for their waste management systems. The methodology of the evaluation process is explained using the example of an Association of Local Authorities in Dolina, Poland. For the purpose of the study extensive theoretical papers on assessment and methods of assessment have been set in relationship to the specific requirements and needs which have been identified in the field study. To evaluate an exemplary waste management system model depicting the management, disposal processes and participants, has been created. Furthermore, four disposal alternatives have been displayed. Municipalities, households, waste collectors and operators of waste treatment plants have been identified as participants. The waste management processes to be considered encompass the steps from the generation of waste up to recycling or disposal. Disposal alternatives are quantitative development scenarios of municipal waste management system. The assessment process covers the areas of: economy, ecology and social aspects (representing the three pillars of sustainability). Technical aspects are also examined. To determine results in these areas three decisive assessment methods have been applied: cost benefit analysis, life cycle assessment and worth value analysis. In the economic area, the cost of municipal waste is presented by means of cost benefit analysis. The economic viability is quantitatively determined by comparing revenues with the cost of the systems subject to other economic factors such as the negative impact of waste disposal plants. In the area of ecology potential effects on the environment of disposal alternatives are quantitatively obtained by using the LCA method. Those impacts on the environment which are particularly relevant in connection with waste disposal facilities have been measured: climate impact, toxicity and resource consumption. Regarding the social aspects acceptance and attitude of the population have been examined. Regarding the technical aspects the conditions related to waste disposal plants and the collection of waste have been recorded. For the analysis and measurement of these aspects questionnaires were developed and distributed to participants in the waste disposal process. The calculation of the results was achieved with the aid of a utility analysis. For a comprehensive evaluation of the waste disposal alternatives under consideration, the three assessment methods which were applied were combined in one overall result. To achieve this a method, the multi-criteria decision analysis, Promethee I and II were applied. Furthermore, an approach to describe the optimization potential in the field of municipal waste management has been developed. This approach includes the evaluation of the questionnaires, the comparison of the actual situation with the desired state as described by EU objectives, quantitative and qualitative, for waste management and the analysis of the results of the sensitivity analyses. In the municipality of Dolina under consideration, in addition to the baseline scenario (waste disposal: landfill) three other disposal scenarios are modelled: separate collection of bio waste and recyclables, MBT and landfill. Within the evaluation carried out, the scenario with a waste incinerator has proved to be the most advantageous. Moreover, the assessment system described in this thesis, along with the insights gained, present ways of raising environmental awareness and social acceptance of certain waste disposal alternatives, as well as incentives for promoting the introduction of separate waste collection. Investment in waste disposal made possible by EU funds represents not only a chance to improve the environmental status but also an opportunity to maintain waste disposal safety and to fulfil the objectives of waste management in the long term.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-07-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2578</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27056</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27056</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-89720-558-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2578/kapsa_karolina.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2578/kapsa_karolina_Titelseite.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
