<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:49Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2072">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2072</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">New Insights into the Oxidative Dehydrogenation of Propane and Ethane on SupportedVanadium Oxide Catalysts</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Neue Einblicke in die Oxidative Dehydrierung von Propan und Ethan an getr√§gerten Vanadiumoxid Katalysatoren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dinse, Arne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The oxidative dehydrogenation of propane (ODP) and ethane (ODE) was investigated using different supported vanadium oxide catalysts in order to get a better insight into the reaction mechanism. Initial results revealed a strong influence of the support material (CeO2, TiO2, Al2O3, ZrO2 and SiO2) on selectivities, activation energies and turn over frequencies of ODP. Because of their different catalytic behaviour, TiO2, Ô?ß-Al2O3 and SiO2 (SBA-15) supported catalysts were subject to a subsequent study by High-Frequency Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (HF-EPR) in order to determine the paramagnetic V4+ and V3+ states, before and after being exposed to ODP reaction conditions. While the SBA-15 support exhibits reduced vanadium sites as the only electron sink during the catalytic reaction, Al2O3 apparently localizes further electron density as oxoradicals in the support surface. If TiO2 is used as a support, Ti3+ as well as surface trapped O2(-) species are generated, indicating a more complex involvement of the support material in the reaction. The increase in catalytic activity in the order of SBA-15 &lt; Al2O3 &lt; TiO2 was attributed to different reduction mechanisms depending on the support material. No V3+ was detected in any of the samples, indicating that such centres are either short lived or non-existent during ODP. Because the SBA-15 supported catalyst showed no influence of the support material on the catalytic reaction it was used for a kinetic study of ODP in a fixed bed reactor. Because of fast reoxidation processes it could be shown that the applied microkinetic model simplifies to a first order rate law. In this study kinetic parameters are provided and it is indicated that the weaker allylic C-H bond of propene is involved in the rate determining step of the consecutive propene combustion. Finally, Al2O3 supported vanadium oxide was investigated to understand the effects of lattice oxygen and vanadium oxidation state on the product selectivity. Both fully oxidized catalysts, and samples partially reduced by H2 were exposed to ODE without the presence of gas phase oxygen. The ethene selectivity increases upon pre-reduction in H2, which could be explained by a lower ratio of V4+ to V3+ cations attained as compared to a pre-reduction in C2H6. As a consequence, the lower Lewis acidity of the catalyst inhibits the adsorption of the nucleophilic ethylene double bond and therefore its consecutive combustion.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Arbeit gew√§hrt einen tiefer gehenden Einblick in die oxidative Dehydrierung von Propan (ODP) und Ethan (ODE) an unterschiedlich getr√§gerten Vanadiumoxid-Katalysatoren. Zun√§chst wurde ein starker Einfluss des Tr√§germaterials (CeO2, TiO2, Al2O3, ZrO2 and SiO2) auf Selektivit√§t, Aktivierungsenergie und Aktivit√§t der ODP festgestellt. Aufgrund ihres unterschiedlichen katalytischen Verhaltens wurden TiO2, Ô?ß-Al2O3 and SiO2 (SBA-15) getr√§gerte Katalysatoren, bevor und nachdem diese f√ºr die ODP verwendet wurden, mit Hilfe von Hochfrequenz-Elektronspinresonanz (HF-ESR) untersucht, um die paramagnetischen V4+ und V3+ Zust√§nde nachzuweisen. W√§hrend der SBA-15 Tr√§ger reduzierte Vanadiumzentren als einzige Elektronensenke aufweist, wurden bei Al2O3 auch Elektronen als Oxoradikale an der Tr√§geroberfl√§che lokalisiert. Im Fall von TiO2 wurden sowohl Ti3+ als auch oberfl√§chenlokalisierte O2(-)-Radikale nachgewiesen. Die Zunahme der katalytischen Aktivit√§t in der Reihenfolge SBA-15 &lt; Al2O3 &lt; TiO2 kann damit verschiedenen Reduktionsmechanismen zugeschrieben werden. V3+-Zentren konnten in keiner der Proben nachgewiesen werden, was darauf hindeutet dass diese Spezies entweder sehr kurzlebig oder nicht an der Reaktion beteiligt ist. Der SBA-15-getr√§gerte Katalysator wurde aufgrund des geringen Einflusses des Tr√§gers auf die Reaktion f√ºr eine weitergehende kinetische Studie der ODP in einem Festbettreaktor ausgew√§hlt. Das angewandte mikrokinetische Modell vereinfacht sich aufgrund der schnellen Reoxidation des Katalysators zu einem Geschwindigkeitsgesetz erster Ordnung. Die ermittelten kinetischen Parameter deuten eine Beteiligung der allylischen C-H-Bindung des Propens im geschwindigkeitsbestimmenden Schritt der Propenverbrennung an. Abschlie√üend wurde der Effekt von ‚ÄûGittersauerstoff‚Äú und Oxidationszustand des Vanadiums auf die Produktselektivit√§t an einem Al2O3 getr√§gerten Katalysator untersucht. Sowohl an einem voll oxidierten als auch partiell mit H2 reduziertem Katalysator wurde die ODE ohne Zugabe von Gasphasensauerstoff untersucht. Dabei nahm die Produktselektivit√§t bei Vorreduktion in H2 zu. Dies kann mit einem, im Gegensatz zu einer Reduktion in C2H6, geringeren Verh√§ltnis von V+4 zu V+3 erkl√§rt werden. Die dann geringere Lewis-Acidit√§t des Katalysators verhindert dann die Adsorption der nucleophilen Ethen-Doppelbindung und damit dessen Verbrennung.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21768</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21768</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2072/dinse_arne.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
