<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:46:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:581">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:581</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Catalytic study of copper based catalysts for steam reforming of methanol</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Purnama, Herry</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Im Rahmen meiner Promotion wurden die katalytischen Eigenschaften von kupferbasierten Katalysatoren für die Wasserstoff-Gewinnung aus Methanol untersucht. Die Katalysatoren wurden im Rahmen des gemeinsamen Projekts Nanochemie für eine zukünftige Automobiletechnik: Möglichkeit der Optimierung von kupferbasierten Katalysatoren für die on-board-Gewinnung von Wasserstoff aus Methanol auf verschiedenen Präparationswegen hergestellt. Das Projekt wird von ZEIT-Stiftung gefördert. Der kommerzielle Katalysator für das Steam-Reforming von Methanol ist der CuO/ZnO/Al2O3-Katalysator, der auch für die Methanolsynthese verwendet wird. Zwei wesentliche Nachteile dieses Katalysators sind die mangelnde Langzeitstabilität und die hohe Bildung von Kohlenmonoxid im Produkt, das hauptsächlich aus Wasserstoff und Kohlendioxid besteht. Es ist bekannt, dass Kohlenmonoxid ein Gift für die Pt-Elektrode in der Brennstoffzelle ist. Ein Ziel dieser Arbeit ist die Untersuchung der Bildung von CO bei der Nutzung des kommerziellen CuO/ZnOAl2O3 Katalysators, die als Grundlagen für die Entwicklung von neuen optimierten Reforming-Katalysatoren angewendet werden können. Es werden die katalytischen Eigenschaften von Cu/ZrO2-Katalysatoren untersucht, die nach verschiedenen Methoden (Fällung, mesoporöses Trägermaterial, makroporöses Trägermaterial) hergestellt wurden. Zum Vergleich wurde der kommerzielle CuO/ZnO/Al2O3-Katalysator herangezogen. Diese Arbeit gliedert sich in 3 wesentliche Abschnitte. Der erste Teil der Arbeit beinhaltet die ausführliche Untersuchung der CO-Bildung am kommerziellen CuO/ZnO/Al2O3-Katalysator und die Ermittlung von kinetischen Parametern. Es wird in der Literatur postuliert, dass die Bildung von CO durch die Spaltung von Methanol erfolgt und mit Wasser in der sogenannten Wassergas-Shift-Reaktion zu Kohlendioxid und Wasserstoff weiter reagiert. Die Ergebnisse der Experimente zeigen, dass die CO-Konzentration im Produktstrom mit zunehmender Verweilzeit in sigmoidaler Form zunimmt. Dies deutet darauf hin, dass CO in einer Folgereaktion gebildet wird. Die experimentellen Ergebnisse konnten mit einem kinetischen Modell mit guter Genauigkeit beschrieben werden, das reversible Methanol Steam-Reforming und die reverse Wassergas-Shift-Reaktion berücksichtigt. Es kann auch gezeigt werden, dass die CO-Bildung im Produktstrom durch Stofftransport-Limitierung im Katalysator beeinflusst werden kann. Je größer die Stofftransport-Hemmung in dem Partikel des Katalysators ist, desto größer ist die CO-Konzentration im Produkt. Da CO als Folgeprodukt in der reversen Wassergas-Shift-Reaktion gebildet wird, besteht die Möglichkeit, die CO-Bildung mit Hilfe einer geeigneten technischen Reaktionsführung zu unterdrücken.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The aim of this work is to study the catalytic properties of copper based catalysts used in the steam reforming of methanol. This method is known as one of the most favourable catalytic processes for producing hydrogen on-board. The catalysts investigated in this work are CuO/ZrO2 catalysts, which were prepared using different kinds of preparation methods and a commercial CuO/ZnO/Al2O3 catalyst which was used as a reference. The results of the studies can be divided into three sections: (i) The catalytic study reported in chapter 4 is focused on the investigation of the CO formation during steam reforming of methanol on a commercial CuO/ZnO/Al2O3 catalyst. The reaction schemes considered in this work are the methanol steam reforming (SR) reaction and the reverse water gas-shift (rWGS) reaction. The experimental results of CO partial pressure as a function of contact time at different reaction temperatures show very clearly that CO was formed as a consecutive product. The implications of the reaction scheme, in particular with respect to the production of CO as a secondary product, are discussed in the framework of onboard production of H2 for fuel cell applications in automobiles. Potential chemical engineering solutions for minimizing CO production are outlined. (ii) In chapter 5, the catalytic properties of a CuO/ZrO2 catalyst synthesized by a templating technique were investigated with respect to activity, long term stability, CO formation, and response to oxygen addition to the feed. It is shown that, depending on the time on stream, the temporary addition of oxygen to the feed has a beneficial effect on the activity of the CuO/ZrO2 catalyst. After activation, the CuO/ZrO2 catalyst is found to be more active (per copper mass) than the CuO/ZnO/Al2O3 catalyst, more stable during time on stream, and to produce less CO. (ii) In chapter 6, the study of the catalytic behaviours has been carried out on the six CuO/ZrO2 catalysts. The catalysts were synthesized with different preparation methods, i.e. incorporation of CuO in ZrO2-nanopowder, in mesoporous ZrO2 and in macroporous ZrO2. The activity of CuO/ZrO2 catalysts can be improved by oxygen treatment. The catalysts which have been used in the reaction provide a much larger value of the Sa than the fresh catalysts. This indicates that the new CuO/ZrO2 catalysts provide much higher stability with respect to the sintering of metal particles in comparison to the commercial CuO/ZnO/Al2O3 catalyst. The result concerning the increase of Sa correlates well with the increase of the activity of the used catalysts compared to the fresh catalysts. No linear correlation was found between the activity and copper surface area. However, the activity of the catalysts can be correlated with the preparation methods. In comparison to the commercial CuO/ZnO/Al2O3, the CuO/ZrO2 catalysts are more active. The CO concentration determined as a function of methanol conversion shows very clearly that less amount of CO was formed over CuO/ZrO2 catalysts than the commercial CuO/ZnO/Al2O3 catalyst.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2004-01-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/581</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-5751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-5751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/581/purnama_herry.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
