<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:46Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2244">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2244</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The NpSRII photocycle and its dependence on theelectric field ‚Äì a combined quantum chemical and Ramanspectroscopic study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Der Photozyklus von NpSRII und dessen Abh√§ngigkeit vom elektrischen Feld - eine kombiniert quantenchemisch und Ramanspektroskopische Studie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Naumann, Hendrik</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">SRII from Natronomanas pharaonis (NpSRII) constitutes the sensory part of the archaeal signalling system mediating phototaxis. It represents a well-established model system for sensory proteins in general and for G-protein coupled receptors in particular. In the Ô¨?rst part of this work time resolved Raman spectroscopic techniques are developed that allows probing the NpSRII photocycle in a wide dynamic range (1¬µs ‚Äì 5s), thereby considerably expanding the applicability of time-resolved resonance Raman (RR) spectroscopy to reversible photoconvertible systems. Thus, the RR spectra of the parent state NpSRII500 and the intermediates L495 , M400, N485and the O535 as well as their temporal evolution were determined. In addition to the N485 state, a previously undescribed N-like intermediate, named N‚àó, was identiÔ¨?ed that is clearly diÔ¨Äerent to the N intermediate of bacteriorhodopsin. In order to analyze the vibrational RR spectra of the protein-bound chromophore in terms of its polyene geometry, a quantum chemical (density functional theory - DFT) approach was established that is not only limited to NpSRII but can be applied to retinal proteins in general. It is based on the B3-P86 functional with the 6-31G(d) basis set in conjunction with the PCM solvent model. In addition the distance between the counter ion and the Schiff base is used as an adjustable parameter to mimic protein-cofactor interactions. The method provides a very good description for the RR spectra of various model systems and test proteins, including rhodopsin and bacteriorhodopsin. On the basis of this approach, the RR spectra of the various states of NpSRII were analyzed. SpeciÔ¨?cally, it was concluded that the retinal chromophore of the N‚àó intermediate probably adopts a 13-cis 14-s-cis conformation. The formation of this species requires an extension of the previous assumed photocycle model and, in addition, provides novel information into the mechanism of the reprotonation mechanism in NpSRII in comparison to bacteriorhodopsin. Furthermore, the experimental concept is extended to NpSRII immobilized on a silver electrode, employing for the Ô¨?rst time pump-probe time-resolved surface enhanced RR (SERR) spectroscopy to a biological photoreceptor. Establishing this technique is a prerequisite for analyzing the eÔ¨Äects of electric Ô¨?eld on the molecular mechanism of the photoinduced reaction cascade of NpSRII. It is shown that the photocycle of the NpSRII wild type protein is largely independent of the electric Ô¨?eld, whereas a distinct efect was observed for the F86D mutant for which a clear proton-pump activity was shown in electrophysiological studies. These Ô¨?ndings are consistent with the view that under physiological conditions the proton pump-dependent energy conversion of bacteriorhodopsin may beneÔ¨?t from an regulatory electric Ô¨?eld control, where as the light-sensing function of NpSRII should be independent of the electric Ô¨?eld.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">SRII aus Natronomanas pharaonis (NpSRII) ist der sensorischen Teil eines archebakteriellen Signaltransductionssystems welches die phototaktische Reaktion des Organismus steuert. Es stellt ein gut etabliertes Modellsystem f√ºr sensorische Proteine im allgemeinen und f√ºr G-Protein gekoppelte Rezeptoren in speziellen dar. Im ersten Teil dieser Arbeit wird die Entwicklung von zeitaufgel√∂sten ramanspektroskopischen Techniken beschrieben, welche die Untersuchung des NpSRII Photozyklus in einem gro√üen dynamischen Bereich (1¬µs - 5s) erlauben. Hierbei wurden die Anwendungsm√∂glichkeiten der zeitaufgel√∂√üten Resonanzramanspetroskopie (RR) auf photokonvertible Systeme deutlich erweitert, was die Aufnahme der RR-Spektren des Ausgangszustands NpSRII500 und der Intermediate L495, M400, N485 und O535 erm√∂glichte. Des weiteren konnte die zeitliche √Ñnderungen dieser Spezies ermittelt werden. Neben dem N485 Zustand, wurde ein weiterer vorher unbekannter N √§hnlicher Zustand gefunden. Dieses N* benannte Intermediat unterscheidet sich deutlich vom N Intermediat des Bacteriorhodopsins. Des weiteren wurde eine quantenchemische Methode (Dichtefunktionaltheorie - DFT) entwickelt, um Schwingungsraman Spektren von proteingebunden Chromophoren die Geometrie der Polyenstruktur zuzuordnen. Diese Methode ist nicht nur auf die Untersuchung von NpSRII beschr√§nkt, sondern l√§sst sich auf Retinalproteine generell anwenden. Sie basiert auf dem B3-P86 Funktional und dem 6-31G(d) Basissatz in Kombination mit dem PCM L√∂semittelmodell. Zus√§tzlich wird der Abstand zwischen Gegenion und Schiffscher Base als justierbarer Parameter benutzt, um die Protein-Kofaktor Wechselwirkung zu simulieren. Diese Methode erlaubte eine sehr genaue Berechnung der RR Spektren verschiedener Testsysteme, wie Rhodopsin und Bacteriorhodopsin. Unter Verwendung dieses Ansatzes wurden die RR Spektren der verschieden Zust√§nde des NpSRII analysiert. Die Analyse des RR Spektrums des N* Intermediats zeigte, das der Retinal Chromophor wahrscheinlich in der 13-cis 14-s-cis Konformation vorliegt. Um die Bildung dieser Spezies zu beschreiben, musste eine Erweiterung des bisher angenommenen Photozykluses vorgenommen werden. Dar√ºber hinaus liefert die Entdeckung der N* Spezies neue Informationen √ºber den Mechanismus der Reprotonierung der Schiffchen Base in NpSRII im Vergleich zu Bacteriorhodopsin. Der experimentelle Ansatz wurde au√üerdem um die Untersuchung von auf Silberelektroden immobilisierten NpSRII erweitert. Dabei wurde die bisher ersten zeitaufgel√∂√üten (pump-probe) oberfl√§chenverst√§rkten RR (SERR) Experimente an einem biologischen Photorezeptor durchgef√ºhrt. Die Etablierung dieser Technik ist die Voraussetzung zur Untersuchung des Effekts des elektrischen Feldes auf den molekularen Mechanismus der photoinduzierten Reaktionskaskade des NpSRII. Es konnte gezeigt werden, das der Photozyklus des Wildtyps von NpSRII gr√∂√üten Teils unabh√§ngig vom elektrischen Feld ist. Im Gegensatz dazu wurde ein deutlicher Effekt f√ºr die F86D Mutante gefunden, welche in elektrophysiologischen Studien eine deutliche Aktivit√§t als Protonenpumpe zeigt. Beide Ergebnisse sind Konsistent unter der Annahme, dass unter physiologischen Bedingungen der regulatorische Effekt des elektrischen Feldes f√ºr die protonen gebundene Energiegewinnung von Bacteriorhodopsin f√ºr den Organismus vorteilhaft ist, wohingegen die Empfindlichkeit gegen√ºber den Lichtverh√§ltnissen unabh√§ngig vom elektrischen Feld sein sollte.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2244</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-23521</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-23521</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2244/naumann_hendrik.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-SA: Creative Commons Lizenz: Namensnennung, Weitergabe zu gleichen Bedingungen</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
