<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:27Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3058">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3058</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Kinetic studies of propane oxidation on Mo and V based mixed oxide catalysts</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Kinetische Untersuchungen zur Propanoxidation an Mo- und V-basierten Mischoxidkatalysatoren </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Csepei, Lénárd-István</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The present work concentrates on the systematic kinetic study of the one-step propane oxidation to acrylic acid over a well defined, phase-pure M1 MoVTeNbOx catalyst. The bulk structural stability of the catalyst is a key issue for kinetic studies. The stability of the phase-pure M1 MoVTeNbOx catalyst under various conditions (steam-containing, steam-free, net reducing, stoichiometric and net oxidizing feed compositions) was evidenced by an in-situ XRD experiment which suggested that the bulk structure is homogeneous and constant under reaction conditions. Thereby, the heterogeneously catalyzed reactivity is exclusively determined by the surface properties, which in turn, are controlled by the chemical potential of the gas phase. A kinetic study on the reaction variables (temperature, steam content and redox potential) was carried out. Stable catalytic performance was observed for all the conditions. Cycling experiments showed the reversibility of the conversion and selectivity decrease upon exposing the catalyst to dry and reducing feed, respectively. Further catalytic experiments revealed that the reactivity spans over 5 orders of magnitude in the order of acrolein oxidation&gt;&gt;propylene oxidation&gt;propane oxidation&gt;&gt;carbon monoxide oxidation~water gas shift reaction. The negligible CO oxidation activity suggested that the CO and CO2 are formed via two independent pathways in propane oxidation over M1. The stage-wise addition of oxygen lead to an improvement of the catalytic performance by 5% compared to the conventional single-tube reactor. Further experiments in the two-stage reactor revealed that the phase-pure M1 is not reoxidized by N2O. The addition of propylene in the two-stage reactor revealed a slight competitive adsorption on the active sites with propane, which observation was supported by the results of microcalorimetric experiments. On the other hand, the addition of CO and CO2 in the two-stage reactor showed that these products do not adsorb competitively with the educt or intermediates. In the literature much of the kinetic data was reported for ill-defined catalyst surfaces. In contrast to that, the present work reports the kinetic study of propane selective oxidation to acrylic acid on a well defined phase-pure and structurally stable M1 MoVTeNbOx catalyst. This study may contribute to the better kinetic and mechanistic understanding of the propane selective oxidation reaction.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Arbeit enthält systematische kinetische Untersuchungen zur einstufigen, selektiven Oxidation von Propan zu Acrylsäure an wohl definierten, phasenreinen M1-MoVTeNbOx-Katalysatoren. Die Stabilität der phasenreinen M1-Katalysatoren unter verschiedenen Reaktionsbedingungen (in Wasserdampf, wasserdampffrei, netto-reduzierende, stöchiometrische und netto-oxidierende Feed-Zusammensetzung) konnte in In-situ-XRD-Experimenten bewiesen werden. Da die Festkörperstruktur homogen ist und beständig unter Reaktionsbedingungen, kann die unterschiedliche Reaktivität des heterogenen Katalysators allein durch seine Oberflächeneigenschaften bestimmt werden, welche wiederum stark vom chemischen Potential der Gasphase abhängen. Es wurden kinetische Studien zu den Reaktionsparametern Temperatur, Wasserdampf-anteil und Redoxpotential durchgeführt, wobei die Systeme unter allen Bedingungen stabile Katalysatorleistungen aufwiesen. Zyklische Experimente zeigten die Reversibilität des Umsatz- und Selektivitätsrückgangs, sowohl unter wasserfreiem als auch reduzierendem Feed. Zudem konnten in den Katalysetests Unterschiede in den Reaktivitäten von bis zu 5 Größenordnungen ermittelt werden, mit Acrolein &gt;&gt; Propylen &gt; Propan &gt;&gt; CO-Oxidation~Wassergas-Shift. Die bestimmte Oxidationsaktivität von CO war vernachlässigbar klein, was die Bildung von CO und CO2 auf zwei voneinander unabhängigen Reaktionspfaden suggeriert. Über eine stufenweise Zufuhr von Sauerstoff konnte eine Steigerung der katalytischen Aktivität um 5% im Vergleich zum konventionellen, einstufigen Reaktor erreicht werden. Die Versuche im zweistufigen Reaktor zeigten auch, dass der phasenreine M1-Katalysator in N2O nicht reoxidiert. Weiterhin konnte unter Zugabe von Propylen im zweistufigen Reaktor eine teilweise kompetitive Adsorption zu Propan an die aktiven Zentren des Katalysators beobachtet werden. Im Gegensatz dazu, stand die Adsorption von CO und CO2 nicht in Konkurrenz mit der Adsorption von Edukten oder Zwischenprodukten. Die kinetischen Untersuchungen der, im Gegensatz zu den meisten Systemen in der Literatur, wohl definierten, strukturstabilen M1-MoVTeNbOx-Katalysatoren könnten einen entscheidenden Beitrag zum Verständnis von Kinetik und Reaktionsmechanismus der Propanoxidation leisten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-10-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3058</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3058/csepei_lenard.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
