<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:13Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1952">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1952</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Synthesis and Investigation of Phase-pure M1 MoVTeNbOx Catalysts for Selective Oxidation of Propane to Acrylic Acid</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">MoVTeNbOx Katalysatoren für die selektive Oxidation von Propan zu AcrylsäureSynthese und Untersuchung von phasenreinem M1 </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Celaya Sanfiz, Almudena</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Hydrothermal synthesis of MoVTeNbOx catalysts has been investigated. It has been shown that the phase composition of the crystalline catalyst strongly depends on the conditions of the hydrothermal process. The X-ray amorphous product of the hydrothermal synthesis shows a long-range order of structural motifs in [001] direction. Subsequent heat treatment of the precursor in inert atmosphere leads to crystallization. The target structure is an orthorhombic bronze-like structure, denominated as M1. M1 phase has been associated with high activity and selectivity in the direct oxidation of propane to acrylic acid. Other phases formed are, e.g. the orthorhombic M2 phase (isostructural to KW3O9 phase), Mo5O14, V0.95Mo0.97O5 and TeMo5O16. Independent of the technical parameters of the autoclave used, phase-pure M1 has been successfully synthesized by optimization of the hydrothermal conditions (e.g. temperature and reaction time). As evidenced by SEM/EDX, precursor materials of M1 catalysts are characterized by a fairly homogeneous distribution of the elements and a significant higher Nb-content compared to that reported in the literature. According to EXAFS analysis, Nb is located into pentagonal bi-pyramidal units but also into octahedral coordinated positions, which is in contradiction to the established structural model. Furthermore, it was shown by XRD and TG/MS that the presence of ammonium containing phases in the precursor leads to the formation of phase mixture after the heat treatment. Additionally, the impact of phase composition on the catalytic behavior of hydrothermally prepared MoVTeNbOx catalysts in the selective oxidation of propane to acrylic acid has been investigated. Phase cooperation of M1 and M2 phase was not found in this contribution. For phase-pure M1 catalysts, the propane conversion increases with increasing the specific surface area. Other properties, such as chemical composition and aspect ratio of the needle-like M1 crystallites may influence the catalytic activity as well. In the present study the role of the (001) plane of the M1 phase in the propane oxidation is addressed by providing a M1 model catalyst that exposes preferentially this plane. The molecular structure and dynamic nature of the active moiety on the M1 surface under conditions of propane oxidation, is the key for understanding the catalytic behaviour of these catalysts. X-ray photoelectron spectroscopic experiments in presence of the reactants propane, oxygen and water indicated re-distribution of the elements at the catalyst surface, in response to changes in the gas mixture. Furthermore, phase-pure M1 showed a reasonable stability under reaction conditions in laboratory-scale experiments, which is of a great importance for their potential industrial application. The composition of multi-metal oxide catalysts has been varied. Metal substitution and/or addition of suitable diluents to the Mo-V-X-Nb (X=Te, P, Bi) oxides has been performed. The catalysts have been investigated in the selective oxidation of propane to acrylic acid. The results underlined the exceptional role of M1 phase. On the other hand, it has been proven that M1 is not necessarily required for acrylic acid formation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Hydrothermalsynthese von MoVTeNbOx Katalysatoren ist untersucht worden. Es hat sich gezeigt, dass die Phasenzusammensetzung des kristallinen Katalysators stark von den Bedingungen des Hydrothermalprozesses (Temperature, Reaktionszeit) abhängt. Das Diffraktogramm des amorphen Syntheseprodukts (Precursor) zeigt, dass bereits hier eine langreichweitige Ordnung von strukturellen Elementen in [001] Richtung vorliegt. Die anschließende Temperung des Precursors in inerter Atmosphäre führt zur Kristallisation. Die Zielstruktur ist eine orthorhombische, bronzeartige Phase, die als M1 bezeichnet wird und die mit der hohen Aktivität und Selektivität von MoVTeNb-oxid Katalysatoren in der direkten Oxidation von Propan zu Acrylsäure in Verbindung gebracht wird. Andere Phasen, die gebildet werden, sind z. B. die orthorombische M2 Phase (isostrukturell mit KW3O9), Mo5O14, V0.95Mo0.97O5 und TeMo5O16. Wie mittels SEM/EDX gezeigt, zeichnen sich Precursor Materialien von M1 Katalysatoren durch eine homogene Verteilung der Elemente und einen, im Vergleich zu Literaturangaben, erhöhten Nb-Gehalt aus. Basierend auf der EXAFS Analyse von phasenreinem M1 liegt Nb sowohl in pentagonal bipyramidaler Koordination, als auch oktaedrisch koordiniert vor, was im Widerspruch zu publizierten Strukturmodellen steht. Außerdem wurde durch XRD und TG/MS gezeigt, dass die Anwesenheit von ammoniumhaltigen Phasen im Precursor zur Bildung von Phasengemischen während der thermischen Behandlung führt. Desweiteren ist der Einfluss der Phasenzusammensetzung auf die katalytischen Eigenschaften von hydrothermal hergestellten MoVTeNbOx Katalysatoren in der Oxidation von Propan zu Acrylsäure untersucht worden. Eine Kooperation zwischen M1 und M2 Phase wurde in diesem Beitrag nicht gefunden. Für phasenreine M1 Katalysatoren, nimmt der Propanumsatz mit der Erhöhung der spezifischen Oberfläche zu. In der vorliegenden Untersuchung wird die Rolle der (001) Netzebene der M1-Phase in der Propanoxidation untersucht. Dazu wurde ein Modellkatalysator hergestellt, bei dem vorzugsweise (001) Ebenen exponiert sind, während die Seitenflächen der Nadeln mit SiO2 passiviert wurden. Die Kenntnis der molekularen Struktur und der dynamischen Eigenschaften der M1 Oberfläche unter den Bedingungen der Propanoxidation ist der Schlüssel, um das katalytische Verhalten dieser Katalysatoren zu verstehen. Photo-elektronenspektroskopische Experimente in Anwesenheit von Propan, Sauerstoff und Wasser zeigten, dass sich die chemische Zusammensetzung der Oberfläche stark von der des Volumens unterscheidet und dass diese darüber hinaus von der Zusammensetzung der Gasphase abhängt. Außerdem ist phasenreines M1 in der Propanoxidation über 50 Stunden stabil, was von Bedeutung für eine potentielle industrielle Anwendung des Katalysators ist. Desweiteren wurde die Zusammensetzung der Multimetalloxidkatalysatoren variiert und SiO2, ZrO2, und Cr2O3 als Verdünnungsmittel zu MoVXNbOx (X=Te, P, Bi) zugegeben. Die Katalysatoren wurden in der Oxidation von Propan zu Acrylsäure getestet. Die Ergebnisse unterstreichen die außergewöhnliche Bedeutung der M1 Phase für die selektive Aktivierung von Propan. Andererseits konnte gezeigt werden, dass die kristalline M1-Phase für die Acrylsäurebildung nicht notwendigerweise erforderlich ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-10-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1952</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20242</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20242</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1952/original_celayasanfiz_almudena.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1952/celayasanfiz_almudena.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
