<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:55Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2950">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2950</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Investments in Liberalized Electricity Markets and the Low-Carbon Energy Transition: A Mixed-method Analysis of the German Case</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Investitionen in liberalisierten Stromm√§rkten und der √úbergang zu einer kohlenstoffarmen Energieversorgung: Eine Untersuchung am Fallbeispiel Deutschland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pahle, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Because of the high number of low-cost mitigation options the power sector will play an important role in combating global climate change. Given the current worldwide trend of liberalization, the main challenge is to incentivize investments in low-carbon technologies under market rules. This thesis investigates the combined questions of how investments are made in liberalized electricity markets, and to which extent climate policy instruments are effective in inducing cleaner technology choice. It uses Germany as a case study, where during the last years a considerable number of new coal power plants have been brought on the way. This ‚Äúdash for coal‚Ä?, apparently contradicting political efforts to transform the energy system, serves as the guiding issue around which several aspects of the aforementioned questions are investigated. The first analysis explores the drivers and decision factors that likely lead triggered the ‚Äúdash for coal‚Ä?. Because no integrated theory of investments in liberalized electricity markets yet exists, it compiles a list of potentially influential economic, technological and socio-political factors in a first step. Examining these factors in more detail in a second step, it turns out that the extensive coal investments can be attributed to six main reasons. They are: (1) replacement requirements due to the nuclear phase out, (2) the onset of a new investment cycle in the power market, (3) favourable economic and technological prospects for coal compared to natural gas in the long run, (4) a status-quo bias of investors in regard to future renewable deployment, (5) explicit political support for coal, and (6) the ineffectiveness of public protest in hampering new projects. Two of these are looked at in more detail in the succeeding parts of this thesis. The second analysis deals with how emission certificate allocations had distorted fossil investments in favour of coal technologies. The EU Emission Trading Scheme (EU ETS), implemented in 2005, was set up to incentivize cleaner investments by putting a price on CO2 emission through tradable certificates. However, in its first phase initial certificate allocations for new plants in Germany were technology specific, leading to a considerably higher number of total certificates for coal compared to natural gas. Because suppliers incurred windfall profits by passing-through the opportunity costs of these certificates, coal plants were expected to receive higher additional cash flows than natural gas plants, which effectively subsidized coal. In fact, results suggest that disproportionate windfall profits compensate more than half the total capital costs of a hard coal plant. Only auctioning of certificates or a single best available technology benchmark would have made natural gas the predominant technology of choice. This underlines that implementation details had a great impact on investment incentives, unintentionally increasing the edge of coal over natural gas rather than decreasing it. The third analysis leaves the level of a single investor and looks at how the market as a whole responds to a price on CO2. More specifically, it investigates technology choice and the optimal CO2 price level from a welfare perspective. Motivated by the structure of the German market where four big suppliers own the major share of capacities, imperfect competition with strategic behaviours by these suppliers is assumed. Moreover, based on the finding of the first analysis, investments in coal plants are limited to the strategic suppliers, which adds a so called technological market power. Model results indicate that in such a setting investments in natural gas occur at lower CO2 price levels and more gradually than in a perfect competitive market. This happens due to the strategic reduction of output that increases electricity prices, which in turn makes natural gas profitable even when the comparative advantage in emission costs is still low. In a perfect competitive market though, investments switch from exclusively coal to exclusively natural gas only if the carbon price is 37 ‚Ç¨/t or higher. Furthermore, the impact of market power on overall welfare is relatively moderate and losses never exceed 1% if the price of CO2 is set at the optimal level. This shows that a price on CO2 can indeed be an effective instrument to induce investments into cleaner technologies, especially natural gas. Nevertheless, relatively high prices are needed for a fundamental transition, and it remains to be seen if this will become reality in the future.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Aufgrund der g√ºnstigen Vermeidungsoptionen spielt der Stromsektor im Kampf gegen den globalen Klimawandel eine wichtige Rolle. In Anbetracht der weltweit stattfindenden Liberalisierungen besteht die Hauptaufgabe darin, Anreize f√ºr Investitionen in kohlenstoffarme Technologien zu schaffen. Diese Arbeit untersucht die miteinander verbundenen Fragen, wie Investitionen in liberalisierten Stromm√§rkten erfolgen, und wie klimapolitische Instrumente eine ‚Äûsaubere‚Äú Technologiewahl induzieren k√∂nnen. Als Fallbeispiel dient Deutschland, wo innerhalb der letzten Jahre eine gro√üe Zahl neuer Kohlekraftwerke in Bau gegangen sind. Dieser "Dash for Coal", der offensichtlich im Widerspruch zu aktuellen politischen Bem√ºhungen hinsichtlich des Umbaus des Energiesystems steht, dient daf√ºr als Ausgangspunkt. Die erste Untersuchung erkundet die Treiber und Entscheidungsfaktoren, die vermutlich zum "Dash for Coal" gef√ºhrt haben. In einem ersten Schritt wird dazu eine Liste m√∂glicher √∂konomischer, technologischer und soziopolitischer Einflussfaktoren zusammen gestellt. In einem zweiten Schritt werden diese Faktoren genauer betrachtet und insgesamt sechs Gr√ºnden f√ºr die umfangreichen Neubauten identifiziert. Diese sind: (1) Der Ersatzbedarf an Kapazit√§ten aufgrund des Kernenergieausstiegs. (2) Der Beginn eines neuen Investitionszyklus im Strommarkt. (3) Die im Vergleich zu Erdgas vorteilhaften √∂konomischen und technologischen Bedingungen f√ºr Kohle auf l√§ngere Sicht. (4) Eine gewisse Z√∂gerlichkeit gegen√ºber erneuerbaren Energien seitens der Investoren. (5) Explizite politische Unterst√ºtzung f√ºr Kohle. (6) Mangelnder Erfolg √∂ffentlicher Proteste gegen Bauvorhaben. Zwei dieser Gr√ºnde werden im Folgenden genauer untersucht. Die zweite Untersuchung besch√§ftigt sich mit der Frage, wie die Allokation von Emissionszertifikaten Investitionen in fossile Technologien zugunsten von Kohle verzerrt hat. Der seit 2005 existierende EU Emissionshandel (EU ETS) wurde ins Leben gerufen, um Anreize f√ºr klimafreundlichere Investitionen mithilfe eines Preises auf CO2 Emissionen zu schaffen. Allerdings wurden in der ersten Phase in Deutschland Zertifikate f√ºr neue Kraftwerke nach technologiespezifischen Ma√ügaben verteilt, was zu einer insgesamt deutlich h√∂heren Zuweisung an Kohlekraftwerke im Vergleich zu Gaskraftwerken f√ºhrte. Weil Investoren zus√§tzliche Profite (windfall profits) durch die Einpreisung der Opportunit√§tskosten der Zertifikate erzielen konnten war zu erwarten, dass Kohlekraftwerke deutlich h√∂here zus√§tzliche Einnahmen erzielen k√∂nnten. Die Modellergebnisse der Untersuchung zeigen, dass ungleiche windfall profits ungef√§hr die H√§lfte der Kapitalkosten eines neuen Kohlekraftwerks gedeckt h√§tten. Nur eine Auktionierung der Zertifikate oder eine Zuweisung nach einem Benchmark der bestm√∂glichen Technologie h√§tten Gas zur bevorzugten Technologie werden lassen. Das unterstreicht, dass die Details der Implementierung des Instruments in diesem Fall einen gro√üen Einfluss auf die Investitionsanreize hatten, und kontr√§r zur Zielstellung dem Neubau von Kohlekraftwerken f√∂rderlich waren. Die dritte Untersuchung abstrahiert von der Perspektive eines einzelnen Investor und besch√§ftigt sich damit, wie der Markt als Ganzes auf einen Preis auf CO2 Emissionen reagiert, wenn durch den Kernenergieausstieg ein erheblicher Bedarf an Ersatzinvestitionen besteht. Im Detail werden sowohl die Technologiewahl als auch der optimale Preis von CO2 unter Gesichtspunkten der Wohlfahrt betrachtet. Bedingt durch die Struktur des deutschen Markts wird dabei unvollst√§ndiger Wettbewerb mit strategischem Verhalten dieser Erzeuger angenommen. Die Modellergebnisse zeigen, dass bei diesen Annahmen Investitionen in Gaskraftwerke schon bei niedrigeren CO2 Preisen und insgesamt schrittweiser get√§tigt werden als bei perfektem Wettbewerb. Dies ist der Fall, weil die strategische Reduzierung der erzeugten Strommenge zu h√∂heren Preisen f√ºhrt, wodurch Gaskraftwerke auch bei geringeren komparativen Kostenvorteilen bez√ºglich der Emissionen schon profitabel sind. Im Gegensatz dazu erfolgt bei perfektem Wettbewerb ein strikter Bruch in der Technologiewahl. Bei einem Preis von 36 EUR/t oder weniger wird ausschlie√ülich in Kohle investiert, ab einem Preis von 37 EUR/t oder h√∂her ausschlie√ülich in Gas. Unter Gesichtspunkten der Wohlfahrt allerdings spielt dieses deutlich unterschiedliche Verhalten kaum eine Rolle, denn die Verluste durch Marktmacht sind kleiner als 1% wenn der CO2 Preis optimal gesetzt wird. Das unterstreicht, dass ein Preis auf CO2 Emissionen in der Tat ein effektives Instrument sein kann, um Anreize f√ºr Investitionen in klimafreundliche Technologien ‚Äì insbesondere Erdgas ‚Äì zu schaffen. Allerdings bleibt abzuwarten, ob die f√ºr einen fundamentalen Umbau ben√∂tigten hohen Preise in der Zukunft auch tats√§chlich verwirklicht werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-07-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31384</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31384</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2950/pahle_michael.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
