<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:52Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2084">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2084</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Sustainability Management in Clean Development Mechanism (CDM) Project Activities</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Nachhaltigkeitsmanagement in Clean Development Mechanism (CDM)-Projektaktivit√§ten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>M√ºller-Pelzer, Felicia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The present PhD thesis is a study of ‚ÄúSustainability Management in Clean Development Mechanism (CDM) Project Activities‚Ä?. The study focuses on the research question of which approach would be suitable to demonstrate the contribution to sustainable development of a CDM project activity. This question is examined from the perspective of both the project developers and the Designated National Authorities (DNAs). The literature research done for this PhD thesis shows that the topics of sustainability and sustainable development have been largely addressed by different scientific disciplines and that a broad range of management and evaluation approaches has been developed. Yet, there is a considerable lack of transparent information about the contribution to sustainable development of most CDM project activities. Although tools have been created to demonstrate the contribution of a project activity, they are not largely applied. The reason for this deficiency is the DNA dilemma: if they set strict selection criteria, they run the risk of deterring investors and thereby of obstructing the access to decisive financial sources. On the contrary, if they set lax or no criteria, they risk that the project activities do not contribute to sustainable development or that they even have negative impacts. To overcome this, the author developed an approach, namely the Sustainability Management Approach (SMA), which considers both management needs of the CDM project developers and the evaluation needs of the DNAs. Three case studies in Peru revealed that project developers can apply the SMA by themselves to a great extent. In addition, a worldwide survey among the DNAs demonstrated that there is a broad acceptance for the SMA because it delivers the basis information needed for the assessment of project activities but at the same time stays manageable. Therefore, the author recommends using the SMA to further strengthen the evaluation process of CDM project activities with regard to their contribution to sustainable development.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Dissertation untersucht ‚ÄûNachhaltigkeitsmanagement in Clean Development Mechanism (CDM)-Projektaktivit√§ten‚Äú. Die Studie konzentriert sich auf die Forschungsfrage, welcher Ansatz geeignet w√§re, den Beitrag einer CDMProjektaktivit√§t zur nachhaltigen Entwicklung darzulegen. Diese Fragestellung wird sowohl aus der Perspektive der Projektentwickler als auch der der Designated National Authorities (DNAs) untersucht. Die Literaturrecherche zeigt, dass Nachhaltigkeit und nachhaltige Entwicklung von verschiedenen wissenschaftlichen Disziplinen ausgiebig behandelt worden sind und dass eine breite Palette an Management- und Evaluationsans√§tzen existiert. Dennoch gibt es einen starken Mangel an transparenter Information, was den Beitrag zur nachhaltigen Entwicklung der meisten CDM-Projektaktivit√§ten angeht. Zwar wurden Instrumente entwickelt, um den Beitrag einer Projektaktivit√§t zu zeigen, jedoch finden sie keine breite Anwendung. Der Grund f√ºr diese Unzul√§nglichkeit ist das DNA-Dilemma: Wenn sie strikte Auswahlkriterien festlegen, laufen sie Gefahr, Investoren abzuschrecken und sich damit den Zugang zu entscheidenden Finanzquellen zu verbauen. Legen sie hingegen weiche bzw. keine Kriterien fest, riskieren sie, dass die Projektaktivit√§ten keinen Beitrag zur nachhaltigen Entwicklung erbringen bzw. dass sie sich sogar negativ auswirken. Um dieses zu √ºberwinden, entwickelte die Autorin einen Ansatz, den Sustainability Management Approach (SMA), der sowohl Managementanforderungen der Projektentwickler sowie Evaluationsanforderungen der DNAs ber√ºcksichtigt. Drei Fallstudien in Peru ergaben, dass Projektentwickler den SMA gr√∂√ütenteils selbst√§ndig anwenden konnten. Au√üerdem zeigte eine weltweite Umfrage unter den DNAs eine breite Zustimmung zum SMA auf, da er die grundlegenden Informationen zur Beurteilung von Projektaktivit√§ten liefert, aber dabei handhabbar bleibt. Deshalb empfiehlt die Autorin, den SMA zu verwenden, um den Evaluationsprozess f√ºr CDM-Projektaktivit√§ten hinsichtlich ihres Beitrags zur nachhaltigen Entwicklung zu weiter st√§rken.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2084</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21741</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21741</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2084/original_muellerpelzer_felicia.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2084/muellerpelzer_felicia.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
