<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3018">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3018</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:750</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Studien zu Mair von Landshut</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Research Studies about Mair of Landshut</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gammel, Marianne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:750</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Obwohl von Mair von Landshut (um 1450/60 ‚Äì ca. 1504) eine Reihe von vor allem signierten Graphiken erhalten sind, ist er als K√ºnstlerpers√∂nlichkeit schwer fassbar. Es gibt nur wenig Nachrichten, die ihm eindeutig zuzuordnen sind. Herkunft und k√ºnstlerischer Werdegang lassen sich nur ansatzweise rekonstruieren; gleiches gilt f√ºr seine T√§tigkeit in Landshut. Dar√ºber hinaus ist sein Umfeld schlecht bearbeitet. Die kunsthistorische Forschung hat sich deshalb nur wenig f√ºr ihn interessiert. Er wird als ‚ÄûMair maler von freising‚Äú im M√ºnchner Stadtsteuerbuch von 1490 bezeichnet. Mit hoher Wahrscheinlichkeit kann er in einem Sippengeflecht der bedeutendsten Augsburger Patrizier- und K√ºnstlerfamilien verortet werden. Als sich Mair in Landshut 1499 dem Kupferstich widmete in Kooperation mit Hans Wurm, reihte er sich ein in eine lange bestehende Tradition schw√§bischer K√ºnstler in Landshut. Mair geh√∂rt zu einer Gruppe von K√ºnstlern, die am Beginn der Wende um 1500 stehen. Diese Maler sind noch der sp√§tgotischen Kunst verpflichtet, andererseits sehr experimentierfreudig, was h√§ufig zu Manierismen, Widerspr√ºchlichkeiten und Karikierendem f√ºhrte. Der bekannteste unter ihnen ist Hieronymus Bosch. Der Freisinger Fu√üwaschungsaltar, eine Memorialstiftung des Tristan von Nussberg, gibt einen geographischen Anhaltspunkt f√ºr Mairs Schaffen: Die Dissertation thematisiert erstmals das komplexe Gesamtprogramm des Altares in der Freisinger Domsakristei und seine inhaltliche und formale Konzeption. Das Retabel wird als ein innovatives und theologisch aufgeladenes Konzept diskutiert. Die ausgekl√ºgelte Phantasie legt die Annahme ganz spezieller W√ºnsche vonseiten des Stifters nahe. Wie im Fu√üwaschungsaltar ist auch im gesamten Werk Mairs eine Befassung mit den ma√ügeblichen religi√∂sen Texten festzustellen, die bislang noch nicht mit den Werken Mairs in Verbindung gebracht wurden. Im Zusammenhang mit der Signiermethode Mairs auf einem cartellino kommt dem Starck‚Äôschen Kreuzaufrichtungstriptychon in Washington eine Schl√ºsselrolle zu. Mair ist auf seiner Gesellenwanderung durch Franken insbesondere im engen Kreis des Meisters des Kreuzaufrichtungs-Triptychons zu verorten. Als Ergebnis der Werkanalyse konnte mit der Feststellung von Mairs Kenntnis der fr√§nkischen Kunst eine wichtige Forschungsl√ºcke geschlossen werden. Insbesondere in Mairs Architekturdarstellung zeigt sich die Wirkung der Kunst Wolfgang Katzheimers, vor allem in den kubischen, monumentalen Architekturen, wie sie ab 1490 von Mair als Spezialist f√ºr Architekturdarstellung in der Werkstatt Jan Polacks wieder aufgegriffen wurden. Mairs gemalte Architekturen im Bild sowie die Architekturdarstellungen in seinen Kupferstichen erweisen sich als Architekturphantasien. Die Entschl√ºsselung des vielf√§ltigen Einflussspektrums, das Mair in seinem Werk verarbeitete, l√§sst ihn als √§u√üerst sprunghaften K√ºnstler erscheinen. Gleichzeitig ist festzustellen, dass sich sein Oeuvre dem Modell einer linearen Stilentwicklung widersetzt, ja vielmehr ein Stilpluralismus festzustellen ist, der je nach Umfang und Aufwand des Auftrages variiert. Die vorliegende Arbeit will als Grundlage f√ºr eine Neubewertung dienen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Mair of Landshut (1450/60 to about 1504) is an outstanding artist, but his person is almost impossible to grasp. There are only few clear references pointing to him, although there still exists a number of his signed graphic artwork. His family background and his artistic career can only be rudimentary reconstructed. The same must be considered about the time he was working at Landshut. But it is not just Mair‚Äôs life, which is still a secret; his surrounding field is also poorly researched. Therefore there is a lack of assured art historical research concerning the entire research field of this art historical period and location. Mair‚Äôs name is mentioned 1490 in the city tax book of Munich as ‚ÄúMair maler von freising‚Ä? (Mair painter of freising‚Ä?). It is very probable that around this time he can be located within a clan network of the patrician and artist families of Augsburg. When in 1499 Mair started to concentrate on cooper engravings in cooperation with Hans Wurm, he joined a long tradition of Swabian artists in Landshut. Mair belongs to a group of artists, who marked the stylistic change at the beginning of 1500. Those painters were bound to the late Gothic art, but at same time were keen to experiment with new interpretations. In many cases this led to mannerism, discrepancies and sometimes to a style close to caricature. The most famous artist among them is Hieronymus Bosch. Tristan of Nussberg endowed to the cathedral of Freising an altar retable depicting ‚Äúthe foot washing of Christ‚Ä?, which helps us to locate geographically Mair‚Äôs producing. The dissertation explores for the first time this altar retable, which is still in its original place in the vestry of the cathedral. The research studies concentrate on the complex programms of Mair‚Äôs pictures with regard to its content and formal conception. Discussing this altar retable it will be focused on its innovative and theological charged concept. The elaborate fantasy underlying Mair‚Äôs artwork suggests that he had to carry out the very special wishes of the benefactor. It can be observed that Mair‚Äôs altar depicting ‚Äúthe foot washing of Christ‚Ä? as well as his entire artistic artwork shows a strong influence of religious texts, which until now had not been considered as part of Mair‚Äôs work. Concerning Mair‚Äôs special method of signing on ‚Äúcartellinos‚Ä? the Starck triptych of ‚Äúthe erection of the cross of Christ‚Ä? in Washington has a key role. When Mair went on his journeyman years through Franconia, he was supposed to belong to the inner circle of the Master of the Starck triptych of ‚Äúthe erection of the cross of Christ‚Ä?. The research studies about Mair of Landshut show that Mair was quite familiar with the Franconian art of his time. This result closes an important research gap. The depiction of architecture within Mairs work particularly shows the influence of Wolfgang Katzheimer. This artist used a monumental and cubical architecture in his pictures. Mair adapted this style and reused it while he was working as specialist for depicting architecture in the painter workshop of Jan Polack. Mair invented in his paintings and in his copper engravings architectural fantasies, which have no equivalent in reality. Decoding the varied influences Mair used in his work, he gives us the impression of a volatile artist. The reason for this might be that his Oeuvre opposes the model of a linear stylistic development. In fact Mair preferred a variety of styles depending on the amount and complexity of his contracts These research studies provide a basis for a new judgment of Mair of Landshut.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-08-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3018</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31114</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31114</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3018/gammel_marianne.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
