<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:49Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3358">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3358</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Climate Change, Water Scarcity, and the Depletion of Non-renewable Resources. A theoretical microeconomic analysis of contemporary topics in environmental economics</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Klimawandel, Wasserknappheit, und die Erschöpflichkeit Nichterneuerbarer Ressourcen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wittmann, Nadine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Wie schon der Titel dieser Dissertation nahelegt werden im Zuge dieser Arbeit drei verschiedene Themengebiete bearbeitet. Dabei werden verschiedene mikroökonomische Modelle entwickelt welche einige der wichtigsten umweltökonomischen Fragestellungen aufgreifen. Dabei wird eine detaillierte und stringente Analyse der Effekte und Auswirkungen von Politik- und Regulierungsinstrumenten innerhalb gegebener Marktstrukturen durchgeführt. Jedes der drei Kapitel behandelt und umfaßt die folgenden Aspekte: • Überblick und Diskussion ausgewählter Literatur welche zum jeweiligen Thema veröffentlicht wurde • Analyse von Marktstrukturen sowie relevanter Marktakteure und Variablen • Die Erstellung eigener ökonomischer Modelle • Herleitung von Ergebnissen und graphische Interpretation • Kritische Würdigung und Fazit Die Struktur der Arbeit ist wie folgt: Das erste Kapitel gibt einen präzisen Überblick über Inhalt und Intention der Arbeit. Kapitel zwei behandelt das erste der drei Hauptthemen, den Klimawandel. Insbesondere wird die Frage behandelt wie sich nachfrageseitige Regulierungsinstrumente in einem bereits stark regulierten Energiemarkt auswirken. Kapitel drei befaßt sich mit der Regulierung von Wassernutzung bzw. -verschmutzung von Fließgewässern. Kapitel vier behandelt die Thematik der nicht-erneuerbaren Ressourcen, insbesondere die der fossilen Brennstoffe und der inländischen Preispolitik Erdöl exportierender Nationen. Kapitel fünf schließt die Arbeit mit einem kritischen Fazit ab. Insgesamt kann die Essenz der Arbeit wie folgt umschrieben werden: • Die Regulierung ökonomischer Aktivität muß mit Bedacht erfolgen • Eine einfache mikroökonomische Analyse kann hilfreiche Einblicke in die Auswirkungen von Regulierungsinstrumenten bieten • Eine genaue und detaillierte Analyse der Marktstruktur sowie der relevanten Marktakteure ist entscheidend für die Qualität und Bedeutsamkeit der Ergebnisse Alles in allem ist die Arbeit dazu gedacht die Bedeutung und vielfältige Anwendbarkeit ökonomischer Theorie und ökonomischer Modelle aufzuzeigen. Sie zeigt zudem, daß viele Bereiche der Umweltökonomie mittels der Anwendung grundlegender mikroökonomischer Theorien analysiert werden können. Selbstverständlich ist die Realität selbst äußerst komplex und kein Modell wird daher je in der Lage sein diese in Ihrer Gesamtheit zu erfassen. Daher konzentrieren sich die Modelle auf die wichtigsten und relevantesten Aspekte der Wirklichkeit.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">As the title of this PhD thesis suggests, there are three different topics discussed in the course of this work. The intuition behind this is to construct several microeconomic models dealing with some of the most pressing issues in today’s environmental economics. Thereby, a thorough and straightforward analysis of the effects and the impact of policy measures or regulatory instruments within a given market structure is conducted. Each of the three chapters is concerned with and comprises the following aspects: • Reviewing and discussing the ideas presented in selected pieces of literature which have been published on the respective topic • Identifying and analyzing market settings and structure, as well as relevant actors and variables • Creating own microeconomic models • Calculating and deducting results and presenting graphical interpretations • Critical summary and conclusion The structure of the work is as follows: Chapter 1 gives a concise overview over both content of and intention behind this work, while Chapter 2 deals with the first of the three main topics, namely Climate Change. In particular, the analysis deals with identifying the impact of implementing a demand side oriented policy measure in an energy market, whose supply side is already highly regulated. Chapter 3 will deal with a model of a river basin that is exposed to water consumption or manmade effluents. The special aspect incorporated in this model is the location-specific nature of the problem, as upstream action triggers downstream effects. Chapter 4 is dedicated to special topics in the field of non-renewable resources with special reference to the effects of pricing policies in oil exporting nations. Chapter 5 is comprised of some concluding remarks. The essence of this work can be characterized as follows: • Any regulation of economic activity is an instrument that has to be applies with caution. • A simple microeconomic analysis can yield helpful information on the nature and intensity of effects that a specific regulatory tool will inflict on the regulated market and its parties involved. • Identifying the market structure and its relevant economic agents and other aspects is crucial to setting up a model that will render useful and meaningful results. This work is supposed to shed some light onto the value as well as the vast applicability of economic theory and theoretical modeling. It shows that many fields of interest in environmental economics can be analyzed applying basic microeconomic theory. Naturally, reality is complex and complicated and no model will ever be able to fathom and comprise all of it. Hence, models never reveal the entire scope of the real setting but focus on the most important characteristics of reality.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-06-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34378</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34378</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3358/wittmann_nadine.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
