<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:36Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3311">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3311</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Economic Valuation of Wetland Ecosystem Services.Accounting for wetland ecosystem service benefits in cost benefit analysis of river basin management options with case studies from the Elbe River Basin. </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ökonomische Bewertung von Ökosystemdienstleistung von Feuchtgebieten. </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Grossmann, Malte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Wetlands provide a multitude of ecosystem services such as livestock fodder production, recreational opportunities, habitat and biodiversity conservation or regulation of nutrient and greenhouse gas fluxes. Wetland management inevitably involves trade-offs regarding the management and allocation of the two key resources, land and water, that taken together determine the status of wetland ecosystems and the potential flow of benefits to human wellbeing. The case studies presented in this thesis addresses two types of typical central European wetlands: river floodplains and lowland peat wetlands. Floodplain wetland management requires trade-offs between the benefits of conducting activities on the floodplain against the risk and adverse consequences to these activities caused by flooding and trade-offs between the benefits and costs of reducing this flood risk, for example through the conversion of active floodplains to protected floodplains by construction of dikes. The management of lowland peat wetlands, on the other hand, requires trade offs between the benefits of drainage and conversion of wetland land for increased agricultural production and the loss of benefits from other ecosystem services. Wetland land uses are interdependent with water regulation and all wetlands require sufficient water at the appropriate time to maintain their wetland status. Particularly lowland peat wetlands are dependent on the inflow of river water and constitute important water users within river basin that compete with other water uses. Trade offs are therefore also required regarding the allocation of scarce water resources both within the basin and within wetlands. From an economic perspective, the key difficulty in determining whether restoration of wetlands or water allocation to wetlands are an appropriate policy or management goal lies in the difficulty of determining the value of the public benefits provided by wetlands. There is a gap between the market valuation and the economic value of many ecosystem services. The challenge of valuation of ecosystem services that have a public goods character and the integration of wetland ecosystem service benefits into the economic appraisal of river basin management options in a cost - benefit analytical framework are the two central issues of this thesis. The thesis is based on eight papers with case studies from the Elbe River Basin (Germany). The first five papers have a methodological focus and each applies a different valuation method to the valuation of a specific wetland ecosystem services. These are the (1) the provision of habitats and biodiversity using stated preference methods and benefits transfer, (2) recreation using the travel cost method, (3) flood risk regulation using avoided damage method, (4) greenhouse gas regulation using a shadow price or alternative cost approach and (5) nutrient regulation using an alternative cost approach. The final three papers present case studies of an integrated economic assessment using the framework of an extended cost benefit analysis. These analyses build on the valuation approaches developed in the previous papers. The first paper presents a strategic cost benefit analysis of floodplain management options for the Elbe River. The second paper presents an assessment of water management options for regulated lowland peat wetlands with a case study from the Spreewald wetland. The final paper presents wetlands as major water users amongst all other water uses within an integrated economic-hydrologic approach to assess the effects of climate change induced risks of low flows at the scale of the complete Elbe River Basin.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Feuchtgebiete stellen eine Vielzahl von Ökosystemdienstleistungen zur Verfügung, wie z.B. die Erzeugung von landwirtschaftlich nutzbarere Biomasse, Erholungsmöglichkeiten, Lebensräume für genutzte und ungenutzte Bestände von Wildtieren und Fischen oder die Regulierung von Nährstoff- und Treibhausgasflüssen. Die Bewirtschaftung von Feuchtgebieten erfordert zwangsläufig Abwägungen bezüglich der Nutzung und Allokation der beiden wichtigen Ressourcen Land und Wasser, die zusammengenommen den Status der Feuchtgebietsökosysteme und deren ökonomischen Nutzen im weitesten Sinne bestimmen. Die in dieser Arbeit vorgestellten Fallstudien beziehen sich auf zwei typische mitteleuropäische Feuchtgebietstypen: Flussauen und Niederungsmoore des Tieflands. Bei der Eindeichung und Drainierung von Auen- und Moorstandorten sind Abwägungen bezüglich des Nutzens dieser wasserbaulichen Maßnahmen hinsichtlich einer Erhöhung der agrarischen Produktion und deren sozialen Kosten hinsichtlich verminderter Produktion von solchen Ökosystemdienstleistungen, die den Charakter öffentlicher Güter haben, erforderlich. Dies gilt in der Umkehrung auch bei der Wiedervernässung von Mooren und Deichrückverlegung an Flussauen. Gleiches gilt für die Allokation von Wasserressourcen in einer Flussgebietseinheit, bei der zwischen dem erzielbaren Nutzen an Feuchtgebietstandorte und bei anderen Wassernutzungen im Einzugsgebiet abgewogen werden muss. Aus der Perspektive der ökonomischen Bewertung von Handlungsoptionen für die Bewirtschaftung von Feuchtgebietstandorten sowie der Wasserressourcen eines Flussgebiets ist das zentrale Problem die Bestimmung des Wertes der Ökosystemdienstleistungen, die zugleich öffentliche Güter sind. In diesen Fällen besteht eine Kluft zwischen dem Marktwert und dem volkswirtschaftlichem Wert der Leistungen des Ökosystems. Die beiden zentralen Themen dieser Arbeit sind daher empirische Methoden zur Bewertung von öffentlichen Gütern sowie Methoden zur systematischen Berücksichtigung des Nutzens von Ökosystemdienstleistungen in der Kosten - Nutzen Analyse von Bewirtschaftungsmaßnahmen. Die Arbeit basiert auf acht Artikel mit Fallstudien aus dem Einzugsgebiet der Elbe. Die ersten fünf Aufsätze haben einen methodischen Schwerpunkt und jedes wendet eine andere Methode zur Bewertung einer bestimmten Ökosystemdienstleistung an: (1) der Nutzen von Biodiversitäts- und Lebensraumschutz wird mit Hilfe einer Meta-Analyse von Zahlungsbereitschaften die mit der Zahlungsbereitschaftsmethode generiert wurden bewertet, (2) der Erholungsnutzen mit der Reiskostenmethode, (3) der Nutzen der Hochwasserschutzwirkung anhand des vermiedenen Schadens, (4) die Senkenfunktion für Treibhausgase sowie (5) die Nährstoffretention anhand des Schattenpreis bzw. der marginalen Vermeidungskosten. Die letzten drei Artikel präsentieren Fallstudien zu einer integrierten ökonomischen Bewertung durch im Rahmen einer erweiterten Kosten-Nutzen-Analyse. Die Analysen stützen sich auf die Bewertungsansätze die in den vorangehenden Arbeiten entwickelt wurden. Im ersten Beispiel wird eine strategische Kosten-Nutzen-Analyse von Deichrückverlegungsoptionen für die Flussauen der Elbe vorgestellt. Das zweite Beispiel bezieht sich auf die Bewertung von Bewirtschaftungsoptionen für wasserstandsregulierte Niederungsfeuchtgebiete anhand einer Fallstudie aus dem Spreewald. Das letzte Beispiel untersucht die Auswirkungen des Klimawandels für die Ökosystemdienstleistungen von Niederungsfeuchtgebieten im Rahmen eines integrierten ökonomisch – hydrologischen Modellierungsansatzes zur Bewertung der Wasserverfügbarkeit auf der Skalenebene des gesamten Einzugsgebiet der Elbe.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-05-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3311</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35063</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35063</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3311/grossmann_malte.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
