<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2369">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2369</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Measuring organizational complexity and its impact on organizational performance – A comprehensive conceptual model and empirical study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Messung von Unternehmenskomplexität und dessen Einfluss auf den Unternehmenserfolg - ein ganzheitliches Messkonzept und eine empirische Studie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schwandt, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The thesis presents a theoretical discussion about the measurement of organizational complexity, as well as an empirical study. In the beginning, a general definition of complexity is given, and the relationship between complexity and globalization is examined. It is found that globalization and complexity are two highly interlinked phenomena and that they create the following major dilemmas for organizations. • Fragmentation of markets vs. economies of scale, • Multi-brand/channel conflict vs. internal cooperation, • Local leadership vs. standardized processes, • Short term profitability vs. long-term sustainability, • Strategic flexibility vs. dominant logic, • Core competencies vs. knowledge accumulation. These dilemmas express the fundamental challenges in coping with growing complexity in practice. The theoretical discussion in the thesis shows that there is no clear theoretical recommendation on how organizations can cope with growing complexity. The postulates given by Ashby and Luhmann lead to an inconsistency that current research has not been able to solve. Consequently, the hypothesis that organizations should enhance (Ashby) or reduce (Luhmann) organizational complexity to cope with growing complexity in the business environment are discussed theoretically and tested empirically in this thesis. The theoretical discussion required a differentiation between market-driven and organization-driven complexity, which enables a partial reconciliation of the inconsistency. If increasing business environment complexity challenges organizations, they should carefully enhance the market-driven complexity of the organization and be aware of the value-creating and non-value creating character of this category of organizational complexity. Furthermore, to ensure success, they should reduce organization-driven complexity. To empirically test this theoretical framework, a comprehensive model for measuring organizational complexity is developed. The empirical study focuses on market-driven complexity and is based on a data sample of 305 organizations. Firstly, an Exploratory Factor Analysis is performed to identify the underlying dimensions (drivers) of market-driven complexity and to examine the theoretical assumptions of the four major drivers. It is found that market-driven complexity is driven by six factors: size, depth and breadth, organizational change, technological intensity, globalization, product diversification. Secondly, a Structural Equation Model is designed to test the relationship between market-driven complexity and organizational performance. It shows that Ashby is right in his assumptions in regard to market-driven complexity. A positive relationship between market-driven organizational complexity and organizational performance is confirmed. In contrast to the theoretical assumption that this relationship would vary between different levels of market-driven organizational complexity, no significant differences is found. Furthermore, the Structural Equation Model confirms that the relationships between the drivers and the construct of market-driven complexity are significant and therewith confirm the multi-dimensionality of the construct. Thus, researchers should not limit their models to one overarching complexity indicator, but should rather incorporate multivariate drivers. On the level of the drivers, significant differences are found and it is noted that, for example, the driver product diversification has a negative impact on organizational performance if the level of market-driven complexity increases. Only in the lowest complexity group the influence on performance is positive. Besides that, the multi-group comparison shows that the several dimensions of organizational performance are affected in different ways and on distinct levels of market-driven complexity. In particular, it shows that growing market-driven complexity leads to significantly lower increases of shareholder value in highly complex organizations than in low complex ones. This thesis has far reaching implications for the theory of complexity science. First, the presented distinction between market-driven and organization-driven complexity allows for a partial reconciliation of the inconsistent approaches to how to respond to growing complexity in the system (business) environment. Second, the thesis contributes to the advancement of complexity theory by establishing a solid basis for future empirical studies.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Doktorarbeit führt eine empirische Studie zum Einfluss der Unternehmenskomplexität auf den Unternehmenserfolg durch. In der einleitenden theoretischen Diskussion wird das Phänomen der Komplexität ausführlich diskutiert und besonders der Zusammenhang zwischen Globalisierung und Komplexität erläutert. Es werden sechs zentrale Dilemmata identifiziert, welche durch das intensive Zusammenwirken beider Phänomene für Unternehmen entstehen und in der Praxis fundamentale Herausforderungen für Unternehmen darstellen. - Zersplitterung der Märkte contra Skaleneffekte - Mehrmarken-und Vertriebskanalkonflikte contra interne Kooperation - Lokale Führung contra Standardisierung von Prozessen - Kurzfristige Profitabilität contra Nachhaltigkeit - Strategische Flexibilität contra dominante Logik - Konzentration auf Kernkompetenzen contra Wissensakkumulation. Die Ausführungen zeigen, dass es zwei unterschiedliche theoretische Ansätze zum Umgang mit gestiegener Unternehmensumweltkomplexität gibt (Luhmann vs. Ashby). In der theoretischen Diskussion der Arbeit wird daher eine Unterscheidung zwischen marktgetriebener und organisationsgetriebener Unternehmenskomplexität vorgenommen. Dadurch wird es möglich den theoretischen „Widerspruch“ zu entschärfen. Um diese theoretischen Überlegungen empirisch zu testen, wurde im Rahmen der Dissertation ein umfassendes Messmodell für die Unternehmenskomplexität entwickelt. Es umfasst 38 Indikatoren, welche die vier zentralen Komplexitätsdimensionen nach Steger (2008) - Diversity, Interdependence, Ambiguity und Fast flux - reflektiv abbilden. Basierend auf Unternehmenskennzahlen von 305 Unternehmen wird eine empirische Studie durchgeführt die sich auf die marktgetriebene Unternehmenskomplexität konzentriert. Mit Hilfe einer explorativen Faktorenanalyse werden im ersten Schritt die Dimensionen der Unternehmenskomplexität extrahiert und die Multidimensionalität des Komplexitätsphänomens bestätigt. Im Detail werden folgende sechs Dimensionen (Treiber) der marktgetriebenen Unternehmenskomplexität identifiziert: Größe, Wertschöpfungstiefe/Forschungsintensität, organisationaler Wandel, technologische Intensität, geografische Diversifikation und Produktdiversifikation. Im zweiten Schritt wird der Zusammenhang zwischen marktgetriebene Unternehmenskomplexität und Unternehmenserfolg mit Hilfe eines Strukturgleichungsmodells getestet. Ashbys Postulat der Komplexitätsentsprechung kann für die marktgetriebene Unternehmenskomplexität bestätigt werden, da ein positiver Zusammenhang identifiziert wurde. Bei der Durchführung eines weiterführenden Multigruppenvergleichs können keine signifikanten Unterschiede in der Stärke dieses Zusammenhanges bei verschieden Komplexitätsgraden der Unternehmenskomplexität bestätigt werden. Wenn Unternehmen also mit wachsender Umweltkomplexität konfrontiert sind, ist eine Erhöhung der marktgetriebenen Unternehmenskomplexität sinnvoll (Ashby). Gleichzeitig ist aber auch darauf zu achten, die organisationsgetriebene Unternehmenskomplexität zu reduzieren (Luhmann).</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-12-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2369</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-23752</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-23752</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2369/schwandt_alexander.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
