<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:26Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1526">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1526</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Methodological Issues in the Measurement of Income and Poverty</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Methodische Probleme bei der Messung von Einkommen und Armut</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Goebel, Jan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The main focus of this thesis are the important methodological problems that arise in the field of poverty and income analysis when using empirical data from large surveys. The problems of measuring poverty addressed here are the aggregation problem and the measurement of poverty over time, considering possible income mobility. In the empirical analysis, the results on the robustness for mean-based and median-based poverty lines as well as for monthly and annual income are presented. With the help of this concept, the differences in the consequences of mobility on poverty status are described for the USA and Germany. The results make clear that the kind of income used (pre- or post-government income) is very important when comparing countries that differ so widely, especially with respect to the characteristics of the welfare state. Issues of the quality of data for empirical analysis in a wider sense are also discussed in two chapters. The first of these deal with the robustness of imputation methods using a special dataset of the Finnish part of the European Household Panel, in which register information is available for missing values on income questions. The empirical results show that multi-method imputation algorithms are more robust, especially if they allow the user to adjust all settings to the specific problem at hand. The second chapter of these two deals with the problems of correctly measuring high-income households, carried out here with a special high-income sample from the German Socio-Economic Panel. The analysis also looks at the impact of better coverage of these cases, as well as the effects of integrating them into an ongoing panel survey. Furthermore, the distribution of the high-income households is described with the help of a Pareto distribution for both, the new and old samples. The last chapter presents an empirical application of the decomposition of inequality as measured with the Gini coefficient by German regions. The regional variation in income inequality and the development over time in Germany since reunification is analyzed. Concluding from the empirical results with respect to post-government income, one must reject the hypothesis that East and West Germany are moving towards a common income distribution. The picture is much different concerning the pre-government income distribution, however: here we see that East Germany already surpassed the Western level of inequality in the early 1990s and that this difference has increased continuously since. Even when enlarging the number and structure of the regions under consideration by splitting the western part into its northern, central and southern components, a clear picture of East Germany as still very different from the rest of the country is seen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der Hauptfokus dieser Arbeit liegt auf methodischen Problemen bei der Messung von Einkommen und Armut mit Hilfe von empirischen Daten aus Bevölkerungsumfragen. Im Bereich Armutsmessung wird das Aggregationsproblem sowie die Messung von Armut über die Zeit unter Berücksichtigung von Einkommensmobilität untersucht. In der empirischen Analyse zu diesem Kapitel werden Robustheitsanalysen für den entwickelten Messansatz unter Verwendung verschiedener Armutsgrenzen und Einkommenskonzepten durchgeführt. Mit der Hilfe des eingeführten Armuts-Stabilitäts-Koeffizienten werden die Unterschiede in den Auswirkungen der Einkommensmobilität auf die Persistenz von Armut in Deutschland und den USA verglichen. Es wird deutlich, das die Art des Einkommens (verfügbares oder Markt-Einkommen) entscheidend ist für den Vergleich von Armut für Länder mit starken Unterschieden in der Ausgestaltung des staatlichen Steuer- und Transfersystems. Darüberhinaus ist Datenqualität im weiteren Sinne Gegenstand von zwei Kapiteln. Eines dieser Kapitel analysiert die Robustheit von Imputationsmethoden mit Hilfe eines speziellen Datensatzes des finnischen Teils des Europäischen Haushaltspanels, der für fehlende Einkommensangaben die entsprechenden Werte aus offiziellen Registern beinhaltet. Sogenannte multi method'' Imputations Strategien zeigen sich dabei als am robustesten, insbesondere wenn sie sehr flexibel auf die jeweiligen Anforderungen vom Nutzer angepaßt werden können. Das anschließende Kapitel befaßt sich mit dem Problem der korrekten Erfassung von Haushalten mit hohen Einkommen. Die genutzte Datenbasis ist hierbei eine spezielle Teil-Stichprobe des Sozio-oekonomischen Panels. Analysiert werden die Auswirkungen einer besseren Abdeckung dieser Fälle und die Integration in ein laufendes Panel. Die Verteilung der hohen Einkommen wird mit Hilfe einer Pareto Verteilung geschätzt und für die neue Stichprobe und die laufende Panelbefragung verglichen. Das letzte Kapitel nutzt eine Zerlegung der Ungleichheit, gemessen mit dem Gini Koeffizienten, nach Regionen in Deutschland. Die regionalen Unterschiede der Einkommensungleichheit und deren zeitliche Entwicklung seit der Wiedervereinigung wird dabei dargestellt. Auf Grund der empirischen Ergebnisse muß die Hypothese, dass Ost- und Westdeutschland sich bezüglich der Verteilung und Ungleichheit des verfügbaren Haushaltseinkommen angleichen als widerlegt angesehen werden. Allerdings ist die Situation gänzlich unterschiedlich hinsichtlich der Verteilung des erzielten Markteinkommens. Die gemessene Einkommensungleichheit ist bei diesem Einkommenskonzept bereits in den frühen 90er Jahren höher als in den alten Bundesländern und der Abstand wuchs seitdem kontinuierlich. Auch bei einer weiteren Differenzierung von Westdeutschland in einen nördlichen, zentralen und südlichen Teil bleibt die klare Unterscheidbarkeit Ostdeutschlands bestehen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-06-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1526</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15792</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15792</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1526/original_goebel_jan.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1526/goebel_jan.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
