<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:07Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2791">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2791</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Competitive Strategy of Private Equity: Boundary of the Investment Firm</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Wettbewerbsstrategie von Private Equity: Unternehmensgrenze der Investmentgesellschaft</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kukla, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The private equity (PE) sector is maturing, strategic postures of many firms are undergoing considerable change, and indicators are signaling that the prevailing view of PE as a monolithic financing technique is overdue for modification. Daniel Kukla investigates related phenomena from multiple angles and offers helpful landmarks for future research in PE. A historical perspective and recent statistical data shed light on the origin and present state of the sector. Moreover, various fields of research have been catalogued into a new framework, synthesizing the gist of relevant existing knowledge. Empirically the research triangulates insights from quantitative and qualitative methods. The quantitative part is framed by strategic grouping theory. Based on a hand-collected dataset, statistical tests suggest that PE entities are increasingly pursuing differentiated strategic thrusts. The qualitative part is framed by the theory of the firm. Based on interviews with representatives of leading PE firms, the endeavor explores forces that shape corporate boundaries of investment firms. Overall, this thesis offers two major contributions. First, it distills new insights about the heterogeneity of PE firms. Second, it closes a missing conceptual link in the continuum between monolithic niche financiers and integrated multi-business investment banking and asset management entities.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Private Equity (PE)-Branche entwickelt sich weiter, viele Firmen verändern grundlegend ihre strategischen Positionen, und Indikatoren signalisieren, dass eine Modifikation des weitverbreiteten Bildes von PE als monolithische Finanzierungstechnik längst überfällig ist. Aus unterschiedlichen Blickwinkeln untersucht Daniel Kukla dieses Phänomen und schafft Orientierungspunkte für die zukünftige PE-Forschung. Eine historische Perspektive sowie aktuelle Daten beleuchten die Ursprünge und die aktuelle Situation des Sektors. Zudem wurden verschiedene Forschungsfelder in einem neuen Schema katalogisiert, welches die Quintessenz des vorhandenen relevanten Wissens zusammenfasst. Empirisch trianguliert die Studie quantitative und qualitative Methoden. Den Rahmen des quantitativen Teils bildet die ‚Strategic Grouping Theory‘. Basierend auf einem eigens generierten Datensatz zeigen statistische Tests, dass die Strategien von PE-Firmen immer differenzierter werden. Der qualitative Teils baut auf der ‚Theory of the Firm‘ auf. Mittels Interviews mit Repräsentanten von führenden PE-Firmen wird untersucht, durch welche Kräfte sich die Unternehmensgrenzen von Investment-Häusern formen. Übergreifend leistet die Dissertation zwei wesentliche Beiträge: Erstens werden neue Erkenntnisse über die Heterogenität von PE-Firmen herausgerabeitet. Zweitens wird die konzeptionelle Lücke zwischen monolithischen Nischenfinanciers und integrierten multi-divisionalen Investment Banking- und Asset Management-Institutionen geschlossen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-02-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2791</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29587</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29587</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2791/kukla_daniel.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
