<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2943">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2943</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Real Estate Valuation and Investment</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Immobilienbewertung und -investition</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wersing, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Real estate investments are among the most important investment decisions during the life of many private households. This is particular true for residential real estate investments, such as purchasing a single-family house. Uncertainties about future house prices imply that it is difficult to assess the future value of one of the most important sources of wealth for many households. To our understanding of households' investment decisions it is thus essential to measure real estate price risk. A fundamental problem of measuring real estate price risk is the valuation of residential real estate assets. This dissertation empirically analyzes valuation approaches for single-family houses, the measurement of market-wide movements in the price of housing, and the extent to which real estate price risk affects a household's investment decisions into residential real estate. An extensive database on real estate transactions in Berlin, Germany is used for the econometric analysis of different valuation approaches for single-family houses. Furthermore, data from the German Socio Economic Panel Study is used for the measurement of market-wide price movements, as well as the econometric analysis of private households' investment decisions.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Immobilieninvestionen sind eine der wichtigsten Anlageentscheidungen im Leben vieler privater Haushalte. Dies gilt insbesondere für den Erwerb von Wohnimmobilien, wie den Kauf eines Eigenheims. Unsicherheiten über zukünftige Hauspreise führen dazu, dass die Wertentwicklung eines Grossteils des privaten Vermögens nur schwierig abzuschätzen ist. Für unser Verständniss des Investionsverhaltens privater Haushalte ist die Messung von Immobilien-preisrisiken daher von fundamentaler Bedeutung. Ein grundlegendes Problem für die Erforschung von Immobilienpreisrisiken ist die Wertermittlung. Die vorliegende Dissertation analysiert empirisch Bewertungsverfahren für Wohnimmobilien, die Messung von den mit Immobilieninvestitionen verbundenen Preisrisiken und wie die Wirtschaftakteure in ihren Investitionsverhalten mit diesen Risiken umgehen. Für die ökonometrischen Analysen zur Wertermittlung wird auf eine umfangreiche Datenbank zu Berliner Einfamilienhaustransaktionen zurückgegriffen. Für die Messung von Immobilienpreisrisiken und für die ökonometrischen Analysen zu dem Investionsverhalten von privaten Haushalten werden die Daten des Sozio-ökonomischen Panels verwendet.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-06-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2943</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30804</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30804</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2943/wersing_martin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
