<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:28Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3063">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3063</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:330</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Investment Strategies for Climate Change Mitigation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Investitionsstrategien zur Vermeidung von Klimawandel </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baumstark, Lavinia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:330</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The substantial threat of anthropogenic climate change implies the reducing of greenhouse gas emissions. This thesis deals with the costs and strategies of climate change mitigation. In particular, investment strategies for climate change mitigation are investigated. The thesis is separated into five parts each focusing on subquestions of the overall research question. After an introduction into the problem of climate change and the important macro-economic mechanisms for mitigation, these subquestions are answered in separate chapters. For the analysis Integrated Assessment models are used. First, the impacts of technological spillovers under climate policies are analyzed by means of a multi-regional model with technological change in form of interregional spillovers. Model results indicate that the higher the ratio between the spillover intensities for energy and labour efficiency, the lower are mitigation costs. As well, first-mover advantages and commitment incentives for climate policy scenarios are investigated. A multi-regional hybrid model with a more complex energy system is used for studying investments into energy technologies in detail. In climate policy scenarios the entire energy consumption is reduced, while renewable energy and CCS technologies are expanded immediately. Different regions follow quite different mitigation strategies. While ambitious climate targets can be reached with moderate global costs, the regional costs show a high variance. In addition, Integrated Assessment models are used to investigate what happens if the world will not agree on a climate friendly policy within the next years. The impacts of early investments into renewable energy technologies in first-best and second-best worlds are analyzed. Mitigation costs increase significantly, if the climate policy implementation is delayed. In contrast, early deployment of renewable energy technologies reduces the global costs. Within a five-region hybrid model the impacts of dynamics and direction of technological change under climate change mitigation are studied. It turns out that mitigation costs and strategies are quite sensitive to these variables. Further experiments indicate that the impacts depend on the set of available technologies. For studying the role of endogenous technological change for climate change mitigation, this model is extended by a new formulation of efficiency improvements. It turns out that investments into the efficiency of some energy sectors play a crucial role for low mitigation costs. In climate policy scenarios, the increased mitigation costs of technological restrictions can be overcome by R&amp;D investments into energy efficiencies. However, the results of this thesis demonstrate the important role of investment strategies for climate change mitigation costs. The world gains from early investments into both a broad portfolio of technologies and energy efficiencies. Thereby the immediate support and high diversity of investments mainly provide low mitigation costs.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der anthropogene Klimawandel verlangt die Reduktion von Treibhausgasen. Diese Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit den Kosten und Strategien zur Vermeidung des Klimawandels. Dabei werden vor Allem Investitionsstrategien der Vermeidung untersucht. Die Arbeit is unterteilt in fünf Teile, die jeweils Unterfragen der allgemeinen Forschungsfrage untersuchen. Nach einer Einleitung in das Problem des Klimawandels und MakroÖkonomischen Mechanismen der Vermeidung werden diese Unterfragen in einzelnen Kapiteln beantwortet. Die Analyse basiert auf Integrated Assessment Modellen. Zuerst werden die Auswirkungen von technologischem Spillover in einem Mehrregionenmodell mit technologischem Wandel in Form von interregionalem Spillover analysiert. Modellergebnisse zeigen, daß je größer der Quotient zwischen Arbeits- und Energieeffizienz steigernden Spilloverintensität ist, desto geringer sind die Vermeidungskosten. Außerdem werden die Vorteile von Vorreitern und Anreize für eine Klimapolitik untersucht. Ein mehrregionales Hybridmodell mit einem detailierten Energiesystem wird benutzt, um die Investitionen in Energietechnologieen im Detail zu analysieren. In Klimapolitikszenarien wird der gesammte Energiekonsum verringert, während erneuerbare Energie und CCS Technologieen sofort ausgebaut werden. Verschiedene Regionen verfolgen grundsätzlich untershciedliche Vermeidungsstrategieen. Während ambitionierte Klimaschutzschranken zu moderaten globalen Kosten erreicht werden können, variieren die regionalen Kosten deutlich. Des Weiteren werden Integrated Assessment Modelle genutzt, um herauszufinden, was es bedeutet, wenn die Welt sich in den nächsten Jahren nicht auf eine klimafreundliche Politik einigen kann. Die Auswirkungen von frühzeitigen Investitionen in erneuerbare Energieen in erstbesten und zweitbesten Welten wird analysiert. Die Vermeidungskosten steigen signifikant, wenn die Implementierung von Klimapolitik verzögert wird. Hingegen verringert ein frühzeitiger Einsatz von erneuerbaren Energieen die globalen Kosten. In einem Hybridmodell mit fünf Regionen werden die Auswirkungen von Dynamik und Richtung des technologischen Wandels unter Klimapolitik untersucht. Es zeigt sich, daß die Vermeidungskosten und -strategieen sensitiv auf diese Variablen reagieren. Weitere Experimente deuten an, daß die Auswirkungen vom Spektrum der zur Verfügung stehenden Technologieen abhängt. Um die Rolle des endogenen technologischen Wandels für die Vermeidung des Klimawandels zu studieren, wird dieses Modell um eine neue Formulierung von Effizienssteigerungen erweitert. Es zeigt sich, daß Investitionen in die Effizienz von einigen Energiesektoren eine entscheidende Rolle für niedrige Vermeidungskosten spielen. In Klimapolitikszenarien können die durch technologische Einschränkungen erhöhten Vermeidungskosten durch F&amp;E Investitionen in die Energieeffiezienz reduziert werden. Wie auch immer, zeigen die Ergebnisse dieser Arbeit die wichtige Rolle von Investitionsstrategien für die Vermeidungskosten von Klimawandel. DieWelt profitiert von frühzeitigen Investitionen in eine große Bandbreite von Technologieen und in Energieeffizienz. Dabei erbringen vor allem die unmittelbare Förderung und die hohe Diversität der Investitionen niedrige Vermeidungskosten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-10-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3063</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31919</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31919</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3063/baumstark_lavinia.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-SA: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, Weitergabe zu gleichen Bedingungen</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
