<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:48Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2710">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2710</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">An analysis for some methods and algorithms of quantum chemistry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rohwedder, Thorsten</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In the field of ab-initio calculation of the properties of atoms, molecules and solids, the solution of the electronic Schrödinger equation, an operator eigenvalue equation for the Hamiltonian of the system, plays a major role. Of utmost significance is the lowest eigenvalue of H, representing the ground state energy of the system. To meet the requirements of the multitude of possible applications of the elctronic Schrödinger equation, the last decades have seen the development of a variety of different methods designed to approximate the solution of this extremely high-dimensional minimization problem. The aim of the present work is to deliver a (mathematical) analysis for some aspects of some of these methods used in the context of quantum chemistry. The work consists of four parts: The first part gives an introduction to the mathematical background, mainly belonging to the field of functional analysis, that is needed for the rigogous treatment of the electronic Schrödinger equation as an operator eigenvalue equation, and provides many of the technical means needed in the later chapters. The second part is concerned with a gradient algorithm with orthogonality constraints, which is used for the solution Hartree-Fock and Kohn-Sham equations playing an important role in the description of larger systems and which also serves for the algorithmic treatment of the CI method and - outside of the field of electronic structure calculation - for the calculation of invariant subspaces. The algorithm is formulated as an abstract method for the treatment of minimization problems on the so-called Grassmann manifold [1]; with the help of this formalism, linear convergence of the algorithm and quadratic convergence of the corresponding eigenvalues is proven. The third part of the work is concerned with the Coupled Cluster method, being of high practical significance in calculations where high accuracy is demanded. We lift the method, usually formulated as an ansatz for the approximation of the Galerkin solution in a finite dimensional, discretised subspace [2] to the continuous, undiscretised space, resulting in what we will call the continuous Coupled Cluster method. To define the continuous method, we first prove the continuity of the cluster operator T as an operator mapping the Sobolev space H1 to itself; with the help of this result, the infinite dimensional globalization of the canonical) Coupled Cluster equations can be formulated. Afterwards, we prove local strong monotonicity of the CC function, from which we derive existence and (local) uniqueness statements and a goal-oriented a-posteriori error estimator in the fashion of [3]. Finally, we discuss the algorithmic treatment of the CC root equation. The last part of this work features an analysis for the acceleration technique DIIS that is commonly used in quantum chemistry codes. We identify DIIS with a variant of a projected Broyden's method [4] and show that when applied to linear systems, the method can be interpreted as a variant of the well-known GMRES method. For the global nonlinear case, we finally prove two local convergence results and discuss the circumstances under which DIIS can show superlinear convergence. [1] T. A. Arias, A. Edelman, S. T. Smith, SIAM J. Matrix Anal. and Appl. 20, 2, 1999. [2] R. Schneider, Num. Math. 113, 3, 2009. [3] R. Becker, R. Rannacher, Acta Numerica 2000 (A. Iserlet, ed.), Cambridge University Press, 2001. [4] D. M. Gay, R. B. Schnabel, Nonlinear Programming 3, Academic Press, 1978.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der theoretischen Berechnung der Eigenschaften von Atomen, Molekülen und Festkörpern spielt die Lösung der elektronischen Schrödingergleichung, einer Operatoreigenwertgleichung für den Hamiltonoperator H des jeweiligen Systems, eine zentrale Rolle. Besondere Bedeutung kommt hierbei dem kleinsten Eigenwert von H zu, der die Grundzustandsenergie des Systems angibt. Um den unterschiedlichen Anforderungen in der Fülle von Anwendungsgebieten der elektronischen Schrödingergleichung gerecht zu werden, wurden in den letzten Jahrzehnten verschiedenste Näherungsverfahren entwickelt, um die Lösung dieses extrem hochdimensionalen Minimierungsproblems zu approximieren. Das Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit ist es, eine (mathematische) Analysis für Aspekte einiger der verwendeten Methoden der Quantenchemie zu liefern. Zu diesem Zweck gliedert sich die Arbeit in vier Teile: Der erste Teil gibt eine Einführung in den mathematischen, hauptsächlich der Funktionalanalysis zuzuschreibenden Hintergrund, der bei der Behandlung der elektronischen Schrödingergleichung als Operatoreigenwertgleichung notwendig ist, und stellt viele der in den späteren Kapiteln benötigten Handwerkszeuge zur Verfügung. Der zweite Teil beschäftigt sich mit einem Gradientenalgorithmus mit Orthogonalitätsnebenbedingungen, der zur der Lösung der in der Beschreibung größerer Systeme wichtigen Hartree-Fock- und Kohn-Sham-Gleichungen, aber auch zur algorithmischen Behandlung der CI-Methode und außerhalb der Elektronenstrukturberechnung in der Berechnung invarianter Unterräume verwendet wird. Wir formulieren den Algorithmus allgemeiner als Verfahren zur Behandlung von Minimierungsproblemen auf der sogenannten Grassmann-Mannigfaltigkeit [1] und beweisen mit Hilfe dieses Formalismus unter anderem lineare Konvergenz des Algorithmus und die quadratische Konvergenz der zugeh√∂rigen Energien. Im dritten Teil der Arbeit wird die in der Praxis für hochgenaue Rechnungen bedeutsame Coupled-Cluster-Methode, traditionell ein Ansatz zur Approximation der Galerkinlösung der Schrödingergleichung innerhalb einer gegebenen Diskretisierung [2], als Verfahren im unendlichdimensionalen, undiskretisierten Raum formuliert. Zu diesem Zweck wird zunächst die Stetigkeit des Clusteroperators T als Operator vom Sobolevraum H1 in sich bewiesen: hieraus lässt sich dann die (unendlichdimensionale Verallgemeinerung der bekannten) Nullstellengleichung für die Coupled-Cluster-Funktion formulieren. Wir zeigen die lokale starke Monotonie der CC-Funktion, mit deren Hilfe wir Existenz- und Eindeutigkeitsaussagen und einen zielorientierten Fehlerschätzer nach [3] beweisen. Schließlich diskutieren wir die algorithmische Behandlung der oben genannten Nullstellengleichung. Teil 4 beschäftigt sich mit der DIIS-Methode, einem im Rahmen der Quantenchemie standardmäßig verwendeten Verfahren zur Konvergenzbeschleuningung iterativer Algorithmen. Wir identifizieren DIIS mit einer Variante des projezierten Broyden-Verfahrens [4] und zeigen, dass sich das Verfahren, angewandt auf lineare Probleme, als Variante des GMRES-Verfahrens auffassen lässt. Für den allgemeinen Fall beweisen wir schließlich zwei lokale Konvergenzaussagen und diskutieren die Umstände, unter denen DIIS superlineares Konvergenzverhalten zeigen kann. [1] T. A. Arias, A. Edelman, S. T. Smith, SIAM J. Matrix Anal. and Appl. 20, 2, 1999. [2] R. Schneider, Num. Math. 113, 3, 2009. [3] R. Becker, R. Rannacher, Acta Numerica 2000 (A. Iserlet, ed.), Cambridge University Press, 2001. [4] D. M. Gay, R. B. Schnabel, Nonlinear Programming 3, Academic Press, 1978.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-11-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2710</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28521</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28521</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2710/rohwedder_thorsten.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
