<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:48:00Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:836">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:836</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Stochastic Heat Equation and Catalytic Super-Brownian Motion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zähle, Henryk</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit der Existenz von bestimmten stochastischen Prozessen mit unendlich-dimensionalen Zustandsräumen sowie mit Regularitätseigenschaften von deren Pfaden. Ein Hauptteil des Interesses gilt der 1-dimensionalen stochastischen Wärmeleitungsgleichung mit singulärem Drift, die durch ein inhomogenes weißes Zeit-Raum-Rauschen angetrieben wird. Das quadratische Variationsmaß des weißen Rauschens muss dabei weder im Raum noch in der Zeit absolut stetig bezüglich des Lebesguemaßes sein. Wir beweisen Aussagen über die Existenz, Eindeutigkeit und Nichtnegativität von stetigen Lösungen. Weiterhin beschäftigen wir uns mit der d-dimensionalen katalytischen super-Brownschen Bewegung (KSBB). Wir führen eine neue Zulässigkeitsbedingung für den Katalysator ein und zeigen verschiedene Eigenschaften der zugehörigen KSBB. Die Hauptfrage, die wir studieren, lautet: Für welche Katalysatoren und in welcher Dimension besitzt die KSBB ein stetiges (Lebesgue) Dichtefeld? Es stellt sich heraus, dass es in Dimension d=1 eine große Klasse von nichtatomaren Katalysatoren gibt, die ein reguläres Dichtefeld induzieren. Das letztgenannte kann als eindeutige schwache Lösung einer Version der oben beschriebenen stochastischen Wärmeleitungsgleichung charakterisiert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This thesis concerns the existence of certain stochastic processes with infinite-dimensional state spaces as well as regularity properties of their sample path. A main object of interest is the 1-dimensional stochastic heat equation with singular drift and driven by an inhomogeneous time-space white noise. The quadratic variation measure of the white noise is not required to be absolutely continuous w.r.t. the Lebesgue measure, neither in space nor in time. We prove statements on existence, uniqueness and non-negativity of continuous solutions. Another object of interest is the d-dimensional catalytic super-Brownian motion (CSBM). We introduce a new admissibility condition for the catalyst and establish various features of the corresponding CSBM. The main question we study is: For which catalysts and in which dimension does the CSBM possess a jointly continuous (Lebesgue) density field? As it turns out, in dimension d=1 there is a large class of non-atomic catalysts inducing a regular density field. The latter can be characterized as unique weak solution to a certain version of the stochastic heat equation described above.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2004-11-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/836</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-8290</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-8290</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/836/zaehle_henryk.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
