<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:36Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2660">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2660</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Continuum modeling, analysis and simulation of the self-assembly of thin crystalline films</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Kontinuumsmodellierung, Analysis und Simulation der Selbstorganisation dünner kristalliner Filme</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Korzec, Maciej Dominik</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Derivation of realistic continuum models for epitaxial growth of thin solid films on crystalline substrates yields Cahn-Hilliard type equations of fourth or sixth order. To describe and understand solutions and solution spaces to these semi- or quasilinear partial differential equations (PDEs), the development of elaborated theory is necessary. Existence of solutions has to be shown in untypical high order Sobolev spaces, the numerics has to be capable to deal with high order derivatives for the time-dependent problems and with high order phase spaces for the stationary case and methods of matched asymptotics require matching at many orders. In this work new theory is presented for reduced models of high order. For a sixth order PDE that describes the faceting of a growing surface in 2D it is shown that weak solutions exist. While for a related convective Cahn-Hilliard equation proving the existence of absorbing balls directly brings along existence of solutions, estimates for the sixth order model are more difficult to obtain since the anisotropic surface energy leads to undesired terms. The problem is solved by application of fractional operators to derive lower order bounds from a transformed equation, which are then used to obtain higher order bounds from the original equation. Next, new types of stationary solutions are found by an extension of a method of matched asymptotics where exponentially small terms are retained. By using this generalization of the ansatz by Lange, the hump spacing is related to the Lambert W function and analytical expressions are found for the far-field parameter in the limit of small driving force strength. These solutions live in a five dimensional phase space and a continuation technique allows to track them on branches in a parameter plane. The asymptotic solutions can be used as initial input for the numerical method. Numerical studies show that periodic and traveling wave solutions exist and that the characteristic wave number grows for increasing driving force strengths. A new model for the self-assembly of quantum dots has been derived. It extends an existing work by an anisotropic surface energy and an atomic flux such that realistic simulations of a Stranski-Krastanov growth can be carried out. A linear stability analysis to the fourth order quasilinear PDE shows the destabilizing effect of the anisotropy, which can also be observed in simulations based on a pseudospectral method. While in the work for the isotropic case single bell-shaped dots were calculated, here huge arrays - hundreds of faceted nanoislands - are simulated, so that the evolution of the structures can be compared to experiments. Higher flux rates yield bigger island densities and smaller dots are absorbed in favor of the bigger ones, resulting in an Ostwald ripening process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Bei der Herleitung von Kontinuumsmodellen für Wachstum von dünnen, kristallinen Filmen erhält man Gleichungen vom Cahn-Hilliard Typ vierter oder sechster Ordnung. Um die Lösungen und Lösungsräume dieser partiellen Differentialgleichungen (PDGLn) beschreiben zu können, ist ausgearbeitete Theorie vonnöten. Existenz von Lösungen muss in hohen Sobolevräumen gezeigt werden, die Numerik muss mit hohen Ableitungen umgehen können und bei der Methode angepasster Entwicklungen muss die Abgleichung in vielen Ordnungen passieren. In dieser Arbeit wird neue Theorie für reduzierte Modelle hoher Ordnung präsentiert. Für eine PDGL sechster Ordnung, die die Facettierung wachsender Oberflächen in 2D beschreibt wird die Existenz von Lösungen bewiesen. Während für eine verwandte konvektive Cahn-Hilliard Gleichung ein solches Ergebnis aus der Existenz absorbierender Bälle folgt, sind Abschätzungen für das Modell sechster Ordnungen schwieriger herzuleiten. Das Problem kann gelöst werden, indem gebrochene Operatoren angewendet werden, um Beschränkungen in Räumen niedrigerer Ordnung aus einer transformierten Gleichung zu erhalten. Hiermit zeigt man Beschränkungen in besseren Räumen. Als nächstes wurden neue stationäre Lösungen mit Hilfe einer erweiterten Methode von Lange gefunden, bei der exponentiell kleine Terme bei der Abstimmung beibehalten werden. Nulldurchläufe der Lösungen können zu der Lambert W Funktion bezogen werden und analytische Ausdrücke für das Fernfeld wurden im Limes verschwindender Abscheidungsraten gefunden. Die Lösungen befinden sich in einem fünf-dimensionalen Phasenraum und formen Lösungsäste in einer Parameterebene. Die asymptotischen Lösungen können als Input für die numerische Methode verwendet werden. Ein neues Modell zum Selbstzusammenbau von Quantenpunkten wurde hergeleitet. Es erweitert existierende Theorie indem anisotrope Oberflächenenergie und ein Atomfluss betrachtet werden, so dass realistische Simulationen von Stranski-Krastanov Wachstum durchgeführt werden können. Eine lineare Stabilitätsanalyse dieser quasilinearen PDGL vierter Ordnung zeigt den destabilisierenden Effekt der Anisotropie. Während in der Arbeit für den isotropen Fall einzelne glockenförmige Quantenpunkte berechnet wurden, werden hier sehr große Arrays - hunderte facetierter Nanoinseln - mit Hilfe einer Pseudospektralmethode simuliert. Höhere Flussraten resultieren in größeren Inseldichten und kleinere Punkte werden zu Gunsten größerer aufgesaugt, so dass ein realistischer Ostwald-Reifungsprozess statt findet.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-10-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2660</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2660/korzec_maciej.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
