<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2893">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2893</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Inexact Adaptive Finite Element Methods for Elliptic PDE Eigenvalue Problems</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Inexakte Adaptive Finite Elemente Methoden für elliptische PDE Eigenwertprobleme</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Miedlar, Agnieszka</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Since decades modern technological applications lead to challenging PDE eigenvalue problems, e.g., vibrations of structures, modeling of photonic gap materials, analysis of the hydrodynamic stability, or calculations of energy levels in quantum mechanics. Recently, a lot of research is devoted to the so-called Adaptive Finite Element Methods (AFEM). In most AFEM approaches it is assumed that the resulting finite dimensional algebraic problem (linear system or eigenvalue problem) is solved exactly and computational costs for this part of the method as well as the fact that they are solved in the finite precision arithmetic are typically ignored. The goal of this work is to analyze the influence of the accuracy of the algebraic approximation on the adaptivity process. Efficient and reliable adaptive algorithms should take into consideration not only discretization errors, but also iteration errors and especially for non-symmetric problems the conditioning of eigenvalues. Our new AFEMLA algorithm extends the standard AFEM approach to incorporate approximation errors into the adaptation process. Furthermore, we show that the adaptive mesh refinement may be steered by the discrete residual vector, e.g., when the problem is stated in a discrete formulation where only the underlying matrices and meshes are available. Moreover, we discuss how to reduce the computational effort of the iterative solver by adapting the size of the Krylov subspace. With classical perturbation results we prove upper bounds of the eigenvalue and the eigenfunction error. Under certain assumptions similar results are obtained for convection-diffusion problems. We introduce functional perturbation results for PDE eigenvalue problems including the functional backward error and the functional condition number. These results are used to establish a combined a posteriori error estimator embodying the discretization and the approximation error. Based on known perturbation results in H^{1}- and H^{−1}-norm and a standard residual a posteriori error estimator a balancing AFEM algorithm is proposed. The eigensolver stopping criterion is based on the equilibrating strategy, i.e., iterations proceed as long as the discrete part of the error estimator dominates the continuous part. A completely new approach combining the adaptive finite element method with the homotopy method is introduced to determine the particular eigenvalue of the convection-diffusion problem. The adaptive homotopy approach derived here emphasizes the need of the multi-way adaptation based on three different errors, the homotopy, the discretization and the iteration error. All our statements are illustrated with several numerical examples.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Seit Jahrzehnten führen technische Anwendungen, wie z.B. Strukturschwingungen, die Modellierung von photonische Bandlücke Materialien, Analyse von hydrodynamischer Stabilität oder die Berechnung von Energieleveln in der Quantenmechanik, auf PDE Eigenwertprobleme. Zur Zeit konzentriert sich die Forschung auf sogenannte Adaptive Finite Elemente Methoden (AFEM). In den meisten AFEM Ansätzen wird angenommen, dass das resultierende endlichdimensionale algebraische Problem (lineares Gleichungssystem oder Eigenwertproblem) exakt gelöst wird und der Berechnungsaufwand, sowie die Tatsache, dass die Lösungen nur in endlicher Genauigkeit vorliegen, wird vernachlässigt. Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, den Einfluss der Genauigket der algebraischen Approximation auf den adaptiven Prozess zu analysieren. Effiziente und verlässliche adaptive Algorithmen sollen betrachtet werden, d.h. nicht nur die Diskretisierungsfehler sondern auch die Iterationsfehler und insbesondere die Kondition der Eigenwerte für unsymmetrische Probleme müssen berücksichtigt werden. Unser neuer AFEMLA Algorithmus erweitert die üblichen AFEM Ansätze durch Berücksichtigung des Approximationsfehlers im adaptiven Prozess. Desweiteren zeigen wir, dass die adaptive Gitterverfeinerung durch den diskreten Residuenvektor gesteuert werden kann, z.B. wenn das Problem in diskreter Form gegeben ist und nur die zugrundeliegenden Matrizen und Gitter verfügbar sind. Wir zeigen, wie der Berechnungsaufwand des iterativen Lösers durch Anpassung der Dimension des Krylov-Unterraums reduziert werden kann. Mit Hilfe von klassischen Störungsresultaten beweisen wir obere Schranken für den Fehler in den Eigenwerten und Eigenfunktionen. Ähnliche Resultate werden für Konvektions-Diffusions Probleme angegeben. Wir betrachten funktionale Störungsresultate für PDE Eigenwertprobleme, d.h. funktionale Rückwärtsfehler und funktionale Konditionzahl. Diese Resultate werden verwendet um einen gemeinsamen a posteriori Fehlerschätzer zu entwickeln, der Diskretisierungs- und Approximationsfehler berücksichtigt. Basierend auf bekannten Störungsresultaten in der H^{1}- und H^{-1}-Norm und den residuenbasierten a posteriori Fehlerschätzern wurde ein balancierter AFEM Algorithmus entwickelt. Das Abbruchkriterium des Eigenwertlösers basiert auf Gleichgewichtsstrategien, d.h. die Iteration erfolgt so lange wie der diskrete Anteil des Fehlerschätzers den kontinuierlichen Anteil dominiert. Ein neuer Ansatz, der die Adaptive Finite Elemente Methode mit Homotopie verbindet, wird vorgestellt, um den Eigenwert des Konvektions-Diffusions Problems zu berechnen. Die entwickelte adaptive Homotopie hebt die Notwendigkeit von mehrfacher Adaptivität hervor, d.h. basierend auf den Homotopie-, Diskretisierungs- und Iterationsfehlern. Alle unsere Ergebnisse werden mit verschiedenen numerischen Beispielen illustriert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-05-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2893</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30598</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30598</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2893/miedlar_agnieszka.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
