<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:56Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3174">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3174</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Geometry, Kinematics, and Rigid Body Mechanics in Cayley-Klein Geometries</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Geometrie, Kinematik, und Mechanik starrer Körper in Cayley-Klein Geometrien</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gunn, Charles</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This thesis presents a modern formulation of rigid body mechanics in spaces of constant curvature. It consists of a theoretical and a practical part. It develops the necessary theory -- from projective geometry, exterior algebra, and quadratic forms -- required to describe a class of Cayley-Klein spaces including the three classical spaces of constant curvature: euclidean, elliptic, and hyperbolic. These n-dimensional Cayley-Klein geometries are then realized as real Clifford algebras constructed on the dual projectivized Grassmann algebras, of which only the euclidean case is degenerate. Poincare duality provides non-metric access to the standard Grassmann algebra. These Clifford algebras for n=2 and n=3 are described in detail. The role of non-simple bivectors and their connection to classical line geometry for n=3 receives particular attention. The isometry groups of these spaces are shown to be generated by proper reflections. These are then implemented as conjugation operators in the algebra, known as rotors, leading to the definition of pin (spin) groups as finite coverings of the indirect (direct) isometry groups. For n=3, the sub-algebra of scalars and pseudo-scalars is explored, leading to the definition of an axis of a bivector. This provides the key to an algorithm for calculating the logarithm of a rotor, and to its factorization as the product of two commuting rotations. Resulting connections to known results of Lie groups and Lie algebras are given. Equipped with these algebraic tools, kinematics and dynamics in these spaces is then explored. Isometric motions are defined. Taking derivatives of such motions in different coordinate systems leads to the Lie bracket, as the commutator product in the algebra. Bivectors act as Lie algebra elements; the induced vector field is decomposed as the composition of a null polarity and a metric polarity. Statics is briefly handled in this framework. Newtonian particles are defined in a metric-neutral way and the inertia tensor of such particles are calculated. Rigid bodies are constructed out of such particles. The inertia tensor of a rigid body, a positive definite quadratic form, is represented as a separate Clifford algebra. Conservation of energy and momentum of such a body under force-free motion leads to Euler equations for the motion, and numerical solutions are indicated. External forces and work are handled. Dual euclidean geometry is introduced in this framework, yielding a group of four geometries closed under dualization. Finally, the practical implementation and visualization results focused on rigid body motion simulations in elliptic and hyperbolic geometry are presented, first in the plane and then in space. The visualization environment is described, including what is displayed and how it is displayed. Results are shown featuring the orbit of the center of mass for a variety of initial conditions of body symmetry and momentum type (proper, ideal, improper). In the absence of a Poinsot theory of such motion, a phenomenological approach is used, combining qualitative observations with heuristic reasoning. Innovative visualizations of the polhode concludes this chapter. While the thesis is primarily concerned with establishing the kinematic and dynamic results, the development of the metric-neutral Clifford algebra toolkit for calculating in these Cayley-Klein geometries represents a separate innovative achievement of the thesis.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Arbeit präsentiert eine moderne Formulierung der Mechanik starrer Körper in Räumen konstanter Krümmung. Die Arbeit besteht aus einem theoretischen und einem praktischen Teil. Zunächst werden theoretische Grundlagen aus projektiver Geometrie, äußerer Algebra und quadratischen Formen vorgestellt, um darauf aufbauend eine Klasse von Cayley-Klein Räumen zu beschreiben. Diese Klasse enthält die drei klassischen Räume konstanter Krümmung (euklidisch, elliptisch und hyperbolisch). Die entsprechenden n-dimensionalen Cayley-Klein Geometrien werden dann als reelle Clifford-Algebren realisiert. Diese Algebren werden aus dem Dual der projektivierten Grassmann Algebra konstruiert, wobei der ausgeartete euklidische Fall eine besondere Stellung einnimmt. Als nächstes, wird gezeigt, dass die Isometriegruppen dieser Räume konstanter Krümmung durch eigentliche Spiegelungen erzeugt sind. Diese Spiegelungen werden als Konjugationsoperatoren der Form in der Algebra, realisiert, was zur Definition von Pin (Spin) Gruppen als endliche überlagerungen der indirekten (direkten) Isometriegruppen führt. Für n = 3 wird die Sub-Algebra der Skalare und Pseudoskalare untersucht und die Definition der Achse eines Bivectors gegeben. Als Ergebnis erhält man einen Algorithmus zur Berechnung des Logarithmus eines Rotors (Element der Spin-Gruppe). Zusammenhänge zu bekannten Ergebnissen über Lie-Gruppen und Lie-Algebren werden erläutert. Ausgestattet mit diesen algebraischen Werkzeugen, werden anschließend Kinematik und Dynamik in diesen Räumen erforscht. Die zugehörige Lie-Klammer wird, wie üblich, als Kommutator (der Bivektoren) beschreiben. Das von einem Bivektor induzierte Vektorfeld wird eindeutig in eine null Polarität und die dem betrachteten Raum zugrundeliegende metrische Polarität zerlegt. Newtonsche Partikel werden auf eine metrisch-neutrale Art und Weise definiert und starre Körper werden als aus solchen Partikeln aufgebaut verstanden. Es wird gezeigtl, wie der Trägheitstensor eines starren Körpers eine separate Clifford Algebra induziert, deren 1-Vektoren Elemente von sind. Energie- und Impulserhaltung eines solchen Körpers unter Abwesenheit externer Kräfte führt zu den Euler-Gleichungen der Bewegung. Der Einfluss externer Kräfte und die entsprechend verrichtete Arbeit werden ebenfalls betrachtet. Der praktische Teil der Arbeit behandelt im Wesentlichen die Visualisierung der Ergebnisse. Es werden Simulationen in elliptischer und hyperbolischer Geometrie vorgestellt, zunächst in der Ebene und anschließend im 3-dimensionale Raum. Es werden Beispiele für eine Vielzahl von Randbedingungen (Körper-Symmetrie bzw. Impuls-Typ) präsentiert. In Ermangelung einer Poinsot Theorie der zu beschreibenden Bewegung wird ein phänomenologischer Ansatz verwendet, um einige qualitative Beobachtungen mit heuristischen Argumentationen zu begründen. Innovative Visualisierungen der Polhodie (der Achsen der instantanen Geschwindigkeiten) bilden den Schluss des praktischen Teils. Während die Arbeit in erster Linie der Ausarbeitung der kinematischen und dynamischen Ergebnisse gewidmet ist, stellt die Entwicklung des metrik-neutralen Clifford-Algebra-Toolkits für das Rechnen in Cayley-Klein-Geometrien eine eigene innovative Leistung der Dissertation dar.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-12-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3174</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33228</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33228</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3174/gunn_charles.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
