<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:38Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3320">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3320</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Optimal boundary control of quasilinear elliptic partial differential equations: theory and numerical analysis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Optimale Randsteuerung quasilinearer elliptischer partieller Differentialgleichungen: Theorie und numerische Analysis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dhamo, Vili</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This thesis is concerned with a class of optimal control problems governed by quasilinear elliptic partial differential equations (PDEs) with inhomogeneous Neumann boundary conditions. The boundary datum will be considered as the control variable which must satisfy given inequality constraints. Control of equations of this type is interesting, because in many practical applications of optimal control theory to problems in engineering and medical science the underlying PDEs are quasilinear; for instance, in models of heat conduction, where the heat conductivity coefficient depends on the spatial coordinate and on the temperature of the system. The quasilinear equation under consideration is not monotone, because the leading coefficient of the differential operator is dependent on the solution of the equation. Control problems with quasilinear elliptic equations of non-monotone type were recently considered by Casas and Tröltzsch. The authors have treated the case of distributed controls and their contributions include not only the derivation of necessary and sufficient optimality conditions but also the analysis of the numerical approximation of those control problems. It is known that in the case of boundary controls the analysis is more difficult, since the regularity of the states is lower than that of distributed controls. The goal of the present work is to extend the results obtained by Casas and Tröltzsch to the case of Neumann boundary controls problems in polygonal domains of dimension two. In order to tackle different aspects of the theoretical and numerical analysis of the control problem, it is necessary to perform a comprehensive study of the well-posedness of the state equation and further to analyze the differentiability of the control-to-state mapping. The first chapter deals with these topics as well as contains some useful regularity results concerning the adjoint state equation. Chapter 2 is dedicated to the finite-element based approximation of the state and adjoint state equation. Our main focus is the error analysis for these approximations. A serious difficulty in this analysis is that the uniqueness of a solution of the discrete quasilinear equation is an open problem. To overcome this difficulty a local uniqueness result can be provided which is sufficient for further investigations. In Chapter 3, the optimal control problem associated with the quasilinear equation is formulated and the question of existence of solutions is answered positively. Furthermore, first- and second-order optimality conditions are established and some higher regularity results for optimal controls are derived. Chapter 4 contains the numerical analysis of the control problem. Approximating the state and adjoint state by finite elements of degree one and the control by step functions, the strong convergence of discrete local optimal controls to a strict local optimal control of the continuous problem can be shown. Finally, the error analysis for the optimal controls is carried out and confirmed by numerical experiments. In the last chapter, some extensions of the results concerning the numerical approximation of the quasilinear equation to three-dimensional polyhedral domains are presented.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit Optimalsteuerungsproblemen von quasilinearen elliptischen partiellen Differentialgleichungen mit inhomogenen Neumann-Randbedingungen. Das Randdatum wird als Kontrollvariable aufgefasst und muss vorgegebenen Ungleichungsrestriktionen genügen. Die Steuerung von quasilinearen Gleichungen ist interessant, denn in vielen praktischen Anwendungen der Theorie der optimalen Steuerung in Ingenieur- und Medizinwissenschaften die zugrunde liegenden partiellen Differentialgleichungen sind quasilinear. Zum Beispiel in Modellen der Wärmeleitung, in denen der Wärmeleitfähigkeitskoeffizient von räumlichen Koordinaten aber auch von der Temperatur des Systems abhängt. Die hier untersuchte quasilineare Gleichung ist nicht monoton, weil der Hauptkoeffizient des Differentialoperators selbst von der Lösung der Differentialgleichung abhängt. Die optimale Steuerung von nicht monotonen quasilinearen elliptischen Gleichungen ist erst vor Kurzem von Casas und Tröltzsch untersucht worden. Die Autoren haben den Fall verteilter Steuerungen behandelt und ihr Beitrag umfasst nicht nur die Herleitung von notwendigen und hinreichenden Optimalitätsbedingungen, sondern auch die Analysis der numerischen Approximation solcher Probleme. Es ist aber bekannt, dass im Falle der Randsteuerung die Analysis komplizierter ist, da die Zustandsfunktionen eine niedrigere Regularität aufweisen als jene verteilter Steuerungen. Das Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit ist die Erweiterung der Ergebnisse von Casas und Tröltzsch auf den Fall von optimalen Neumann-Randsteuerungsproblemen in zweidimensionalen, polygonal berandeten Gebieten. Um verschiedene Aspekte der theoretischen und numerischen Analysis von Optimalsteuerungsproblemen zu diskutieren, ist eine umfangreiche Untersuchung der Wohldefiniertheit der Zustandsgleichung und der Differenzierbarkeit des Steuerungs-Zustands-Operators notwendig. Diese Themen sind Gegenstand des ersten Kapitels, welches auch einige nützliche Ergebnisse zur Regularität der adjungierten Zustandsgleichung enthält. Kapitel 2 widmet sich der Finite-Elemente-Approximation der Zustands- und adjungierten Zustandsgleichung. Der Schwerpunkt wird dabei auf die Fehleranalysis dieser Approximation gelegt. Dass die Eindeutigkeit der Lösung der diskreten quasilinearen Gleichung ein offenes Problem ist, stellt eine ernste Schwierigkeit dar. Um diese Schwierigkeit zu überwinden, wird eine lokale Eindeutigkeitsaussage bewiesen, welche für die weitere Diskussion ausreichend ist. Im dritten Kapitel wird nun das zur quasilinearen Gleichung gehörige Optimalsteuerungsproblem formuliert und die Frage der Lösbarkeit des Problems positiv beantwortet. Darüber hinaus werden Optimalitätsbedingungen erster und zweiter Ordnung hergeleitet sowie eine Regularitätsaussage für optimale Steuerungen bewiesen. Kapitel 4 beschäftigt sich mit der numerischen Analysis des Optimalsteuerungsproblems. Für die Approximation des Zustands und adjungierten Zustands durch finite Elemente erster Ordnung und der Steuerung durch stückweise konstante Funktionen wird die Konvergenz von diskreten lokalen Lösungen gegen eine strikte lokal optimale Steuerung des kontinuierlichen Problems gezeigt. Abschließend wird die Fehleranalysis für optimale Steuerungen aufgeführt und durch numerische Experimente bestätigt. Im letzten Kapitel werden einige Erweiterungen der Ergebnisse der numerischen Approximation der quasilinearen Gleichung auf dreidimensionale, polyedrisch berandete Gebiete präsentiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3320/dhamo_vili.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
