<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2039">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2039</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Polyhedral Surfaces, Polytopes, and Projections</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Polyedrische Flächen, Polytope und Projektionen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rörig, Thilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The main focus of the thesis is the construction of polyhedral surfaces and polytopes with interesting combinatorial and geometric properties. Using projections of high-dimensional polytopes, we obtain particular embeddings of surfaces. Furthermore we develop a new method that allows us to show, that not all of the surfaces constructed or skeleta of particular polytopes may be embedded in low-dimensional space using projections. After a short introduction of the basic definitions in Chapter 1 we introduce two new methods in Chapter 2. In Section 2.1 we explain a method that allows us to prove that certain subcomplexes of high-dimensional polytopes cannot be preserved by certain projections: We associate a simplicial complex embedded in a polytopal sphere to the complex that should be preserved under projection. By showing that this associated complex does not embed into any sphere of the appropriate dimension we deduce that the chosen subcomplex cannot survive the projection. In Section 2.2 we describe a new method to parametrize the realization space of a simple polytope. Using this parametrization we obtain lower bounds on the dimensions of the realization spaces of polytopes and subcomplexes that are obtained via projections of simple polytopes. In Chapter 3 we analyze the projectability of polytope skeleta. The starting point of this investigation is the observation, that there exists no realization of the product of two triangles such that a projection to the plane preserves all 9 vertices. Using the method of Section 2.1 we generalize this result to arbitrary skeleta of products of simplices and products of polygons. These results complement previous work of Ziegler (2004) and Sanyal &amp; Ziegler (2007) on products of polygons. We start Chapter 4 by defining the wedge product of two polytopes. The 2-skeleta of the wedge products of p-gons and a (q-1)-simplices contain regular surfaces of type {p,2q}, i.e. all faces are p-gons and all vertices have degree 2q. This family of surfaces comprises known families of Coxeter (1937) and McMullen, Schulz &amp; Wills (1983). We construct realizations of the wedge products of p-gons and 1-simplices containing the surfaces of McMullen, Schulz &amp; Wills. These realizations yield new embeddings of the surfaces of type {p,4} in 3-space via orthogonal projections. Hence we are able to use the method developed in Section 2.2 to get non-trivial lower bounds on the number of moduli of these embeddings. Additionally, we are able to realize the prisms over the surfaces in the boundaries of a 4-polytopes. Hence we obtain embeddings of the dual surfaces of type {4,p} in the Schlegel diagrams of the dual polytopes. For q &gt;= 3 and p &gt;= 4 we prove that we cannot obtain realizations of the surfaces in the boundaries of a 4-polytopes via projections of the corresponding wedge products. In Chapter 5 we deal with two types of Hamiltonian surfaces in the products of even polygons. The first family consist of regular surfaces and contains all surfaces of type {4,p} of McMullen, Schulz &amp; Wills (1983). The surfaces of the second family are not regular any more, but they have arbitrarily large vertex degree and an average polygon size arbitrarily close to 8. All these surfaces may be embedded in 3-space via orthogonal projections of deformed realizations of the corresponding products of polygons. A related question by Brehm &amp; Wills is, whether there exist embeddings of surfaces of type {p,q} in 3-space for p &gt; 4 and q &gt; 4. Our realizations do not answer this question, but yield surfaces with arbitrary vertex degree and polygon size of approximately 8. Similar to the previous chapter we obtain lower bounds on the number of moduli via the method of Section 2.2. Further we are again able to use polytope duality to obtain realizations of the dual surfaces in 3-space as well. The starting point of Chapter 6 are the "Ukrainian easter eggs" of Eppstein (Geometry Junkyard). These "easter eggs" are 3-dimensional zonotopes with a central cut of asymptotically maximal size. We construct d-dimensional dual zonotopes with n zones that have a projection to a polygon with O(n^(d-1)) vertices. Via duality this yields d-dimensional zonotopes on n zones with a 2-dimensional central cut with O(n^(d-1)) vertices and edges. These zonotopes are also interesting with respect to the arrangement method of Koltun (2006) for linear programming. The new methods of Chapter 2 were developed together with Raman Sanyal (Section 2.1) and Günter M. Ziegler (Section 2.2). Chapter 3 is joint work with Raman Sanyal. The polyhedral surfaces and wedge products of Chapter 4 have been worked out together with Günter M. Ziegler. Chapter 6 was written in collaboration with Nikolaus Witte and Günter M. Ziegler and is published in Discrete &amp; Computational Geometry.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Im Zentrum dieser Arbeit steht die Konstruktion von polyedrischen Flächen bzw. Polytopen mit besonderen kombinatorischen und geometrischen Eigenschaften. Dabei benutzen wir Projektionen von hoch-dimensionalen Polytopen, um besondere Einbettungen von Flächen zu erhalten. Darüberhinaus wird eine neue Methode entwickelt mit der gezeigt wird, dass nicht alle konstruierten Flächen oder auch Skelette von bestimmten Polytopen mittels Projektionen eingebettet werden können. Nach einer kurzen Einführung in Kapitel 1 stellen wir in Kapitel 2 zwei neue Methoden vor. In Abschnitt 2.1 (Zusammenarbeit mit Raman Sanyal) erklären wir eine Methode, die es uns ermöglicht zu zeigen, dass manche Teilkomplexe von hoch-dimensionalen Polytopen unter Projektion nicht erhalten bleiben können. Dazu assozieren wir einen Komplex zu dem zu erhaltenen Teilkomplex. Wenn nun der Teilkomplex unter Projektion erhalten bleibt, dann hat dieser assoziierte Komplex eine Einbettung in eine polytopale Sphäre. Also kann eine solche Projektion nicht existieren, falls der assoziierte Komplex keine Einbettung in die passende Sphäre erlaubt. In Abschnitt 2.2 (Zusammenarbeit mit Günter M. Ziegler) beschreiben wir eine neue Methode, um den Realisierungsraum eines einfachen Polytops zu parametrisieren. Damit erhalten wir untere Schranken für die Dimension des Realisierungsraums von Polytopen und Komplexen, die durch generische Projektionen von einfachen Polytopen entstehen. In Kapitel 3 (Zusammenarbeit mit Raman Sanyal) analysieren wir die Projizierbarkeit von Polytopskeletten. Mittels einer Spezialisierung der Methode aus Abschnitt 2.1 können wir nun Projizierbarkeitsresultate für beliebige Skelette von Produkten von Polygonen und Produkten von Simplizes beweisen. Dies ergänzt die Resultate von Ziegler (2004) und Sanyal &amp; Ziegler (2007), welche sich mit deformierten Produkten von Polygonen mit gerader Eckenanzahl beschäftigen. In Kapitel 4 (Zusammenarbeit mit Günter M. Ziegler) führen wir zunächst Keilprodukte (wedge products) von zwei Polytopen ein. Das 2-Skelett des Keilprodukts eines p-Ecks mit einem (q-1)-Simplex enthält eine reguläre Fläche vom Typ {p;2q}, d.h. eine reguläre Fläche aus p-Ecken und mit konstantem Eckengrad 2q. Diese Familie von Flächen beinhaltet bereitsbekannte Flächen von Coxeter (1937) bzw. von McMullen, Schulz &amp; Wills (1983). Für das Keilprodukt, welches die Flächen von McMullen, et. al. enthält, geben wir eine spezielle deformierte Realisierung an. Diese Realisierung liefert neue Einbettungen der Flächen vom Typ {p;4} mittels orthogonalen Projektionen in den 3-dimensionalen Raum. Daher ist es uns möglich die Methode aus Abschnitt 2.2 zu verwenden, um nicht triviale untere Schranken für die Freiheitsgrade unserer Einbettungen anzugeben. Da wir auch das Prisma über der Fläche im Rand eines 4-Polytops realisieren können, erhalten wir zusätzlich Einbettungen der dualen Flächen vom Typ {4;p}. Für p &gt;= 4 und q &gt;= 3 beweisen wir, dass man mittels Projektion des passenden Keilproduktes keine Einbettungen der Flächen im Rand eines 4-Polytops erhalten kann. Kapitel 5 beschäftigt sich mit zwei Familien von hamiltonschen Flächen in Produkten von Polygonen mit gerader Eckenanzahl. Die erste Familie besteht aus regulären Flächen und enthält alle polyedrischen Flächen vom Typ {4;q} von McMullen, et. al. (1983). Die Flächen der zweiten Familie sind zwar nicht regulär, aber sie haben einen beliebig hohen Eckengrad und eine durchschnittliche Polygongröße, die sich 8 annähert. Alle diese Flächen können durch Projektionen von deformierten Produkten im 3-dimensionalen Raum eingebettet werden. Eine verwandte offene Frage von Brehm &amp; Wills ist, ob es für p &gt; 4 und q &gt; 4 eingebettete Flächen vom Typ {p;q} im 3-dimensionalen Raum gibt. Die Einbettungen der zweiten Familie von Flächen im 3-dimensionalen Raum liefern zwar keine Antwort, aber immerhin Flächen mit beliebig hohem Eckengrad und durchschnittlicher Polygongröße von ~ 8. Wie im vorherigen Kapitel erhalten wir eine untere Schranke für die Anzahl der Freiheitsgrade unserer Realisierungen. Außerdem können wir wiederum Dualität von 4-Polytopen verwenden, um Einbettungen der dualen Flächen zu erhalten. Ausganspunkt für die Konstruktionen in Kapitel 6 (Zusammenarbeit mit Nikolaus Witte und Günter M. Ziegler) sind die "ukrainischen Ostereier" von Eppstein. Diese "Ostereier" sind 3-dimensionale Zonotope, die einen zentralen Schnitt von asymptotisch maximaler Größe erlauben. Wir konstruieren duale d-dimensionale Zonotope mit n Zonen, die als 2-dimensionale Projektionen Polygone mit O(n^(d-1)) Ecken haben. Mittels Dualität erhalten wir daraus d-dimensionale Zonotope mit n Zonen, die einen 2-dimensionale Schnitt mit O(n^(d-1)) Ecken und Kanten haben.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-01-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21451</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21451</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2039/original_roerig_thilo.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2039/roerig_thilo.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
