<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1544">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1544</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:660</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">A pore-flow-through membrane reactor for selective hydrogenation reactions</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ein Porendurchflussmembranreaktor für selektive Hydrierungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmidt, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:660</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">A membrane reactor in pore-flow-though (PFT) mode was developed for selective hydrogenation reactions with the aim to increase yield, selectivity and space-time-yield compared to conventional fixed bed or slurry reactors that represent state of the art. Mass transfer limitations like internal pore diffusion that often occur in porous catalyst pellets can be prevented by forcing the reactants through the pores of a membrane which results in increasing the effective reaction rate and suppressing side reactions. The catalytically active membranes were prepared by chemical wet impregnation of Al2O3-membrane tubes with a noble metal precursor. Characterization included AAS, SEM, TEM and EPMA. The partial hydrogenation of 1,5-cyclooctadiene served as a model reaction for a detailed study of process parameters like flow velocity, membrane pore size and catalyst loading. Intrinsic kinetics for this reaction was studied in a wide range of operating conditions with a Pd/alumina powder catalyst in a slurry reactor. The selectivity for cyclooctene obtained in the membrane reactor was 95 % at complete conversion which exceeds the selectivity obtained in a fixed bed with common catalyst pellets. A mathematical model was developed for simulation of the hydrogenation of 1,5-cyclooctadiene in the membrane reactor and to predict the performance of the hydrogenation process under different operating conditions. The proposed model can predict the influence of circulation rate and Pd-content of the membranes that were verified experimentally. A scale-up from the laboratory experimental setup with a single capillary (membrane area: 20 cm²) to a pilot plant with bundles of 27-capillaries (membrane area: 540 cm²) was accomplished by multiplication of the volume of the liquid phase, the membrane area and the circulation rate. The application of the membrane reactor for industrially important hydrogenation reactions was tested for the fat hardening process, the partial hydrogenation of alkynes, the selective hydrogenation of geraniol, an allylic terpenic alcohol, and the selective hydrogenation of cinnamaldehyde, an unsaturated aldehyde. For the partial hydrogenation of the alkynes higher alkene selectivities were obtained in the PFT-reactor than in a fixed bed reactor. The selective hydrogenation of geraniol to citronellol failed because of severe deactivation of the catalytic membranes. The partial hydrogenation of polyunsaturated fatty acids in sunflower oil in the PFT-reactor resulted in a significantly lower content of saturated fatty acids than in a slurry reactor but the formation of trans fatty acids could not be prevented. The hydrogenation of cinnamaldehyde was carried out with selectivities of 80 % for the saturated aldehyde at complete conversions but at extremely low reaction rates compared to an egg shell catalyst in a slurry reactor. Deactivation of catalytic membranes was found to be more pronounced than of the egg shell catalyst.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Ein Membranreaktor im Porendurchflussmodus (PFT-Reaktor) wurde für selektive Hydrierungen mit dem Ziel entwickelt, Ausbeute, Selektivität und Raum-Zeit-Ausbeute gegenüber konventionellen Festbett- und Slurry-Reaktoren, die momentan den Stand der Technik repräsentieren, zu erhöhen. Stofftransportlimitierungen durch Porendiffusion, die häufig in porösen Katalysatorpellets auftreten, können vermieden werden, wenn das Reaktionsgemisch konvektiv durch die Poren einer Membran strömt. Dadurch können Nebenreaktionen vermieden und die effektive Reaktionszeit verkürzt werden. Katalytisch aktive Membranen wurden durch nasschemische Imprägnierung von Al2O3-Röhrchen mit entsprechenden Edelmetall-Precursoren hergestellt. Die Charakterisierung umfasste AAS, REM, TEM und EPMA. Die partielle Hydrierung von 1,5-Cyclooktadien diente als Modellreaktion für die detaillierte Studie von Prozessparametern wie Fließgeschwindigkeit, Porengröße und Katalysatorbeladung. Die intrinsische Kinetik für diese Reaktion wurde in einem weiten Bereich von Reaktionsbedingungen mit einem Pd/Al2O3-Pulverkatalysator in einem Slurry-Reaktor untersucht. Die Selektivität für Cyclooktadien, die in dem Membranreaktor erreicht wurde, betrug bei vollständigem Umsatz 95 %. Dies übertrifft die Selektivität, die mit gewöhnlichen Katalysatorpellets in einem Festbettreaktor erzielt werden. Ein mathematisches Modell wurde entwickelt, um die Hydrierung von 1,5-Cyclookten im Membranreaktor zu simulieren und um den Ablauf der Reaktion unter verschiedenen Reaktionsbedingungen hervorsagen zu können. Das vorgeschlagene Modell bildet die experimentell beobachteten Einflüsse von Volumenstrom durch die Membran und Pd-Gehalt der Membran gut ab. Ein Scale-Up vom Labormaßstab mit einer Einzelkapillare (Membranfläche: 20 cm²) in den Pilotmaßstab mit 27-Kapillarbündeln (Membranfläche: 540 cm²) wurde durchgeführt, indem das Flüssigkeitsvolumen, die Membranfläche und die Durchflussrate jeweils um den Faktor 27 erhöht wurden. Die Anwendung des Membranreaktors für industriell interessante Hydrierungsreaktionen wurde für die Fetthärtung, die partielle Hydrierung von Alkinen, für die selektive Hydrierung von Geraniol und Zimtaldehyd getestet. Für die partielle Hydrierung der Alkine wurden im PFT-Reaktor höhere Selektivitäten erzielt als in einem Festbettreaktor. Die selektive Hydrierung von Geraniol zu Citronellol scheiterte im PFT-Reaktor wegen einer starken Deaktivierung der katalytischen Membranen. Für die partielle Hydrierung von mehrfach ungesättigten Fettsäuren im Sonnenblumenöl war der Gehalt von gesättigten Fettsäuren im PFT-Reaktor sehr viel geringer als in einem Slurry-Reaktor. Die Bildung von trans-Fettsäuren konnte im PFT-Reaktor allerdings nicht verhindert werden. Die Hydrierung von Zimtaldehyd lief im PFT-Reaktor viel langsamer als im Slurry-Reaktor, aber mit vergleichbaren Selektivitäten für den gesättigten Aldehyd ab; die Deaktivierung war in der Membran stärker ausgeprägt als mit den Katalysatorpellets.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-07-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1544</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16097</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16097</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1544/original_schmidt_andrea.docx</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1544/schmidt_andrea.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
