<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:52Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3819">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3819</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-10-28</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">New synthetic methodologies using enyne olefin metathesis : application in natural product synthesis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Neue Synthesemethoden unter Verwendung der Enin Olefin Metathese : Anwendung in der Naturstoffsynthese</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Porta Garcia, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The presented investigations deal with three related topics regarding metathesis methodology with amine-containing compounds. The main focus of this work lies on the application of diastereoselective ring-rearrangement metathesis (enyne dRRM) in the synthesis of naturally occurring 5,8-disubstituted indolizidine alkaloids. Starting from cheap chiral-pool-substances such as (S)-proline and (S)-glutamic acid, different bicyclic substrates containing a prochiral C-5-thethered cycloolefine have been prepared and subjected to metathesis studies. For amide-based compounds, diastereoselectivity can be controlled by means of catalyst choice. A wide range of commercially available complexes as well as recently developed Ru-catalysts have been screened, and values of diastereoselectivity from 1:10 to 4:1 (cis:trans) have been obtained. For the particular case of amine-based substrates, the Lewis basic character of the nitrogen atom can be overcome by formation of the corresponding ammonium salt to avoid catalyst deactivation. For the first time in metathesis transformations, it has been demonstrated that the counterion of such ammonium salts play an important role in the reaction outcome. After extensive substrate screening it has been possible to control the dr, obtaining values from 1:3 (cis:trans) to complete selectivity towards the desired cis-diastereoisomer. These results were next applied in the concise synthesis of C-5 and C-8 epimers of indolizidines 223J, 219F and 223AA. Further investigations towards indolizidine 193E and 1,4-disubstituted quinolizidines have been performed and further synthetic studies have been proposed for the conclusion of such approaches. The second part of this work is an investigation into the influence of the counterion on metathesis reactions with structurally different ammonium salts, including dRRM. From the obtained results it can be concluded that the use of Brønsted acids is a very effective methodology for avoiding catalyst deactivation when unprotected amines are used as substrates in metathesis. Further, it has been proven that the counterion plays an important role in the outcome of the metathesis reaction. For the investigated transformations, ammonium salts derived from HBF4 and pTSA furnished better conversion towards the desired product than the substrates obtained by reaction with HCl. Trifluoromethane sulfonic acid salts have been used for the first time in metathesis reactions and have shown, for certain substrates, to deliver improved results in terms of conversion and selectivity. The last part of the presented research deals with the development of a hydroamination-alkyne addition-metathesis sequence which is based on the combination of DBI-Zn-complexes with ruthenium-based metathesis catalysts. This methodology enables the formation of unsaturated N-heterocycles in an one-pot procedure, and is one of the few examples on both bi-catalyzed hydroamination and bi-catalyzed metathesis one-pot reactions, being the first report of a Zn-Ru sequential catalysis. The described transformation is suitable for benzylic amines, anilines and other heterocyclic amines and the products obtained, as well as further possible synthetic derivatives, are amine-containing compounds that resemble the structural core of different natural products.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurden verschiedene Metatheseverfahren durchgeführt, wobei Aminoderivate als Substrate umgesetzt wurden. Der Schwerpunkt dieser Untersuchungen liegt in der Anwendung der neu entwickelten diastereoselektiven Ringumlagerungsmetathese (dRRM) in der Synthese von 5,8-disubstituierten-Indolizidinalkaloiden. Ausgehend von preiswerten „chiral-pool“-Verbindungen wie (S)-Prolin und (S)-Glutaminsäure wurde eine Reihe von Vorläufer, die ein prochirales C-5-Cycloolefin enthalten, synthetisiert und in der Metathese eingesetzt. Mit auf Amiden basierenden Substraten konnte die Diastereoselektivität durch die Verwendung unterschiedlicher Ru-Komplexe kontrolliert werden wobei Diastereomeren-verhältnisse von 1:10 bis 4:1 (cis:trans) erhalten wurde. Dabei wurde sowohl eine große Vielfalt kommerziell erhältlicher, als auch einige neu entwickelte Präkatalysatoren eingesetzt. Im Falle der aminbasierenden Substrate konnte der Lewis-basische Charakter des Stickstoffs durch die Bildung des korrespondierenden Ammoniumsalzes beseitigt, und somit eine Deaktivierung des Katalysators vermieden werden. Zum ersten Mal konnte in einer Metathesereaktion gezeigt werden, dass das Gegenion einen großen Einfluss auf die Diastereoselektivität bei der Produktbildung haben kann. Nach ausführlichem Substratscreening war es möglich, die Reaktion so zu steuern, dass Selektivitäten von 1:3 (cis:trans) bis hin zur vollständigen Bildung des gewünschten cis-Diastereoisomers erhalten werden konnten. Das synthetische Potenzial dieser Metathesereaktion fand in der kurzen Totalsynthese der C-5- und C-8-Epimere der Indolizidine 223J, 219F and 223AA erfolgreiche Anwendung. Weitere Studien zur Synthese des Naturstoffes 193E und weiterer 1,4-disubstitutuierter Quinolizidine wurden angestellt. Im zweiten Teil dieser Arbeit wurde der Einfluss des Gegenions bei der Verwendung verschiedener Ammoniumsalze in diversen Metathesereaktionen, die dRRM eingeschlossen, untersucht. Aus den Ergebnissen kann geschlossen werden, dass die Verwendung von Brønstedsäuren eine effektive Methode zur Vermeidung der Deaktivierung des Katalysators ist, die bei Einsatz von freien Aminen in der Metathese stattfinden würde. Außerdem wurde gezeigt, dass die Wahl des Gegenions Einfluss auf die Produktbildung hat, wobei die Ammoniumsalze von HBF4 und pTSA bessere Ergebnisse lieferten, als die entsprechenden Hydrochloride. Die Salze der Trifluormethansulfonsäure wurden erstmals in einer Metathesereaktion eingesetzt und zeigten bei einigen Substraten eine Verbesserung des Umsatzes und der Selektivität. Der letzte Abschnitt befasst sich mit der Entwicklung einer neuartigen Synthesesequenz, die Hydroaminierung, Alkynylierung und Metathese in sich vereint. Erstmals konnten in einem Verfahren für den Aufbau von N-Heterozyclen Zn-katalysierte Prozesse mit der Metathese kombiniert werden. Mit dieser Strategie gelang ausgehend von einfachen Substraten der Aufbau von hoch komplexen Strukturen in einem Eintopfverfahren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-11-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3819</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3819/porta_garcia_marta.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
