<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:52Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2082">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2082</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Multi-Responsive Hybrid Colloids Based On Microgels And Nanoparticles</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Multi-Responsive Hybrid-Kolloide auf der Basis von Mikrogelen und Nanopartikeln</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Karg, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Since the first report on a hydrogel undergoing a temperature-induced volume phase transition by Tanaka in 1977, an enormous interest in such, so-called ‚Äúintelligent‚Ä? or ‚Äúsmart‚Ä?, gels arose. The responsive behavior of this class of gels is interesting for numerous methods of investigation and also for different technical or medical applications. A polymer, which was frequently used in the last decades is made of the monomer N-isopropylacrylamide (NIPAM). Poly-NIPAM (PNIPAM) undergoes a temperature-induced volume phase transition due to its lower critical solution temperature (LCST) behavior. This volume phase transition was the topic of countless investigations comprising different scattering methods such as light and neutron scattering. Recently, especially inorganic/organic hybrid microgels were the topic of several publications, since they combine the properties of different materials. Such a hybrid can e.g benefit from thermoresponsive properties stemming from the organic component and optical, catalytic or magnetic properties stemming from the inorganic material. Due to their unique properties, these composite systems are interesting for many applications including sensor design, ‚Äúsmart‚Ä? surface coatings and drug delivery. The present thesis is devoted to multi-responsive copolymer microgels and hybrid microgels with different morphologies on the basis of NIPAM. The objective of this work includes the preparation and also the detailed characterization of different ‚Äúsmart‚Ä? microgel systems. Pure PNIPAM microgels with different crosslinker densities were prepared and their swelling behavior was studied using different scattering techniques. While the swelling in terms of the overall particle dimensions was investigated by dynamic light scattering (DLS), the microgel collapse on the local length scale was followed by small angle neutron scattering (SANS). SANS provides the network correlation length Ô?∏, which a measure of the network fluctuations. Neutron spin echo spectroscopy (NSE) as a quasi-elastic scattering technique was used to study internal network motions in dependence on the crosslinking. The improvement of the preparation of core-shell microgels with inorganic nanoparticles of different compositions as core material was a major objective of this work. The size effect of the core on the incorporation into the microgel network as well as the resulting effect on the swelling behavior was studied using different-sized silica particles as core material. Core-shell hybrids with optical properties were achieved by the use of gold nanoparticles, while magnetic properties were obtained using iron oxide-silica composite particles as cores. Characterization was mainly done by DLS and SANS. The effect of network charge was studied using copolymer microgels made of the monomer NIPAM and allylacetic acid (AAA) as a charged comonomer. The respective copolymer microgels show a thermoresponsive behavior and additionally an enhanced sensitivity to ionic strength and solution pH. Hence, the swelling behavior was investigated as a function of salt concentration and solution pH. Hybrid microgels with well-pronounced, unique optical properties were prepared by covering NIPAM-based microgel particles with positively charged gold nanorods. The degree of surface coverage was varied over a broad range and the respective thermoresponsive optical properties were investigated by UV-vis spectroscopy. The possible degree of nanorod coverage, which is attributed to electrostatic interactions between the oppositely charged materials, depends strongly on the charge density of the microgel particles and the free surface area. The observed optical properties comprise strong plasmon shifts due to electronic interactions between the gold nanorods. These shifts make these hybrids especially interesting for the design of new optical sensors.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">√úber Hydrogele, die einen Volumenphasen√ºbergang zeigen, wurde erstmals von Tanaka im Jahr 1977 berichtet. Seitdem existiert ein gro√ües Interesse an solchen, als ‚Äûintelligent‚Äú oder ‚Äûsmart‚Äú bezeichneten, Gelen. Aufgrund ihres responsiven Verhaltens ist diese Art von Gelen interessant f√ºr verschiedene Untersuchungsmethoden, sowie f√ºr unterschiedliche technische oder medizinische Anwendungen. Ein Polymer, welches in den letzten Jahren h√§ufig Verwendung gefunden hat, wird aus dem Monomer N-Isopropylacrylamid (NIPAM) synthetisiert. Poly-NIPAM (PNIPAM) durchl√§uft einen Temperatur-induzierten Volumenphasen√ºbergang aufgrund seines LCST (lower critical solution temperature) Verhaltens. Dieser Phasen√ºbergang wurde in der Vergangenheit intensiv untersucht, wobei Methoden wie Licht- und Neutronenstreuung zum Einsatz kamen. Derzeit sind besonders anorganisch/organische Hybrid-Mikrogele Thema vieler Ver√∂ffentlichungen, da diese die Eigenschaften ihrer verschiedenen Materialien vereinen. Ein Hybrid-Mikrogel kann z.B. vom thermosensitiven Verhalten der Polymer-Komponente und optischen, katalytischen oder magnetischen Eigenschaften, stammend von der anorganischen Komponente, profitieren. Wegen dieser einzigartigen Eigenschaften sind diese Komposit-Systeme interessant f√ºr zahlreiche Anwendungen wie Sensorik, Oberfl√§chenbeschichtungen und Drug Delivery. Die vorliegende Arbeit ist multi-responsiven Copolymer-Mikrogelen und Hybrid-Mikrogelen mit verschiedenen Architekturen auf der Basis von NIPAM gewidmet. Ziele waren hierbei sowohl die Pr√§paration als auch die detaillierte Untersuchung verschiedener ‚Äûsmarter‚Äú Mikrogel-Systeme. Reine PNIPAM-Mikrogele mit verschiedenen Quervernetzergehalten wurden synthetisiert und deren Quellverhalten mittels verschiedener Streumethoden charakterisiert. W√§hrend die Partikelgr√∂√üe und deren temperaturabh√§ngige Ver√§nderung mit Hilfe von dynamischer Lichtstreuung (DLS) untersucht wurden, kam die Methode der Kleinwinkel-Neutronenstreuung (KWNS) zum Einsatz, um den Kollaps der Mikrogele auf einer lokalen L√§ngenskala zu studieren. KWNS liefert die Korrelationsl√§nge Ô?∏ des Mikrogelnetzwerkes, welche ein Ma√ü f√ºr die Netzwerkfluktuationen ist. Neutronen-Spin-Echo Spektroskopie (NSE) kam zum Einsatz, um die interne Dynamik des Netzwerkes in Abh√§ngigkeit vom Quervernetzungsgrad zu verfolgen. Die Optimierung der Darstellung von Kern-Schale-Mikrogelen mit anorganischen Nanopartikeln verschiedner Zusammensetzung als Kernmaterial war eines der Schwerpunkte dieser Arbeit. Um den Gr√∂√üeneffekt des Kernes auf den Einbau in die Mikrogelnetzwerke und schlie√ülich auf das Quellverhalten der Hybride zu bestimmen, wurden Silica-Nanopartikel verschiedener Gr√∂√üen als Kerne verwendet. Kern-Schale-Partikel mit Plasmoneigenschaften wurden durch die Verwendung von Gold-Nanopartikeln erhalten, w√§hrend f√ºr magnetische Eigenschaften Silica-Eisenoxid Komposit-Kerne zum Einsatz kamen. Diese Systeme wurden im Wesentlichen mit DLS und KWNS charakterisiert. Der Einfluss der Ladungsdichte des Mikrogelnetzwerkes wurde an Copolymer-Mikrogelen aus NIPAM und Allylessigs√§ure, als geladenes Comonomer, untersucht. Diese Copolymere zeigen sowohl ein thermosensitives Verhalten, als auch eine erh√∂hte Sensitivit√§t bez√ºglich der Ionenst√§rke und des pH-Wertes des L√∂sungsmittels, was mittels DLS verfolgt wurde. Hybrid-Mikrogele mit herausragenden optischen Eigenschaften wurden pr√§pariert, indem Mikrogelpartikel mit positiv-geladenen Gold-St√§bchen umh√ºllt wurden. Der Bedeckungsgrad wurde √ºber einen weiten Bereich variiert und die entsprechenden thermosensitiven optischen Eigenschaften mittels UV-vis Spektroskopie studiert. Die gefundenen Verschiebungen der Plasmon-Resonanz machen diesen Hybrid-Typen interessant f√ºr die Entwicklung neuer optischer Sensoren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>text/x-tex</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2082</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21780</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21780</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2082/original_karg_matthias.tex</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2082/karg_matthias.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
