<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1780">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1780</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Untersuchung von reinen Stoffen in periodisch mesoporösen Silikamaterialien mit thermophysikalischen Methoden und in-situ Röntgenkleinwinkelstreuung </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Study of pure substances in periodic mesoporous silica material with thermophysical methods and in-situ small-angle x-ray-diffraction</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jähnert, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Geordnete mesoporöse Silikamaterialien, deren Herstellung unter der Ausnutzung struktur-dirigierender, amphiphiler Substanzen erfolgt, weisen ein hohes Potenzial für Anwendungen im Bereich der Gas- oder Flüssigadsorption oder in der Katalysetechnik auf. Da diese Materialien gut definierte Porenweiten und Strukturen besitzen, eigenen sie sich ebenfalls für grundlegende Studien, die den Effekt von räumlich eingeschränkten Geometrien auf die thermophysikalischen Eigenschaften und die Struktur von flüssigen und festen Stoffen in den Poren untersuchen. Besonders die Silikamaterialien vom Typ MCM-41 und SBA-15 weisen eine regelmäßige Anordnung von zylindrischen Mesoporen auf (MCM-41: 2-5nm; SBA-15: 5-12nm). In dieser Arbeit wurden eine Reihe solcher Materialien synthetisiert und ihre Porenstruktur mit Hilfe von Röntgendiffraktion, Stickstoffadsorption und elektronenmikroskopischen Aufnahmen charakterisiert. Diese Materialien wurden dann genutzt, um strukturelle Aspekte der Porenauffüllung und Effekte der räumlichen Begrenzung auf das Schmelz- und Gefrierverhalten zu untersuchen. Untersuchungen mittels dynamischer Differenzkalorimetrie (DSC) des fest/flüssig Phasenüberganges von H2O und D2O in einer Reihe von MCM-41 Materialien und von Benzol in MCM-41 und einer Reihe von SBA-15 Materialien weisen eine Verschiebung des Phasenübergangs zu tieferen Temperaturen auf. In diesen Fällen lässt sich die Gefrierpunkt-erniedrigung ΔTm als Funktion des Porenradius R mit Hilfe einer modifizierten Gibbs-Thomson-Gleichung beschreiben. Diese Gleichung liefert einen Parameter t, der im Fall Wasser in MCM-41 als nicht-frierende Schicht von etwa zwei Wassermolekülen an den Porenwänden interpretiert werden kann. Für die Untersuchung von Benzol ergibt sich ein t entsprechend der Größe von 2-3 Moleküle Benzol, aber in dem Fall muss die strukturelle Besonderheit der SBA-15 Materialien (raue Porenwände, bzw. Corona) mit berücksichtig werden, was die Interpretation von t erschwert. Außerdem konnte die Schmelzenthalpie Δh des Porenfluids bestimmt werden. In MCM-41 und SBA-15 nimmt Δh stark ab mit sinkendem Porenradius. Für Wasser in MCM-41 ergibt sich eine lineare Abhängigkeit von Δh vs. 1/Rs mit Rs = R – t, woraus folgt, dass Δh Null wird bei einem Porenradius R=1.4nm. Die Ergebnisse deuten darauf hin, dass in Poren mit Radien R &lt; 1.4nm für Wasser kein Phasenübergang erster Ordnung stattfindet. Bei Benzol in SBA-15 erfolgt die Korrektur von Δh unter der Annahme, dass der Anteil Benzol in der mikroporösen Corona nicht am Schmelzprozess teilnimmt. In dem Fall wird Δh=0 bei einem Radius von 2.1nm. Strukturelle Besonderheiten der Porenauffüllung eines SBA-15 Silikamaterials durch Gasadsorption wurden am Synchrotron mit Hilfe von in-situ SAXD-Messungen untersucht. Für diese Experimente wurden eine spezielle Messzelle und ein Gasdosiersystem konstruiert. Strukturelle Informationen über die evakuierte Silikamatrix und die Adsorption (von Perfluorpentan und Dibrommethan) in die geordneten zylindrischen Mesoporen lassen sich aus der Analyse der Integralintensitäten der zehn führenden Braggreflexe, resultierend aus der 2d- hexagonalen Anordnung der zylindrischen Poren gewinnen. Die einzelnen Braggreflexe ändern ihre Intensität mit steigender Beladung der organischen Flüssigkeit in SBA-15. Die Änderung der Peakintensitäten können mit zwei hier vorgestellten Formfaktormodellen, die eine mikroporöse Corona (bzw. eine raue Porenwand) der zylindrischen Poren beschreiben, quantitativ erklärt werden. Um Aussagen über die Adsorption von Flüssigkeit in die ungeordneten Regionen der Silikamatrix machen zu können, wurde der diffuse Streuanteil der Probe mit steigender Beladung ausgewertet. So können letztendlich detaillierte Informationen über die Auffüllung der Silikamatrix und den Filmwachstum des flüssigen Films an den Porenwänden mit steigender Beladung der Flüssigkeit gemacht werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Ordered mesoporous silica material like MCM-41 and SBA-15, which are accessible by using surfactants or amphiphilic block copolymers as structure-directing templates, have attained much attention regarding their potential application in gas or liquid adsorption processes and as catalyst supports. Due to their well-defined pore size and geometry such materials are also useful for fundamental studies of the effect of confinement on the thermo-physical behaviour and structure of pure fluids and solid guest materials in the pores. Specifically, MCM-41 and SBA-15 constitute regular arrays of cylindrical pores in a range of pores sizes from 2 to 5nm (MCM-41) and from 5 to 12nm (SBA-15). In this work, a series of such materials was synthesized and their pore structure was characterized by X-ray diffraction, nitrogen adsorption, and electron microscopy. The materials were then used to study structural aspects of the pore filling with organic fluids by in-situ X-ray small-angle diffraction (in-situ SAXD), and the confinement effect on the melting and freezing of water and benzene in the pores was studied by differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) in combination with sorption isotherm measurements. DSC studies of the solid/liquid phase transition of H2O and D2O water in a series of MCM-41 materials, and of benzene in MCM-41 and several SBA-15 materials reveals a pronounced shift of the phase transition to lower temperatures. In both cases the melting point depression ΔTm as a function of the pore radius R can be represented by a modified Gibbs-Thomson equation, using an additional parameter t. In the case of water this parameter t can be taken as a thin non-freezing layer of water at the pore wall, which corresponds to about two molecular diameters. In the case of benzene t corresponds to 2-3 molecular diameters. But we have to take into account the structural specifics of SBA-15 (corrugated pore wall or Corona), which makes the interpretation more difficult. The melting enthalpy Δh was estimated from the DSC pore melting peak areas and the amount of material in the pores that participates in the phase transition. The resulting Δh decreases strongly with decreasing pore size and can be represented within experimental accuracy by a linear relation of Δh vs. 1/Rs where Rs = R – t. From the extrapolation of this linear relation one finds that Δh becomes zero at a pore radius of about 1.4nm for water in MCM-41. This result and the disappearance of melting/freezing hysteresis at a similar pore size seems to indicate, that no first-order solid/liquid phase transition of water in the pores occurs below this pore size. In the case of benzene Δh we took into account, that the amount of benzene in the microporous Corona do not participates in the phase transition. So one finds that Δh becomes zero at a pore radius of about 2.1nm. Structural peculiarities of the pore filling of a well-characterized SBA-15 silica by vapour adsorption were studied by in-situ SAXD using synchrotron radiation. For these experiments a special sample cell and gas dosing system for organic fluids (perfluoropentane, dibromomethane) was developed. Structural information about the pore wall structure and the adsorbed fluid in the ordered arrays of cylindrical mesopores is derived from the integrated intensities of the leading ten Bragg diffraction peaks resulting from the two-dimensional hexagonal packing of the mesopores. The integrated intensities of the individual Bragg peaks increase or decrease with increasing adsorption of the fluid in the pores. These changes in peak intensity can be reproduced quantitatively by form factor models which take into account a microporous corona (or corrugated pore wall) of the cylindrical pores. In order to account for the amount of fluid in the disordered porous matrix it is necessary to analyse the diffuse scattering of the sample as a function of the amount adsorbed. A combination of these two contributions provides detailed information about the filling of the silica matrix and the growing thickness of the liquid film at the pore walls as a function of the vapour pressure of the fluid.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-05-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1780</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1780/jaehnert_susanne.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
