<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:46:10Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:433">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:433</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Systematische sicherheitstechnische Untersuchungen zu Synthesereaktionen ausgewählter Alkylperoxide</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Systematically safety investigation of the synthesis of selected alkylperoxides</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schreck, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Organische Peroxide werden in der chemischen Industrie vielseitig eingesetzt. Ihre Herstellung birgt jedoch ein hohes Gefahrenpotential. Für die sichere Reaktionsführung ist daher eine systematische sicherheitstechnische Bewertung von Herstellungsprozessen organischer Peroxide von großer Bedeutung. Eine solche Bewertung des Herstellungsprozesses beinhaltet sowohl Untersuchungen zum Normalbetrieb als auch zum gestörten Betrieb. In dieser Arbeit wird die sicherheitstechnische Bewertung der Alkylierung von Wasserstoffperoxid zum Alkylperoxid an drei unterschiedlichen Beispielen vorgestellt. Als Alkylierungsmittel werden 2-Methyl-2-propanol, 2-Methyl-2-butanol und 2-Methyl-1-penten eingesetzt. Am Beispiel der tertiär-Butylhydroperoxid-Synthese wird insbesondere auf die Auswirkung variierter Prozeßbedingungen eingegangen. Die für die Bewertung der Alkylierungsreaktionen erforderlichen Daten werden mit einem thermischen Screening-Test (MCPVT), dem BAM Stahlrohrtest 50/60 kavitiert und einem Reaktionskalorimeter (RC1) ermittelt. Die gewonnenen Ergebnisse zeigen sichere und unsichere Reaktionsabschnitte während der Peroxidsynthesen, wobei als Kriterium hierfür der Vergleich von maximaler Temperatur der Synthesereaktion (MTSR) mit einer festgelegten Grenztemperatur (Tiso 24) herangezogen wird. Neben der sicherheitstechnischen Bewertung des chemischen Verfahrens wird an zwei Beispielen auch der sichere Betrieb des semi-batch Prozesses im RC1 überprüft und die Auswirkung von Maßstabsveränderungen des Reaktorgefäßes untersucht. Hierzu werden die reaktionskinetischen Parameter (Damköhlerzahl und Aktivierungsenergie) bestimmt. Die Simulation der Umsatzverläufe mit den ermittelten kinetischen Parametern liefert eine gute Übereinstimmung mit den experimentellen Daten. In vergleichenden Untersuchungen wird ein Einfluß der Kettenlänge des Alkylierungsmittels auf die Eigenschaften der Eduktmischungen festgestellt. So verringert sich der Detonationsbereich von Mischungen aus H2O2 und Alkylierungsmittel bzw. sinkt die Grenztempera-tur (Tiso 24) von Eduktmischungen mit zunehmender Kettenlänge. Die spezifischen Reaktionswärmen der Alkylierungsreaktionen nehmen dagegen mit steigender Kettenlänge zu. Unter sicherheitstechnischen Aspekten zeigt sich somit, daß das Gefahrenpotential für die Alkylierung von H2O2 mit zunehmender Kettenlänge des Alkylierungsmittels steigt.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Organic peroxides are used as educts for the production of a great variety of chemical products. Occasional accidents or difficulties during the production of organic peroxides point out the hazard potential of these substances. To prevent hazardous situations associated with organic peroxides or mixtures of hydrogen peroxide and organic chemicals, respectively, systematic safety assessments of the production procedure are necessary. This includes the investigation of normal and disturbed production processes. The aim of this work is the assessment of the alkylation of hydrogen peroxide to alkyl peroxide by means of three different examples. 2-Methyl-2-propanol, 2-methyl-2-butanol and 2-methyl-1-pentene were used as substrates for the alkylation of hydrogen peroxide. The effect on different process conditions have been studied by example of the synthesis of butyl hydroperoxide. The assessment data of the alkylation reactions were obtained by using a thermal screening test (MCPVT), the BAM steel tube test 50/60 (cavitated version) and a reaction calorimeter (RC1). The results of this study point out safe and unsafe parts of the reaction during the synthesis of peroxides. The criterion used the comparison of the maximum temperature of the synthesis reaction (MTSR) with a defined limited temperature (Tiso24). Apart from the safety assessment of the chemical procedure the safety of the semi-batch process has been investigated in the reaction calorimeter (RC1) and also the scale-up effect is discussed. Thus, kinetic parameters (Damköhlerzahl and activation energy) were determined. The simulation which is based on this kinetic parameters is in good agreement with the conversions obtained experimentally. The comparison of the three synthesis reactions clearly establish the dependency of the chain length of the alkylation substance on the characteristics of the mixed reactants. With increasing chain length the detonation range of the mixture of hydrogen peroxide and the alkylation substance or the limited temperature (Tiso24) of the reactants and its mixtures is reduced. In contrast, the specific heat of reaction of the alkylation reactions increases with prolonged chain length. Summarizing these results under process safety aspects, the dangerous potential of the alkylation of hydrogen peroxide is directly proportional with the chain length of the alkylation substance.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2003-07-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/433</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-4281</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-4281</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/433/schreck_andreas.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
