<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:31Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3291">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3291</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Mechanistic Studies on Metal-Mediated Bond-Activation Reactions in Gaseous Ions</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Mechanistische Studien zu Metallvermittelten Bindungsaktivierungsreaktionenin Gasphasen-Ionen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Butschke, Burkhard</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this work, mass-spectrometric experiments complemented by isotope-labeling studies and DFT-based calculations are presented that are employed to investigate the fragmentations of organometallic complexes of the type [M(X)(L)]+ (M = Ni, Pd, Pt; X = CH3, F, Cl, Br, I, CH3COO; L = bidentate N,N‚Äô-coordinating ligands) as well as their reactions with hydrocarbons such as benzene, toluene, and methane. Moreover, ion/molecule reactions of ‚Ä?rollover‚Ä?-cyclometalated [Pt(bipy - H)]+ (bipy = 2,2‚Äô-bipyridine) with ethers and chloromethanes are discussed. All complexes are conveniently produced by electrospray ionization (ESI). In the fragmentation studies employing [M(X)(bipy)]+ (M = Ni, Pd, Pt; X = CH3, Cl), distinct differences between the platinum complexes and those of the other two metals become obvious, and this metal and ligand-controlled behavior is a consequence of the rather different energetic requirements for the direct loss of X versus elimination of HX via C-H bond activation of the bipy ligand. Deuterium-labeling experiments have revealed that formation of HX is only for the platinum complexes due to a genuine ‚Ä?rollover‚Ä?-cyclometalation process, i.e. selective abstraction of a hydrogen atom from the C(3)-position of bipy. In the thermal ion/molecule reactions of mass-selected [M(CH3)(bipy)]+ (M = Ni, Pd, Pt) with benzene and toluene, hydrogen-atom abstraction occurs that results in the loss of neutral CH4. In the reactions with toluene, the Ni and Pd complexes attack exclusively the arene C-H bonds (without any pronounced preference for the ortho-, meta-, or para-positions). In the reaction with [Pt(CH3)(bipy)]+, however, 10 % of the hydrogen originates from the methyl group of toluene, i.e. the reactivity is increased at the cost of the regioselectivity. In the reaction with methane, it is only the platinum complex that brings about a degenerate H/D exchange with CD4. The chloro analogues [M(Cl)(bipy)]+ (M = Ni, Pd, Pt) are not able to abstract hydrogen atoms from benzene and methane to form HCl. In the ion/molecule reactions of cyclometalated [Pt(bipy - H)]+ with ethers, the initial step corresponds to a platinum-mediated transfer of a hydrogen atom from the ether to the (bipy - H) ligand, and a three-membered oxygen-containing metallacycle serves as a key intermediate. Oxidative C-C-bond coupling, as observed as the main process in the reaction with dimethyl sulfide, is practically absent for dimethyl ether. In the reactions of [Pt(bipy - H)]+ with the chloromethanes CH(4-n)Cl(n) (n = 1 - 4), C-Cl insertion of the platinum center corresponds to the initial step, which is followed by the migration of the (chlorinated) methyl group to the platinum-bound carbon atom of the (bipy - H) ligand for most of the reaction channels.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Arbeit umfasst massenspektrometrische sowie DFT-basierte Studien zur Fragmentation kationischer Organometall-Komplexe des Typs [M(X)(L)]+ (M = Ni, Pd, Pt; X = CH3, F, Cl, Br, I, CH3COO; L = zweiz√§hnige N,N‚Äô-koordinierende Liganden) als auch ihrer Reaktivit√§t gegen√ºber den Kohlenwasserstoffen Benzol, Toluol und Methan. Au√üerdem werden die Reaktionen von ‚Ä?rollover‚Ä?-cyclometaliertem [Pt(bipy - H)]+ (bipy = 2,2‚Äô-Bipyridin) gegen√ºber Ethern und Chlormethanen vorgestellt. Alle Komplexe lassen sich durch Elektrosprayionisierung (ESI) erzeugen. In den Fragmentationsstudien mit [M(X)(bipy)]+ (M = Ni, Pd, Pt; X = CH3, Cl) sind deutliche Unterschiede zwischen den Platinkomplexen und den Komplexen der anderen beiden Metalle feststellbar. Dieses durch die Wahl sowohl des Metallzentrums als auch des Liganden gesteuerte Verhalten ergibt sich aus den unterschiedlichen energetischen Anforderungen, die mit dem direkten Verlust des Liganden X auf der einen Seite und der Eliminierung von HX durch C-H-Bindungsaktivierung des bipy-Liganden auf der anderen Seite verbunden sind. Auf der Basis von Deuterium-Markierungsexperimenten l√§sst sich folgern, dass der Verlust von HX nur f√ºr die Platinkomplexe die Folge einer echten ‚Ä?Rollover‚Ä?-Cyclometallierung ist. In thermischen Ion/Molek√ºl-Reaktionen von massenselektiertem [M(CH3)(bipy)]+ (M = Ni, Pd, Pt) mit Benzol und Toluol wird H-Abstraktion unter Bildung von CH4 beobachtet. In den Reaktionen mit Toluol aktivieren die Nickel- und Palladium-Komplexe ausschlie√ülich die Aryl-C-H-Bindungen des Substrats (allerdings ohne ausgepr√§gte Pr√§ferenz f√ºr die ortho-, meta- oder para-Position). F√ºr [Pt(CH3)(bipy)]+ wird zu 10 % auch H-Abstraktion von der Methylgruppe beobachtet; die erh√∂hte Reaktivit√§t geht also folglich mit einer verminderten Regioselektivit√§t einher. Lediglich der Platinkomplex geht mit CD4 einen degenerierten H/D-Austausch ein. Die Chlorokomplexe [M(Cl)(bipy)]+ (M = Ni, Pd, Pt) sind nicht in der Lage, aus Benzol und Methan Wasserstoff zu abstrahieren. In Ion/Molek√ºl-Reaktionen von ‚Ä?rollover‚Ä?-cyclometalliertem [Pt(bipy - H)]+ mit Ethern findet im ersten Schritt der Reaktion ein platinvermittelter Transfer eines H-Atoms vom Ether auf den (bipy - H)-Liganden statt, wobei ein dreigliedriger Metallazyklus als Schl√ºsselintermediat gebildet wird. Oxidative C-C-Bindungskn√ºpfung, die den Hauptreaktionskanal in der Reaktion mit Dimethylsulfid ausmacht, wird f√ºr Dimethylether nicht beobachtet. Mit den Chlormethanen CH(4-n)Cl(n) (n = 1 - 4) reagiert [Pt(bipy - H)]+ unter initialer Insertion des Platinzentrums in die C-Cl-Bindung, die f√ºr die meisten Reaktionskan√§le von der √úbertragung der (chlorierten) Methylgruppe auf das platin-gebundene Kohlenstoffatom des (bipy - H)-Liganden gefolgt ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-04-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3291</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34931</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34931</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3291/butschke_burkhard.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
