<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:42Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3785">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3785</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-14</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">High pressure-low temperature induced structures in dairy foams and protein model systems</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Hochdruck-Niedertemperatur induzierte Strukturen in Milchschaeumen und Protein Modellsystemen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Volkert, Marcus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">A diverse range of foods are foams and even if not entirely understood, obtain increasing importance as manufacturers seek to exploit the novelty of bubbles as food ingredients (Campbell &amp; Mougeot, 1999). Dairy foams may be defined as products that contain a gaseous phase stabilized in a matrix where a significant proportion of the principal components are of milk origin (Anderson &amp; Brooker, 1988). Well known examples are whipped cream, spray cream, ice cream or foamed chocolates. The quality of many frozen products is highly influenced by the size and shape of the ice crystals formed during the production process (Fennema, 1966; Sanz, de Elvira, Martino, Zaritzky, Otero &amp; Carrasco, 1999). Besides textural damage due to ice crystal growth and resulting quality loss in plant and animal tissue, the presence of large crystals in products that are consumed in the frozen state negatively affects sensory properties. A well known example is the negative impact of large ice crystals on the sensory properties and texture of ice cream and frozen desserts (Marshall, Goff &amp; Hartel, 2003; Clarke, 2004; Drewett &amp; Hartel, 2007). Furthermore the incorporated air cells essentially affect product quality and make a significant contribution to the sensory and structural properties of frozen foams (Marshall et al., 2003; Eisener, Wildmoser &amp; Windhalb, 2005). For the last decade, there is a growing trend towards increased consumption of reduced-fat products (Robb, Reynolds &amp; Abdel-Ghany, 2007). This trend is highly challenging for the food industry, as fat is an important ingredient to high quality dairy products and plays a key role in the stabilization of frozen dairy foams (Goff, Verespej &amp; Smith, 1999). The general consumer perception is that products labelled as ‚Äúlow fat‚Ä? or ‚Äúno fat‚Ä? do not taste good (Wolfe, 1998). It has been suggested that improvements in product quality for lower fat dairy products are required to deliver the quality expected by consumers (Aime, Arntfield, Malcolmson &amp; Ryland, 2001). In this respect, one of the goals in modifying and developing new products is to provide improvements in the products physical structure to deliver desirable texture. The field of High Pressure-Low Temperature (HPLT) processing embraces high pressure processes with and without water phase transitions in the subzero temperature domain. According to (Urrutia Benet, Schl√ºter &amp; Knorr, 2004) and (Knorr, Schl√ºter &amp; Heinz, 1998) the relevant processes that include liquid to solid water phase transitions under pressure can be summarized as Pressure Shift Freezing (PSF), Pressure Assisted Freezing (PAF) and Pressure induced Crystallization (PIC). Scientific research in the field of HPLT treatment so far is mostly focused on inactivation of microorganisms and the development of gentile freezing processes to minimize textural damage in plant and animal tissue (Urrutia Benet, 2005; Buggenhout, Grauwet, Loey &amp; Hendrickx, 2007). However, the HPLT technology has proven its potential to positively affect the product texture in the freezing step and moreover, high pressure treatments induce new functional properties in protein systems (Merel-Rausch, Kulozik &amp; Hinrichs, 2007; Urrutia Benet, Arabas, Autio, Brul, Hendrickx, Kakolewski et al., 2007). Today, industrial high pressure processes aim on food pasteurization and sterilization, covering a variety of products with low gas content to minimize volume changes during the process (Mathys, 2008). The focus of this work was to study the influence of different process and product parameters on high pressure-low temperature induced structures in dairy foams and protein model systems. A profound understanding of the mechanisms induced by different process parameters, such as pressure level, pressure release rate and ice formation under pressure was of central concern. The basic impact on functionally relevant ingredients was investigated, with special respect to the milk protein fraction. The HPLT technology was evaluated regarding its potential to induce and affect properties of ice crystals and functional ingredients of dairy emulsions, which are involved in the stabilization of air cells and the development of unique product texture. In this respect, HPLT induced functional and textural changes in emulsified aerated and non aerated model systems were investigated and a basic evaluation of the HPLT technology concerning its applicability as a batch or continuous process in frozen food foam processing was performed. Moreover the potential of HPLT treated milk proteins as ingredients for conventionally processed foods was investigated.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Sch√§ume sind Bestandteil einer Vielzahl von Lebensmitteln und r√ºcken zunehmend in das Interesse der Lebensmittelindustrie. Bekannte Beispiele f√ºr aufgesch√§umte Produkte sind Schlag- und Spr√ºhsahne, Eiscreme und Luftschokolade. Die Qualit√§t vieler gefrorener Produkte wird ma√ügeblich von Gr√∂√üe und Form der w√§hrend des Verarbeitungsprozesses gebildeten Eiskristalle bestimmt. Neben der Texturzerst√∂rung durch Eiskristallwachstum und damit verbundenen Qualit√§tsverlusten in pflanzlichen und tierischen Tiefk√ºhlprodukten, wirken sich gro√üe Eiskristalle negativ auf die Sensorik von Produkten aus, die im gefrorenen Zustand verzehrt werden. Ein Beispiel hierf√ºr ist die Beeintr√§chtigung von Sensorik und Textur von Eiscreme. Dar√ºber hinaus beeinflussen Luftblasen in Lebensmittelsch√§umen die Produktqualit√§t und spielen nicht nur in sensorischer Hinsicht eine wichtige Rolle, sondern tragen ma√ügeblich zu strukturellen Eigenschaften bei. In den letzten Jahren zeigt sich ein zunehmender Trend im Verzehr fettreduzierter Lebensmittel. Diesem Trend gerecht zu werden stellt hohe Anforderungen an die Lebensmittelindustrie, da Fette und √ñle wichtige qualit√§tsgebende Inhaltsstoffe f√ºr viele hochwertige Produkte darstellen. So tragen sie ma√ügeblich zur Strukturbildung und Stabilisierung in gefrorenen Lebensmittelsch√§umen (z.B. Eiscreme) bei. Viele Verbraucher assoziieren mit reduziertem Fettgehalt oft auch reduzierten Geschmack. Dementsprechend ergibt sich die Notwendigkeit verbesserter Produktqualit√§t in diesem Sektor um wachsenden Anspr√ºchen der Verbraucher gerecht zu werden. Ein wichtiges Ziel in der Entwicklung neuer Produkte ist es demnach Lebensmittelsysteme zu verbessern und neu zu entwickeln, die hohe Anspr√ºche an Qualit√§t und Textur besser erf√ºllen. Hochdruck-Niedertemperatur (HPLT) Behandlungen umfassen Hochdruckprozesse im Niedertemperaturbereich die abh√§ngig von der Prozessf√ºhrung einen Phasen√ºbergang des Wassers im behandelten Produkt herbef√ºhren k√∂nnen. Entsprechend den von Knorr und Urrutia eingef√ºhrten Definitionen, sind die HPLT-Gefrierprozesse das Pressure Shift Freezing (PSF), Pressure Assisted Freezing (PAF) und Pressure induced Crystallization (PIC). Wissenschaftliche Arbeiten im Bereich der Hochdruck-Niedertemperatur Behandlungen konzentrierten sich bisher weitgehend auf die Entwicklung schonender Gefrierverfahren und auf die Inaktivierung von Mikroorganismen und Enzymen. Durch HPLT Gefrier-Prozesse k√∂nnen Strukturzerst√∂rungen nachweislich vermindert werden und dar√ºber hinaus erm√∂glichen Hochdruckverfahren die Induzierung neuer funktioneller Eigenschaften in Proteinsystemen. In der Industrie angewendete Hochdruckprozesse beschr√§nken sich bis heute jedoch auf die Pasteurisation und Sterilisation. Gaseinschl√ºsse in entsprechenden Produkten werden vermieden um Volumen√§nderungen w√§hrend der Behandlung so gering wie m√∂glich zu halten. Ziel dieser Arbeit ist die Untersuchung der Einfl√ºsse verschiedener Prozess- und Produktparameter auf HPLT induzierte Strukturen in aufgesch√§umten Emulsionen und Milchprotein Modellsystemen. Von besonderem Interesse war hierbei das Aufzeigen verschiedener Mechanismen und deren Abh√§ngigkeit von Prozessparametern wie Druck, Entspannungsrate und dem Einfluss der sich unter Druck und w√§hrend der Entspannung bildenden Eiskristalle. Grundlegende Zusammenh√§nge im Bezug auf funktionelle Inhaltsstoffe wurden Untersucht. Spezielles Interesse galt der Fraktion der Milchproteine. Verschiedene HPLT Verfahren wurden hinsichtlich ihres Potentials untersucht, Eigenschaften von Eiskristallen und funktionellen Inhaltsstoffen zu induzieren, die zur Stabilisierung und Texturierung von milchbasierten Lebensmittelsch√§umen beitragen. In diesem Zusammenhang wurde eine grundlegende Bewertung von HPLT Prozessen als diskontinuierliches oder kontinuierliche Herstellungsverfahren f√ºr gefrorene Lebensmittelsch√§ume vorgenommen und dar√ºber hinaus das Potential von HPLT vorbehandelten Milchproteinen als Inhaltsstoff in konventionell hergestellten Produkten untersucht.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-06-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3785</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22573</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22573</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3785/volkert_marcus.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
