<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:08Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2797">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2797</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">EPR spectroscopy of oxygen-tolerant [NiFe]-hydrogenases</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">EPR-Spektroskopie von sauerstofftoleranten [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Saggu, Miguel Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Hydrogenases are metalloenzymes and play a pivotal role in the energy metabolism of a variety of microorganisms. They catalyze the reversible cleavage of molecular hydrogen into two protons and two electrons. However, one drawback is their catalytic inactivation upon exposure to oxygen.[FeFe]-hydrogenases are irreversibly inactivated by oxygen, whereas [NiFe]-hydrogenases usually are reversibly inactivated to the so-called ’ready’ and ’unready’ states. Only a few [NiFe]-hydrogenases show a remarkable oxygen-tolerance, e.g. the [NiFe]-hydrogenases from the ’Knallgasbacterium’ Ralstonia eutropha H16 investigated in this work. Re H16 harbors three different [NiFe]-hydrogenases, all of them being able to oxidize molecular hydrogen under ambient oxygen concentrations. The goal of this work was to understand the origin of this oxygen-tolerance on a molecular level and to study structure/function-relationships of the involved cofactors using a combination of EPR and FTIR spectroscopy. An important aspect of this thesis was to study biological systems in their native environment, e.g. in whole cells or membrane fragments. The membrane-bound [NiFe]-hydrogenase (MBH) from Re H16 was studied mainly in its native environment, i.e. in membrane fragments that harbor over-produced MBH. All catalytically active redox states of the [NiFe] center were identified. However, the ’unready’ Niu-A, observed in standard [NiFe]-hydrogenases could not be detected, which seems to be a common feature of all oxygen-tolerant [NiFe]-hydrogenases. It was shown, that the MBH contains an additional highpotential paramagnetic center. Concomitant electrochemical experiments revealed that the MBH can be reactivated very fast at high potentials, which might indicate an important role of the additional high-potential center. This center could influence the catalytic cycle by providing electrons to avoid Niu-A formation. The hyperfine structure of the Nir-B state (oxidized enzyme) was investigated in more detail by pulsed EPR methods, namely ENDOR and ESEEM spectroscopy. The results were compared with the standard [NiFe]-hydrogenase from D. vulgaris Miyazaki F. Both hydrogenases showed a similar spin density distribution in their [NiFe] center indicating that the spatial structures of the active sites are identical. Two large hf-couplings arising from the b-protons of one bridging cysteine sulfur were resolved and simulated in orientation-selective ENDOR spectra. With ESEEM spectroscopy a nitrogen located in a histidine residue in the second coordination sphere of the Ni was detected, which is a known property of many [NiFe]-hydrogenases. This histidine is hydrogen-bonded to the same bridging sulfur. Another interesting feature of oxygen-tolerant membrane-bound [NiFe]-hydrogenases is the presence of two additional cysteine residues in the vicinity of the proximal [4Fe4S]-cluster. Mutations of these cysteines revealed that these residues are responsible for an alteration of the proximal [4Fe4S] center, resulting in the additional paramagnetic center(s) detectable at high redox potentials. The oxygen-tolerant soluble hydrogenase (SH) from Re H16 and the closely related bidirectional hydrogenase from Synechocystis PCC 6803 were investigated as well. The SH has been studied in situ in its natural environment in whole cells. It was found, that under these conditions the [NiFe] active site exhibited a standard-type coordination with one CO and two CN ligands at the Fe, which is in contrast to previous studies on purified SH. For comparison, the soluble hydrogenase from the oxygenic phototrophic cyanobacterium Synechocystis PCC 6803 was characterized with EPR and FTIR spectroscopy. The active site Fe was also found to be coordinated with a standard set of inorganic ligands, one CO and two CN. Practically all ready and catalytically active states known from standard [NiFe]-hydrogenases were identified for this enzyme including two different FeS clusters and a flavin-type radical. Both soluble hydrogenases reveal strong similarities with respect to the redox states and FeS clusters. However, no paramagnetic Nir-B/Niu-A EPR-signals could be observed in both hydrogenases, which might be related to a coupling with another paramagnetic species in close vicinity. The Synechocystis hydrogenase can be rapidly activated with hydrogen under anaerobic conditions. Because of its spectral and catalytic properties, the SH from Synechocystis represents a link between standard and oxygen-tolerant [NiFe]-hydrogenases. The unusual oxygen-tolerance of the Ralstonia hydrogenases, at least for the MBH, is probably connected with a modified proximal FeS center of yet unknown structure.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Hydrogenasen sind Metalloenzyme und spielen eine entscheidende Rolle im Metabolismus einer Vielzahl von Mikroorganismen. Diese Enzyme katalysieren die reversible Spaltung von molekularem Wasserstoff in zwei Protonen und zwei Elektronen. Allerdings werden sie durch Sauerstoff katalytisch inaktiviert. [FeFe]-Hydrogenasen werden irreversibel inaktiviert, während [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen normalerweise reversibel inaktiviert werden zu den so genannten ’ready’ und ’unready’ Zuständen. Einige [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen zeigen allerdings eine bemerkenswerte Sauerstofftoleranz, z.B. die in dieser Arbeit untersuchten [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen des ’Knallgasbakteriums’ Ralstonia eutropha H16. Re H16 enthält drei unterschiedliche [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen, von denen alle in der Lage sind, molekularen Wasserstoff unter natürlichen Sauerstoffkonzentrationen zu oxidieren. Ziel dieser Arbeit war es, die Ursache der Sauerstofftoleranz auf molekularer Ebene zu verstehen und Struktur/Funktions-Beziehungen der beteiligten Kofaktoren zu studieren mit einer Kombination aus EPR und FTIR Spektroskopie. Ein wichtiger Aspekt dieser Arbeit war die Untersuchung biologischer Systeme in möglichst nativer Umgebung, z.B. in ganzen Zellen oder Membranfragmenten. Die Membran-gebundene [NiFe]-Hydrogenase (MBH) von Re H16 wurde hauptsächlich in ihrer natürlichen Umgebung untersucht, d.h. in Membranfragmenten, die überproduzierte MBH enthielten. Alle katalytisch aktiven Redoxzustände des [NiFe] Zentrums wurden identifiziert. Allerdings konnte der ’unready’ Zustand Niu-A, bekannt aus Standard-[NiFe]-Hydrogenasen, nicht detektiert werden, was eine gemeinsame Eigenschaft sauerstofftoleranter [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen zu sein scheint. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass die MBH ein zusätzliches ’high-potential’ paramagnetisches Zentrum enthält. Elektrochemische Untersuchungen haben gezeigt, dass die MBH bei hohen Potentialen sehr schnell reaktiviert werden kann, was auf eine wichtige Rolle des zusätzlichen Zentrums hinweisen könnte. Dieses Zentrum könnte den katalytischen Zyklus beeinflussen, indem es Elektronen zur Verfügung stellt, die eine Bildung des Niu-A verhindern. Die Hyperfeinstruktur des Nir-B Redoxzustandes wurde detailliert mit Puls-EPR Methoden untersucht, hauptsächlich mit ENDOR und ESEEM Spektroskopie. Die erhaltenen Resultate wurden verglichen mit der Standard-[NiFe]-Hydrogenase von D. vulgaris Miyazaki F. Beide Hydrogenasen zeigten eine ähnliche Spindichte-Verteilung in ihrem [NiFe] Zentrum, was auf eine vergleichbare Geometrie schliessen lässt. Hyperfeinkopplungen von zwei b-Protonen eines verbrückenden Cystein-Schwefels konnten aufgelöst und simuliert werden. Mittels ESEEM Spektroskopie konnte die Anwesenheit eines Histidin Stickstoffs in der zweiten Koordinationssphäre des Ni nachgewiesen werden, was eine Eigenschaft vieler [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen ist. Eine interessante Eigenschaft sauerstofftoleranter Membran-gebundener [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen ist die Anwesenheit von zwei zusätzlichen Cysteinen in der Nähe des proximalen [4Fe4S] Zentrums. Durch Mutationen dieser beiden Cysteine konnte gezeigt werden, dass eine Modifikation des proximalen [4Fe4S] Zentrums auf sie zurückzuführen ist. Beide scheinen essentiell für die Anwesenheit des zusätzlichen paramagnetischen Zentrums bei hohen Redoxpotentialen zu sein. Die sauerstofftolerante lösliche Hydrogenase (SH) von Re H16 and die eng verwandte Hydrogenase von Synechocystis PCC 6803 wurden ebenfalls charakterisiert. Die SH wurde in situ in ihrer natürlicher Umgebung in ganzen Zellen studiert. Unter diesen Bedingungen verhielt sich das aktive Zentrum wie ein Standard [NiFe] Zentrum mit einem CO und zwei CN-Liganden am Fe, im Gegensatz zu früheren Studien an gereinigter SH. Als Vergleich dazu wurde die lösliche Hydrogenase von Synechocystis PCC 6803 charakterisiert. Das Fe im aktiven Zentrum ist mit dem Standardsatz anorganischer Liganden, einem CO und zwei CN, koordiniert. Praktisch alle ’ready’ und katalytisch aktiven Zustände bekannt aus Standard-[NiFe]-Hydrogenasen konnten für dieses Enzym identifiziert werden inklusive zwei verschiedene FeS Zentren und ein typisches Flavin Radikal. Beide löslichen Hydrogenasen zeigten starke Ähnlichkeiten hinsichtich ihrer Redoxzustände und FeS Zentren. Allerdings konnten keine paramagnetischen Nir-B/Niu-A EPR Signale beobachtet werden, was auf eine Kopplung mit einem anderen benachbarten paramagnetischen Zentrum schliessen lässt. Die Synechocystis Hydrogenase konnte unter anaeroben Bedingungen schnell mit Wasserstoff aktiviert werden. Aufgrund ihres spektroskopischen und katalytischen Verhaltens ist die SH von Synechocystis zwischen Standard- und sauerstofftoleranten [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen anzuordnen. Die ungewöhnliche Sauerstofftoleranz der Ralstonia Hydrogenasen ist zumindest in der MBH wahrscheinlich verbunden mit einem modifizierten FeS Zentrum von dem die Struktur bis jetzt nicht bekannt ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-02-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2797</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25176</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25176</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2797/saggu_miguel.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-SA: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, Weitergabe zu gleichen Bedingungen</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
