<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:44Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2695">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2695</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Homogeneously catalysed Suzuki coupling reaction in microemulsion systems with recycling of the catalyst</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Homogen katalysierte Suzuki Kupplung in Mikroemulsionen mit Recycling des Katalysators</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nowothnick, Henriette</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The Suzuki cross coupling reaction of 2-Bromobenzonitrile and 4-Methylbenzeneboronic acid was investigated in microemulsions (heptane/water/surfactant) and catalysed by the water soluble catalyst complex Pd-TPPTS. Thereby, the formulation of microemulsions was studied under reaction conditions with the aim of enhancing the rate in comparison to a biphasic system (without surfactant). Furthermore, the use of heptane/water resulted in unselective reaction with the production of homocoupling product of arylboronic acid. As a benchmark, the Suzuki coupling was performed also in acetonitrile as often-used solvent for C-C coupling reactions, showing that no faster rate was observed as in microemulsions and in addition no catalyst recycling was possible. The most promising aspect of using microemulsions as reaction media is the location of miscibility gaps, which were utilised for product isolation, catalyst recycling and the removal of the salts. Therefore, especially nonionic surfactants show the required ability to form liquid three phase systems. It was found that the phase behaviour is shifted during reaction progress. The microemulsion system was tuned in order to obtain the three phases at complete conversion what means that the observation was used as indicator that no online analytic was necessary. A subsequent catalyst recycling was carried out, by removing the heptane phase for isolation of the product, the replacement of the aqueous phase by a new batch to prevent a salinity effect (poisons the catalyst). The catalyst remains in the surfactant-rich phase and is enclosed by the surfactant aggregates. Five runs were performed with Novel 1216CO-8 as most promising nonionic surfactant because of its narrow range molecular weight distribution. It was found by analysing the aqueous phases of all runs, that Pd losses were not crucial. The most impact on reaction rate was observed by the losses of ligand, with 20 % in each run, what finally decreased the rate, as palladium black was formed in the last run. To demonstrate the adaptability of the three phase system, aryl chlorides were also investigated in the coupling with 4-Methylbenzeneboronic acid. Therefore, the water soluble ligand S-Phos developed by Buchwald was chosen. With the appropriate ligands for aryl bromides and chlorides almost the same reaction rate was observed under comparable reaction conditions. The activation energy for the coupling of aryl chlorides was estimated to be 62 kJ/mol for the rate determing step. The drawback of the Buchwald ligand, applied in the microemulsion system was demonstrated in the recycling experiments.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Suzuki-Kupplung von 2-Brombenzonitril mit p-Tolylboronsäure wurde unter Verwendung des wasserlöslichen Katalysatorkomplexes Pd-TPPTS in Mikroemulsionen untersucht. Die Formulierung und das Phasenverhalten von Mikroemulsionen (Heptan, Wasser und Tensid) wurden unter Reaktionsbedingungen untersucht, mit dem Ziel der Steigerung der Reaktionsgeschwindigkeit im Vergleich zu einem Zweiphasensystem (ohne Tensid). In Heptan/Wasser (1:1) wurde ein unselektiver Reaktionsverlauf zum Homokuppelprodukt der Arylboronsäure festgestellt. Als Referenz wurde die Suzuki Kupplung auch in Acetonitril als häufig genutztes Lösungsmittel für derartige Reaktionen durchgeführt. Hierin konnte die Reaktionsgeschwindigkeit nicht merklich gesteigert werden im Vergleich zum Mikroemulsionssystem und des Weiteren ist ein Katalysatorrecycling im polar aprotischen Lösungsmittel nicht möglich. Durch das Auffinden von Mischungslücken bieten Mikroemulsionen als Reaktionsmedium den Vorteil eines einfachen Katalysatorrecyclings, der Produktisolierung und das Entfernen von Salzen. Speziell nichtionische Tenside sind prädestiniert dafür flüssige Dreiphasensysteme zu bilden. Da sich das Phasenverhalten während der Reaktion ändert, wurden die Mikroemulsionen so eingestellt, dass das Dreiphasengebiet erst bei vollständigen Umsätzen erscheint und so als Indikator genutzt werden kann, was heißt, dass keine Online-Analytik nötig ist. Das Katalysatorrecycling wird durchgeführt, indem die Öl- und die wässrige Phase entfernt und durch frische ersetzt werden. Das Produkt kann dabei aus der Ölphase isoliert werden, während durch den Austausch der wässrigen Phase die Salze entfernt werden, die den Katalysator vergiften können. Der Katalysator verbleibt dabei im Reaktor, in der tensidreichen Phase (Mitte). Fünf aufeinander folgende Reaktionen wurden mit Novel 8 als viel versprechendes Tensid durchgeführt. Die Wasserphasen jedes Recyclingschrittes wurden analysiert, wobei der Phosphorverlust (20 % jeweils) sich entscheidend auf die Reaktionsrate ausgewirkt hat, da mit dem letzten Zyklus Pd schwarz gebildet wurde. Um die allgemeine Anwendbarkeit von Dreiphasensystemen zu testen, wurden auch Arylchloride unter Verwendung des wasserlöslichen Buchwald-Liganden gekuppelt. Mit den jeweils geeigneten Liganden wurden ähnliche Reaktionsverläufe für Arylchloride und -bromide erhalten. Die Aktivierungsenergie für die Kupplung von Arylchloriden wurde für den geschwindigkeitsbestimmenden Schritt zu 62 kJ/mol bestimmt. Ein Nachteil des Buchwald-Liganden im Mikroemulsionssystem zeigte sich in den unvollständigen Recyclingschritten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-11-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2695</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28377</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28377</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2695/nowothnick_henriette.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
