<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:47:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:770">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:770</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Modellgestützte Überwachung und Führung von Fed-Batch-Prozessen zur Antibiotikaproduktion</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Model Predictive Monitoring and Control for Fed-Batch Processes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Heine, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Ziel der Arbeit ist die Entwicklung und Erprobung von onlinefähigen Prozessführungsstrategien für strukturiert modellierte biologische Systeme. Als mathematische Modelle dienen zwei verschiedene, nichtlineare mittelstrukturierte Kompartimentmodelle mit bis zu 16 Modellzuständen und bis zu 65 Modellparametern. Durch reale Fermentationsläufe der Stämme Streptomyces griseus und Streptomyces tendae wird die praktische Umsetzung der angewandten Verfahren veranschaulicht. Die Identifikation der Parameter des Kompartimentmodells für den Stamm S. griseus wurde mit Hilfe der Maximum-Likelihood-Estimation durchgeführt. Die hierfür benötigte Kovarianzmatrix des Messrauschens basiert auf einer statistischen Auswertung von 11200 Einzelmessungen. Die Güte der Parameteridentifikation wurde im Sinne einer Validierung durch die in dieser Arbeit gezeigten Prozessführungen und anhand von Experimenten, die nicht Grundlage der Identifikation waren, überprüft. Der zu erwartende, verbleibende Parameterfehler lässt sich mit der Fischer'schen Informationsmatrix, die auch die Grundlage der Optimalen Versuchsplanung bildet, abschätzen. Die in der Arbeit gezeigten Prozessführungskonzepte basieren auf offline geplanten Prozesstrajektorien. Für die genannten, eingeschränkt steuerbaren biologischen Systeme wurden mittels direkter Schießverfahren optimale Zustands- und Messgrößentrajektorien berechnet. Aufgrund von Störungen und verbliebenen Modellunsicherheiten weicht ein Fermentationsprozess immer wieder vom wunschgemäßen Verlauf ab. Im Onlinebetrieb sind diese Abweichungen messtechnisch nicht zugänglich und müssen mit Hilfe von Zustandsschätzverfahren, wie dem Constrained-Extended-Kalman-Fiter oder der Moving-Horizon-State-Estimation, aus den online verfügbaren Messgrößen rekonstruiert werden. Die Einstellungen der Zustandsschätzverfahren basieren auf einer nichtlinearen Optimierung der Prädiktionsgenauigkeit des Extended-Kalman-Filters. Zur Koordination der Einzelaufgaben bei der modellbasierten Prozessauslegung, -führung und -überwachung wurde ein netzwerkfähiges, modulares Prozessleitsystem (PLS) entwickelt, dessen interne Kommunikation auf Standards wie TCP/IP/UDP, OPC und ODBC basiert. Um dem hohen Rechenbedarf von optimierungsbasierten Prozessführungskonzepten gerecht zu werden, können die Computer des PLS bei der Optimierung zu einem Rechencluster zusammengeschaltet werden. Zwei Prozessführungskonzepte, die nichtlineare modellprädiktive Folgeregelung (NMPC) und die online durchgeführte wiederholte Trajektorienplanung, werden anhand von gestörten Fermentationsläufen zur Antibiotikaproduktion verglichen. Der Prozessverlauf wird dezentral auf Internetseiten visualisiert. Hier sind die Zeitverläufe der Mess- und Schätzdaten, die Modellprädiktionen und ein Ablaufreport der Prozessführung dargestellt. Die wichtigsten Daten werden für den Zugriff von WAP-fähigen Mobiltelefonen aufbereitet und als Grafiken in ein WAP-Dokument eingebunden. Bei auftretenden Störungen erfolgt die Alarmierung durch Versenden von Email und SMS. Über eine Text-to-Speech Engine wird die Störung den Prozessbetreuern durch einen Telefonanruf gemeldet. Der Zugriff auf prozessnahe Regler des PLS ist für die Prozessbetreuer auch aus der Ferne über Email und Internet möglich.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Biological processes show complex internal regulation mechanisms and strong nonlinear behaviour which makes it difficult to find an appropriate control concept. Classical approaches based on heuristics or linearized models often yield insufficient results for biological systems. Therefore, the need for nonlinear model-based algorithms for process development, control and monitoring has increased. The quality of model-based concepts directly depends on the accuracy of the model and its parameters. Hence, in order to describe the complex internal regulation cycles, structured models have to be used. These models predict the dynamic interaction of the biological compartments, e.g. DNA, RNA and proteins, by using coupled nonlinear differential equations. The models for Streptomyces tendae and Streptomyces griseus, including up to 16 states and over 60 parameters, form the basis of the present work. The unknown parameters of the S. griseus model were identified using the Maximum-Likelihood-Estimation. An adaptation of this algorithm for biological fermentations allowed the identification of the parameters with a high degree of accuracy from pure, nonequidistant and noisy measurements. The remaining estimation errors were evaluated by analyzing the Fischer-Information-Matrix of the identification experiments. The design of optimal dynamic experiments for parameter estimation then further minimized the remaining error in the model parameters. Furthermore, cyclic application of this algorithm, realization of the experiments and parameter identification were undertaken. This resulted in an accurate mathematical description of the fermentation process. The model obtained could be used to develop optimal model-based process control and process monitoring strategies. For the application of model-based control, knowledge of the system's state is required. During fermentation the real state differs from the model state prediction. Therefore, state estimation has to be performed. Well-known state estimation algorithms for nonlinear state space systems are the Extended-Kalman-Filter (EKF), the Constrained-EKF (CEKF) and the Moving-Horizon-State-Estimation (MHSE). In particular, the CEKF and MHSE provided better results than the EKF for the fermentations considered, because they are based on a constrained nonlinear optimization. In order to guarantee an optimal state estimation, the design of the parameters of the filter was performed by nonlinear optimization of the state estimation quality. This was based on extensive experimental data. In addition, tuning of a Maximum-Likelihood like expression was used as an objective function for this filter. In order to obtain high productivity it was necessary to find the optimal fermentation strategy. In a fed-batch the productivity is affected by the cost of the fermentation and its product yield. By optimizing the feeding profiles, it was possible to identify the trajectory which resulted in the highest product yield. Based on this optimal trajectory, open loop control is possible. However, because of disturbances the real state of the system will differ from the trajectory projected offline, resulting in sub-optimal productivity. Thus, a closed loop control is needed. As the system is strongly nonlinear and as a dynamic setpoint trajectory is obtained, it is not possible to use linear control strategies for fed-batch fermentations. The classical nonlinear model predictive control and a control algorithm based on online optimization of the complete future trajectory were applied to fermentations of S. griseus and S. tendae. The application of the model-based process development, control and monitoring to real fed-batch fermentations requires a hard- and software infrastructure. Therefore, a modular process control system was developed, which evenly distributed the optimization tasks to the computers in the local area network. The monitoring of the online measurements and the state estimations was possible over an internet web page which displayed the plotted data. The alarm management system can issue alerts by automatically sending e-mails and SMS text messages or by making telephone voice calls automatically reading the error message until it is acknowledged by one of the operators. The control mode and the setpoints of the most important controllers can be set either over the internet or by sending e-mails. The present work comprises all the required steps of model-based process development, control and monitoring for closed loop nonlinear model predictive controlled fermentations.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2004-11-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/770</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-7646</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-7646</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/770/heine_thomas.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
