<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:24Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1759">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1759</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Simulationsgestützte Methoden zur Ermittlung der Wirkung partizipativer Maßnahmen auf den lokalen Verkehr</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Simulation-based Methodology for Determining the Impact of Partizipative Intervention on Local Traffic Conditions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sumpf, Joachim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Ziel Diese Arbeit zeigt einen Weg auf, wie sich die Auswirkungen lokaler Verkehrsmaßnahmen mittels eines Simulators darstellen lassen. Zielgruppe sind die Teilnehmer von Bürgerversammlungen, denen eine Vorstellung darüber vermittelt werden soll, welche Folgen die vorgeschlagenen Eingriffe in den Verkehrsraum haben.. Bisher war es vergleichsweise schwierig bzw. teuer, die Wirkungen kleinräumiger Maßnahmen vorab zu ermitteln. Ausgangslage Für diesen Zweck fehlte bisher ein Simulationsprogramm mit ausreichender Detaillierung. Die für großräumige Projekte eingesetzten Simulatoren können lokale Verkehrssituationen auf Stra-ßenabschnitten mit Sammelfunktion und Durchgangsverkehr in Bereichen mit verdichtetem Wohnen nur unzureichend abbilden bzw. ihr Einsatz ist, bezogen auf das Bauvorhaben, zu teuer. Aufgabe Es war eine praktikable Methode zu schaffen, mit der sich die Wirkungen der verschiedenen lo-kaler Verkehrsmaßnahmen darstellen und miteinander vergleichen lassen. Eine besondere Her-ausforderung lag darin, dieses mit Mitteln zu erreichen, die auch den beteiligten Bürgern zugäng-lich sind. (Simulation sollte z.B. durchführbar sein auf handelsüblichem PC/Laptop. Hierzu war ein geeigneter Simulator zu identifizieren und über Versuchsreihen nachzuweisen, dass mit ihm realitätsnah Verkehrsfluss, Emissionen, Kraftstoffverbrauch und Unfallrisiken wie-dergegeben werden können.. Dieses Verfahren soll auch einen Beitrag leisten können zu einem Interessenausgleich zwischen sozialer Verträglichkeit des Verkehrs und dessen Effizienz. Lösungsweg Anstelle eines schon länger verfügbaren makroskopischen Typs, wurde für diese Zielsetzung ein submikroskopischer Simulator eingesetzt, da dieser die Spezifika einzelner Fahrer und Fahrzeuge, ihre Interaktion und individuellen Verhaltensweisen in lokalen Verkehrssituationen besonders realitätsnah darstellen kann. Jeder Fahrer wird durch sein Reaktions- und Schätzvermögen und seine Risikobereitschaft charakterisiert. Wichtiger Faktor für einen realitätsnahen Verkehrsfluss ist Folgeverhalten und Annäherung. Des Weiteren sollten die Fahrer nur Informationen verarbeiten, die auch für sie sichtbar sind, um nur auf dieser Basis zu entscheiden und zu handeln. Um die auf diesem Simulatortyp basierende Methode zur Ermittlung der Auswirkungen von Ein-griffen zu verifizieren, wurde ein Versuchsprogramm aus Simulationsläufen aufgestellt, durch das die Machbarkeit des Vorgehens und die Erzeugung realitätsnaher Daten durch Vergleiche mit den Deskriptionsformeln der verkehrstechnischen Literatur belegt werden kann. Ergebnis Die Untersuchungen waren in die Breite, nicht in die Tiefe angelegt. Daher gab es nicht ausrei-chend viele vergleichbare Werte, um sie nach den strengen Kriterien von Signifikanz überprüfen zu können. Vielmehr war es das Ziel dieser Arbeit, die Zulässigkeit und Durchführbarkeit der Methode nachzuweisen. Diese Vorgabe wurde erreicht, wobei sich weitere Möglichkeiten zeigten, die Einflussfaktoren auf Emissionen und Unfallursachen genauer zu bestimmen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Simulation-based Methodology for Determining the Impact of Par-tizipative Intervention on Local Traffic Conditions Target The thesis is presenting a methodology to assess and display the effects of locally limited inter-ventions on roads by using a simulation. It is targeted on the participants of civic assemblies to better assess the outcomes of traffic interferences under consideration. In fact, it was hitherto complicated respectively expensive to assess the impact of locally introduced measures. Basics As to now, for the purpose of sufficiently detailed results, no adequate simulation programme has been available. Simulations used for big scale traffic projects are not applicable to display local traffic situations, since their ability to reproduce these local situations is rendered not satisfactory or inadequately expensive. This accounts primarily to sections of collector roads particularly with through traffic in dense housing areas. Tasks The task is to create a practical method to compare and to display the effects of various interven-tions on local traffic. The particular challenge in reaching this goal is the employment of means and tools accessible to the participating or concerned persons, i.e. a simulation feasible to run on an ordinary personal computer or laptop.For that purpose a suitable simulation programme has to be identified and its ability to realistically model traffic flow, emissions, consumption and acci-dent risk has to be verified via appropriate test suits. Moreover, this methodology is made to bal-ance the conflicting targets of transport, i.e. its social reasonability and its efficiency. Technical Solution Instead of the macroscopic type in use for some time, a microscopic simulation is applied in order to get realistic results with a higher refinement of the results. This special type is made to process the specific attributes of every driver and vehicle, their interaction and the individual attitudes under local traffic situation. Every driver is characterized by his or her ability to judge and react to traffic situations, as well as his or her willingness to take risks. A crucial criterion for reproducing a realistic traffic flow is the tailgating and approaching process. Lastly, since drivers are reacting only to visible or audible information available, for the simulation only such information is taken into account. In order to verify the methodology to assess the outcomes of interventions based on the chosen type of simulation tool, a broad test scheme has been implemented to prove the accountability of the processes applied, as well as the validity of data generated by comparing them with the results of describing formulas, specified in the traffic technology literature. Result The test series were not designed to generate an in depth result, but rather a wide scale outcome. Hence, no sufficient provisions of similar and comparable sets of data were gained that could be verified under the strict criteria of statistical significance. The intention of the thesis was rather to prove feasibility and practicability of the selected methodology. This objective was met and, moreover, the results are identifying some additional potential to determine more interdependen-cies between traffic flow and emissions and likewise, accident causation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-04-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18429</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18429</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1759/sumpf_joachim.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
