<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:48:27Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:938">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:938</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Entmischungs- und Kristallisationsverhalten des metallischen Massivglases Pd40Cu30Ni10P20</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Decomposition and crystallisation behaviour of bulk metallic glass Pd40Cu30Ni10P20</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Davydov, Evgeny</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das metallische Massivglas Pd40Cu30Ni10P20 gehört zu den besten Glasbildnern. Dieses Glas hat eine große thermischen Stabilität gegen Kristallisation im Bereich der unterkühlten Schmelze und kann bereits bei kritischen Abkühlraten ? 0.1 K/s in Form massiver, vollständig amorpher Körper hergestellt werden. Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit wurde das Entmischungs- und das Krisatllisationsvehalten dieses Massivglases mit Hilfe von Differentialwärmeflusskalorimetrie, Röntgendiffraktometrie, Rasterelektronenmikroskopie, hochauflösender Elektronenmikroskopie, energiedispersiver Röntgenspektrometrie und dreidimensionaler Atomsondenanalyse (3DAP) untersucht. Das Ausgangsmaterial war vollständig amorph ohne Anzeichen von Inhomogenitäten. Bei Wärmebehandlung dicht oberhalb der Glasübergangstemperatur entmischt das Glas bereits lange vor Einsetzen der Kristallisation. Nach 20 h Wärmebehandlung bei 590 K zeigte die 3DAP-Analyse eine amorphe Entmischung aller Legierungselemente im nm-Bereich. Erst nach 30 h bei dieser Temperatur ergaben sich im Röntgendiffraktogramm erste Anzeichen einer Kristallisation. Die Zusammensetzung der Primärkristalle folgt der durch die vorangegangene Entmischung vorgegebenen Richtung unter weiterer Ni- und P-Anreicherung. Die amorphe Matrix zwischen den Ästen der sternförmigen Primärkristalle ist an Ni und an P verarmt. Untersuchungen bei verschiedenen Temperaturen der Wärmebehandlung zeigten eine starke Abhängigkeit des Kristallisationsverhaltens von der thermischen Vorgeschichte und Temperaturführung. Bereits bei einer geringen Erhöhung der Temperatur von 590 K auf 600 K bilden sich weitgehend andere kristalline Phasen. Die Phasen, die bei Wärmebehandlung des Glases kristallisieren, wurden mit den Phasen, die aus der langsam abgekühlten flüssigen Schmelze kristallisieren, verglichen. Dabei ist zumindest die primäre kristalline Phase, die bei der langsammen Erstarrung entsteht, eine Gleichgewichtsphase des Pd-Cu-Ni-P-Systems. Die Zusammensetzung dieser Phase ähnelt der primären Phase, die aus dem Glas kristallisiert. Ein Vergleich der entsprechenden Röntgendiffraktogramme ergibt Anzeichen für strukturelle Ähnlichkeiten.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The bulk metallic glass Pd40Cu30Ni10P20 is one of the best glass formers with a high thermal stability against crystallisation in the region of the undercooled liquid. It can be produced as completely amorphous bulky samples from the liquid melt at critical cooling rates ≥ 0.1 K/s. The decomposition and crystallisation behaviour of this glass were investigated here by differential scanning calorimetry, X-ray powder diffraction (XRD), scanning electron microscopy, transmission electron microscopy, energy dispersive X-ray spectrometry and three-dimensional atom probe analysis (3DAP). In the as-cast state the glass was completely amorphous without any indication of inhomogeneity. The glass decomposed by annealing just above the glass transition temperature, well before the beginning of the crystallisation. After annealing at 590 K for 20 h the 3DAP-analysis showed an amorphous decomposition of all elements on the nm-scale. Indications of crystallisation were detected by XRD first after 30 h annealing time at this temperature. The composition of the primary crystals follows the direction defined by the preceding decomposition, with further Ni- and P-enrichment. Accordingly the amorphous matrix between the branches of these star-shaped primary crystals was depleted in Ni and P. Investigations at different annealing temperatures showed a very strong dependence of the crystallisation behaviour on the thermal history and the temperature conditions. Even at the slightly increased temperature of 600 K completely different crystalline phases form to a great extent. The phases, crystallised after annealing the glass, were compared with the phases which had formed during the slow cooling of the liquid alloy melt. At least the primary phase, developed during the slow solidification, was an equilibrium phase of the Pd-Cu-Ni-P-system. The composition of this phase was similar to that of the primary phase, crystallised from the glass. A comparison of the X-ray diffractograms indicated structural similarities of these both phases.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2005-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/938</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-9319</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-9319</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/938/davydov_evgeny.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
