<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:50Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2485">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2485</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Zuverl√§ssigkeitsuntersuchung von GaAs Hetero√ºbergang-Bipolartransistoren </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Reliability investigation of GaAs heterojunction bipolar transistors</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pazirandeh, Reza</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wurde die Zuverl√§ssigkeit von Hochfrequenz-GaAs-Hetero√ºbergang-Bipolartransistoren (HBTs), die am Ferdinand-Braun-Institut f√ºr H√∂chstfrequenztechnik (FBH) f√ºr Anwendungen mit hohen Zuverl√§ssigkeitsanforderungen (Mobilfunk, Weltraum) hergestellt wurden, untersucht. Die Lebensdaueruntersuchungen erfolgten parallel zur Technologieentwicklung, um den Einfluss der Variation der Technologieparameter auf die Lebensdauer der HBTs zu untersuchen und der Technologie entsprechende R√ºckmeldungen zu geben. Zus√§tzlich wurden analytische Untersu-chungen an degradierten HBTs durchgef√ºhrt, um Schwachstellen und die f√ºr Ausf√§lle verantwortli-chen Degradationsmechanismen zu identifizieren und zu charakterisieren. Die Bestimmung der mittleren Lebensdauer der HBTs in einem angemessenen Zeitraum erfolgte unter Beschleunigung der Alterung durch Erh√∂hung der Umgebungstemperatur und der Kollektorstromdichte. Mit Hilfe der Arrhenius-Gleichung wurde die mittlere Lebensdauer bei normalen Bedingungen aus den Daten der beschleunigten Alterung (unterschiedliche Temperaturen, gleiche Kollektorstromdichte) durch Extrapolation bestimmt. Hierf√ºr wurde ein HBT mit einem Emitterfinger von 3√ó30 ¬µm2 entworfen, der in allen Layouts integriert und auf allen prozessierten Wafern hergestellt wurde. F√ºr die Alterungsmessungen wurden Messmethoden entwickelt und dazu passende Messpl√§tze entworfen. Die Unterst√ºtzung der Entwicklung der HBTs mit Zuverl√§ssigkeitsuntersuchungen f√ºhrte zur Steigerung der mittleren Lebensdauer auf = 1,1√ó107 Stunden, die den Anforderungen um eine Gr√∂√üenordnung √ºbertrifft. Diese Werte geh√∂ren zu den besten publizierten Werten, obwohl sie bei deutlich h√∂heren Stromdichten erreicht wurden, was f√ºr die besondere Zuverl√§ssigkeit dieser Bauelemente spricht. Die Untersuchung von degradierten HBTs nach Degradationsmechanismen ergab, dass die rekombinationsbeschleunigte Defektreaktion (REDR) der Hauptdegradationsmechanismus ist. Bei diesem Degradationsmechanismus f√ºhrt die durch nichtstrahlende Rekombination freigesetzte Energie zur Entstehung von Punktdefekten, die wiederum als nichtstrahlende Rekombinationszentren agieren und die Entstehung weiterer Punktdefekte beschleunigen. Das f√ºhrt zur Ausbildung von Punktdefektclustern und zum Wachstum und zur Ausbreitung von Versetzungen. Die Defektentstehung und -ausbreitung konnten mithilfe von Elektrolumineszenzuntersuchungen beobachtet werden. Untersuchungen in TEM zeigten, dass degradierte HBTs Versetzungen aufweisen, die vom Emitter ausgehen und in die Basis reichen, in manchen F√§llen sogar bis in den Kollektor. Die Charakterisierung der Versetzungen zeigt, dass es sich um Mischtypen handelt. Diese sind durch die besonders lange Alterung und starke Degradation aus verschiedenen Typen von Versetzungen enstanden. Weitere Degradationsmechanismen wie Metalldiffusion ins Halbleitermaterial oder die Entstehung von Kohlenstoffpr√§zipitaten in der Basisschicht wurden bei diesen HBTs nicht beobachtet. Zusammenfassend kann festgestellt werden, dass eine zuverl√§ssige Methodik und Messtechnik zur Bestimmung der Lebensdauer von HBTs entwickelt und etabliert wurde. Die Entwicklung der GaAs-HBT-Technologie am FBH konnte durch Einsatz der Messtechnik und physikalischen Analysemethoden unterst√ºtzt werden, um zuverl√§ssige Bauelemente zu entwickeln, die den Anspr√ºchen der potenziellen Anwendungen gerecht werden und international konkurrenzf√§hig sind.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work describes the investigation of reliability of InGaP/GaAs heterojunction bipolar transistors (HBT) fabricated at the Ferdinand-Braun-Institut f√ºr H√∂chstfrequenztechnik (FBH) in Berlin, Germany. Measurement methods and setups to determine the reliability of the GaAs HBTs were developed and established. Analytic methods were used to localize and to characterize the degradation mechanisms in these devices. The investigation and measurements were performed close to device development to give feedback on the influence of technology parameter variations on the reliability of the HBTs for further optimization of the devices. The reliability of the HBTs was determined by stressing the devices at elevated temperature and collector current densities to accelerate the degradation and to obtain life time results within a reasonable time frame. The mean time to failure (MTTF) at ‚Äúnormal‚Ä? operating conditions was extrapolated from the accelerated data in accordance with the theory of Arrhenius, which describes the temperature dependence of reaction rate. The reliability measurements were all performed on HBTs with one emitter finger with dimensions of 3√ó30 ¬µm2. Increased epitaxial layer quality and the quality of the active layer interfaces led to increased MTTF of the HBTs to 1.1√ó107 h. Comparable values were also obtained by other groups, but at much lower current densities. This shows the world class quality of the technology and its reliability without loss of performance. The degradation mechanisms were investigated on degraded HBTs, which result that recombination enhanced defect reaction (REDR) is the main degradation mechanism in these devices. This process can be explained as follows: recombination in the base leads to emission of photons, but at some existing defects the energy of the non-radiative recombination is emitted as phonons and can lead to creation of more defects or to growth of existing defects to defect clusters or dislocations and even to gliding of the dislocations. These defects and dislocation act also as recombination centers and amplify this mechanism through a positive feedback. The mechanism is known as recombination enhanced defect reaction - REDR. The existence and creation of the defects and other degradation mechanisms were investigated on degraded HBTs in transmission electron microscope. Dislocations were observed in the base and collector having their origin in the base-emitter junction. The existence of the dislocation in the collector can be explained by their glide through receiving the energy from recombination at the dislocation. Material analysis with energy dispersive x-ray spectroscopy (EDXS) found diffusion of Indium out of the emitter in degraded HBTs in areas without defects or dislocations. Further element analysis with EDXS showed no diffusion of metal into the semiconductor material and also no carbon precipitates were observed, as were reported from other groups. This confirms the stability of the epitaxial materials and the contact metallization. During this work the development of reliable GaAs based hetero-junction bipolar transistors was successfully supported. Setups for on-wafer and long-term reliability measurements were established to determine the median time to failure (MTTF) of the devices. With this setup the superior reliability of GaAs HBTs fabricated at FBH was demonstrated at high current densities. It was shown that the main degradation mechanism in the HBTs is the recombination enhanced defect reaction.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-04-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2485</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26237</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26237</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2485/pazirandeh_reza.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
