<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3487">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3487</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:300</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Community-based environmental sanitation planning approaches for the South: the household-centred approach</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Partizipative Siedlungshygiene in Entwicklungsländern: der haushaltszentrierte Ansatz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lüthi, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:300</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This paper PhD is the result of several years of cross-country comparative research in Africa, Asia and Latin America on demand-led, participatory sanitation planning. The area of study are poor, unplanned settlements in urban and per-urban areas of the Global South. The research focuses on the question of how poor and disenfranchised urban communities can gain access to basic urban services and infrastructure that are affordable and sustainable. Three case studies are analysed and compared in Laos, Nepal and Tanzania, where the household-centred planning approach (HCES) was validated between 2008 and 2010. In the three countries, poor and unplanned neighbourhoods of various contextual formation tested the sanitation planning approach, followed by a ex-post evaluation. This research confirms the utility of open-ended, participatory planning processes and the early and meaningful engagement of citizens. Three main advantages can be noted: i) meaningful community participation leads to more sustainable solutions and services that can guarantee financial and operational sustainability; ii) there is a causality between the formation of social capital in the urban communities studied and the early engagement with communities in planning processes; iii) thanks to the household-centred approach, linkages between soft factors (such as behaviour change) and hardware (new infrastructure)could better be achieved.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese kumulative Dissertation ist das Ergebnis mehrjähriger vergleichender Feldforschung in Afrika, Asien und Lateinamerika zu partizipativen Planungsverfahren, die die Verbesserung städtischer Infrastrukturen in Armutssiedlungen in Entwicklungsländern zum Ziel hat. Die Studie befasst sich mit der aktuellen Fragestellung, wie Lebensbedingungen und Basisdienstleistungen in unterversorgten Armutssiedlungen kosteneffizient und nachhaltig geplant und umgesetzt werden können. Für die vorliegende Studie wurde in drei Ländern ein Planungskonzept für sanitäre Infrastruktur validiert - besser bekannt als haushaltszentrierte Siedlungshygiene (household-centred environmental sanitation- HCES). In Armutssiedlungen diverser Grössen und Ausprägung wurde das haushaltszentrierte Planungskonzept HCES zur Verbesserung der Siedlungshygiene zwischen 2007 und 2010 in Laos, Nepal und Tansania getestet. Dabei wurden die einzelnen Planungsschritte analysiert und eine Ex-Post Evaluation nach Abschluss des Planungsprozesses durchgeführt. Diese unterstreicht den Nutzen von partizipativen, ergebnisoffenen Entscheidungsprozessen und den frühzeitigen Einbezug von betroffenen Stadtteilbewohnern in dreierlei Hinsicht: i) Die erhöhte Aneignung städtischer Infrastruktur (ownership) bietet die Möglichkeit zu nachhaltigeren Lösungen, deren Unterhalt eher gewährleistet werden kann; ii) Durch eine frühzeitige und relevante Mitsprache im Planungsverfahren wird die Entstehung von Sozialkapital in armen städtischen Siedlungen in Bezug auf kollektive Problemlösung, Vertrauen und Solidarität gefördert; iii) Eine Verzahnung von technischen und ‚weichen‘ Faktoren wie Verhaltensänderung oder Zahlungsbereitschaft kann so eher erreicht werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-10-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3487/luethi_christoph.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
