<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:01Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1898">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1898</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:300</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Fragmented perspectives, transiting signs of urbanity - Everyday life's representations and uses of space in Dhaka, Bangladesh </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Fragmentarische Perspektiven, vergehende Zeichen von Urbanität - Alltagsrepräsentationen und -Nutzungen vom Raum in Dhaka, Bangladesch</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bertuzzo, Elisa Tullia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:300</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Can urbanisation processes, traditional study object of planners, demographers and sociologists, be analysed from a cultural point of view? This dissertation's starting point consists of the insight that, in order to understand, and possibly plan, increasingly complex and steadily changing cities, urban studies need to focus on people. Conceived of as an empirical study, it examines spaces and situations of the mega city Dhaka in direct and differentiating way. It takes hereby the twofold risk to apply a philosophical construct like Henri Lefebvre's theory of the „Production of Space“ and to trust the power of language not only to describe, but to „make perceivable“ urban processes. Object of interest is Dhaka's space, understood in Lefebvre's sense as the result of three continuously interacting production processes, or fields. In particular, space is physically, mentally and socially „produced“ by means of practices of everyday life, which constitute the focus of the observation. Material features characterising the physical field – architectural and infrastructural aspects as well as routines and mobility – are described on the basis of own observation and associative walks in six different urban structural types within Dhaka City Corporation's area. A questionnaire and mental maps, collecting the dwellers' ideas on space and urban places, provide an insight into spatial thinking and representations, concerned by the mental field. The role played by everyday life social interaction for the production of space is demonstrated by means of six different „settings“, which were analysed thanks to participant observation. The study succeeds in demonstrating that, for dwellers' representations of space, emotional and symbolic features have primary relevance compared to architecture and urban design. That is to say: space is not only „perceived“ on a sensual or physical level, but loaded with symbolic meanings and actively interpreted according to personal and cultural values. This allows to state that primarily mental factors of the production of space, and not the actual congestion and lack of space itself in the mega city, are determinant for spatial behaviour and use. Among others, the dissertation describes the production of „enriched“, or multifunctional, spaces through everyday life practices. The chronic informality characterising all sectors of social life in Dhaka is showed to offer a potential for the emergence of mixed forms of urban management. The empirical application to a concrete city demonstrates the actuality and value of Lefebvre's trialectic model for the analysis of contemporary urbanisation processes. At the same time, it recognises in philosophy, able to deliver models that can guide the approach of also concrete objectives, a potential for urban studies.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Ausgehend von der Erkenntnis, dass Stadtforschung - will sie zunehmend komplexe urbane Gesellschaften in ihrem Wandel verstehen und Grundlagen für ihre Planung liefern - ihren Fokus auf den Menschen setzen muss, erforscht diese empirische Studie Räume und Situationen der Mega City Dhaka direkt und differenzierend. Dabei nimmt sie die zweifache Herausforderung an, ein philosophisches Konstrukt wie die Theorie der Produktion des Raums von Henri Lefebvre anzuwenden, und auf die Kraft der Sprache als Medium nicht nur des Beschreibens, sondern des einprägsamen Spürbar-Machens zu setzen. Die Aufmerksamkeit wird bewusst auf den gesamten Stadtraum gerichtet, verstanden im Sinne Lefebvres als Ergebnis drei kontinuierlich aufeinander wirkender Produktionsprozesse, oder Felder: Physisch, mental und sozial wird Raum aufgrund menschlicher sozialer Praktiken stets „produziert“. Die materiellen Gegebenheiten des physischen Felds - architektonische, bauliche und infrastrukturelle Eigenarten sowie Routinen und Mobilität – werden aufgrund von Aufenthalten und assoziativen Spaziergängen in sechs verschiedenen Stadtstrukturtypen im Bereich der Dhaka City Corporation beschrieben. Räumliches Denken und Repräsentationen im Rahmen des mentalen Felds werden anhand eines Fragebogens und Versuche mit mental maps ergründet, welche die Vorstellungen der Bevölkerung über Raum und städtische Orte sammelten. Die Bedeutung sozialer Interaktionen im Alltag für die Produktion vom Raum wird am Beispiel von sechs Lebensräumen ersichtlich, die durch teilnehmende Beobachtung analysiert werden konnten. Zu den wichtigsten Ergebnisse der Arbeit zählt die Erkenntnis, dass Raum nicht nur in seiner physischen Zusammenfassung sinnlich wahrgenommen, sondern mit symbolischen Bedeutungen geladen und anhand persönlicher und kultureller Werte interpretiert wird. Dies gibt Grund zu behaupten, dass primär mentale Faktoren der Produktion von Rau, und nicht der Mangel oder die Überbevölkerung vom Raum selbst, räumliches Verhalten und Nutzung determinieren. Unter anderem wird die Produktion von „angereicherten“, oder multifunktionalen Räumen durch Alltagspraktiken beschrieben. In der charakteristischen Informalität aller Felder sozialen Lebens wird ein möglicher Auslöser für die Entstehung tragfähiger Mischformen der Stadtentwicklung erkannt. Die empirische Anwendung an einer konkreten Stadt beweist, dass Lefebvres trialektisches Modell der Produktion des Raums wesentliche Vorteile für die Analyse aktuell stattfindender Urbanisierungsprozesse aufweist, und räumt der Philosophie mit ihrem Vermögen, weit umfassende Reflexionen über auch konkrete Sachverhalte zu liefern, eine wichtige Rolle für die Stadtforschung ein.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-09-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1898</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-19643</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-19643</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1898/bertuzzo_elisatulia.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1898/bertuzzo_elisatullia_appendix.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
