<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3449">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3449</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Coherent phenomena and control in quantum transport - Correlations, dark states and control in the transport through coupled quantum dots</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Kohärente Phänomene und Kontrolle im Quantentransport - Korrelationen, Dunkelzustände und Kontrolle im Transport durch gekoppelte Quantenpunkte </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pöltl, Christina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In electronic transport through zero dimensional structures, such as coupled quantum dots, coherent effects have become an important aspect. A way to obtain informations about the coherences is to measure the current correlations of the transport devices, since the correlations of the particle flow eventually also contain information about the coherences in the system. The standard parameter evaluated in this field is the zero frequency Fano factor, which defines whether an electron flow is sub- or super-Poissonian in the long time limit. In general it is assumed that a super-Poissonian signal is also bunched and a sub-Poissonian signal is also anti-bunched. We extend the tools for the investigation of transport devices by the g2-function, which is originally used in quantum optics to differentiate whether photon emissions are anti-bunched or bunched. The optical g2-function can be used analogous in electronic transport through few-electron systems. We show that according to the definition of the g2-function an anti-bunched electron flow is not necessarily sub-Poissonian and a bunched electron flow is not necessarily super-Poissonian. A very interesting coherent effect are dark states, which can occur in electronic transport through few-electron systems. Here, one or more electrons become trapped in a coherent superposition of the system, that is decoupled from the outgoing lead, and the transport through the device is blocked. Although the state, in which the electrons are trapped, lies in the transport window. We explain this effects on a triple quantum dot and introduce several systems in which one-electron and two-electron dark states exist. Particularly interesting is a double quantum dot system which is a promising candidate for an experimental realizable dark state and a device which enables the creation of spin entangled two-electron dark states. The last topic of this thesis is the introduction of a feedback control scheme by coherent rotations after the electron jump processes. Here, it should be mentioned that we use a generalized master equation, which enables the inclusion of coherences in a master equation of Lindblad form. This master equation describes not only the dynamics of the occupations, but also the dynamics of the coherences. Due to the Lindblad form of the master equation, a change of the particle number in the device is modeled by projections, the jumps, to a state with a different particle number. An instantaneous rotation right after a jump enables the rotation of the originally state, after the jump, into a desired pure state. With our control scheme we are able to stabilize pure states in the transport devices. We demonstrate our control scheme on two examples. The first example is a double quantum dot, where we show that it is possible to stabilize half the states on the Bloch sphere. The second example are two double quantum dots coupled by Coulomb interaction. This device enables the stabilization of an entangled pure state.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Rolle von kohärenten Effekten im elektronischen Transport durch nulldimensionale Strukturen, wie zum Beispiel Quantenpunkte, ist in den letzten Jahren wichtig geworden. Eine Möglichkeit Informationen über Kohärenzen zu gewinnen ist das Messen von Stromkorrelationen, da diese Korrelationen des Teilchenflusses von den Kohärenzen beeinflusst werden. Der Parameter der in diesem Gebiet am häufigsten berechnet und gemessen wird ist der Fano Faktor, der definiert ob der Teilchenfluss im Langzeitlimies sub- oder super-poissonisch ist. Im Allgemeinen wird angenommen, dass ein sub-poissonisches Signal auch anti-bunched ist und ein super-poissonsches Signal auch bunched ist. Die Einführung der g2-Funktion in den elektronischen Transport differenziert dieses Bild. Die g2-Funktion ist ein Standardparameter in der Quantenoptik um zu messen ob ein Photonenfluss bunched oder anti-bunched ist. Es zeigt sich, dass die g2-Funktion analog im elektronischen Transport durch wenig Elektronensysteme verwendet werden kann. Nach dieser Definition ist ein bunched Elektronenfluss nicht notwendiger Weise super-poissonisch und ein anti-bunched Elektronenfluss muss nicht sub-poissonisch sein. Ein interessanter kohärenter Effekt, der im Transport durch gekoppelte Quantenpunkte auftauchen kann, sind Dunkelzustände in denen ein oder mehrere Elektronen in einer kohärenten Superposition gefangen werden, die vom hinausführenden Elektronenreservoir entkoppelt ist. Der Transport wird blockiert obwohl der Zustand in dem die Elektronen gefangen sind im Transportfenster liegt. In dieser Arbeit wird die Bildung eines Dunkelzustandes anhand eines Dreiquantenpunktsystems erklärt, bevor einige Systeme vorgestellte werden in denen ein- und zweielektronen Dunkelzustände existieren. Besonders erwähnenswert sind hier ein Doppelquantenpunktsystem, das ein interessanter Kandidat für einen experimentell nachweisbaren Dunkelzustand ist, und ein System, das die Präparation von Spin-verschränkten Dunkelzuständen ermöglicht. Das letzte Thema dieser Arbeit ist die Einführung eines Feedback-Kontrollformalismus, durch unitäre Operationen nach den Elektronsprungprozessen. An diesem Punkt sollte erwähnt werden, dass für die Beschreibung der Transportsysteme eine verallgemeinerte Lindblad-Mastergleichung verwendet wird, die die Dynamik der Kohärenzen der sich im System aufhaltenden Elektronen exakt beschreibt. Durch die Lindbladform dieser Gleich\-ung wird eine Änderung der Teilchenzahl im System durch eine Projektion auf einem Zustand mit einer anderen Teilchenzahl beschrieben. Wenn sofort nach einem Sprungprozess eine unitäre Operation auf die sich im System befindenden Elektronen angewandt wird, können diese in einen beliebigen reinen Zustand gedreht werden. Diese Kontrolloperation ermöglicht die Stabilisierung reiner Transportzustände. Dies wird an zwei Beispielen präsentiert. Zum einen ein Doppelquantenpunkt, der als Ladungsqubit fungieren kann. Das andere System sind zwei Doppelquantenpunkte, die durch Coulomb Wechselwirkung gekoppelt sind. Bei diesem System ist die Stabilisierung verschränkter Zustände möglich.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-09-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3449</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36816</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36816</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3449/poeltl_christina.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
