<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:05Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2782">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2782</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Self-organized Quantum Dots for Single Photon Sources</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Selbstorganisierte Quantenpunkte als Einzelphotonequelle</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stock, Erik</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Efficient generation of single or entangled photons is the crucial prerequisite for novel quantum key distribution systems and quantum information processing. Single semiconductor quantum dots (QDs) with their unique electronic structure are capable of emitting such photons on demand using pulsed current injection. In the work at hand self-organized InGaAs/GaAs quantum dots are investigated as sources of single photons both on a fundamental level for understanding of their quantenmechanical properties and in ready-to-use devices. The characterization is done using a micro-photoluminescence and -electroluminescence setup with the required high spatial and spectral resolution. The second order photon correlation function is measured in a Hanbury-Brown Twiss setup equipped with state-of-the-art avalanche photodiodes and new superconducting single photon detectors for increased time-resolution. Three types of devices each of them representing an important development stages towards a high efficient ultra-fast single photon source are characterized. The first device is a simply pin diode structure with a layer of QDs. A single QD is pumped electrically by applying a bias well below the flatband condition. Concurrent resonant tunneling of electrons and holes can be observed in this device by optical means. In the second type of devices the maximum pump rate is increased by an AlOx aperture, which constricts the current to pump only a single QD. This device is the ultimate limit of a light emitting diode (LED) and demonstrates a record pure spectrum with clear single photon emission. In the third device the out-coupling efficiency and repetition rate is significantly improved by the realization of a resonant cavity LED. This device allows perfect single photon emission at record pumping rates of up to 1 GHz with a twenty times enhanced out-coupling efficiency. Since the optical response is too fast for APDs, new superconducting detectors are used in photon correlation measurements. Electron-phonon coupling strongly influences the luminescence line shape, dephasing and coherence of the emitted phonons and thereby the most important characteristics of a non-classical light source. In this work, for the first time, the optical and acoustic phonon scattering in a single InGaAs QD is investigated. By comparing experimental data with calculated spectra a quantitative understanding of the line shape and the dominating phonon modes is achieved. A vanishing fine-structure splitting (FSS) of the exciton bright state is crucial for the generation of entangled photon pairs. A new approach, using QDs on (111) GaAs, to reduce the FSS is investigated. The first spectroscopic study on single QDs grown on (111) GaAs substrates are presented and significant reduction of the FSS for this new kind of QDs is demonstrated.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die effiziente Erzeugung von einzelnen Photonen oder verschränkten Photonenpaaren ist der Schlüssel für neuartige Quantenkryptografie und Quantencomputer. Einzelne Halbleiter Quantenpunkte (QPe) mit ihren einzigartigen elektronischen Eigenschaften, haben bereits bewiesen, dass sie solche Photonen durch elektrische Pulse erzeugen können. In der vorliegenden Arbeit werden selbstorganisierte InGaAs/GaAs Quantenpunkte sowohl auf der fundamentalen Ebene als auch in fertigen Bauelementen auf ihre Eignung als Einzelphotonenquelle untersucht. Für diese Charakterisierung wird ein Mikro-Photolumineszenz und -Elektrolumineszenz Aufbau benutzt, der die notwendige Orts- und Spektralauflösung besitzt. Drei verschiedene Bauelemente werden untersucht, wobei jedes einen bedeutenden Schritt in der Entwicklung zu einer hocheffizienten und sehr schnellen Einzelphotonenquelle darstellt. Im ersten Bauteil, das nur aus einer pin-Struktur besteht, kann ein einzelner QP elektrisch gepumpt werden, indem eine Spannung deutlich unterhalb der Flachband-Spannung angelegt wird. Gleichzeitiges resonantes Tunneln von Elektronen und Löcher in den QP kann mit optischen Methoden nachgewiesen werden. Um die maximale Pumprate zu erhöhen, wird im zweiten Bauelement der Strompfad durch eine AlOx Apertur auf einen einzelnen QP eingeschränkt. Dieses Bauelement repräsentiert den absoluten Grenzfall einer Leuchtdiode und zeigt ein extrem reines Spektrum mit eindeutiger Einzelphotonencharakteristik. Durch die Realisierung einer resonanten Kavitäts Leuchtdiode kann die Auskoppeleffizienz und die maximale Wiederholungsrate verbessert werden. Dieses Bauelement zeigt perfekte Einzelphotonenemission bei einer Rekord-Wiederholungsrate von bis zu 1GHz sowie einer um den Faktor 20 verbesserten Auskoppeleffizienz. Die optische Reaktion dieses Bauteils ist zu schnell für herkömmliche Lawinenfotodioden und es werden daher neuentwickelte supraleitende Detektoren verwendet. Die Elektron-Phonon Wechselwirkung beeinflusst sowohl die spektrale Linienform, die Dephasierung als auch die Kohärenzlänge des emittierten Photons und damit die entscheidendsten Parameter einer nichtklassischen Lichtquelle. In dieser Arbeit wird um ersten Mal die Wechselwirkung von Exzitonen mit akustischen und optischen Phononen in einem einzelnen In- GaAs QP im Detail analysiert. Durch Vergleich mit theoretischen Modellen wird ein Verständnis für die Linienform und die entscheidenden Phononenmoden erzielt. Die Feinstrukturauspaltung (FSA) ist bedeutend für die Erzeugung von verschränkten Photonenpaaren. Ein neuer Ansatz die FSA zu reduzieren wird untersucht. Die ersten spektroskopischen Untersuchungen an einzelnen QP gewachsen auf (111) GaAs werden gezeigt und eine deutliche Verringerung der FSA präsentiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-02-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2782</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29457</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29457</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2782/stock_erik.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
