<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:11Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3657">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3657</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Optical and structural properties of Indium-Nitride epilayers and their growth by High-Pressure Chemical Vapor Deposition</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Optische und strukturelle Eigenschaften von Indiumnitrid Epi-Schichten und deren Wachstum mittels Hochdruck-Gasphasenepitaxy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bügler, Max Johann Ludwig</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In the framework of this work, the structural and optoelectronic properties of epitaxial group III-nitride alloys grown with different deposition techniques will be correlated. A strong emphasis lays in the growth and characterization of epitaxial indium nitride (InN) and indium-rich indium gallium nitride (InGaN) layers by means of high-pressure chemical vapor deposition (HPCVD). The work will provide a brief summary of the advantages and disadvantages of the various deposition techniques presently explored for the growth of InN and InGaN epitaxy, motivating the exploration of HPCVD to overcome the present encountered processing limitations. HPCVD (also denoted as superatmospheric CVD) is a rather new thin film growth technique presently explored at Georgia State University (GSU), with the goal of assessing to what extent superatmospheric reactor pressure enables the stabilization of indium-rich InGaN and their integration into wide bandgap III-nitrides. Different series of InGaN epilayers have been characterized to assess the influence of reactor pressure, the molar group V/III precursors ratio, and precursor pulse separation times, on the structural and optoelectronic properties of the epilayers. Systematic studies on the influence of the precursor exposure timing sequence on the growth surface chemistry revealed that transport and incorporation of the volatile nitrogen species to and at the growth surface are growth limiting steps. Thus, the precursor pulse separation in between ammonia and the following metalorganic precursor has to be as short as possible for the growth of InN, while larger separations are required as the Ga concentration in InGaN is increased. The optimization of InN growth at 15 bar reactor pressure revealed that for a V/III molar precursor flow ratio of 2800 and at a growth temperature of 876°C high quality InN epilayer can be deposited. Adjusting the timing sequences for the growth of InGaN demonstrated the ability to grow single phase, indium-rich InGaN over a wide compositional range. The photoluminescence (PL) spectra for HPCVD grown InN epilayers show broad PL at photon energies below 0.8 eV, tailing down to 0.7 eV. This is due to the high free carrier concentration in the epilayer, filling the conduction band and effectively increasing the optical bandgap. High quality MOCVD and MBE grown epilayers show a shift of the PL to lower photon energies (red shift) and show longitudinal-optical phonon-plasmon (LPP) coupling. The comparison of InN samples grown with different growth techniques shows a further red shift with lower carrier concentration. These results are in good agreement with results obtained from LPP measurements. Temperature and excitation power as well as polarization dependent measurements of the sample with the highest crystalline quality are presented. The free carrier concentration is on the edge towards a degenerated semiconductor, showing degenerated behavior for increased excitation power and temperatures. To assess how high doping levels effect the structural and optical properties of III-nitrides, GaN layers highly doped with silicon (Si) and germanium (Ge) have been investigated. The PL analysis revealed that doping with Ge allows for considerably higher free carrier concentrations of up to 2*10^20 cm^-3 without significant compensation or structural degradation. Almost strain free growth of the Ge doped films on GaN buffers is observed, whereas for Si-doping high tensile strain and strong compensation is observed. The free carrier concentration in the layers were analyzed by LPP measurements and by Hall-effect measurements, both agreeing well. The optical analysis showed that even in the highest Ge-doped sample excitonic transitions can be observed, indicating the existence of so called Mahan excitons.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit werden Untersuchungen der optischen und strukturellen Eigenschaften von epitaktisch gewachsenen Gruppe-III-Nitrid Filmen sowie des Wachstums von Indiumnitrid (InN) und indiumreichem Indiumgalliumnitrid (InGaN) mittels Hochdruck-Gasphasenepitaxie (High-Pressure Chemical Vapour Deposition, HPCVD) dargestellt. Die Vor- und Nachteile verschiedener Wachstumsverfahren für InN und InGaN werden kurz erläutert, um die Forschung an Hochdruck-Gasphasenepitaxy zur Überwindung gegebener Limitierungen im Wachstumsprozess zu motivieren. HPCVD (auch als Superatmospheric-CVD bezeichnet) ist eine recht neue Technik, die an der Georgia State University (GSU)erforscht wird. Ziel der Arbeit ist es, zu zeigen, wie weit die Wachstumstemperatur von indiumreichen Gruppe-III Nitriden, durch die Stabilisierung der Wachstumsoberfläche in einer Hochdruck-Stickstoffatmosphaere, erhöht werden kann. Es werden verschiedene Serien von Proben untersucht, um den Einfluss des Drucks im Reaktor, des Massenflussverhältnisses von Gruppe-V und Gruppe-III Präkursoren und des Abstands der Präkursorpulse, auf die strukturellen und optischen Eigenschaften zu bestimmen. Systematische Variationen der Expositionszeiten der Wachstumsoberfläche zum Ammoniak zeigen, dass der Transport und Einbau des flüchtigen Stickstoffs das Wachstum limitieren. Daher muss für das Wachstum von InN der Abstand zwischen einem Ammoniakpuls und dem folgenden Puls des metallorganischen Präkursors so kurz wie möglich sein, für InGaN dagegen ist mit steigendem Ga-Gehalt ein größerer Abstand zwischen diesen Pulsen nötig. Optimierungen des Wachstums von InN bei einem Reaktordruck von 15 bar haben gezeigt, dass bei einem V/III-Verhältnis von 2800 und einer Temperatur von 876°C qualitativ hochwertige InN Schichten gewachsen werden können. Mit angepassten Pulsseparationen wird das Wachstum von phasenreinem, indiumreichem InGaN über einen weiten Kompositionsbereich demonstriert. Die Photolumineszenz(PL)-Spektren von HPCVD InN Epi-Schichten zeigen eine breite PL unterhalb von 0,8 eV, mit einer abfallenden Flanke bis zu 0,7 eV. In Folge hoher freier Ladungsträgerdichte kommt es zum Auffüllen des Leitungsbands und zu einer Vergrößerung der effektiven optischen Bandlücke. Qualitativ hochwertige MOCVD und MBE Proben zeigen longitudinal-optische Phonon-Plasmonen (LPP) Kopplung und geringere Übergangsenergien. Der Vergleich dieser Filmen zeigt, zusammen mit Ergebnissen aus Messungen der LPP-Moden, ein Schieben der PL zu niedrigeren Energien mit abnehmender Ladungsträgerdichte. Für die Probe mit der besten Kristallqualität werden temperatur-, leistungs- und polarisationsabhängige PL-Messungen gezeigt. Die Ladungsträgerdichte liegt gerade an der Grenze zum degenerierten Halbleiter, bei Erhöhung von Anregungsleistung oder Temperatur wird der Übergang zum degenerierten Halbleiter beobachtet. Um den Einfluss hoher Ladungsträgerdichten auf die strukturellen und optischen Eigenschaften von Gruppe-III-Nitriden zu erforschen, werden mit Silizium und Germanium hochdotierte GaN Filme untersucht. Die PL zeigt, dass mit Ge deutlich höhere freie Ladungsträgerdichten von bis zu 2*10^20 cm^-3 erreicht werden, ohne dass Kompensation oder eine Verschlechterung der Materialqualität auftritt. Für Ge dotierte Filme wird ein nahezu unverspanntes Wachstum auf GaN Pufferschichten beobachtet, mit Si wird starke tensile Verspannung und Kompensation beobachtet. Für die freie Ladungsträgerdichte wird eine gute Übereinstimmung mittels der Analyse der LPP-Moden und Hall-Eekt Messungen erzielt. Selbst bei höchster Dotierung werden exzitonische Übergänge, sogenannte Mahan-Exzitonen, beobachtet.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-03-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3657</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38999</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38999</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3657/buegler_max_johann_ludwig.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
