<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:24Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3486">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3486</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Partitioning of cytochrome c in multicomponent lipid membranes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Aufteilung von Cytochrome c in multikomponenten Lipidmembranen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pataraia, Salome</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The interaction of water soluble proteins like cytochrome c (cyt c) with lipid membranes plays an important role in a number of biological processes. Cyt c is a positively charged heme protein located at the inner membrane of mitochondria. The main function of this protein is related to electron transport trough the respiratory chain during adenosine triphosphate (ATP) synthesis. cyt c is also one of the pro-apoptotic proteins, which activates the chain of cysteine proteases upon apoptotic stimuli, causing cell death. Thus, the activity of cyt c and the related interactions with membranes are involved at many levels of cell life. Previous studies have shown that at low ionic strength, cyt c inserts into the membrane, while at high ionic strength only a binding process takes place. It has been also demonstrated that insertion of cyt c into charged lipid membranes is stipulated for low lipid-protein ratios. Here we characterized the binding of this protein to multicomponent lipid membranes and resolved the influence of cyt c on the phase state of membranes as well as role of the bilayer surface charge and lipid composition. As a model system, giant unilamellar vesicles (GUVs) were used. To mimic the membrane composition of the inner mitochondrial membrane we employed lipid mixtures of the charged dioleoylphosphatidylglycerol (DOPG), sphingomyelin (SM) and cholesterol. As a first step, we characterized the phase behavior of this mixture from confocal microscopy observations on fluorescently labeled GUVs. Afterwards, we have investigated the alteration of phase behavior of the lipid ternary mixture induced by 0.6 mM Yeast cyt c. The protein concentration as well as the negatively charged lipid component, DOPG were chosen to mimic biologically relevant systems. After characterizing the membrane phase diagram in the presence of cyt c, we focused on the two fluid phase coexistence region, biologically relevant to rafts, and its surrounding environment. We studied the partitioning of cyt c in vesicles which belong to the two fluid phases: liquid ordered (Lo) raft and liquid disordered (Ld), non-raft phases. Analyzes of intensity profiles from fluorescence from the protein partitioning in the two phases yielded partitioning ratios of cyt c in the different domains. Our results indicate that cyt c prefers the DOPG-rich Ld domains, however there is a weak partitioning of cyt c into the Lo domains indicating compositional complexity of the membrane. The specific affinity of the protein to each of the fluid phases and the thermodynamic characterization of these interactions were quantified with isothermal titration calorimetry. We resolved the preferential binding of cyt c to the ternary lipid membranes close either to the Lo or the Ld phases. In parallel, the influence of cyt c on the membrane surface charge and vesicle size was monitored with dynamic light scattering and electrophoretic mobility measurements.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Wechselwirkung von dem wasserlöslichen Proteinen Cytochrome c (Cyt c) mit Lipidmembranen spielt in einer Reihe von biologischen Prozessen eine wichtige Rolle. Cyt c ist ein positiv geladenes Hämprotein, das sich in der inneren Membran der Mitochondrien befindet. Funktionell ist dieses Protein für die Synthese von Adinosintriphosphat (ATP) mitverantwortlich, das beim Elektronentransport der Atmungkette entsteht. Desweiteren ist Cyt c ein pro-apoptotisches Protein. Cyt c kann eine Reihe von Cystein-Proteasen aktivieren, die schließlich zum Absterben von Zellen führen können. Auf diese Weise ist Aktivität von Cyt c und seine Wechselwirkungen mit Membranen auf verschiedenen Ebenen im Leben von Zellen beteiligt. Vorherige Untersuchungen in vitro haben gezeigt, dass in Puffern mit niedrigen Ionenstärken Cyt c in Membranen eingebaut wird, hingegen führen höhere Ionenstärken lediglich zu einer Bindung an die Membran. Außerdem ist bekannt, dass niedrige Lipid-Protein-Verhältnisse für das Einbauen von Cyt c in geladene Lipidmembranen erforderlich sind. Wir untersuchten die Bindung dieses Proteins an multikomponente Membranen. Wir bestimmten den Einfluss von Cyt c auf das Phasenverhalten von Membranen und untersuchten dabei die Rolle von Oberflächenladung und Zusammensetzung der Membranlipide. Als Modellsystem wurden unilamellare Riesenvesikel (GUVs) genutzt. Um die Zusammensetzung der mitochondrialen Membran nachzuahmen, setzten wir Mischungen aus geladenem dioleoylphosphatidylglycerol (DOPG), Sphingomyelin (SM) und Cholesterol ein. Im ersten Schritt charakterisierten wir das Phasenverhalten dieser Mischungen mit dem confokalen Mikroskop und fluoreszent markierten GUVs. Nachfolgend studierten wir die Änderung des Phasenverhaltens der ternären Lipidmischungen durch Zusatz von 0.6 mM Cyt c. Die Konzentrationen des Proteins und des negativ geladenen Lipids DOPG entsprachen denen des biologischen Systems. Im Anschluss konzentrierten wir uns auf die Region im Phasendiagramm die für Lipid-Rafts relevant sind und in der zwei flüssige Membranphasen coexistieren: Flüssig-geordnete (Lo) „Raft-Domänen“ und flüssig-ungeordnete (Ld) „Non-Raft-Domänen“. Wir untersuchten die Verteilung von Cyt c in Vesikeln mit beiden Flüssigphasen. Die Analysen von Fluoreszenz-Intensitätsprofilen der Protein-Verteilung in den beiden Phasen ergaben unterschiedliche Verteilungen von Cyt c in beiden Domänen. Unsere Ergebnisse zeigen, dass Cyt c die DOPG-reichen Ld-Domänen bevorzugt, allerdings ist auch ein geringer Anteils von Cyt c in den Lo-Domänen zu finden. Die spezifische Affinität des Proteins zu den beiden flüssigen Phasen und die thermodynamische Charakterisierung dieser Wechselwirkungen wurden mittels isothermischer Titrations-Kalorimetrie gemessen. Wir fanden eine bevorzugte Bindung von Cyt c zu ternären Lipidmembranen sowohl in der Lo-, als auch in der Ld- Phase. Parallel dazu wurde der Einfluss von Cyt c auf die Oberflächenladung und die Größe von Vesikeln mit Messungen der elektrophoretischen Mobilität bzw. mittels dynamischer Lichtstreuung kontrolliert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-10-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37152</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37152</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3486/pataraia_salome.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
