<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:36Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2027">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2027</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Mesoscopic and Continuous Photoresist Development Simulation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Mesoskopische und kontinuierliche Simulation der Entwicklung von Photolacken</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Philippou, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wurden verschiedene Algorithmen entwickelt um die Entstehung der Kantenrauhigkeit von Photolacken in der Lithograhie zu beschreiben. Dabei wurde speziell für den in der Lithographie vorkommenden Entwicklungsschritt nach der Belichtung und dem "Post-exposure bake" (PEB) verschiedene kontinuierliche und mesoskopische Algorithmen erforscht. Um die Lackentwicklung auf einer mesoskopischen Skala zu simulieren wurde ein auf dem Gillespie-Algorithmus bzw. auf der kinetischen Monte-Carlo Methode basierender Ansatz implementiert. Eine Front wird dabei in der Zeit propagiert wobei die Rauhigkeit des resultierenden Profils von der Polymergrösse und der Perkolation des Entwicklers abhängt. Das Herauslösen einzelner Polymere basiert dabei auf dem Critical-Ionization Modell bei dem eine bestimmte Anzahl von funktionellen Gruppen innerhalb eines Polymers ionisiert sein müssen, damit es in einer wässrigen Base gelöst werden kann. Kombiniert mit einem bereits existierenden mesoskopischen PEB Modell wurden dabei fundamentale Auflösungsgrenzen von Photolacken untersucht. Dabei wurde in Übereinstimmung mit bereits bekannten experimentellen veröffentlichten Trends eine Abhängigkeit der Rauhigkeit vom Schutzgruppenkontrast gefunden. Ebenso führt eine Erhöhung der Säure erzeugenden "Photoacid generators" (PAG) zu einer Verringerung der Rauhigkeit. Der Einfluss der Polymergrösse auf die Rauhigkeit wurde dabei im Modell untersucht. Dabei wurde auch ein neuer Ansatz entwickelt in dem die Polymerstruktur mittels Molekulardynamik-Simulationen auf einer mikroskopischen Skala beschrieben und die Strukturinformation in dem mesoskopischen Modell eingebaut wurde. Da dieses Modell aufgrund des fundamentaleren Ansatzes im Vergleich zu kontinuierlichen Simulatoren eine wesentlich höhere Rechenzeit benötigt wurde das mesoskopische PEB Modell mit einem kontinuierlichen Fast-Marching Ansatz kombiniert wobei der Einfluss einzelner Polymere vernachlässigt wurde. Der Fast-Marching Ansatz ist bereits seit 1995 als ein Standardansatz zur Frontpropagation bekannt. Der hier entwickelte Algorithmus wurde dabei anhand von analytischen Lösungen und einem Level-Set Algorithmus verifiziert. Der so entwickelte Ansatz erlaubt eine Simulation bei beliebiger Auflösung die nicht mehr darin limitiert ist eine funktionelle Gruppe innerhalb eines Polymers aufzulösen. Dieses Modell wurde anhand von experimentell gemessenen Kontaktlochdaten im Vergleich zum Critical-Ionization und einem Level-Set Modell verifiziert. Zusammenfassend war durch die in dieser Arbeit entwickelten Algorithmen eine Beschreibung des Photolackes auf einer mesoskopischen Skala möglich wobei bereits bekannte experimentelle und simulatorische Ergebnisse in der Literatur erklärt und reproduziert werden konnten.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this thesis several algorithm for simulating the photoresist dissolution on a macroscopic and mesoscopic scale were developed. For the macroscopic scale a continuous development algorithm based on a fast marching approach was realized for the resist dissolution. It completes a software for continuous lithography simulation which was for the first time applied to a customized problem where a new double exposure process was investigated. For simulating on a mesoscopic scale a novel development algorithm based on the Gillespie algorithm was implemented. A developer front is integrated in time taking into account the various fluctuations arising from polymer size, ionization-neutralization reactions and developer percolation. The polymer dissolution is here based on the critical ionization model where polymers are removed as soon as a certain amount of polymer sites are ionized. Additionally base diffusion was incorporated into the mesoscopic post-exposure bake approach convergence with a continuous solution of the rate equations verified. To our knowledge the complete description ranging from exposure over post-exposure bake and resist development on a mesoscopic scale by means of Monte Carlo techniques is in its specific implementation unique. In the obtained results it is comparable to previous work from other groups. Thereby the development module incorporates ionization-neutralization reactions of polymers by means of logarithmic classes and von Neumann rejection while at the same time introducing instantaneous nearest neighbour developer diffusion. Also the approach of creating polymers by molecular dynamics simulation to obtain structural information on a microscopic level and incorporating the results back to a mesoscopic level is in its specific implementation unique. With the mesoscopic software main-chain scission of polymers in the extreme-ultraviolet regime were studied. Previous experimental results on LER trends for increasing PAG concentration or the dependance of LER on inhibitor contrast at the later forming edge could be verified. Finally the effect of polymer molecular weight on LER for chain-like polymers was discussed. To allow for a faster simulation a new model for line edge roughness simulation comparable to a soluable site density model was developed. This was achieved by combining the previously developed continuous fast marching algorithm with the mesoscopic post-exposure bake simulation where polymer properties were now neglected allowing for simulation at arbitrary resolutions. For verification purposes edge roughness of contact holes were studied. It is shown that similar roughness trends as observed in printing experiments of isolated contact holes can be modelled where an offset between experimental and simulated roughness exists. To reduce this offset a level-set algorithm was implemented where a curvature term was identified with a surface reordering at the resist-developer interface by means of a surface tension. Its effects were discussed. With the development of the above algorithms basic roughness effects in resists could be described well but many open questions remain. When arriving at the level of a single polymer repeat unit various resist effects were not considered. E.g. to accurately describe the total magnitude of LER further effects regarding polymer reordering during PEB and development need to be considered. There are complex interactions between the developer solution consisting of a solvent, a strong base, and various surfactants and the photoresist polymers which may go beyond a simple critical ionization model. These effects include the swelling behaviour of photoresists in contact with the developer which might be important when investigating the impact of polymer size on line edge roughness. Regarding the performance of the current approach to LER simulation it is still computational expensive compared to established continuous models. Therefore it might be questionable whether including more fundamental effects is really desired. However, the current kind of mesoscopic models are the only ones able to offer a detailed physical insight into the basic polymer reaction kinetics. They will become advantageous when the length scale of feature sizes approaches the dimensions of single polymers. The long-term implications of this thesis are that semiconductor industry will face a major issue when coming to smaller feature sizes as LER cannot be reduced below a certain limit. This limitation arises as part of the chemical amplification of photoresist and the finite size of the polymers and cannot be avoided.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-01-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17586</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17586</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2027/philippou_alexander.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
