<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2897">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2897</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Präparation spezieller Biokatalysatoren für die chemisch-technische Nutzung zur Bereitstellung von Aromaten und chiralen α-Hydroxyketonen</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Preparation of specific biocatalysts for chemical-technical use to provide aromatics and α-hydroxyketones</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bieler, Nora Christiane</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Teil 1 Bereitstellung der Biokatalysatoren LAC, LiP und MnP für deren chemisch-technische Nutzung Die drei Oxidoreduktasen Laccase (LAC), Lignin- und Manganperoxidase (Li- und MnP) aus Weißfäulepilzen sind technisch sehr interessant, da sie unter Anderem Lignin abbauen können. Vor allem deren zeitaufwändige Produktion in den ligninolytischen Organismen limitiert jedoch industrielle Anwendungen. Daher wurden Möglichkeiten zur Bereitstellung dieser Biokatalysatoren überprüft. So war es Ziel, die LAC aus Cyathus bulleri, die als besonders reaktiv und stabil charakterisiert wurde, heterolog zu exprimieren. Als Expressionssystem wurde die Hefe Pichia pastoris ausgewählt, da diese leicht im industriellen Maßstab zu kultivieren ist und da die Expression vieler eukaryotischer Proteine in dieser Hefe bereits gelang. Zunächst wurde die vollständige Nukleotidsequenz der LAC aus C. bulleri identifiziert. Die heterologe Expression gelang anschließend mit einer exzellenten maximalen volumetrischen Aktivität von 125 U/mL. Nachfolgend wurde die rekombinante LAC biochemisch charakterisiert. Weiteres Ziel war es, die bereits gut untersuchte und sehr reaktive LiPH8 aus P. chrysosporium, analog zu vorherigen Forschungsergebnissen, in der Hefe Pichia methanolica zu exprimieren. Als weiteres Hefeexpressionssystem wurde zudem die Hefe Pichia pastoris untersucht. In beiden hefen konnte keine LiP-Expression detektiert werden. Bei der MnP-Klonierung wurde ebenfalls die bereits umfassend untersuchte MnP aus P. chrysosporium ausgewählt. Da die Expression dieses Enzyms in P. pastoris bisher zu keiner zufriedenstellenden Expressionsrate geführt hat, wurde auf das gut untersuchte Kluyveromyces lactis Expressionssystem zurückgegriffen, welches im Vergleich zu anderen Hefen rekombinante Produkte oft in besserer Qualität und höherer Ausbeute produziert. Im Falle der MnP-Klonierung konnte keine Expression festgestellt werden. Teil 2 Präparation der BAL für die chemisch-technische Nutzung PVA/PEG-Hydrogele werden zur Einhüllung vieler Katalysatoren genutzt. Bisher ist die Produktion jedoch ausschließlich manuell möglich, was industrielle Anwendungen verhindert. Hier ist es gelungen eine automatisierte Produktion von im Hinblick auf Größenverteilung, Form und Gelmorphologie genau definierten PVA/PEG-Polymermatrices mit einer hohen Produktivität von bis zu 1500 Kugeln pro min zu realisieren. Ein weiteres Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit war es, Möglichkeiten der Optimierung für die technische Anwendung der Benzaldehydlyase (BAL) aus Pseudomonas fluorescens zur Bereitstellung enantiomeren-reiner α-Hydroxyketone zu untersuchen. Exemplarisch wurde die (R)-2,2’-Furoinsynthese, katalysiert durch in PVA/PEG-Kugeln immobilisierte BAL, in einem kontinuierlich betriebenen Wirbelschichtreaktor untersucht. Es wurde überprüft, ob die Synthese durch einen Lösungsmittelwechsel, vom bisher stets verwendeten apolaren n-Hexan hin zu polareren Lösungsmitteln (MIBK, MTBE, 2-Methyl-THF) mit erhöhter Produktextraktionskraft, optimiert werden kann. Hierbei zeigte sich, dass die Inaktivierung der BAL durch ihre eigenen Substrate inaktivierende Effekte der Lösungsmittel vollständig überlagert. Des Weiteren war die Entwicklung einer Eintopfsynthese des sterisch sehr anspruchsvollen α-Hydroxyketon (R)-4,4’-Biphenylbenzoin durch Kombination einer Palladium-katalysierten Kreuzkupplung mit einer BAL-katalysierten Carboligation Gegenstand der vorliegenden Arbeit. Zunächst wurden beide Reaktionen einzeln charakterisiert und optimiert. (R)-4,4’-Biphenylbenzoin konnte letztendlich mit einer Gesamtausbeute von ~60% und einem ee von über 99,99% synthetisiert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Part 1 Preparation of the biocatalysts LAC, LiP and MnP for chemical-technical use In their capacity to transform xenobiotics, polluting compounds and lignin, the fungal peroxidases Laccase (LAC), Lignin- and Manganese Peroxidase (Li- and MnP), and their use in the environmental field have a recognized and important potential. However, limited availability of these interesting oxidoreductases has delayed the development of industrial applications. Based on this, possibilities to express these biocatalysts from white rot fungi in adequate yeast expression systems were examined in this work. The goal was to express the LAC from Cyathus bulleri, which was characterized in previous studies as highly reactive and stable, in the yeast Pichia pastoris. P. pastoris was chosen as expression system, since it can be easily cultivated in industrial scale. In addition, several eukaryotic proteins were already successfully expressed in this yeast. At first, the complete nucleotide sequence of the LAC from C. bulleri was identified. Afterwards, the LAC was expressed in P. pastoris with an excellent maximal volumetric activity of 125 U/mL. Consequently, the recombinant enzyme was biochemically characterized. In addition, heterologous expression of the well-characterized and highly reactive LiPH8 from the white rot fungi Phanerochaete chrysosporium was investigated. In previous studies this LiP was already successfully expressed in Pichia methanolica. Therefore P. methanolica was selected as expression system. As a further expression system, Pichia pastoris was tested. In both yeast systems no expression of LiP was detected. For the cloning of MnP, the already extensively characterized MnP from P. chrysosporium was chosen. Since, up to now, expression of this enzyme in P. pastoris did not lead to satisfying expression rates, Kluyveromyces lactis was tested as expression system. In comparison to other yeast expression systems, this well characterized yeast produces recombinant products often in better quality and higher yields. In case of MnP-cloning no expression was detected. Part 2 Preparation of BAL for chemical-technical use Entrapment in PVA/PEG cryogels is a widely applied method for the immobilization of catalysts. Up to now, these promising immobilisates can be produced manually and exclusively in small scale. Therefore, industrial application is hindered. In this study, a device for the automated production of PVA/PEG beads in lab scale is presented. The resulting PVA/PEG beads are exactly defined regarding to bead shape, size, as well as gel morphology. The developed production unit yields up to 1500 beads per minute. A further goal was the investigation of possibilities to optimize the technical application of Benzaldehyde Lyase (BAL) from Pseudomonas fluorescens to provide enantiopure α Hydroxy-ketones. As a model reaction, (R)-2,2’-Furoinsynthesis, catalyzed by BAL immobilized in PVA/PEG-beads, was investigated in a continuously run fluidized bed reactor. The chance to optimize the synthesis by a change of the usually used apolare n-hexane to more polar solvents with a higher product extraction strength (MIBK, MTBE, 2-Metyl-THF) was analyzed. As a result, it was discovered that the inactivation of BAL by its own substrates completely overlays inactivation effects of organic solvents. Furthermore, synthesis of the sterically demanding α-hydroxyketone (R)-4,4’-Biphenylbenzoin was examined. Synthesis was performed in a one-pot reaction by combination of a Palladium-catalyzed Suzuki reaction with a BAL-catalyzed Carboligation. First, both reactions were characterized and optimized. At last, (R)-4,4’-Biphenylbenzoin was produced with an overall yield of ~60% and an excellent ee of more than 99,99%.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-05-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30625</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30625</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2897/bieler_nora.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
