<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:34Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2021">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2021</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Biologische Funktionsfähigkeit und Dynamik des sandigen Interstitials unter dem Einfluss induzierter Uferfiltration am Tegeler See (Berlin)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Biological functioning and dynamics of the interstices in the sandy littoral zone of Lake Tegel (Berlin) involving in bank filtration </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hoffmann, Anja</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das sandige Litoral des Tegeler See bildet die Hauptinfiltrationszone bei der induzierten Uferfiltration. Die Struktur des Interstitials und die saisonale Dynamik der Prozesse wurde zwischen 2004 und 2006 bis zu einer Sedimenttiefe von 50 cm untersucht, um die biologische Funktionsfähigkeit aufzuklären. Diese basiert v. a. auf der Sauerstoffversorgung, dem Kohlenstoffumsatz und der Regulierung von Kolmationsprozessen durch die Biozönose. Im Einzelnen wurden die Infiltrationsraten, Durchlässigkeitsbeiwerte, Kolmation(sursachen), physiko-chemische Parameter und die Zusammensetzung der Biozönose regelmäßig erfasst und ein Schema zum Kohlenstoffumsatz abgeleitet. Bei insgesamt hoher Variabilität lag der Median der Infiltrationsraten bei 9,0 L m-2 h-1, während die in situ beobachteten, oberflächennahen kf-Werte zwischen 4 x 10-7 m s-1 und 6 x 10-5 m s-1 schwankten. Im Winter waren die Durchlässigkeitsbeiwerte stets geringer. Die Infiltration wird nicht nur hydraulisch gesteuert, sondern auch durch die erhebliche Kolmation des Interstitials beeinflusst. Zur Kolmation trägt in starkem Maß partikuläres organisches Material (bestehend aus Rhizomen von Makrophyten, Algen, Biofilm und Detritus) bei, das in den oberen 10 cm annähernd die Hälfte des Porenvolumens verfüllt. Auch der Eintrag von Seston und atmosphärischer Luft bzw. eine interne Gasproduktion stellen wirksame Cloggingfaktoren dar. Die Kolmation führt zu einem effektiven Partikelrückhalt insbesondere im obersten Sedimentzentimeter, wie Enclosureversuche unter Dotierung von inerten Melaminharzpartikeln (2,44 µm) und natürlichem FPOM als Fluoreszenztracer zeigten. Epipsammische Diatomeen erreichten in den oberen 4 cm Sediment maximale Biomassen von 24 µg Chl a mL-1 und ebenso markante Abundanzen von 1,5 x 107 mL-1. Die von ihnen produzierten extrazellulären polymeren Substanzen sind maßgeblich an der Biofilmbildung beteiligt. Die mit Sauerstoffoptoden gemessene Nettoprimärproduktion war geringer als nach der Algenbiomasse zu erwarten wäre, hier besteht weiterer Forschungsbedarf. Die der Sauerstoffzehrung entsprechende Menge mineralisierten Kohlenstoffs variierte zwischen 3 und 7 mg dm-2 d-1 im Winter bzw. Sommer und stimmt relativ gut mit den POC-Veränderungen im oberen Sedimentausschnitt von 5 cm überein. Dieser schwankt hier saisonal um den Jahresmittelwert von 1 %. Der POC-Umsatz übertrifft den Umsatz von DOC, der über die Infiltration eingetragen wird, um ein Vielfaches. In den oberen 26 cm nimmt der infiltrierende DOC um 13 – 20 % ab. Die stärksten Gradienten der physiko-chemischen Parameter wurden im obersten Sedimentzentimeter beobachtet. Der starke POC-Umsatz führt während des Sommers zunächst zu anaeroben Verhältnissen im untersuchten Tiefenausschnitt, die die Selbstreinigungskraft einschränken. Im Zuge wechselnder Grundwasserstände und der Ausdehnung ungesättigter Bereiche erfolgt dann eine Reoxidation. Die detritivore Meiofauna steuert einerseits durch ihre Fraßaktivität und Sedimentauflockerung (z. B. durch Wohnröhren) einer Kolmation entgegen, reduziert jedoch auch das Porenvolumen zu Zeitpunkten maximaler Abundanzen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The structure and seasonal dynamics of the interstices in the sandy littoral zone of Tegel Lake involving considerable in bank filtration were investigated during 2004 – 2006 to obtain an integrated understanding of the biological functioning and the highly complex interactions involved. The biological functioning process is based on oxygen supply, carbon input, transfer and turnover, as well as on the control of clogging processes by the inhabiting microflora and meiofauna. Therefore infiltration rates, permeabilities, clogging factors, physico-chemical parameters and the composition of the biocoenosis were examined continously up to a sediment depth of 50 cm. In addition, data were used to derive a scheme of organic carbon turnover. Infiltration rates and kf values in the upper 2 cm, calculated according to Darcy’s Law, both were highly variable, resulting in median infiltration rates of 9.0 L m-2 h-1 and a range of hydraulic conductivity between 4 x 10-7 m s-1 and 6 x 10-5 m s-1. Kf values generally were lower during the winter. The infiltration process is not only controlled hydraulically, but also determined by severe clogging processes, mainly triggered by biological components in the upper sediment horizon. In addition, seston input and intermittent gas production/intrusion are considered to be important clogging factors. In the upper 10 cm nearly half of the interstitial volume is filled with particulate organic matter (POM), which is mainly composed of macrophyte rhizomes, epipsammic algae, biofilms and detritus. The clogging leads to an effective particle retention and filtration capacity. No significant in place transport of either inert microparticles (2.44 µm) nor natural FPOM (&lt; 1 mm) used as fluorescing tracers in enclosure experiments was observed below 2 cm sediment depth during 3 to 14 days or even longer periods of exposure. The biomass and the number of epipsammic diatoms in the 0 –4 cm depth range, was very high, reaching maximum chlorophyll a values of 24 µg mL-1, and abundances of 1.5 x 107 mL-1. However net primary production measured by using planar optodes was much lower than values calculated from algae biomass, either due to light limitation or oxygen emission to the overlying water column. Measured carbon mineralisation rates varied between 3 and 7 mg dm-2 d-1 in winter and summer, respectively, and are quite reasonable compared to changes of the particulate organic carbon (POC) in the upper sediment layer. The turnover of POC exceeds that of the infiltrating dissolved organic carbon (DOC), especially during the summer, when POC and probably also biofilms are prone to degradation due to high temperatures and enhanced microbial activity. Over the course of the year, DOC decreases about 13 % to 20 % within the upper 1 to 26 cm sediment, while POC oscillates around 1 %. Gradients of all observed soluble parameters were highest in the topmost centimeter. The enhanced POC turnover leads to anaerobic conditions over a wide sediment interval in the summer, thereby influencing physico-chemical parameters and reducing the self-purification potential as well as meiofaunal abundance. Reoxidation occurs by enhanced atmospheric exchange of the unsaturated zone due to alternating well field operations and falling ground water levels during the summer. The meiofauna counteracts clogging processes by its detritivorous activity and surficial tube dwellings, but also reduces pore volume when its abundance is high. Population maxima up to 17,000 Ind. dm-3 in the autumn and spring seem to be bottom up controlled.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-01-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21094</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21094</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2021/hoffmann_anja.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
