<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2192">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2192</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Processing of expected values in human visual cortex</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kallerhoff, Philipp</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Experience might effectively modulate our choice if prior stimulation reveals some information about future reward. For example, experience might accumulate to an expected reward at different target locations. Following Pascal (1670) the expected reward is given as the predictability of the reward and the amount of reward associated with each location. In the first study, we modulated the expected reward in a simple binary choice task in order to test rational decision making in the context of complex expected value functions. We found that the subjects likely match, but do not maximize the expected reward and likely implement a short‚Ä?term average over stimulus appearances, but not the true generative model. In the second study, our aim was to gradually modulate the endogenous orientation of attention with the expected value of distributed reward in the environment. Shifts in attentional focus were induced by linking one location with a higher expected reward than other locations. Larger expected values should then increase the likelihood that subjects would focus their attention on one location rather than distribute it across the entire display. The discrimination performance at a target location is a close indicator of attention. Therefore we setup a discrimination task and measured the behavioral discrimination performance. In fact, we found that subjects increasingly discriminate the target status with a larger expected value. The models proposed in the first study account quite closely for basic properties of the behavioral results. However, a close analysis on a trial‚Ä?by‚Ä?trial basis showed that the true generative model cannot account for subjects‚Äô behavior, which is however well explained by short‚Ä?term average over stimulus appearances. In the third study, we measured the event‚Ä?related potential (ERP) during the discrimination task introduced in the second study and compared the ERP modulations to the decision making models proposed in the first study. Grand average ERP waveforms showed an increase in components as early as the N1 component with increasing expected reward of the stimulus location. In fact, the performance in the discrimination task and the rewardmodulation are closely reflected in the amplitude of these early‚Ä?visual, attention‚Ä?related EEG‚Ä?responses. We therefore conclude the processing of expected rewards in early‚Ä?visual components of EEG.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Erfahrung k√∂nnte unsere Entscheidung ver√§ndern, wenn wir etwas √ºber die zuk√ºnftige Belohnung gelernt haben. Insbesondere k√∂nnten wir an einem Zielort eine bestimmte Belohnung erwarten. Nach Pascal (1670) ist die erwartete Belohnung gegeben als die Vorhersehbarkeit der Belohnung und die H√∂he der Belohnung an dem Zielort. In der ersten Studie, haben wir die erwartete Belohnung in einer einfachen bin√§ren Wahlaufgabe ver√§ndert, um rationale Entscheidungen im Kontext von komplexen erwarteten Belohnungsfunktionen zu untersuchen. Wir haben festgestellt, dass die Versuchspersonen wahrscheinlich der erwarteten Belohnung folgen und nicht maximieren, sowie wahrscheinlich einen kurzfristigen Durchschnitt benutzen, aber nicht das wahre generative Modell. In der zweiten Studie war es unser Ziel, die endogene Ausrichtung der Aufmerksamkeit graduell mit der erwarteten Belohnung zu modulieren. Verschiebungen in der Aufmerksamkeit wurden erzeugt, indem an einem Zielort eine h√∂here Belohnung erwartet werden konnte als an Anderen. Eine h√∂here erwartete Belohnung sollte dann die Wahrscheinlichkeit erh√∂hen, dass die Verswuchspersonen ihre Aufmerksamkeit auf einen Zielort konzentrieren und nicht √ºber den gesamten Bildschirm verteilen. Die Diskriminierungsleistung an einem Zielort ist ein genauer Indikator der Aufmerksamkeit. Deshalb haben wir eine Diskriminierungsaufgabe erstellt und die Diskriminierungsleistung gemessen. Tats√§chlich haben wir festgestellt, dass die Versuchspersonen die Diskriminierungsaufgabe besser gel√∂st haben, wenn die erwartete Belohnung am Zielort h√∂her war. Die Modelle aus der ersten Studie erkl√§ren auch diese Ergebnisse sehr genau. Jedoch hat eine exakte Analyse auf der Basis der einzelnen Durchl√§ufe ergeben, dass das wahre generative Modell wieder das Verhalten der Versuchspersonen nicht erkl√§ren kann, wohl aber ein kurzfristiger Durchschnitt √ºber die letzten Zielorte. In der dritten Studie, haben wir das evozierte Potential (ERP ‚Äì event‚Ä?related potential)w√§hrend der Diskriminierungsaufgabe der zweiten Studie gemessen und mit den Entscheidungsmodellen der ersten Studie verglichen. Die durchschnittlichen ERP Wellen haben eine Zunahme in der fr√ºhen visuellen N1 Komponente mit zunehmender erwarteter Belohnung am Zielort gezeigt. Tats√§chlich spiegeln sich die Diskriminierungsleistung und die Modulation durch Belohnung eng in den fr√ºhen‚Ä?visuellen und aufmerksamkeitsverwandten Komponenten des EEG wider. Daher kommen wir zum Schluss, dass die erwartete Belohnung in fr√ºhen visuellen Komponenten des EEG verarbeitet werden kann.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-07-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2192</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22679</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22679</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2192/original_Thesis_Philipp_Kallerhoff_UB.docx</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2192/kallerhoff_philipp.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
