<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1487">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1487</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-21</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Microbiological and molecular analysis of bacterial communities of an urban soil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Molekulare und mikrobiologische Untersuchungen der bakteriellen Gemeinschaft eines urbanen Bodens </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Braun, Burga</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Soil water repellency is a common phenomenon which occurs throughout the world and is influenced by physical, chemical and biological factors. It prevents water from infiltrating into the soil and influences soil properties. Changes in soil wettability may represent a significant source of stress for microbial communities and affect bacterial composition and soil microbial processes. Up till now, little is known about the effects of water repellency on soil bacterial communities and vice versa. The aim of this study was to gain a more profound insight into the bacterial community structure of wettable and water repellent soils. The horizontal and vertical distribution of the bacterial population was analyzed with regard to soil water repellency. Furthermore, the molecular diversity and active bacterial population subjected to water stress was monitored in microcosm experiments. Finally, the effects of hydrophilic and hydrophobic bacterial biofilms on soil wettability were investigated. For determination of alterations in the bacterial structure and their metabolic potential cultivation- and molecular methods were combined. The application of cultivation independent methods did not allow to distinguish between water repellent and wettable soil samples. Whereas determination of CFU and metabolic fingerprints resulted in differences between wettable and water repellent soil areas. Variations in community structure as well as in community function and activity were observed within the soil profile. These data indicated that water repellency did not have a significant effect on the total genetic diversity present but affected the physiological status, so that the bacteria capable of responding to laboratory culture methods were altered in activity without changes in phylogenetic distribution. Therefore, the bacterial communities of this urban soil seemed to be adapted to different moisture conditions by regulating their physiological cell activity. Microcosm experiments revealed no effects of water stress on the bacterial community, as no moisture related changes in the bacterial population were observed. To gain insights how biofilms may affect surface properties of soil, soil samples were inoculated with bacteria of different cell surface hydrophobicity: Bacillus sphaericus (hydrophilic), Variovorax paradoxus (hydrophobic) and an α- Proteobacterium (hydrophobic). The results demonstrated the effect that bacterial biofilms can have on soil wettability, as biofilms were able to hydrophilize or hydrophobize soil samples.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Nicht benetzbare Böden stellen ein allgemeines und weltweites Problem dar, welches durch physische, chemische und biologische Faktoren beeinflusst wird. Die Benetzungshemmung der Bodenoberfläche hat einen Einfluss auf die Wasserinfiltration und die räumliche Verteilung der Bodenfeuchte. Änderungen in der Benetzbarkeit des Bodens können einen bedeutenden Stressfaktor für bakterielle Bodengemeinschaften darstellen und die bakterielle Zusammensetzung sowie mikrobielle Prozesse im Boden beeinflussen. Über die Auswirkungen von nicht benetzbaren Böden auf die bakterielle Bodengemeinschaft und umgekehrt ist bisher nur wenig bekannt. Ziel dieser Dissertation ist zum einen den Einfluss der Benetzungshemmung des Bodens auf die bakterielle Bodengemeinschaft zu ermitteln, sowie die Charakterisierung von Bakterien in einem Bodenprofil. Weiterhin sollte der Einfluss von Wasserstress auf die bakterielle Gemeinschaft durch Trocknung und Wiederbefeuchtung in Mikrokosmosversuchen untersucht werden. Letztlich wurde der Einfluss von hydrophilen und hydrophoben Biofilmen auf die Benetzbarkeit des Bodens ermittelt. Um Änderungen in der bakteriellen Zusammensetzung und ihres physiologischen Potentials zu bestimmen, wurden kultivierungsabhängige und –unabhängige Methoden verwendet. Mit der Anwendung von kultivierungsunabhängigen Methoden war keine Unterscheidung von benetzbaren und nicht benetzbaren Bodenproben möglich. Die Erzeugung von metabolischen Fingerabdrücken, sowie die Bestimmung der Kolonie bildenden Einheiten zeigte jedoch Unterschiede zwischen benetzbaren und nicht benetzbaren Bodenbereichen. Innerhalb des Bodenprofils konnten Variationen in der Zusammensetzung und des physiologischen Potentials, sowie der Aktivität ermittelt werden. Diese Ergebnisse weisen darauf hin, dass die Benetzungshemmung von Böden keinen signifikanten Einfluss auf die gesamte genetische Diversität hat, den physiologischen Status der Gemeinschaft jedoch beeinflusst. Die Untersuchungen von Wasserstress in Mikrokosmosexperimenten zeigten keinen Einfluss auf die bakterielle Bodengemeinschaft, da keine feuchtigkeitsabhängigen Veränderungen beobachtet werden konnten. Daher scheinen die bakteriellen Gemeinschaften dieses urbanen Bodens an die unterschiedlichen Bodenfeuchten angepasst zu sein, indem sie ihre physiologische Zellaktivität regeln. Um Einblicke zu gewinnen, wie Biofilme Oberflächeneigenschaften von Böden beeinflussen können, wurden Bodenproben mit Bakterien verschiedener Hydrophobizität der Zelloberfläche beimpft: Bacillus sphaericus (hydrophil), Variovorax paradoxus (hydrophob) und ein α- Proteobacterium (hydrophob). Die Ergebnisse zeigten, dass Biofilme einen Einfluss auf die Benetzbarkeit des Bodens haben können, da sie in der Lage sind Bodenproben zu hydrophilisieren bzw. zu hydrophobisieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-04-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15259</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15259</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1487/original_all_dokument.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1487/braun_burga.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
