<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:46Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1834">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1834</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Potential of Multi-Winglet Systems to Improve Aircraft Performance</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Potenzial von Multi-Winglet Systemen zur Flugleistungssteigerung von Flugzeugen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Berens, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The potential of multi-winglet configurations to increase aircraft performance is the subject of the present thesis. Multi-winglet systems are well-known from the avian world. It has repeatedly been attempted to exploit the theoretically predicted potential for technical applications, which, however, was only successful in very few cases. The obvious discrepancy between the success of the multi-winglet configuration in nature as well as the theoretically large potential to reduce induced drag and to mitigate wake vortex intensities on the one hand and the modest results of technical implementations on the other form the motivation to look more closely at the characteristics of multi-winglet configurations. A multidisciplinary analysis tool, termed VLM++, has been developed on the basis of an implementation of the 3D vortex lattice method. Apart from consideration of profile and interference drag, the method also considers effects that need to be regarded particularly in the case of multi-winglet configurations. The effect of mutual interference among the winglets on the individual surfaces maximum loadabilities is considered, producing values which normally differ from those of the basic airfoil sections. Another module permits to explicitly model the nonlinear lift characteristics on the basis of generalised lift polars. A comparison of the numerical results with published low speed measurement data of multi-winglet configurations having symmetrical NACA 0015 airfoil sections proves that the extended analysis model correctly predicts the lift and drag behaviour even in the case of partly separated flow. The computational model correctly identifies the root sections of the foremost winglets as the locations where flow separations first occur when the angle of attack is increased. A parametric study going beyond the range of available measurement data shows that cambering the planar inner wing part reduces the aerodynamic loads on the critical winglet and hence extends the attached flow lift range with its comparably small drag figures. Also, the maximum lift coefficients are increased. These findings are expected to hold at least as far as the inner wing sections operate at supercritical Reynolds numbers. No other measure leads to a comparable improvement of multi-winglet efficiency. An extended parametric study on the basis of a general aviation aircraft scenario was performed. In addition to aerodynamics, wing structure masses were computed by means of a simplified wing sizing approach. For performance computations, employment of an ideal propeller propulsion system was assumed. The results show that the multi-winglet configuration does not offer a significant improvement in payload-specific fuel consumption for range-optimal flight conditions as compared to the corresponding best planar wing with identical prescribed wing total surface area, span and takeoff mass. This is in contrast to flight conditions for maximum endurance where a clear advantage in terms of the aforementioned figure of merit for the multi-winglet configuration is predicted.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Gegenstand der vorliegenden Arbeit ist die Untersuchung des Potenzials von Multi-Winglet Konfigurationen zur Leistungssteigerung von Flugzeugen. Multi-Winglet Systeme sind aus der Vogelwelt bekannt. Die offensichtliche Diskrepanz zwischen dem Erfolg der Multi-Winglet Konfiguration in der Natur sowie dem theoretisch großen Potenzial zur Verringerung des induzierten Widerstands und der damit verbundenen Abschwächung der Intensität der Nachlaufwirbel auf der einen und den gleichzeitig mäßigen Ergebnissen bei technischen Umsetzungen auf der anderen Seite bilden die Motivation, die Besonderheiten der Konfiguration näher zu betrachten. Hierzu wurde ein multidisziplinäres Analysetool VLM++ auf der Basis eines 3D Wirbelleiterverfahrens entwickelt, das über Erweiterungen zur Berechnung des Profil- und des Interferenzwiderstands hinaus besondere, bei Multi-Winglet Konfigurationen auftretende Effekte explizit berücksichtigt. Zum einen wird der Effekt verschiedener Anordnungen einzelner Winglets auf die jeweilige und in der Regel von den Profilwerten abweichende aerodynamische Belastbarkeit modelliert. Zum anderen erlaubt das Tool den nicht-linearen Auftriebsanstieg bei Erreichen des Grenzauftriebsbeiwerts eines Profilschnitts auf der Basis generalisierter aufgelöster Polaren zu berücksichtigen. Ein Vergleich der numerischen Ergebnisse mit veröffentlichten Niedergeschwindigkeitsmessdaten für Multi-Winglet Konfigurationen mit symmetrischen NACA 0015 Profilen weist die korrekte Nachbildung des Auftriebs- und Widerstandsverhaltens mit dem erweiterten Simulationsmodell auch für den Fall teilweise abgelöster Strömung nach. Durch das Analysetool werden die Wurzelbereiche der vordersten Winglets als Stellen, an denen bei steigendem Anstellwinkel zuerst Ablösungen auftreten, richtig identifiziert. Eine über den Umfang der Messungen hinausgehende Parameterstudie zeigt, dass die Verwölbung des planaren Innenflügels am besten geeignet ist, diese Belastung zu verringern und damit den ablöse- und widerstandsarmen Auftriebsbereich deutlich zu vergrößern. Weiterhin werden die Maximalauftriebsbeiwerte erhöht. Dies gilt zumindest dann, wenn bei den Innenflügelprofilen überkritische Reynoldszahlen vorliegen. Keine andere Maßnahme führt zu ähnlich großen Leistungsverbesserungen. Eine umfangreiche Parameterstudie wurde auf Basis eines für die Allgemeine Luftfahrt typischen Kleinflugzeugszenarios durchgeführt. Zusätzlich zur Analyse der aerodynamischen Eigenschaften wurden die Flügelstrukturmassen mittels eines vereinfachten Ansatzes für die Flügeldimensionierung berechnet. Für die Flugleistungsrechnungen wurde die Verwendung eines idealen Propellerantriebs vorausgesetzt. Die Ergebnisse zeigen, dass sich mit der Multi-Winglet Konfiguration keine signifikante Verbesserung des nutzlastspezifischen Kraftstoffverbrauchs bei reichweitenoptimalen Flugbedingungen im Vergleich zum besten planaren Flügel bei vorgeschriebener Gesamtflügelfläche, Spannweite und Abflugmasse erzielen lässt. Dagegen wird ein deutlicher Vorteil der Multi-Winglet Konfiguration hinsichtlich der genannten Gütegröße bei Flugbedingungen für maximale Flugdauer prognostiziert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-07-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1834/original_berens_martin.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1834/berens_martin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
