<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:34Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3305">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3305</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Modelling the Diffusion of Innovative Heating Systems in Germany – Decision Criteria, Influence of Policy Instruments and Vintage Path Dependencies</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Modellierung der Diffusion von innovativen Heizungssystemen in Deutschland - Entscheidungskriterien, Einfluss von Politikinstrumenten und Pfadabhängigkeiten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Henkel, Johannes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In the past decade several new technologies appeared on the German heating market. The most important of these are electric heat pumps, wood pellet boilers and solar thermal panels. The present dissertation tries to answer the question about the future development of the heating market by applying a mathematical simulation model. This model basically comprises of two parts: a decision model with a focus on the individual heating system decision and a market model which sets the frame. The decision model is a conditional multinomial logit model and is fitted based on survey data. It quantifies the influence of characteristics of the different heating systems as well as of the deciders, i.e. the households, on the heating system decision. The market model is a vintage stock model of heating systems in Germany and includes the modelling of further exogenous developments, like fuel prices and the application of policy instruments. The model results show that the market share of electric heat pumps will increase sharply in the years to come. This development constitutes an intensification of a trend already visible in the past years and is at the cost of decreasing numbers of fuel oil heating systems. In the segment of newly constructed buildings, heat pumps will displace gas condensing boilers as market leader. But also in existing buildings they will become an important player with more than 20% of market share in 2025. As main driver of the success of heat pumps, learning effects could be identified. Moreover, operational costs are favourable for heat pumps if prices for fuel oil and natural gas increase. Although electric resistance heating systems will be nearly completely phased out by 2025, demand for electricity in the heating market will be about 30 TWh higher than today, which will have significant impacts on the electricity market. As gas heating systems remain the most often chosen technology in existing buildings, yearly demand for natural gas in the heating market remains nearly constant. Although wood pellet heating systems can steadily increase their market share as well, their annual sales figures remain constantly on the level of the past years. Thus, wood pellet heating systems remain a niche technology with slightly more than 2% market share in 2025. Solar thermal boiler support is used in about 15% of all heating systems in 2025 and distributes more or less evenly to the different boiler types. As a consequence of the presented technological development, yearly CO2 emissions in the heating market will decrease strongly by more than 25% by 2025. Half of this value can be explained by exogenous energy efficiency gains of buildings, the other 50% by technological change and a decreasing CO2 intensity of electricity. In a sensitivity analysis, the presented results proved relatively robust. Furthermore, by applying an innovative random-walk methodology the author could show that the presented results are also quite stable across different fuel price scenarios.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Im vergangenen Jahrzehnt haben im deutschen Heizungsmarkt einige neue Technologien Relevanz gewonnen. Allen voran sind in diesem Zusammenhang Wärmepumpen, Holzpelletheizungen sowie solarthermische Kollektoren zu nennen. Die vorliegende Dissertation wagt einen Ausblick in die kommenden Jahre bis 2025 und schätzt die zukünftige Entwicklung des deutschen Heizungsmarktes mit Hilfe eines mathematischen Simulationsmodells ab. Das Modell ist zweistufig aufgebaut: Ein Teil des Modells (ein konditionales multinomiales Logit-model) konzentriert sich auf die individuelle Entscheidung eines Haushaltes für ein spezielles Heizungssystem und basiert auf Umfragedaten. In diesem Modellteil wird die Bedeutung unterschiedlicher Merkmale der Heizungen sowie der Entscheider (also der Haushalte) quantifiziert. Der andere Teil gibt den Rahmen vor und bildet die Entwicklung des Bestands an Heizungssystemen sowie exogener Einflüsse, wie z.B. der Brennstoffpreise oder angewandter Politikinstrumente, ab. Aus den Ergebnissen der Modellierung ergibt sich, dass der Marktanteil elektrischer Wärmepumpen in den nächsten Jahren stark ansteigen wird. Dieser Anstieg geht auf Kosten eines deutlich sinkenden Anteils von Ölheizungen und stellt eine Fortsetzung und Intensivierung eines Trends dar, welcher bereits in den letzten Jahren sichtbar war. Im Neubausegment werden Wärmepumpen in den kommenden Jahren die Gasheizung als Marktführer ablösen. Aber auch im Gebäudebestand können sie bis 2025 einen Marktanteil von über 20% erreichen. Als hauptsächliche Treiber des Wärmepumpen-Booms konnten Lernkurveneffekte sowie relative Betriebskostenvorteile bei steigenden Preisen für Heizöl und Erdgas identifiziert werden. Aus der genannten Entwicklung resultiert ein stark ansteigender Strombedarf im Wärmemarkt: Trotz eines deutlichen Rückgangs der Zahl installierter Elektroheizungen steigt der jährliche Strombedarf um ca. 30 TWh bis zum Jahr 2025. Da Gasheizungen im Gebäudebestand nach wie vor das meistgewählte Heizungssystem sein werden, bleibt der Gasbedarf im Wärmemarkt nahezu konstant. Holzpelletheizungen können zwar auch ihren Marktanteil steigern, im Gegensatz zu Wärmepumpen verharren die jährlichen Verkaufszahlen aber auf dem Niveau der vergangenen Jahre. Pelletheizungen bleiben somit eine Nischentechnologie und werden im Jahr 2025 in etwas mehr als 2% der Haushalte verwendet. Solarthermische Energie zur Kesselunterstützung wird in ca. 15% der Fälle genutzt. Die jährlichen CO2-Emissionen im Wärmemarkt sinken um mehr als 25% im Vergleich zu 2009, was zu gleichen Teilen auf die aufgezeigte Entwicklung sowie auf einen exogen vorgegebenen Effizienzgewinn im Raumwärmebereich zurückgeführt werden kann. In einer Sensitivitätsanalyse sowie durch Anwendung einer innovativen Random-Walk-Methodik konnte weiterhin gezeigt werden, dass die aufgeführten Ergebnisse relativ robust und weitgehend unabhängig vom gewählten Brennstoffpreisszenario sind.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-04-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3305</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3305/henkel_johannes.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-SA: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, Weitergabe zu gleichen Bedingungen</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
