<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:47:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:687">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:687</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Architecture and Access Protocol for a Wavelength-Selective Single-Hop Packet Switched Metropolitan Area Network</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Architektur und Zugriffsprotokoll für ein Wellenlängenselektives Single-Hop Paketvermitteltes Metronetzwerk</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Maier, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Um den Bandbreitenengpaß zwischen Weitverkehrsnetzen und Netzperipherie zu beheben, schlagen wir ein Arrayed-Waveguide Grating (AWG) basiertes Single-Hop Wellenlängenmultiplex (WDM) Metrosternnetz vor. Im Gegensatz zu Multihop Netzen bieten Single-Hop Netze eine minimale Knotenhopdistanz, inhärente Transparenz, einfache Integration neuer Technologien, vereinfachtes Netzmanagement und eine verbesserte Durchsatz-Latenzzeit Leistung, da keine Bandbreite durch Paketweiterleitung verschwendet wird. Das vorgeschlagene Netzwerk besteht aus einem AWG an dessen Eingangs- bzw. Ausgangsports wellenlängeninselektive Combiner bzw. Splitter angeschlossen sind, wobei die Splitter optisches Multicasting ermöglichen. Durch Verwendung passiver Komponenten ist das Netzwerk kosteneffizient und zuverlässig. Jeder Knoten an der Netzperipherie ist ausgestattet mit einem abstimmbaren Transceiver und einer kostengünstigen Bandbreitquelle, deren Signal vom AWG spektral aufgeteilt wird und das Broadcasting von Steuerinformation ermöglicht. Mittels Bandspreizverfahren wird die Netzsicherheit verbessert und können Nutz- und Steuerdaten innerhalb derselben Wellenlänge gleichzeitig gesendet werden ohne Verwendung eines zusätzlichen Steuerkanals und Empfängers. Wellenlängen werden dynamisch zugeteilt durch den Einsatz eines reservierungsbasierten Zugriffsprotokolls welches sowohl Paket- als auch Leitungsvermittlung unterstützt. Das Netz ist skalierbar indem die Reservierungsslots nicht fest zugeteilt werden und Reservierungs-ALOHA (R-ALOHA) und Codemultiplextechniken (CDMA) angewandt werden. Alle Knoten besitzen globales Wissen und regeln die Übertragung von Paketen variabler Länge mit Hilfe eines verteilten deterministischen First-Come-First-Served (FCFS) und First-Fit Algorithmus, welcher keine expliziten Bestätigungen benötigt und Fairness, geringe Latenzzeit und Dienstqualität (QoS) bietet und zudem Kollisionen von Datenpaketen vollständig vermeidet. Die Netzeffizienz wird deutlich gesteigert durch die räumliche Wiederverwendung der Wellenlängen, die Nutzung mehrerer Freispektralbereiche (FSRs) des zugrundeliegenden AWGs und den Einsatz des sog. Wormhole Schedulings. Mittels Analyse und/oder Simulation wurde gezeigt, daß unser Netzwerk für paketvermittelten Unicastverkehr eine mittlere Wellenlängennutzung von über 100%, eine mittlere Kanalnutzung von ungefähr 53% und einen mittleren Gesamtdurchsatz erreicht, welcher ungefähr 70% größer ist als der maximale Gesamtdurchsatz des DT-WDMA Zugriffsprotokolls, welches auf einem passiven Sternkoppler basierten Single-Hop WDM MAN läuft. Effizientes Multicasting wird erreicht durch die Partitionierung von Multicastübertragungen in Verbindung mit räumlicher Wellenlängenwiederverwendung und durch die Ausnutzung der Reservierungsphasen unseres Zugriffsprotokolls. Mittels effizienter multiobjektiver Optimierungstechniken wurden Durchsatz und Latenzzeit unseres Netzes und Zugriffsprotokolls Paretooptimiert, um dynamische Multiservicekonvergenz effizient zu ermöglichen. Wir haben das innovative Konzept der heterogenen Schutzschaltung entworfen, welches konventionelle Single-Point-of-Failure Schutzmechanismen in Hinsicht auf Durchsatz und Latenzzeit deutlich übertrifft und generell auf alle Single-Hop WDM Netze angewandt werden kann.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Current SONET/SDH metro ring networks create the so-called metro gap which prevents high-speed clients from tapping into the vast amounts of bandwidth available in the backbone. To bridge this gap we propose and investigate by means of analysis and simulation a novel arrayed-waveguide grating (AWG) based single-hop wavelength division multiplexing (WDM) network with a physical star topology. Star networks offer a better optical power budget than ring and bus networks and are easy to install, configure, manage, and troubleshoot. Unlike their multihop counterparts single-hop networks provide a minimum mean hop distance (unity), inherent transparency, future-proofness, easy upgradability, simplified management, and an improved throughput-delay performance since no bandwidth is wasted due to packet forwarding. Owing to spatial wavelength reuse the AWG keeps the wavelength pool small which enables the deployment of fast tunable transceivers with a negligible tuning time. The proposed network consists of an AWG with wavelength-insensitive combiners (splitters) attached to each AWG input (output) port, where the splitters are used for realizing optical multicasting. Due to its completely passive nature the network is cost-effective and reliable. Each node at the network periphery is equipped with one single tunable transceiver and one low-cost broadband light source which is spectrally sliced for broadcasting control information. Direct sequence spread spectrum techniques are deployed to improve the network security and enable simultaneous transmission of data and control within the same wavelength channel without requiring any additional control wavelength and receiver. Each node has access to all wavelengths resulting in efficient multicasting and load balancing. Wavelengths are on-demand allocated by means of a reservation medium access control (MAC) protocol which provides both packet and circuit switching. By not fixed assigning the reservation slots and deploying performance enhancing reservation ALOHA (R-ALOHA) and code division multiple access (CDMA) the network is made scalable. All nodes have global knowledge and schedule variable-size packets on a deterministic first-come-first-served and first-fit basis without requiring explicit acknowledgements guaranteeing fairness, decreased latency, and quality of service (QoS) and completely avoiding both channel and receiver collisions of data packets. The network efficiency is significantly increased by spatially reusing all wavelengths at each AWG port, exploiting multiple free spectral ranges (FSRs) of the AWG, and wormhole scheduling. For unicast packet switched traffic our AWG based network achieves a mean wavelength utilization of more than 100%, a mean channel utilization of approximately 53%, and a mean aggregate throughput that is about 70% larger than the maximum aggregate throughput of the DT-WDMA access protocol that runs on a PSC based single-hop metro WDM network. Partitioning in conjunction with spatial wavelength reuse and exploiting the reservation phases of the MAC protocol allow for very efficient multicasting. Furthermore, the presented single-hop network significantly reduces the complexity of the protocol stack in that routing is replaced with simple wavelength tuning and the data link layer can be omitted. By using computationally efficient multiobjective optimization techniques the throughput-delay performance of the proposed network and protocol are Pareto-optimized in order to efficiently enable dynamic multiservice convergence. We develop and evaluate the new concept of heterogeneous protection of the single point of failure which clearly outperforms its conventional counterpart in terms of throughput and delay and is generally applicable in all single-hop WDM networks. Our findings aim at contributing to bridge the bandwidth abyss at the metro level, enable new applications benefitting from the huge amounts of bandwidth available in the backbone, stimulate revenue growth, and possibly offer a turnaround in the telecom sector.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2003-06-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/687</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-6813</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-6813</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/687/maier_martin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
