<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:46:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:454">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:454</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Microstructure and residual stress state in the contact zone of rails and wheels</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Mikrostruktur und Eigenspannungszustand im Kontaktgebiet von Schienen und Rädern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wang, Lihong</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Abstract Lihong Wang: Microstructure and Residual Stress State in the Contact Zone of Rails and Wheels Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit wurde am System Rad-Schiene der Einfluss der Betriebsparameter auf Mikrostruktur, Textur und Eigenspannungen an der Oberfläche und im oberflächennahen Bereich von Eisenbahnschienen und Rädern untersucht. Zur zerstörungsfreien Texturanalyse und Eigenspannungsanalyse wurden Beugungsverfahren mit Röntgen- und mittelenergetischer Synchrotronstrahlung eingesetzt. Zur Formulierung eines Mechanismus für die Entstehung der weißen Schichten wurden nicht nur Röntgenanalysen, sondern auch mikroskopische Untersuchungen durchgeführt. Der Ausscheidungszustand wurde mittels ASAXS im DESY, Hasylab, in Hamburg charakterisiert. Mit einem Profilometer wurde die Schienentopographie abgebildet. Durch die hohen Achslasten wurden deutliche mikrostrukturelle Veränderungen an der Schienen- und Radoberfläche hervorgerufen. Die Untersuchungen zeigen, dass die Kombination von mechanischen und thermischen Belastungen an den Oberflächen von Schiene und Rad zur Entstehung der seit längerem bekannten weißen Schichten und Riffelbänder führt. Die lokale starke plastische Verformung, die durch hohe Druckeigenspannung nachgewiesen wurde, verursacht den Bruch des Zementits in eine nanokristalline Struktur und die teilweise Auflösung der Zementitlamelle. Die gleichzeitige starke Temperaturerhöhung und anschließende schnelle Abkühlung der Oberflächen ermöglicht die mehrmaligen thermischen Umwandelungen Ferrit/Perlit  Austenit - Martensit. Eine Modellvorstellung zur Bildung der weißen Schichten wurde erstellt. Das Auftreten der weißen Schichten fördert die weitere Entwicklung der Riffelbänder. Eine &lt;111&gt;-Faser-Textur und eine &lt;551&gt;-Faser-Textur wurden an den Schienen- und Radoberflächen ermittelt. Als Folge der Phasentransformation sinkt die Texturintensität mit steigender Belastung. Das Maximum der Texturkomponente befindet sich nicht an den Oberflächen der Schienen und Räder, sondern innerhalb dieser. Die Untersuchungen von vier unterschiedlich stark beanspruchten Schienen wurden miteinander verglichen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Abstract Lihong Wang: Microstructure and Residual Stress State in the Contact Zone of Rails and Wheels In this thesis, the influences of the loading history of rail-wheel system on the microstructure, texture and residual stress on the superficial surface and also in the near surface area of the rail tracks and wheels have been comprehensively investigated. For determining the texture evolvement and residual stresses, nondestructive diffraction methods using both conventional X-ray radiation and medium energy synchrotron radiation are employed. For clarifying the formation mechanism of the White Etching Layers, both diffraction analyses and microstructural investigations were performed. The distribution of precipitates has been characterized using ASAXS in DESY, Hasylab, in Hamburg. By means of a profilometer, the surface topography of rails has been well reproduced. Due to the increasing high axle loading, the surface of rails and wheels inevitably underwent both topographical changes and microstructural alterations. The investigations in this thesis reveal that the combination of plastic deformation and thermal loading in the rail-wheel system induces the formation of WEL and riffle bands that have been known for nearly 100 years. The distribution of the residual stress indicates high local plastic deformations on the surface of rails and wheels, which accounts for the breaking up of the carbide into the nano size and also for the partial dissolution of the carbide lamellas. The simultaneous heating up and the subsequent quick cooling on the surface of rail and wheel lead to thermal microstructural transformations ferrite / perlite  austenite - martensite. A microstructure model for the evolvement of WELs has been established. The appearance of the WELs is supposed to speed up the development of the riffle bands. A &lt;111&gt; fiber texture and a &lt;551&gt; fiber texture were found in the rail-wheel system. Due to the phase transformation, the texture intensity tends to decrease with increasing loading. The maximum of the texture index was found not directly on the superficial surface, but in the interior of the rail and the wheel. The investigations on four rails with different loading history have been compared.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2002-10-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/454</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-4498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-4498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/454/wang_lihong.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
