<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2961">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2961</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Impact of Pulsed Electric Fields (PEF) on post-permeabilization processes in plant cells</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Einfluss von Hochspannungsimpulsen (HSI) auf post-Permeabilisierungsprozesse in Planzenzellen.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Winter, Anna</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The exposure of biological cell material to Pulsed Electric Fields (PEF) leads to a spectrum of biophysical and biochemical responses. The most important effect, the electrical breakdown of cellular membranes, realizes the temporary or permanent pore formation in cell membranes, which induces an increase in membrane permeability. The loss of semipermeability enables the transport of non-permeating molecules across the cell membrane. The disintegration of the cell membrane as well as the alteration of structural properties offers numerous options to apply this novel, non-thermal and short-time technique in food- and bioengineering. In this thesis the impact of PEF on plant single cells as well as on vegetable tissues was investigated. In order to understand underlying mechanisms at cellular level and to clarify the influence of cell wall on the degree of cell membrane disintegration, protoplasts from cultured tobacco cells (Nicotiana tabacum b.y.-2) and cells with cell wall were compared during and after reversible as well as irreversible PEF treatment. Results showed higher sensitivity of protoplasts to electric fields related to native cells. Protoplasts sizes were measured before and after different treatment intensities and protoplasts shrinkage was used as an indicator for cell rupture. It could be demonstrated that cell volume decrease is influenced by PEF intensity, initial cell size, cell orientation in the electric field and nucleus position. Focus was also put on the potential of PEF to gentle disintegrate plant tissue and thus to apply this technique in food industry. Hence, the enhancement of mass transfer after irreversible membrane permeabilization from potato and asparagus tissue was examined. Results showed the enhanced release of intracellular molecules from permeabilized tissue as well as improved uptake of low molecular substances into the sample. Sugar, one substrate for the Maillard reaction, was decreased in PEF treated potatoes due to membrane permeabilization and the subsequent release of cell vacuole sugar, while conductivity increased after electroporation and soaking in sodium chloride solution, indicating the improved diffusion of salt caused by PEF. Higher release of cell liquid during drying was noticed additionally. This effect increased with the treatment intensity. Furthermore, it was revealed that PEF application leads to a significant reduction of fat content after deep fat frying of potato stripes and thus provides a potential for the production of low-fat French fries. It was noticed additionally that PEF treatment decreases the content of the biopolymer lignin in white asparagus in order to improve macroscopic characteristics and gain softer texture of the spears. It can be presumed that PEF is a capable assistance to thermal treatments in the processing of potato snack products or in the preserving of asparagus for the achievement of structural modifications and the improvement of process conditions.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der hochspannungsimpulsinduzierte Aufschluss der Zellmembran und die daraus folgende Änderung der strukturellen Eigenschaften bergen großes Potential für die Anwendung dieses nicht-thermischen und zeiteffektiven Verfahrens in der Bio- und Lebensmitteltechnologie. Ziel dieser Arbeit war es, den Einfluss von Hochspannungsimpulsen (HSI) auf einzelne Pflanzenzellen als auch auf pflanzliches Zellgewebe zu untersuchen. Zur Erforschung grundlegender Mechanismen auf zellulärer Ebene und zur Klärung des Einflusses der Zellwand auf den Grad der Zellmembranpermeabilisierung wurden Protoplasten kultivierter Tabakzellen (Nicotiana tabacum b.y.-2) und Zellen mit Zellwand bezüglich ihres Verhaltens während und nach reversibler als auch irreversibler HSI-Behandlung untersucht. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass Protoplasten sich sensibler gegenüber dem elektrischen Feld verhalten als native Zellen. Die Zellgröße der Protoplasten wurde vor und nach verschiedenen HSI- Behandlungsintensitäten gemessen. Die Verringerung der Zellgröße diente als Indikator für den Grad des Zellaufschlusses. Es zeigte sich, dass die Reduktion des Zellvolumens von der HSI-Behandlungsintensität, der Ausgangszellgröße, der Zellorientierung im elektrischen Feld und der Position des Zellkerns abhängt. Zudem sollte das Potential elektrischer Felder zum milden Zellaufschluss von pflanzlichem Gewebe für einen möglichen Einsatz in der Spargel- und Kartoffelindustrie untersucht werden. Verbesserte Stofftransportvorgänge HSI-behandelter Kartoffeln führten sowohl zu einer erleichterten Freigabe von intrazellulären Molekülen als auch zu einer verbesserten Aufnahme von niedermolekularen Substanzen in das Gewebe. HSI-behandeltes Kartoffelgewebe zeigte einen geringeren Gehalt an reduzierendem Zucker, ein Substrat für die Maillard-Reaktion, was sich auf die erleichterte Freigabe des Vakuoleninhalts durch die permeabilisierte Zellmembran zurückführen lässt. Im Hinblick auf die verbesserte Molekülaufnahme in das aufgeschlossene Gewebe wurde eine erleichterte Diffusion von Salzionen in HSI-behandelte Kartoffelscheiben beobachtet. Zusätzlich erhöhte sich der Trocknungsgrad permeabilisierter Kartoffelscheiben mit steigender HSI-Behandlungsintensität. Eine Fettextraktion frittierter Kartoffelstäbchen zeigte, dass eine HSI-Vorbehandlung der Fettaufnahme während des Frittierens entgegenwirkt. Der Einsatz von HSI bei der Herstellung fettreduzierter Pommes frites ist daher denkbar. Bei HSI-behandeltem Spargel war eine Reduzierung des Biopolymers Lignin nachweisbar. Dies könnte die ligninbedingte Verholzung der Spargelstangen bei der Verarbeitung vermindern. HSI-induzierte strukturelle Modifikationen und die dadurch verbesserten Prozessbedingungen lassen den Einsatz von HSI in der Kartoffel- und Spargelverarbeitungsindustrie als viel versprechend erscheinen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-07-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2961</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31667</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31667</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2961/winter_anna.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
