<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:41Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1588">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1588</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Investigations on the influence of dextran during beet sugar production with special focus on crystal growth and morphology</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Untersuchungen des Dextraneinflusses während der Rübenzuckerproduktion unter besonderer Berücksichtigung von Kristallwachstum und -morphologie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Soliman, El-Sayed Ali Abdel-Rahman</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In the present study, the sensitivity and accuracy of the common methods of dextran determination were investigated. Concentrations and progressions of dextran during different sugar production processes and industrial periods were determined and for the first time an evaluation of sugar and molasses quality was provided based on the measurement results. Regarding the dextran determination, the results had shown a significant effect of dextran concentration and molecular fractions on the Haze and Robert’s methods. The data demonstrate that the Robert’s method was more accurate for different dextran molecular mass fractions than Haze method. Furthermore, the Haze method was too inaccurate to be genuinely useful as a dextran analysis method especially considering low dextran molecular mass fractions. The isolation and identification of Leuconostoc mesenteroides as an important source of dextran in sugar beet factories was performed. It was observed, that the microorganisms grow during the storage of sugar beet and also during the extraction process. The mean counts of colonies were reduced after washing process from 2.5*103 cfu/g of the sugar beet sample to 6*102 cfu/g of cossettes samples. However, the number of microorganisms increased in raw juice after extraction process to reach almost 4*106. In addition, these numbers depend on the degree of deterioration of the sugar beets. Dextran content increased during the extraction process by 4 % to 20 % for fresh and deteriorated sugar beet, respectively. In contrast, the lime-carbon dioxide juice purification reduced the dextran content in raw juice by 40 % to 60 %. The obtained results from Egyptian sugar beet factories showed a correlation between the increase of sugar loss and the presence of dextran during different industrial periods as well as during the production process itself.. As a main focus in this work the negative effects of the presence of dextran during (isothermal) crystallization were investigated. The growth rate of sucrose crystals and the quality of the sugar production in pure sucrose solution at different temperatures were studied. To elucidate the influence of dextran on the growth rate of sucrose crystals, different molecular mass fractions of dextran from 40,000 g/mol (T40) to 2,000,000 g/mol (T2000) were admixed in different concentrations to pure sucrose solution. The most pronounced effect of dextran was found with T2000 at 60°C. On the other hand, negligible influences of dextran T40 and T500 were observed at the same temperature and supersaturation. The high adsorption ability and the increase of solution viscosity particularly caused by high molecular fractions of dextran were identified as the main reasons for the reduction of crystal growth rate. The application of lower temperatures during crystallization enhances the problems deriving from dextran. Regarding the final crystallization steps (e.g. after product crystallization), levels of dextrans and impurities are enhanced and the mentioned problems will be amplified in these production steps. From the morphological studies, it was found that the presence of dextran in sugar mother liquor leads to elongation of the sucrose crystal shape (elongated along the c-axis). In particular, the lower molecular mass fractions of dextran are involved in this effect. A scanning electron microscope (SEM) was utilized for the evaluation of crystal surfaces and crystal morphology. The surface topography of sucrose crystals was affected by the presence of higher dextran molecular mass fractions (T2000), which causes gaps, rough areas and strong adsorption of micro-particles (micro-crystals) on the crystal surface. Again, the described influences are enhanced by the application of lower temperatures. In addition, in this work it could be confirmed that there is a correlation between the dextran content in syrup and quality of sugar produced, in particular the turbidity of the sugar. So, a relation which has already been described in recent literature for organic macromolecules in general could be specified for dextran molecular fractions.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Studie wurde die Empfindlichkeit und Genauigkeit der gebräuchlichen Methoden zur Dextranbestimmung untersucht. Basierend auf den in unterschiedlichen Produktionsprozessen und industriellen Produktionsphasen ermittelten Dextrangehalten wurde erstmals eine umfassende Bewertung des Einflusses von Dextran auf die Zucker- und Melassequalität erstellt. Bezüglich der Dextranbestimmung zeigten die Ergebnisse einen deutlichen Einfluss der Dextrankonzentration und der molekularen Fraktionen auf die Haze- und Roberts-Methode. Die Daten ergaben, dass die Robertsmethode für unterschiedliche Dextran-Molekulargewichtsfraktionen eine größere Genauigkeit zeigt als die Haze-Methode. Vor allem bei kleineren Dextran-Molekulargewichtsfraktionen war die Haze-Methode nicht für genaue Bestimmungen geeignet. Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit wurde Leuconostoc mesenteroides , eine der wichtigsten Quellen von Dextran in Rübenzuckerfabriken isoliert und identifiziert. Diese Mikroorganismen wachsen sowohl während der Lagerung der Zuckerrüben als auch während des Extraktionsprozesses. Während des Waschens und Schneidens der Rüben nahm die durchschnittliche Koloniezahl von 2.5*103 cfu/g in der Rübenprobe bis auf 6*102 cfu/g in den Schnitzeln ab. Die Koloniezahl erreichte jedoch im Laufe der Extraktion bis zum Rohsaft wieder einen Wert von 4*106. Die Zahlen waren jedoch stark vom Frischegrad der verarbeiteten Rüben abhängig. Die Konzentration an Dextran nahm während der Extraktion von frischen bzw. verdorbenen Rüben um 4 bzw. 20 % zu. Im Gegensatz hierzu verringerte sich der Dextrangehalt um 40 bis 60 % während der Saftreinigung mit Kalk und CO2. Ergebnisse aus ägyptischen Rübenzuckerfabriken zeigen einen klaren Zusammenhang zwischen der Zunahme des Zuckerverlustes und der vorherrschenden Dextrankonzentration während verschiedenen Perioden der Zuckerkampagne aber auch während den einzelnen Produktionsabschnitten auf. Einen Schwerpunkt dieser Arbeit stellt die Untersuchung der negativen Einflüsse von Dextran während des (isothermen) Kristallisationsprozesses aus reinen Saccharoselösungen bei verschiedenen Temperaturen dar. Dextranfraktionen verschiedener Molekularmassen zwischen 40000 g/mol (T40) und 2000000 g/mol (T2000) wurden reinen Saccharoselösungen in verschiedenen Konzentrationen zugesetzt, um den Einfluss von Dextran auf die Kristallwachstumsrate genau charakterisieren zu können. Der stärkste Einfluss war bei dem Zusatz der Fraktion T2000 bei 60°C zu detektieren. Im Gegensatz hierzu besaßen die Dextranfraktionen T40 und T500 einen wesentlich geringeren Einfluss auf die Wachstumsrate bei jeweils gleichen Temperaturen und Übersättigungen. Gründe hierfür liegen in der hohen Adsorptionsfähigkeit und der Erhöhung der Viskosität der Zuckerlösung insbesondere durch die hochmolekulare Fraktion von Dextran. Die Absenkung der Temperaturen während der Kristallisation, wie es aus ökonomischen Gründen häufig angestrebt wird, vergrößert die durch Dextran ausgelösten Probleme. Insbesondere in letzten Kristallisationsstufen (z.B. Nachproduktkristallisation) treten erhöhte Konzentrationen an Dextran und Nicht-Zuckerstoffen auf, wodurch die beschriebenen Effekte noch verstärkt werden. Um den Einfluss von Dextran auf die Kristallmorphologie und die Kristalloberfläche evaluieren zu können, wurden elektronenmikroskopische Aufnahmen angefertigt. Die Ergebnisse zeigen, dass die Kristallform (Verlängerung in Richtung der c-Achse) durch die niedermolekulare Fraktion (T40) beeinflusst wird. Demgegenüber hat die hochmolekulare Dextranfraktion T2000 einen starken Einfluss auf die Qualität der Kristalloberfläche. Beobachtet wurden raue, lückenhafte Kristalloberflächen und die Anhaftung von Mikro-Partikeln (Mikro-Kristalle) auf der Oberfläche. Die beschriebenen Effekte werden wiederum durch den Einsatz tiefer Temperaturen verstärkt. In dieser Arbeit konnte ebenfalls ein Zusammenhang zwischen dem Dextrangehalt und der Qualität des Zuckers, insbesondere der Zuckertrübung, gezeigt werden. Dies spezifiziert für Dextran einen Zusammenhang, der in der aktuellen Literatur allgemein für organische Makromoleküle schon beschrieben wird.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-09-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16340</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16340</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1588/original_soliman_el_sayed.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1588/soliman_elsayed.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
