<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3779">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3779</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-05-28</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:book</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The Local (Public) Transport Plan as an Approach to optimize Urban Public Transport Planning in Iran </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arndt, Wulf-Holger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Döge, Norman</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In many countries, the exclusive concentration on a simple extension of the road based transportation network led to growing individual car traffic hence to additional demand for roads and striking external effects of transport. All issues have a severe negative impact on the living and working conditions within many urban centers. In the last decade, especially in the MENA (Middle East and North Africa) region, municipalities tried to restrict continuous growth of car traffic and intensified their efforts in supporting alternative concepts with focus on environmentally-friendly mobility approaches. However, many of these approaches were quite ambitious and innovative but often rather implemented in a disintegrated way. The transport research activities that have been conducted during the project runtime of the Young Cities in Iran project within in the BMBF (German Federal Ministry of Research and Education) funded Megacities program investigated the urban transport sector of the MENA region in general and the one of Iran in detail. The researchers revealed that the Iranian urban public transport planning system is lacking coordination between the level of the Urban Transportation Masterplan and the level of public transport operators. This publication analyses the tool of the Local (Public) Transport Plan which is already used in many agglomerations worldwide to define fixed quality and service standards for urban public transport. It, moreover, investigates the Iranian urban transport planning system and suggests a way how to adapt the tool to fit with Iranian conditions.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In vielen Städten weltweit hat die alleinige Ausrichtung der Verkehrsplanung auf die Erweiterung der straßenbasierten Verkehrsinfrastruktur zu einem weiteren Anstieg des motorisierten Individualverkehrs geführt. Die wachsenden externen Effekte des motorisierten Individualverkehrs haben sich zunehmend negativ auf die Lebens- und Arbeitsbedingungen in vielen urban Zentren ausgewirkt und diese nachhaltig beeinträchtigt. In der vergangenen Dekade haben zahlreiche Stadtverwaltungen, insbesondere jene der MENA (Mittlerer Osten, Nord Afrika) - Region dem Wachstum des motorisierten Individualverkehrs Einhalt zu gebieten. In diesem Zusammenhang wurden vor allem Anstrengungen unternommen die Umsetzung alternativer Planungskonzepte mit Fokus auf umweltverträglicheren Verkehrsträgern zu befördern. Viele dieser Ansätze waren sehr ambitioniert und innovativ wurden jedoch häufig nur in einer sehr desintegrierten Weise umgesetzt. Die Verkehrsforschungsaktivitäten die während der Projektlaufzeit des vom BMBF geförderten Young Cities Projektes unternommen wurden, konzentrierten sich vornehmlich auf die Verkehrsentwicklung der Städte in der MENA Region im Allgemeinen und die des Iran im Besonderen. Eine Erkenntnis dieser Aktivitäten war dass es dem iranischen Planungssystem an Koordination zwischen der Ebene des Verkehrsentwicklungsplans und den semi-privaten Unternehmen öffentlichen Verkehrsunternehmen mangelt. Diese Publikation analysiert das Werkzeug des in vielen Städten weltweit angewandten „Local Transport Plan“ dahingehend ob es geeignet wäre diese Koordinierungslücke zu füllen und verbindliche Standards für Qualität und Angebot im öffentlichen Nahverkehr iranischer Städte zu setzen. In diesem Zusammenhang wird auch das iranische städtische Verkehrsplanungssystem genauer beleuchtet und es werden Möglichkeiten aufgezeigt dieses Werkzeug in das iranische Planungssystem zu integrieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-06-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>book</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:book</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3779</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40655</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40655</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-7983-2586-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3779/No14_The%20Local%20%28Public%29%20Transport%20Plan%20as%20an%20Approach%20to%20opt.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
