<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:53Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3372">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3372</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Raman spectroscopy investigation of organic matrix orientation and chemistry changes during fracture healing</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ramanspektroskopische Untersuchung der Orientierung organischer Matrices und chemischer Ver√§nderungen w√§hrend der Knochenheilung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Galvis, Leonardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Fracture healing is a complex process that involves cellular and biochemical response to reestablish the biomechanical properties and original geometry of tissues in damaged bone. In order to stabilize and eventually close the fracture gap, a heterogeneous material called callus is generated during healing. Collagen as the primary building material of the organic matrix in callus is highly organized in a variety of meaningful ways. Despite its importance, research has been mainly focused on the mineral phase and there is only a limited understanding of how collagen fibrils orient themselves during fracture healing. One tool that is ideally suited to studying fracture healing in the early stages is Polarized Raman Spectroscopy (PRS) as chemical and orientation of the materials can be obtained with high resolution (0.6-1¬µm) in a non-destructive manner. In the present work, a methodology to obtain the collagen fibril orientation in fracture callus was developed. As a first step, a theoretical analysis of the Raman Amide I band intensity response for collagen structures was performed following the classical Raman theory. Collagen-like peptide structures obtained in the protein data bank (PDB) were rotated ‚Äúin plane‚Ä? and ‚Äúout of plane‚Ä? to evaluate the Amide I response at different polarization angles of the incident light. Collagen oriented ‚Äúin plane‚Ä? exhibit sinusoidal anisotropic response of the Amide I band where the maximal intensity is obtained when the polarization angle of the incident light is perpendicular to the molecule and minimal when parallel. Once the molecule is rotated ‚Äúout of plane‚Ä? the response becomes less anisotropic and when the molecule is positioned perpendicular to the plane of observation the response is isotropic. The methodology proposed to evaluate the collagen orientation using PRS is based on the fitting the anisotropic response of the Amide I band at different polarization angles of the laser. The fitting procedure allows us to obtain parameters related to the orientation of the collagen fibres and the degree of alignment. This procedure was tested in collagen-based materials that are completely isotropic (gelatine) and highly anisotropic (human osteon). Finally, the PRS was employed in embedded rat callus samples to evaluate the collagen orientation and chemical evolution in the fracture callus. The fracture callus samples were harvested at the time points of 2, 3, 4 and 6 week of the healing (two samples per time point). Selected regions of interest (ROI) were chosen on the cortex close to the fracture gap throughout the healing evolution, as well as areas of cartilage and mineralized tissue in the endosteal area were also investigated. It has been possible to obtain Raman images of the most relevant molecular groups on a rat callus sample embedded in PMMA. This has revealed interesting histological features like chondrocytes structures in the cartilage, as well as hydroxyapatite and collagen distribution in soft and hard tissues within the callus. The orientation mapping of collagen fibres on mineralized tissue and cartilage in the endosteal region has revealed a high level of organization at the early stages of fracture healing. Highly oriented collagen fibers found around chondrocytes suggest a templating process of the extracellular matrix in soft tissue. The cortex region close to the fracture gap shows the first signs of the remodeling on the 3rd week of the healing. At the 6th week collagen fibres are orienting in different directions than longitudinal to the cortex exhibiting already an active remodeling process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Knochenheilung ist ein komplexer Prozess, bei dem zun√§chst ein Kallus aufgebaut wird, der die Bruchstelle provisorisch verbindet, bevor in einem Umbauprozess der urspr√ºngliche Aufbau des Knochengewebes wieder hergestellt wird. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurde polarisierte Ramanspektroskopie (PRS) benutzt, um die Orientierung der Kollagenfasern im Kallus zu bestimmen. In einem ersten Schritt wurde eine theoretische Bewertung der Intensit√§t der Amid I Ramanbande f√ºr Kollagenstrukturen mit Hilfe klassischer Ramantheorie vorgenommen. Kollagen√§hnliche Peptidstrukturen aus der Proteindatenbank (PDB) wurden benutzt, um den Einfluss unterschiedlicher Polarisationswinkel des einfallenden Lichts auf die Amid I Bande zu berechnen. In dieser Arbeit wird eine neue Methode vorgeschlagen, um die Orientierung des Kollagens mittels PRS zu ermitteln. Diese basiert auf einer numerischen Analyse des anisotropen Signals der Amid I Bande f√ºr unterschiedliche Polarisationswinkel des Lasers. Dieses Verfahren wurde f√ºr kollagenreiche Materialien benutzt, die sowohl vollst√§ndig isotrop (Gelatine) als auch hochgradig anisotrop (Osteon im menschlichen Knochen) waren. Schlie√ülich wurde die PRS benutzt, um die Kollagenorientierung und chemische Ver√§nderungen w√§hrend des Heilungsverlaufs zu bestimmen. Die untersuchten Proben, welche von einem zuvor an der Charit√© durchgef√ºhrten Versuch mit Ratten stammen, wurden nach Intervallen von 2,3,4 und 6 Wochen Heilung entnommen (2 Proben pro Zeitpunkt). Die Abbildung der Orientierung von Kollagenfasern im mineralisierten Gewebe und im Knorpel im endostealen Bereich lie√ü einen hohen Grad an Ausrichtung w√§hrend des fr√ºhen Heilungsprozesses erkennen. Die Anwesenheit von hochgeordneten Kollagenfasern um die Chondrozyten im Knorpelgewebe deutet auf einen Templatierungsprozess der extrazellul√§ren Matrix des Weichgewebes hin. Der Kortex in der N√§he des Bruchs zeigt die ersten Anzeichen einer Umgestaltung in der dritten Woche des Heilungsprozesses. Ab der sechsten Woche orientieren sich die Kollagenfasern neu und der kortikale Knochen weist bereits Zeichen eines aktiven Umbauprozesses auf. Die neu entwickelte Methode kann daher benutzt werden, um die verschiedenen Stadien des Knochenheilungsprozesses bez√ºglich der Struktur und der Zusammensetzung des Gewebes zu bewerten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-06-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3372</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3372/galvis_leonardo.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
