<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1781">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1781</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Potential of infrared heating as a method for decontaminating food powder. Process development and impact on product quality</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Potential von Infrarotwärme als eine Methode zur Entkeimung von Lebensmittelpulver. Prozessentwicklung und Einfluss auf Produktqualität</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Staack, Norman</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Dried powders, such as spices, may contain high microbial counts, particularly of bacterial spores, which are known for their high heat resistance and good survival ability. Although spores do not germinate in the powders themselves, adding the powders to high-moisture foods provides a suitable environment for microbial growth of spores. This thesis explored the potential of infrared (IR) heating for decontaminating food powders. Paprika powder was used as a model material, wetted to different water activities (aw) and spiked with 7 log10 spores/g of a psychrotropic Bacillus cereus, SIK 340. IR heat flux and wavelength, and the aw of paprika, were assessed for their effects on product qualities and microbial inactivation. IR heating of paprika powder was studied using a pilot plant near- and medium-IR tunnel oven. The paprika powder was placed in three different lab-scale heating units: (1) an open heating unit, and two closed heating units using near-IR-transparent (2) glass and (3) plastic. The IR heating of paprika powder consisted of a warm-up period and a holding period at the desired product temperature. Heating was based on HTST treatment, i.e. rapid heating to a high temperature, which preserves product quality due to a reduced holding time. During IR heating, the surface was the most critical part of the powder mass, displaying undesired browning and drying at temperatures over 100°C. This was predominantly seen with the open system, due to water evaporation and uncontrolled temperature increase when applying constant IR heat fluxes. Such product degradation was limited when the closed units were used, as the closure prevented water evaporation and the temperature was controlled using variable IR heat fluxes. In general, colour changes were a result of initial powder wetting and product temperature over 60°C during heating. However, overall colour and aw were not significantly affected by the surface colour or aw. The higher the IR heat flux, the higher the surface temperature in the paprika powder. At the same heat flux and at aw &lt; 0.8, higher surface temperatures were observed with medium-IR, while near-IR produced a greater heat penetration depth; however, those differences disappeared at aw ≥ 0.8. Microbial reduction was dependent on initial aw and its change during heating, product temperature, and IR holding time. Powder heated to a product temperature of 95–100°C displayed a higher microbial inactivation than did powder heated to 90°C, while the impact of lowering pH from 4.5 to 4.0 was negligible. A microbial reduction of more than 4 log10 B. cereus/g was achieved after 6 min at aw 0.96, 0.88, and 0.76, for the open, closed-glass, and -pouch heating units, respectively. However, in the plastic pouch, the same reduction was achieved after 2–3 min at aw 0.84–0.80. The IR decontamination of portioned paprika placed in sealed plastic pouches is recommended due to the negligible water evaporation, easy handling of flexible plastic material, and avoidance of powder recontamination subsequent to IR treatment. The use of an IR-glass heating unit is recommended when powder is dried to aw 0.50 after IR decontamination due to the easy removal of the top lid. Decontaminated paprika powder was either (a) stored in a sealed plastic pouch at aw 0.76 or 0.84 or (b) mixed with meat or crème fraîche, and then stored at 7°C. Stored paprika powder displayed constant microbial values of 2–3 log10 B. cereus/g for the duration of the 4-month test period, while retaining aw and an acceptable red colour. Paprika-spiced meat displayed maximal 5 log10 B. cereus/g after 20 d, remaining under the contamination level of 6 log10 B. cereus/g found in the untreated paprika powder. Paprika-spiked crème fraîche displayed constant microbial values of 3 log10 B. cereus/g for the duration of the 60 d test period. The IR decontamination of paprika powder, and the subsequent storage and addition of the powder to high-water foods were successfully tested. Any industrial implementation would require the selection of an appropriate IR heat flux and product aw to obtain significant microbial reduction while maintaining high product quality.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Dissertation erforscht die Möglichkeiten der Entkeimung von pulvrigen Lebensmitteln mittels Infrarotwärmestrahlung (IR). Paprikapulver wurde als Modelmaterial gewählt, angefeuchtet und beimpft mit Sporen eines psychrotrophen Bacillus cereus Stammes. Der Einfluss von IR-wärmestrom und -wellenlänge, und der Wasseraktivität (aw) von Paprika wurde hinsichtlich Farb- und aw-veränderungen, und der mikrobielle Entkeimung untersucht. Paprikapulver wurde in drei verschiedene Pulverbehältern im Labormaßstab behandelt: ein (1) offener Pulverbehälter; und zwei geschlossene Pulverbehälter unter Benutzung von transparentem kurzwelligem (2) IR-glas und (3) IR-plastikmaterial. Die IR Erhitzung wurde nach dem HTST-prinzip durchgeführt und bestand aus einer Aufwärmphase und einer nachgeschalteten Halteperiode bei gewünschter Produkttemperatur. Die Pulveroberfläche war der kritische Teil während der Erhitzung. Dort zeigten sich ungewünschte Bräunungserscheinungen und Produkttrocknung durch Temperaturen über 100°C. Dies wurde vor allem beobachtet beim offenen Pulverbehälter, wo Wasserdampf ungehindert entweichen konnte und durch Verwendung eines konstanten Wärmestromes ein unkontrollierbarer Temperaturanstieg stattfand. Durch Produkttemperaturkontrolle, mittels variablem Wärmestrom, und Verwendung eines geschlossenen Pulverbehälters wurden diese negativen Erscheinungen begrenzt. Oberflächliche Farb- und aw-veränderungen hatten keine Auswirkungen auf den Gesamteindruck des Pulvers. Farbveränderungen im Produkt waren ein Ergebnis des Befeuchtens und von Produkttemperaturen während des Erhitzens über 60°C. Je höher der Wärmestrom, desto höher auch die Oberflächentemperatur in Paprika. Bei gleichem Wärmestrom und aw&lt; 0.8, eine höhere Oberflächentemperatur wurde beobachtet für mittelwelliges-IR, während kurzwelliges-IR eine größere Eindringtiefe hatte. Diese unterschiedlichen Eigenschaften verschwanden aber bei aw &gt; 0.8. Mikrobielle Abtötung hing von dem anfänglichen aw und seinen Veränderungen während des Erhitzens, der Produkttemperatur und der IR Haltezeit ab. Produkttemperaturen von 95-100°C zeigten höhere Abtötungsraten als 90°C, wobei eine Erniedrigung des pHs von 4.5 auf 4.0 keinen bedeutenden Effekt hatte. Abtötungsraten von mehr als 4 log10 B. cereus/g wurden für den offenen (aw 0.96), und geschlossenen IR glas (aw 0.88) und IR-plastik (aw 0.76) Pulverbehälter nach 6 min erreicht. Die gleiche Abtötung wurde unter Verwendung des IR-plastik Pulverbehälters (aw 0.84-0-80) allerdings auch schon nach 2-3 min erzielt. IR Entkeimung ist empfohlen für portioniertem Pulver eingeschweißt im IR-plastikbeutel, da hier kein nennenswerter Wasserverlust beim Erhitzen auftrat, das flexible Plastikmaterial einfach zu handhaben ist und eine mikrobielle Verunreinigung nach der Entkeimung ausgeschlossen werden kann. Der geschlossene IR-glas Pulverbehälter ist empfohlen, wenn das Pulver nach der Entkeimung noch getrocknet werden soll, da sich das Glas ganz einfach entfernen lässt. Entkeimtes Pulver (aw 0.76 und 0.84) wurde gelagert entweder für Pulver eingeschweißt im Plastikbeutel, oder nach Zugabe zu rohem Fleisch und Crème fraîche (Lagerung bei 7°C). Paprikapulver, gelagert bis zu 4 Monaten, zeigte mikrobiell stabile Werte von 2-3 log10 B. cereus/g, bei ebenso konstanten Messwerten von Farbe und aw. Paprikapulver vermischt mit Fleisch zeigte einen Anstieg von 2 auf 5 log10 B. cereus/g, nach 12-20 Tagen, wobei die Werte unter dem Vergleichswert der unbehandelten Probe von 6 log10 B. cereus/g blieben. Paprika gewürzte Crème fraiche zeigte konstante Werte von 3 log10 B. cereus/g sogar nach 60 Tagen. Entkeimung, Lagerung und Zugabe zu Lebensmittel wurde erfolgreich getestet für Paprika. Eine industrielle Umsetzung erfordert die genaue Auswahl von IR Wärmestrom und Produkt aw um eine signifikante Abtötungsrate bei Beibehaltung der Produktqualität zu erzielen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-05-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1781</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18606</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18606</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1781/original_Monografie_Norman_Staack_8_May.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1781/staack_norman.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
