<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:23Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1511">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1511</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-21</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Experiments on falling film evaporation of a water-ethylene glycol mixture on a surface with longitudinal grooves</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Experimentelle Untersuchungen der Fallfilmverdampfung binärer Gemische auf einer Oberfläche mit Längsnuten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lozano Avilés, Miriam</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Falling film apparatus are used in the industry amongst others to concentrate temperature sensitive liquid mixtures because of their low required wallsuperheat. A technique to enhance the heat transfer in this kind of apparatus is the use of structured heating surfaces, that not only enlarge the transfer area with respect to a smooth surface. Structured heating surfaces are also believed to modify the waviness of the falling film and thereby to improve the heat transfer. However, the enhance mechanism is not yet understood in-depth. In the present work, the effect of vertical finned and grooved heating surfaces on the hydrodynamic characteristics and the heat transfer of evaporating water and water-ethylene glycol falling films is studied. Two high frequency probes are used to measure the time variation of the film thickness and the wave velocity at a flow length of 800mm in the Reynolds number range from 200 up to 1100. A new statistical data processing method for the characterization of wavy falling films based on probability distributions is developed. The additional achieved information with respect to the available methods in the literature is discussed. The small thickness of falling films results in a low heat transfer resistance. Thus, the thinner the film, the better the heat transfer. However, if the film is very thin, it tends to break and consequently, the performance of the apparatus drops abruptly. The stability of the film is partly determined by the wettability properties of the heating plate and consequently by the interfacial tensions. Also thermocapillary forces affect the breakdown of falling films. In the present work, the wettability of the test plate by water and a water-ethylene glycol mixture is studied. Furthermore, the breakdown of films by means of the Thin Film Pressure Balance Technique is observed and the influence of the grooves on the thermocapillary breakdown of subcooled water films is investigated. The analysis of the measurements reveal an improvement of the heat transfer of falling films on structured surfaces due to their impact on the hydrodynamic characteristics of the film. However, the heat transfer enhancement mechanism can not be generalized because it depends strongly on the physical properties of the liquid. Furthermore, longitudinal grooved surfaces have been found to increase the critical heat flux for breakdown and to prevent the spreading of dry patches in transverse direction to the flow. Printed version available from Dr. Hut Verlag: [http://www.hut-verlag.de/]</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Fallfilmapparate werden in der Industrie unter anderem zur Aufkonzentration von temperaturempfindlichen fluiden Gemischen eingesetzt. Sie eignen sich hierfür wegen der geringen erforderlichen Wandüberhitzungen. Eine Methode zur Verbesserung des Wärmeübergangs in diesen Apparaten ist der Einsatz von strukturierten Heizflächen, die nicht nur die Austauschfläche vergrößern. Es wird vermutet, dass strukturierte Heizflächen auch die Welligkeit des Fallfilmes beeinflussen und dabei den Wärmeübergang verbessern. Allerdings ist der Mechanismus der Verbesserung noch nicht gründlich verstanden. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wird der Einfluss von senkrechten berippten und genuteten Heizflächen auf die Hydrodynamik und den Wärmeübergang von verdampfenden Wasser- und Wasser-Ethylenglykol Gemisch Fallfilmen untersucht. Der zeitliche Filmdickeverlauf und die Wellengeschwindigkeit werden mit zwei Hochfrequenz-Sonden bei einer Lauflänge von 800mm im Reynoldsbereich von 200 bis 1100 gemessen. Ein neues statistisches Auswertungsverfahren basierend auf Wahrscheinlichkeitsverteilungen wird entwickelt. Die ergänzende Information der neuen Methode in Bezug auf die Ergebnisse der in der Literatur vorhandenen Methoden wird diskutiert. Der Wärmeübergangwiderstand in Fallfilmen ist sehr gering aufgrund der niedrigen Filmdicken. Je dünner der Film, desto besser ist der Wärmeübergang. Ist der Film jedoch sehr dünn, neigt er zum Aufzureißen und die Leistung des Apparats sinkt schlagartig. Die Stabilität eines Fallfilmes hängt unter anderem von der Benetzbarkeit der Heizfläche ab und damit von Grenzflächenspannungen. Auch thermokapillare Kräfte beeinflussen das Aufreißen des Filmes. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wird daher die Benetzbarkeit der Heizfläche mit Wasser und mit Wasser-Ethylenglykol untersucht. Ferner wird das Aufreißen von Filmen mittels der ''Thin Film Pressure Balance'' untersucht sowie der Einfluss von Nuten auf das Filmaufreißen von unterkühlten Wasserfilmen aufgrund von thermokapillaren Kräften. Die Messungen zeigen eine Steigerung des Wärmeübergangs von Fallfilmen auf strukturierten Heizflächen aufgrund deren Wirkung auf die Hydrodynamik des Filmes. Allerdings lässt sich der Verbesserungsmechanismus nicht verallgemeinern, weil er von den physikalischen Eigenschaften der Flüssigkeit abhängt. Darüber hinaus erhöhen längsgenutete Heizflächen die kritische Wärmestromdichte, bei der der Film aufreißt, und unterdrücken die Ausbreitung von trockenen Stellen in Querströmungsrichtung. Gedruckte Version im Dr. Hut Verlag [http://www.hut-verlag.de/] erschienen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-05-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-89963-527-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1511/lozano_aviles_miriam.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
