<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:48Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2475">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2475</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Reliability Study of Stud Bump Bonding Flip Chip Assemblies on Molded Interconnect Devices</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Zuverlässigkeits-Analyse von Stud Bump Bonding Flip Chip Verbindungenauf Molded Interconnect Devices</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dreßler, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The Stud Bump Bonding (SBB) flip chip technology on Molded Interconnect Devices (MID) is a highly promising solution to the increasing demand for reliable interconnection technology at high temperatures, a miniaturized assembly and a reduction of costs and parts. Carrying out thermal cycling, this work shows for the first time that the SBB flip chip technology used in combination with Printed Wiring Boards based on the MID technology is a highly reliable packaging technology. Using requirements set by the automotive industry, such as exposing the assembled flip chip interconnections to thermal cycles between 150°C and -40°C, no single electrical failure is detected; it was tested until 3000 thermal cycles. For the flip chip assembly, isotropic conductive adhesive (ICA) in combination with capillary underfill (UF), as well as no-flow underfill such as non-conductive adhesive (NCA) was used. Additionally, two different chip sizes and board thicknesses were used. The influence of oxygen plasma treatment of the surface of the LCP board was investigated, which strongly influences the wetting angle between substrate and underfill. Two potential failure mechanisms were initially theoretically proposed: bulk fillet cracking and delamination between board and underfill. Then, experimental reliability analysis of the SBB flip chip technology on MID boards was carried out and univocally verified the theoretically proposed failure mechanisms. Failure originating from the bump area was not detected. Fracture Mechanics approach was used to describe the failure mechanisms: stress intensity factor for bulk cracking and the energy release rate for the delamination. The proposed failure mechanisms were used to create a guideline to optimize SBB flip chip interconnections. The general conclusion can be drawn that the two failure mechanisms were strongly influenced by local parameters. Parameters which influence the global behavior of the flip chip interconnection such as the chip size and the thickness of the board show negligible influences on the failure mechanisms. A higher impact was observed via the CTE value and Young's modulus of the adhesive. The lower the CTE value and Young's modulus, the lower the risk of bulk fillet cracking. An increase of the adhesive CTE value by 25%, as well as the wetting angle between underfill and substrate, increase the risk of delamination by almost 75%. Based on the results of the present work, optimization of SBB flip chip interconnections on MID boards is based on the present work already possible in the design phase. There are only two failure mechanisms for this kind of interconnection technology when exposed to thermal cycling. Failure at the bump is not a failure mechanism for the studied packaging technology. The proposed guidelines support the selection of the appropriate underfill, board material and geometry such as thickness and chip size. Additionally, the results of this work clearly indicate the use of oxygen plasma treatment on the LCP board prior to flip chip assembly.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Stud Bump Bonding (SBB) Flip-Chip Technologie auf Molded Interconnect Devices (MID) Substraten ist eine vielversprechende Lösung für die wachsende Nachfrage nach zuverlässigen Aufbau- und Verbindungstechnologien bei gleichzeitiger Miniaturisierung und Reduktion von Kosten und Komponenten. Diese Arbeit zeigt, dass die SBB Flip-Chip Technologie in Kombination mit der MID Substrat-Technologie eine höchst zuverlässige Aufbau- und Verbindungstechnik darstellt. Basierend auf Automotive Anforderungen konnte gezeigt werden, dass diese AVT Technologie mindestens 3000 Temperaturwechsel-Lagerungen zwischen 150°C/-40°C ohne jegliche elektrische Ausfälle widersteht. Zum Aufbau der Flip Chip-Verbindungen wurden ein isotrop leitfähiger Klebstoff zusammen mit einem kapillaren Underfiller verwendet, sowie ein nicht elektrisch leitfähigen Klebstoff (NCA). Zusätzlich wurden zwei unterschiedliche Chipgrößen und Substratdicken verwendet. Darüber hinaus wurde der Einfluss der Oberflächenbehandlung mit Sauerstoffplasma untersucht welche den Benetzungswinkel und Meniskusform stark beeinflusst. Anhand von FEM-Analysen wurden zwei potentielle Fehlermechanismen identifiziert: Rissentstehung im oberen Teil des Meniskus und Delaminations-Entstehung zwischen Substrat und Underfill. Diese beiden Ausfallmechanismen konnten in den Zuverlässigkeitsuntersuchungen experimentell nachgewiesen werden. Eine Ausfallinitiierung bzw. Versagen in der Nähe der Stud Bumps wurde, wie theoretisch ebenfalls vorhergesagt, nicht detektiert. Bruchmechanische Größen wurden zur Beschreibung der Ausfallmechanismen verwendet: Spannungsintensitätsfaktor für bulk Risse im oberen Teil des Meniskus und die Energiefreisetzungsrate für die Delamination. Auf Basis dieser Größen wurde ein Auslegungs-Leitfaden für die Optimierung dieser AVT-Technologie erstellt. Eine große Auswirkung haben der Ausdehnungskoeffizient und das E-Modul des Klebstoffs. Je niedriger der Ausdehnungskoeffizient und das E-Modul, desto geringer ist das Risiko einer Rissentstehung im oberen Teil des Meniskus. Eine Erhöhung des CTE-Werts um 25% erhöht das Risiko eines Ausfalls um fast das Dreifache. Ebenso kann das Delaminationsrisiko zwischen Klebstoff und Substrat reduziert werden, wenn der Benetzungswinkel so klein wie möglich gehalten wird. Eine Erhöhung des Winkels um 25% zieht eine Erhöhung des Delaminationsrisikos um mehr als 75% nach sich. Mit Hilfe der Ergebnisse der hier vorliegenden Arbeit kann eine Optimierung und daher Zuverlässigkeitssteigerung einer SBB Flip-Chip Verbindung auf MID Substraten bereits in der Auslegungsphase durchgeführt werden. Der Leitfaden hilft bei der Auswahl der geeigneten Klebstoffe, Substratmaterialien und Geometriegrößen wie Substratdicke und Chipgröße. Als Ergebnis dieser Arbeit ist zudem festzuhalten, dass die Oberflächenbehandlung mit Sauerstoffplasma einen unabdingbaren Prozessschritt darstellt um die Zuverlässigkeit von SBB Flip-Chip Verbindungen auf MID Substraten zu erhöhen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-03-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25986</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25986</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2475/dressler_marc.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
