<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:48Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2474">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2474</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Conceptual  and Structural Design of Buildings made of Lightweight and Infra-Lightweight Concrete </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Konzeptionelles und strukturelles Design von Geb√§uden mit leichtem und infraleichtem Beton</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zareef, Mohamed Ahmed Mohamed El</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Some times the need to reduce the weight of a structural element is not less important than increasing its strength, especially in heavy structures such as tall buildings and bridges where the structure‚Äôs weight is one of the main problems that faces the designers. In spite of the increasing use and demand of Lightweight Concrete (LWC), the conceptual and structural design aspects for buildings made from LWC and Infra-Lightweight Concrete (ILWC) have not been adequately explained. Issues such as element dimensions, connections, and reinforcement types and details as well as short- and long-term deformations and dynamic behaviour for LWC structures should be covered in up-to-date codes. Therefore, this study deals with conceptual and structural design of buildings made from LWC and ILWC and generally consists of two main objectives: - Development and production of new mixtures for LWC and ILWC with minimized dry density and very good mechanical and physical properties. - The ability to apply and involve these new materials in the construction field through intensive series of experimental tests on different structural elements and connections under static and dynamic loads. In order to achieve the first objective in the study, two targets were defined, the first: fair-faced ILWC for walls with minimum dry density (Ô?≤min &lt; 800 kg/m¬≥), minimum thermal conductivity enough to eliminate the heat insulation materials, and maximum strength enough to resist the vertical bearing stress from floors. The second target: fair-faced LWC for construction of floor slabs and beams with minimum dry density, minimum thermal conductivity and maximum strength enough to resist flexural and shear stresses comparable to normal concrete (NC). Once the ILWC and LWC materials were developed and their mechanical and physical properties were determined, a series of large-scale experiments was conducted. For ILWC, a real application i.e. a one-family house in Berlin, was built in 2006. Because of its favourable physical properties and its good durability, ILWC reinforced with GFR was used for the first time as monolithic cast-in-site concrete to construct the outer walls of this house without any additional insulation [Schlaich M., et. al., 2008]. Infra-lightweight concrete is an engineered high-tech material whose potential and various other design aspects are not yet fully exploited. The study shows the limits of ILWC, but also its great potential for fair-faced concrete buildings. For LWC, eight beams constructed from the newly developed LWC mixture with concrete strength class of LC 30/33 and reinforced with glass-fibre bars and steel bars, in addition to two control beams constructed from normal concrete C 30/37 and reinforced with steel bars, were tested experimentally for flexural strength capacity, shear strength capacity, ductile behaviour and bond behaviour in tension and compression zones of the beams. From the economic point of view, using LWC in construction of the floor slabs in tall buildings will reduce the total costs of tall buildings through the reduction of the amount of steel reinforcement, the reduction of foundation volume, and the reduction of vertical members‚Äô cross-sections that saves the used horizontal area. Because they are the most affected components of tall buildings during earthquake excitations, an experimental study was done to investigate the behaviour of interior and exterior joints between LWC beams and NC columns under seismic loads. The development of highly damage-tolerant beam-column connections would allow structural engineers to design joints for moderate shear distortions which exhibit little damage, reduce rotation demands in beam plastic hinges, and eliminate the need for post-earthquake joint repairs. One option for achieving this goal is to use LWC beams which were reinforced with glass-fibre reinforcement bars with superior deformation capacity in beam-column connections.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das Problem der Gewichtsreduzierung einiger Bauteile hat heutzutage die gleiche Bedeutung wie die Steigerung der Festigkeit, speziell bei gro√üen Bauwerken wie Hochh√§user oder Br√ºcken wo das Eigengewicht das Hauptproblem dieser darstellt. Trotz der zunehmenden Verwendung von Leichtbetonen, gibt es keine ad√§quaten Erl√§uterungen bez√ºglich des Konstruieren und Entwerfen von Geb√§uden aus Leichtbeton (LB) und Infraleichtbeton (ILB). F√ºr Probleme wie Dimensionierung, konstruktive Durchbildung, Bewehrungswahl und Detailausf√ºhrung, Kriechen und Schwinden sowie das dynamisches Verhalten der Leichtbetonbauwerke ist es zwingend notwendig, dass diese in neuste Normen aufgenommen werden. Die vorliegende Arbeit besch√§ftigt sich mit den Entwerfen und Konstruieren von Bauwerken aus Leicht- und Infraleichtbeton und umfasst zwei Schwerpunkte: - Entwicklung und Herstellung neuer Rezepturen von LB und ILB mit minimierter Trockenrohdichte und sehr guten mechanischen und physikalischen Eigenschaften. - Eignung dieser Materialien in Bauteilen und Verbindungen anhand von intensiven Testreihen und Experimenten mit statischer und dynamischer Belastung. Um dem ersten Schwerpunkt zu definieren wurden zwei Ziele festgelegt; zum einen: ein Sichtbeton aus Infraleichtbeton f√ºr W√§nde mit einer Mindesttrockendichte von Ô?≤min &lt; 800 kg/m¬≥, eine Mindestw√§rmeleitf√§higkeit um die W√§rmed√§mmung einsparen zu k√∂nnen und hohe Druckfestigkeiten zum Abtragen der Deckenlasten. Zum anderen: ein Sichtbeton aus LB f√ºr Decken, Platten und Balken mit einer Mindesttrockendichte, einer Mindestw√§rmeleitf√§higkeit und einer Druckfestigkeit vergleichbar mit Normalbeton (NB) um Biege- und Querkr√§fte aufnehmen zu k√∂nnen. Sofort nach der Entwicklung und Bemessung des LB und ILB, sowie der Bestimmung der mechanischen und physikalischen Eigenschaften, begann eine gro√ü angelegte Serie von Experimenten. Die erste echte Anwendung fand der Infraleichtbeton in der Errichtung eines Einfamilienhauses in Berlin im Jahre 2006. damit gezeigt, dass sich der Werkstoff in der Praxis behaupten kann. Interessant war dabei vor allem, die konstruktiven und bauphysikalischen Details den Eigenschaften des Werkstoffes anzupassen und teilweise anders als sonst im Stahlbetonbau √ºblich auszuf√ºhren [Schlaich M., et. al., 2008]. Zur Reduzierung der unvermeidbaren Schwindrisse wurde Bewehrung aus Glasfaserst√§ben verwendet, die sowohl das Korrosionsproblem l√∂st als auch W√§rmebr√ºcken vermeidet. Die bisherigen Erfahrungen zeigen, dass Infraleichtbeton gut w√§rmeged√§mmte Sichtbetonbauten erm√∂glicht, und dass er das Potential besitzt, beim Bauen der Zukunft eine nicht zu vernachl√§ssigende Rolle zu spielen. Acht Balken wurden aus Leichbeton LC 30/33, mit Glasfaser und Stahl bewehrt, hergestellt, des weiteren zwei aus Normalbeton C 30/37 mit Stahlbewehrung. Diese wurden alle auf Biege- und Querkrafttragf√§higkeit sowie das Duktil- und Verbundverhalten der Druck- und Zugzone experimentell untersucht. Aus wirtschaftlicher Sicht, k√∂nnen durch den Gebrauch von Leichtbetondecken im mehrgeschossigen Bau, die Kosten gesenkt werden. Die Bewehrungsmenge, Fundamentvolumen und sogar vertikale Tragelemente k√∂nnen reduziert werden. Des Weiteren wurde die Verbindung zwischen Leichtbetonunterzug und Normalbetonst√ºtze unter dynamische Belastung untersucht, da diese Bauteile im Falle eines Erdbebens bei Hochh√§usern besonders gef√§hrdet sind. Die Entwicklung eines Kreuzungsknoten mit hoher Schadenstoleranz erm√∂glicht den Entwurf von Kreuzungspunkten mit moderaten Verformungen infolge Querkr√§ften, die nur eine geringe Sch√§digung verursachen, deren plastische Gelenke die Drehungen reduzieren und die erforderlichen Reparaturen nach einem Erdbeben minimieren. Eine M√∂glichkeit dieses Ziel zu erreichen ist die Verwendung von Balken aus Leichtbeton und St√ºtzen aus Normalbeton. Die Leichtbetonbalken sind mit Glasfaserst√§ben bewehrt. Bisherige Untersuchungen haben gezeigt, dass eine Glasfaserbewehrung hinsichtlich des Verformungsverhaltens einer herk√∂mmlichen Bewehrung aus Betonstahl √ºberlegen ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-03-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2474</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26076</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26076</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2474/zareef_mohamed.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
