<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:56Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2746">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2746</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">A flow cytometric approach to monitor the effects of gentle preservation techniques in the postharvest chain</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ein durchflusszytometrischer Ansatz zum Monitoring der Effekte schonender Konservierungsverfahren in der Nacherntekette</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fröhling, Antje</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Microbial contamination of fruits and vegetables can lead to high economic losses as well as to foodborne diseases. Washing procedures, which arecommonly applied, only reduce the microbial load by 0.5 to 2 log units. Conventional thermal inactivation processes cannot be applied to fresh fruit and vegetables because these products are physiologically active food systems and temperatures above 45 °C can result in unwanted deterioration. Since heat sensitivity of fruits and vegetables limits the application of thermal inactivation processes, new emerging inactivation technologies have to be established to fulfil the requirements of food safety without affecting the produce quality. On one hand an early detection of produce contamination is essential to enable a contamination-related process design and on the other hand the efficiency of inactivation treatments has to be ensured and monitored. Monitoring of inactivation effects is commonly performed using traditional cultivation methods which have the disadvantage of the length of time needed to obtain results. In this study, the potential of flow cytometry in short-time monitoring of inactivation effects (thermal treatment, treatment with peracetic acid, ozone, and atmospheric pressure plasma) was investigated. For this purpose morphological and physiological properties of bacteria (size, granularity, membrane integrity (thiazole orange &amp; propidium iodide), esterase activity (carboxyfluorescein diacetate), pump activity (carboxyfluorescein efflux), and membrane potential (3,3'-diethyloxacarbocyanine iodide)) were determined by flow cytometry. In the initial step appropriate staining procedures had to be developed. Especially, Gram-negative bacteria restrict the dye uptake due to their cell membrane constitution. This limits the determination of esterase activity of Gram-negative bacteria. In this study, an adequate dye concentration (0.83 mmol l-1 carboxyfluorescein diacetate) and incubation time (45 min) at 37 °C were defined which enables a reliable determination of esterase activity of Gram-negative bacteria. This developed staining procedure was successfully applied to monitor inactivation treatments. It was shown that the test bacteria (E. coli, L. innocua, P. carotovorum) lose their culturability due to the applied inactivation treatments but physiological activities were still detectable using flow cytometry. The remaining physiological activities may still result in product spoilage and also may cause human diseases. For example, E. coli cells still showed esterase activity after 10 min of thermal treatment at 70 °C and also after 2 min treatment with 0.25 % PAA at 10 °C. Esterase activity of E. coli cells was also detected after 2 min plasma treatment with an operating power of 40 W. The degree of bacterial damage due to the inactivation processes is highly dependent on treatment parameters as well as on treated bacteria. This study clearly indicates the potential of flow cytometry to monitor the efficacy of inactivation processes within a short time. Additionally, important information regarding the inactivation mechanisms can be obtained by flow cytometric measurements andthis enables the definition of critical process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Bakterielle Kontaminationen können bei der Gemüseproduktion zu hohen ökonomischen Verlusten führen und darüber hinaus auch ein potenzielles Gesundheitsrisiko für den Verbraucher darstellen. Übliche Wasch- undReinigungsschritte reduzieren die Mikroorganismen aber nur um etwa 0,5-2 log Einheiten undkonventionelle thermische Verfahren sind im Bereich leichtverderblicher Produkte wie bspw. frisches Obst und Gemüse in ihrer Anwendung limitiert, da bereits Temperaturen oberhalb von 45 °C zu unerwünschten Veränderungen der charakteristischen physiologischen Produkteigenschaften führen. Um die Qualität der Frischeprodukte zu erhalten und gleichzeitig die anhaftende mikrobielle Schadflora abzutöten, besteht daher ein besonderer Bedarf an innovativen, Produkt schonenden Behandlungsmethoden. Für eine Chargen gerechte Prozessauslegung muss einerseits der Kontaminationsgrad des Produktes frühzeitig erfasst und andererseits der Behandlungserfolg sichergestellt bzw. überwacht werden. Mit konventionellen sehr zeitintensiven mikrobiologischen Verfahren ist dies jedoch nicht möglich. In dieser Studie wurde daher die Durchflusszytometrie im Hinblick auf eine schnelle Charakterisierung des Inaktivierungserfolges verschiedener Inaktivierungsverfahren (Thermische Behandlung, Behandlung mit Peressigsäure, Ozon und Atmosphärendruckplasma) untersucht. Hierzu wurden morphologische und physiologische Eigenschaften der Mikroorganismen (Größe, Oberflächenbeschaffenheit, Membranintegrität (Thiazole Orange &amp; Propidiumjodid), Esteraseaktivität (Carboxfluoreszeindiazetat), Pumpenaktivität (Ausschluss von Carboxyfluoreszein) und Membranpotential (3,3'-Diethyloxacarbocyaninjodid)) durchflusszytometrisch bestimmt. Dabei mussten zuerst geeignete Färbeprotokolle für die verwendeten Farbstoffe entwickelt werden bzw. in der Literatur vorhandene Protokolle modifiziert werden. Insbesondere Gram-negative Bakterien erschweren z.B. die Aufnahme von Carboxyfluoreszeindiacetat zur Ermittlung der Esteraseaktivität aufgrund ihres Zellwandaufbaus. Durch Entwicklung eines Färbeprotokolls konnte eine geeignete Farbstoffkonzentration (0,83 mmol/l Carboxyfluoreszeindiacetat) und Färbezeit (45 min) bei 37 °C für die zuverlässige Bestimmung der Esteraseaktivität Gram-negativer Bakterien ermittelt und für die Überprüfung von Inaktivierungsverfahren verwendet werden. Es hat sich gezeigt, dass die verwendeten Bakterien (E. coli, L. innocua, P. carotovorum) nach den Behandlungsverfahren zwar ihre Kultivierbarkeit verlieren, jedoch teilweise noch physiologische Aktivitäten nachweisbar sind. Damit würde weiterhin die Möglichkeit eines Produktverderbs und Gefährdung der menschlichen Gesundheit bestehen. So konnte z.B. nach einer thermischen Behandlung von 70 °C für 10 min sowie nach einer Behandlung mit 0,25 % Peressigsäure für 2 min noch Esteraseaktivität in E. coli Zellen nachgewiesen werden. Ebenso zeigten E. coli Zellen nach einer zweiminütigen Plasmabehandlung bei 40 W noch Esteraseaktivität. Das Ausmaß der Schädigung der einzelnen Behandlungsverfahren ist dabei stark abhängig von den verwendeten Behandlungsparametern sowie von den behandelten Bakterien. Diese Arbeit zeigt das Potenzial der Durchflusszytometrie einen Inaktivierungserfolg innerhalb kürzester Zeit zu ermitteln und gleichzeitig Aussagen über den jeweiligen verfahrensspezifischen Inaktivierungsmechanismus abzuleiten. Damit wird es ermöglicht, kritische Verfahrensparameter zu bestimmen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-01-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2746</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2746/froehling_antje.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
