<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:51Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3158">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3158</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Modeling, control, and optimization of fuel/air mixing in a lean premixed swirl combustor using fuel staging to reduce pressure pulsations and NOx emissions </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Modellierung, Kontrolle und Optimierung der Luft/Brennstoff-Mischung in einem mageren vorgemischten drall-induzierten Brenner mithilfe einer Brennstoffstufung zur Reduktion von NOx-Emissionen und Druckpulsationen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lacarelle, Arnaud</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work deals with the fuel/air mixing process in a lean premixed gas turbine combustor and how it can be modeled, controlled and optimized to reduce pressure pulsations and NOx emissions. The methodology used to derive models is primarily based on cold flow measurements conducted in a water test rig. The standard fuel injection of the swirl-inducing burner is completed with two additional fuel injection stages. Through adjustment of the fuel distribution, stabilization of the combustion chamber can be achieved, with NOx emissions comparable to the ones produced by standard fuel injection. Measurements of the mean turbulent and coherent flow fields as well as passive scalar mixing properties confirm the similarity of water test rig and combustion chamber. Furthermore, velocity and chemiluminescence measurements with combustion show that the flame has a weak influence on the mean and coherent flow properties just upstream of its stabilization location when it is not anchored inside the burner, validating the cold flow modeling approach. The fuel/air mixing quality at the burner outlet is measured in the water test rig for numerous operating conditions at different axial locations and the flame position recorded in the combustion chamber is used to predict the real mixing quality at the flame. The information gained is then implemented using an experimental fit to more accurately predict the NOx emissions of the burner over a wide operating range. A method is then developed to record and model the temporal response of the burner to fuel/air fluctuations. The so-called measured mixing transfer function confirms that variation of the fuel distribution in the burner strongly influences the convective time delays and partly explains the stabilizing effect of switching the fuel distribution. Using the recorded flame shape recorded by a camera, an estimation of the response of the flame to fuel/air fluctuations is obtained. Comparison with the directly measured flame transfer function shows that a satisfying estimation of the response of the flame to fuel/air fluctuations can be obtained with the new method. An extremum seeking controller (ESC) is implemented on the fuel distribution for the purpose of reduced pressure pulsations and NOx emissions. The chemiluminescence signal is used as a surrogate of the NOx emissions to increase the controller speed. The ESC is then able to track the best injection configuration when the operating conditions are varied as well as avoid local minimum when the cold flow model is taken into account. Passive and active fuel injection methods are then tested to improve the mixing quality at the burner outlet. The investigations show that high frequency fuel injection pulsations can improve the mixing quality recorded at the burner outlet. A fluidic injector array is then developed and implemented at the inlet of the burner. For this configuration, the mixing quality is only weakly influenced by the fluidic injector. However, tested in a generic configuration, these fluidic actuators improved the mixing quality by up to 50% over a wide range of operating conditions, confirming thus the effectivity of such devices. Printed version available: Universitätsverlag der TU Berlin (www.univerlag.tu-berlin.de), ISBN 978-3-7983-2381-0</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit der Luft/Brennstoff Vermischung in einem vorgemischten drallinduzierten Brenner für Gasturbinen. Die Schwerpunkte liegen in der Modellierung, Kontrolle und Optimierung des Mischungsvorgangs, um Druckpulsationen (auch thermoakustische Schwingungen genannt) und NOx-Emissionen zu kontrollieren. Das Modell stützt sich hauptsächlich auf Untersuchungen, die in einem Wasserkanal durchgeführt werden. Die Standard-Gaseindüsung des Brenners wird mit zwei weiteren Brennstoffeindüsungsstufen ergänzt. Durch Anpassung der Brennstoffverteilung können thermoakustische Oszillationen deutlich reduziert werden, ohne dass es zu höheren NOx-Emissionen als bei der Standard-Eindüsung führt. Messungen der mittleren, turbulenten und kohärenten Strömungsfelder sowie des passiven skalaren Konzentrationsfeldes bestätigen die Ähnlichkeit zwischen Wasserkanal und Brennkammer. Desweiteren zeigen Messungen im reagierenden Fall, dass die Flamme einen geringen Einfluss auf das Strömungsfeld stromaufwärts der Verbrennungszone hat wenn diese nicht innerhalb des Brenners verankert ist. Somit ist die Modellierung aus Untersuchungen in nicht reagierenden Systemen gerechtfertigt. Die Qualität der Mischung am Brenneraustritt wird für verschiedene Betriebsbedingungen und an verschiedenen Stellen modelliert. Um die Genauigkeit des Modells zu verbessern, wird die Position der Flamme aufgenommen, um die Mischungsqualitaet an der Flamme abzuschaetzen. Mithilfe einer empirischen Korrelation können dann die NOx-Emissionen genauer vorhergesagt werden. Ein wichtiges Werkzeug zur Entwicklung von stabilen Brennern ist die Flammentransferfunktion. In nicht reagierender Strömung kann zuerst die sogenannte Mischungstransferfunktion gemessen werden. Diese wird aus der Sprungantwort der Mischung und mithilfe von Hoch-geschwindigkeits-Konzentrationsmessungen im Wasserkanal gemessen. Die Mischungstransferfunktion wird dann mit der Flammenposition kombiniert, um eine Abschätzung der reagierenden Flammentransferfunktion zu bekommen. Die Ergebnisse zeigen, dass sich die geschätzte Flammentransferfunktion der in der Brennkammer gemessenen gut annähert. Um die Brennstoffverteilung am Brenner optimal einstellen zu können, wird ein sogenannter Extremwertregler implementiert. Der Regler stellt die Brennstoffverteilung so ein, dass Druckpulsationen und NOx-Emissionen reduziert werden können. Die Fähigkeit des Reglers, lokale Minima zu umgehen, kann durch den Einbau der Stabilitäts- und Emissionsmodelle verbessert werden. Letztlich wurden sowohl aktive als auch passive Maßnahmen eingesetzt, um die Mischungsqualität am Brenneraustritt zu verbessern. In Wasser kann eine Verbesserung der Vermischung am Brenneraustritt mithilfe von rechteckigen Brennstoffpulsationen nachgewiesen werden. Des Weiteren können selbst-oszillierende (fluidische) Aktuatoren an einer generischen Konfiguration sehr gute Ergebnisse erzielen, bei der die Qualität der Mischung, gemessen mit dem Danckwerts "Unmixedness" Kriterium, um etwa 50% verbessert werden kann. Gedruckte Version im Universitätsverlag der TU Berlin (www.univerlag.tu-berlin.de) erschienen, ISBN 978-3-7983-2381-0</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-12-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3158</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-7983-2382-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3158/1_lacarelle_arnaud_text.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3158/2_lacarelle_arnaud_cover.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
