<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:01Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1662">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1662</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Investigation of high-power diode lasers by spectroscopic techniques</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Spektroskopische Untersuchungen an Hochleistungsdiodenlaser</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tran, Tien Quoc</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The subject of the thesis focus on key issues of high-power diode lasers (HPDL) that are related to device reliability and fabrication processes: strain, thermal tuning properties, defects, and the interplay between strain and defects. These issues were investigated by spatially and spectrally resolved photoelectrical techniques (photocurrent spectroscopy - PCS, laser beam induced current - LBIC and near-field optical beam induced current - NOBIC). In the experimental part, we developed the PCS technique to fulfill all requirements of the measurements at HPDLs. The construction of new setups allows for measuring the devices that experience defined external stress, analysis of unpackaged samples as well as the cross-calibration and comparison between PCS and other optical techniques. 1. The mechanical strain had been quantified. By analyzing the whole sequence of QW optical transitions, we analyze - up to a certain degree - even strain symmetry, which is frequently not accessible by competing methods such as Raman-spectroscopy. The major novel results include: ¬∑ strain investigation of HPDL stack. ¬∑ evolutions of mechanical strain during operation. ¬∑ the observation and analysis of additional strain contributions in the immediate vicinity of grooves separating emitters in HPDL arrays. 2. A study on thermal tuning properties of HPDL arrays in operation is presented: ¬∑ the temperature dependences of the thermal tuning rate were presented and the contribution to the tuning rate of compressive packaging-induced strain (pressure-related tuning) was separated. ¬∑ the comparison of the tuning properties of both standard and expansion-matched heat sinks (Cu and Cu-W) indicate an improvement of the tuning characteristics for expansion-matched heat sinks. 3. The microscopic defects play an important role in the understanding of aging processes and were observed in HPDLs. ¬∑ the dynamic of defect signature during device operation shows a clear enhancement of defect concentration of the devices containing ‚Äúinitial‚Ä? defects before aging. ¬∑ for the first time, photoelectric analyses were applied for defect investigation of red-emitting lasers. 4. The interplay between defects and strain in HPDL arrays had been addressed. An enhancement of the concentration of defect levels in single-emitters is accompanied by compressive stress. The effects caused by midgap levels, shallow defects, and band tail states had been distinguished, the latter two of which are assigned to physically different defects, exhibit distinctively different strain-defect relationships. The analysis shows a strong correlation between defect concentration and strain for shallow defect levels and no correlation to midgap defect levels. This novel type of analysis provides knowledge about defect creation scenarios. The approach applied for studying HPDLs in this thesis can be extended to other semiconductor optoelectronic devices.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die optische Spektroskopie wird als Hauptwerkzeug zur Untersuchung von Hochleistungsdiodenlaser (HPDL) eingesetzt. Das schlie√üt die Nutzung von Methoden wie der Photostromspektroskopie (PCS), Laserstrahl-induzierter Str√∂me (LBIC) und Nahfeld- induzierter Str√∂me (NOBIC) ein. Im experimentellen Teil zeigen wir, wie es gelang die PCS-Technik den Erfordernissen von Messungen an verschiedenen HPLDs anzupassen. Das schloss den Aufbau neuer Messpl√§tze f√ºr Messungen an Bauelementen, die definierten externen Verspannungen ausgesetzt waren, Messung von unkonfektionierten Proben, sowie die Kalibrierung der PCS-Methode im Vergleich mit anderen Analysemethoden ein. 1. Mechanische Verspannungen in Halbleiterlasern wurden quantifiziert. Durch Analyse mehrer optischer √úberg√§nge im QW war es sogar m√∂glich, Aussagen zur Symmetrie der Deformation zu machen. Derartige Aussagen sind mit konkurrierenden Methoden, wie der Raman-Spektroskopie meist nicht m√∂glich. Wesentliche neue Ergebnisse beinhalten: ¬∑ Verspannungsuntersuchungen an HPDL-Stacks. ¬∑ Die zeitliche Entwicklung von mechanischen Verspannungen w√§hrend des Betriebes. ¬∑ Die Beobachtung und Analyse von zus√§tzlichen Verspannungsbeitr√§gen, die in der N√§he von ge√§tzten Separationsgr√§ben auftreten. 2. Wir erforschten die thermischen Durchstimmeigenschaften von HPDLs am Arbeitspunkt. ¬∑ Es wurde eine Temperaturabh√§ngigkeit der Durchstimm-Rate gefunden. Zus√§tzlich gelang die Separation desjenigen Beitrages, der seine eigentliche Ursache im Abbau von uniaxialem, durch Konfektionierung eingebrachtem Druck, bei erh√∂hten Temperaturen hat. ¬∑ Der Vergleich der Durchstimmeigenschaften von Standard- und ausdehnungs-angepassten (Cu und Cu-W) W√§rmesenken zeigt eine substanzielle Verbesserung der Homogenit√§t der thermischen Durchstimmeigenschaften beim Einsatz letzterer. 3. Mikroskopische Defekte spielen eine wichtige Rolle im Verst√§ndnis der Alterungsprozesse, die an HPDLs beobachtet werden. ¬∑ Die Dynamik von Defektsignaturen w√§hrend des Bauelementebetriebes deutet insbesondere bei solchen Bauelementen auf eine Konzentrationszunahme hin, in denen auch vor der Alterung Defekte nachweisbar waren. ¬∑ Wir f√ºhrten die ersten photoelektrischen Analysen an rot emittierenden Bauelementen aus. 4. Wir diskutieren die Wechselwirkung von Verspannungen und Defekten in HPDLs. Bei Erh√∂hung der Konzentration von Defektzentren in Einzelemittern wurde eine Zunahme kompressiver Verspannungen beobachtet. Zentren mit Niveaulagen in der Mitte der Bandl√ºcke, flache Zentren und Zust√§nde im Zustandsdichteschwanz zeigen v√∂llig unterschiedliche funktionale Zusammenh√§nge zwischen ihrer Konzentration und der beobachteten mechanischen Deformation des Kristallgitters in ihrer Umgebung. Es gibt eine starke Korrelation zwischen dem Auftreten flacher Zentren und einer Gitterdeformation, w√§hrend Zentren mit Niveaulagen nahe der Mitte der Bandl√ºcke offenbar keinen nachweisbaren Einfluss auf die Gitterdeformation haben. Diese neue Art der Analyse sollte hilfreich dabei sein, Schwachstellen in Bauelementekonstruktionen aufzusp√ºren. Wir gehen davon aus, dass unsere experimentellen Ans√§tze auch auf die Analyse anderer optoelektronischer Bauelemente √ºbertragbar sind.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-01-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1662</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17375</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17375</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1662/original_Tran_QuocTien.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1662/tran_tien.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
