<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2238">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2238</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Quantitative 3D Micro X-ray fluorescence spectroscopy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Quantitative 3D Mikroröntgenfluoreszenzspektroskopie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mantouvalou, Ioanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">X-ray fluorescence (XRF) spectroscopy as an experimental tool for destruction-free elemental analysis is widely used and well accepted. The advent of X-ray optics has rendered lateral micro-analysis feasible. Through the use of two X-ray optics in a confocal arrangement, the third dimension - the depth of a sample - has become accessible. 3D Micro-XRF uses two polycapillary optics - one for the focusing of the excitation radiation and a second lens in front of an energy-dispersive detector. The overlap of the foci of the two optics forms a probing volume from which information is exclusively derived. In this work, the method of 3D Micro-XRF is presented experimentally and introduced as a new analytical tool. The emphasis of this work is laid on new quantification procedures. The full quantification of 3D Micro-XRF measurements of stratified samples with monochromatic excitation has been developed and is described in detail. The quantification relies on a convolution of the shape and sensitivity of the probing volume with the investigated sample. Fluorescence and scattered radiation is used for the reconstruction of thickness and composition of the layers of stratified samples. With the help of especially manufactured reference samples the validity of the quantification model is demonstrated and proved. In general, the overall detected intensity of a confocal measurement is lower compared to Micro-XRF because of the restricted probing volume. The quantification is more laborious and yields higher uncertainties. For each sample new quantification strategies must be developed in oder to optimally use the measured data. Nevertheless, 3D Micro-XRF proves to be one of the only methods, when sectioning or sampling of an object is not an option. The presented possibility of reconstruction of thickness and composition of layers of stratified samples renders this method into a true analytical tool. The quantification of 3D Micro-XRF with X-ray tube excitation is more complex due to the fact that the excitation spectrum is transported with the first capillary lens instead of a monochromatic excitation line. First ideas concerning calibration and quantification procedures are discussed in this work. Due to its non-destructiveness and the fact, that sample preparation is not necessary, 3D Micro-XRF has high potential as an analytical technique in the field of archaeometry. Advantages and inherent limitations of this new technique are discussed with the help of three application examples from this field. The heterogeneity of the objects and the lack of adequate reference samples requires the development of new quantification strategies. The addition of other X-ray methods such as Micro-XRF proves to facilitate the quantification process. Last but not least it is shown, that the careful qualitative analysis of 3D Micro-XRF measurements with X-ray tube excitation can give valuable information without the need for a full quantification or synchrotron radiation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Röntgenfluoreszenzspektroskopie (RFA) ist eine etablierte Methode zur zerstörungsfreien Elementanalyse unbekannter Proben. Durch die Entwicklung von speziellen Röntgenoptiken wurden laterale Untersuchungen im Mikrometerbereich möglich. Die Benutzung zweier Optiken in einer konfokalen Anordnung führt dazu, dass zusätzlich Informationen aus dem Probeninneren erhalten werden können. Bei der 3D Mikro-Röntgenfluoreszenzspektroskopie (3D Mikro-RFA) wird eine Polykapillarlinse benutzt, um die Anregungsstrahlung zu fokussieren, und eine weitere Linse schränkt das Sichtfeld eines energiedispersiven Detektors ein. Informationen über die Probe werden in erster Näherung ausschließlich aus dem Untersuchungsvolumen erlangt, welches durch die Überlagerung der beiden Foki der Linsen entsteht. Im Rahmen der vorliegenden Dissertation wird 3D Mikro-RFA als neue experimentelle und analytische Methode vorgestellt. Der Schwerpunkt der Arbeit liegt dabei auf der Quantifizierung der gewonnenen Messdaten. Die vollständige Quantifizierung von 3D Mikro-RFA Messungen an Schichtsystemen mit monochromatischer Anregung wurde entwickelt und mit Hilfe eigens hergestellter Referenzschichtprobensysteme validiert. Sowohl die Fluoreszenz der Probe als auch die gestreute Anregungsstrahlung gibt dabei Aufschluss über die Schichtzusammensetzung und -dicke. Eine Quantifizierungssoftware wurde erstellt, die flexibel auf verschiedene Probentypen angewandt werden kann. Im Vergleich zu konventioneller Mikro-RFA ist die messbare Fluoreszenz- und Streuintensität geringer, da nur aus einem Mikrovolumen Informationen gewonnen werden. Die Auswertung der Messdaten ist aufwändiger und birgt größere Unsicherheiten in sich. Für jede Probe müssen spezielle Fitstrategien entwickelt werden, um die zu Verfügung stehenden Informationen optimal zu nutzen. Dennoch ist 3D Mikro-RFA eine der wenigen Methoden, wenn das Innere einer Probe von Interesse ist und Mikroprobenentnahme oder Querschnitte nicht zulässig sind. Durch die präsentierte Möglichkeit der Rekonstruktion von Schichtzusammensetzung und -dicke wird die zerstörungsfreie 3D Mikro-RFA in eine analytische Meßmethode überführt. Die Quantifizierung von 3D Mikro-RFA mit Röntgenröhrenanregung ist vergleichsweise komplexer, da die erste Linse ein Anregungsspektrum transportiert anstelle einer monochromatischen Anregungslinie. Erste Modellierungsansätze zum Untersuchungsvolumen sowie Überlegungen zur Kalibrierung und Quantifizierung werden vorgestellt. Als eines der ersten Anwendungsgebiete für 3D Mikro-RFA bietet sich die Archäometrie an, da wertvolle Kulturgüter zerstörungsfrei und ohne Präparation untersucht werden können. Möglichkeiten und Beschränkungen der Quantifizierung werden anhand von drei Beispielen aus diesem Forschungsbereich dargestellt. Kombinationsmöglichkeiten mit anderen Röntgenmethoden wie Mikro-RFA, sowie die Nutzung von rein qualitativen Messungen mit 3D Mikro-RFA Spektrometern mit Röhrenanregung werden diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-09-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2238</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-23153</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-23153</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2238/mantouvalou_ioanna.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
