<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:19Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1970">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1970</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Interface Formation between Hydrocarbon Ring Molecules and III-V Semiconductor Surfaces</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Grenzflächenbildung zwischen ringförmigen Kohlenwasserstoff-Molekülen und III-V Halbleiteroberflächen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Paßmann, Regina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this work a systematical study to investigate the adsorption structures of small hydrocarbon ring shaped molecules on III-V semiconductor surfaces with Photo-Emission Spectroscopy (PES), Reflectance Anisotropy Spectroscopy (RAS), Scanning Tunneling Microscopy (STM) as well as Low Electron Energy Diffraction (LEED) was performed. With these investigations the interface formation between the organic molecules and the III-V semiconductors used in the present work have been clarified. So far, most of the results on hybrid interfaces are reported for the adsorption of organic molecules on Silicon surfaces. A well understood surface in this case is the Si(001)(2x1) reconstruction, which is described by asymmetric buckled Si-Si surface dimers. This asymmetric dimer arrangement is a basic prerequisite for a [2+2] cycloaddition reaction which often occurs between the Si(001)(2x1) reconstructed surface and hydrocarbon ring shaped molecules. Concerning the adsorption of organic molecules on surfaces of the technologically important III-V semiconductor surfaces, on the other hand, only little is known. However, the combination of organic molecules and III-V semiconductor materials offers an ideal platform for applications in the field of electronic and optoelectronic devices. In order to improve the understanding of the interface formation between organic molecules and III-V surfaces it is important to know the first bonding sites of the organic molecules in specific for example if the molecules are flat lying on the surface or upright standing. This knowledge will give the possibility to understand for example in which direction a charge injection or a charge transport through the molecular layer would be possible. This is only one crucial parameter for the improvement of the performance of electronic devices. Hence a systematical study of the adsorption of organic molecules is necessary to find out the parameters which have an influence on the final adsorption structure. Two influences can be investigated by the characterization of the interface formation between hydrocarbon molecules and III-V semiconductors surfaces: the influence of the intra-molecular double bonds and the influence of the surface dimer configuration and surface stoichiometry. To investigate the influence of the surface structure in detail the surface dimer configuration to the adsorption process of organic molecules GaAs(001) surfaces, the c(4x4), the (2x4) and the (4x2) have been investigated as well as the adsorption of cyclopentene on the InP(001)(2x4) reconstructed surface. In the direct comparison it is shown that cyclopentene bonds to the InP(001)(2x4) surface via a cycloaddition like reaction. During this adsorption the double bond splits which is in contrast to the adsorption of cyclopentene on the GaAs(001) surfaces. Therefrom it is concluded that the surface geometry has an influence on the resulting adsorption structure. In order to investigate the influence of the intra-molecular double bonds, cyclopentene (one double bond), 1,4-cyclohexadiene (two double bonds) and benzene (three double bonds) were used for the characterization of the interface formation. With the investigations on the GaAs(001) reconstructed surfaces it was shown that a dependency of the bonding configuration on the intra-molecular double bonds exists. During the adsorption of cyclopentene no evidence was found that the double bond has to be involved in the interface formation while during the adsorption of 1,4-cyclohexadiene and benzene the double bonds are involved. Furthermore it was found that a bonding to As atoms of the surface is more likely than a bonding to Ga atoms. This systematically studies show that there are a clear influences of the surface geometry and the molecule structure on the adsorption structures. This results in a systematic formation of the molecule-semiconductor-interfaces.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wurde eine systematische Untersuchung der Adsorptionsstruktur von kleinen organischen Ringmolekülen auf III-V Halbleitern mittels Photoelektronen-Spektroskopie (PES), Reflexions-Anisotropie-Spektroskopie (RAS), Rastertunnelmikroskopie (STM), sowie niederenergetische Elektronenbeugung (LEED) durchgeführt. Durch diese Untersuchungen wurde die Grenzflächenbildung zwischen den organischen Molekülen und den III-V Halbleitern aufgeklärt. Vor dieser Arbeit existierten zwar zahlreiche Untersuchungen zur Adsorptionskonfiguration, sowie den zugrundeliegenden Bindungsmechanismen von organischen Molekülen auf Si(001) Oberflächen, systematische Untersuchungen der Adsorption auf III-V Halbleitern gab es aber keine. Auf Si(001) Oberflächen erfolgt die Adsorption oft mittels einer Cycloadditionsreaktion. Allerdings sind nicht nur Systeme basierend auf Silizium für Anwendungen interessant, sondern auch jene basierend auf III-V Halbleitern. Kohlenwasserstoff-Moleküle und III-V Halbleiter bieten insbesondere die Möglichkeit systematisch zwei wesentliche Einflüsse zu analysieren: zum Einen den Einfluss der atomaren Oberflächenstruktur der Halbleitermaterialien und zum Anderen den Einfluss der intra-molekularen Strukturelemente. Um den Einfluss der Oberflächenstruktur, insbesondere des Dimers, auf den Adsorptionsprozess von organischen Molekülen zu untersuchen, wurden in dieser Arbeit, vergleichend zu Silizium, die ersten Bindungsplätze auf den GaAs(001) Oberflächen, der c(4x4), (2x4) und (4x2), untersucht, sowie die Adsorption von Cyclopenten auf der InP(001)(2x4) Oberfläche. Im Vergleich zeigte sich, dass Cyclopenten auf InP(001)(2x4) in einer der Cycloadditionsreaktion ähnlichen Adsorptionsstruktur bindet. Dies ist mit dem Aufspalten der Doppelbindung einhergehend, im Gegensatz zu der Adsorption auf GaAs(001). Somit zeigt sich hier, dass die Oberflächengeometrie einen Einfluss auf die resultierende Adsorptionsstruktur hat. Zum Zweiten wurde der Einfluss der intra-molekularen Bindungen in dieser Arbeit mittels Cyclopenten (eine Doppelbindung), 1,4-Cyclohexadien (zwei Doppelbindungen), sowie Benzol (drei Doppelbindungen) charakterisiert. Anhand der Untersuchungen auf rekonstruierten GaAs(001) Oberflächen hat sich gezeigt, dass es eine Abhängigkeit der Bindungskonfiguration von der Anzahl der intra-molekularen Doppelbindung gibt. Bei der Adsorption von Cyclopenten wurde nur eine Einfachbindung zur Oberfläche ausgebildet, während für 1,4-Cyclohexadien und Benzol pro Molekül eine Bindung zu vier Atomen der Oberfläche festgestellt werden konnte. Bei der Adsorption von Cyclopenten gab es keinen eindeutigen Nachweis dafür, dass die Doppelbindung in die Bindung zur Oberfläche involviert sein muss, wohingegen die Adsorption von 1,4-Cyclohexadien und Benzol über die Doppelbindungen stattfindet. Weiterhin zeigte sich eine häufigere Ausbildung von Bindungen zu As-Atomen als zu Ga-Atomen der Oberfläche. Diese systematischen Untersuchungen belegen, dass sowohl die Oberflächengeometrie, als auch die Molekülstruktur einen Einfluss auf die resultierende Adsorptionsstruktur haben und sich daraus eine Systematik bezüglich der Ausbildung der Molekül-Halbleiter-Grenzflächen ergibt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-11-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1970</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20634</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20634</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1970/original_passmann_regina.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1970/passmann_regina.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
