<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:13Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3437">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3437</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Investigation of non-local autoionization processes in rare gas clusters</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Untersuchung von nicht-lokalen Autoionisationsprozessen in Edelgasclustern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Förstel, Marko</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The main topic of this thesis is the investigation of non-local autoionization processes in mixed rare gas clusters after photoionization using synchrotron radiation. In particular, the aim of the work is the experimental detection of ETMD(3) (electron transfer mediated decay). After photoionization and subsequent autoionization of the clusters, the flight times of the resulting photo-electrons and secondary electrons were measured in coincidence using a magnetic bottle electron time-of-flight spectrometer. After excitation of Ar-Kr clusters using synchrotron radiation with an energy of 32eV, two signals are identified in the coincidence spectrum. The first signal occurs only in coincidence with the Ar 3s derived cluster band and is the ETMD(3) signal. A spectrum of the kinetic energy distribution of the ETMD(3) electron is shown. The second signal comes from electron-electron collisions in the cluster. In Ar-Xe clusters, both ETMD(3) and ICD (interatomic coulombic decay) are energetically allowed. It was possible to determine the structure and the composition of the Ar-Xe clusters through detailed analysis of their valence spectra. The spectrum of secondary electrons, recorded in coincidence with the Ar 3s derived cluster band, shows contributions from ICD and ETMD(3). The intensity of these contributions depends on the composition and size of the clusters under study. Furthermore, the structure and shape of the outer valence spectra of homogeneous argon and krypton clusters of different sizes were examined. Both species show a dispersing feature in a small range of excitation energies, which is superimposed on the outer valence cluster band. This feature is observed at cluster sizes starting at about 230 atoms, in the case of argon, and about 270 atoms, in the case of krypton. This results from dispersion of the valence band due to the crystal structure of the clusters investigated. It is therefore an indicator of the development of bulk-like properties of the clusters.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Gegenstand dieser Arbeit ist die Untersuchung von nichtlokalen Autoionisationsprozessen in gemischten Edelgasclustern nach der Photoionisation mit Synchrotronstrahlung. Insbesondere ist das Ziel der Arbeit der experimentelle Nachweis von ETMD(3) (electron transfer mediated decay). Nach der Photoionisation der Cluster wurden die Flugzeiten der resultierenden Photoelektronen und der Sekundärelektronen mit Hilfe eines magnetische Flasche Elektronenflugzeitspektrometers in Koinzidenz gemessen. Nach der Anregung von Ar-Kr Clustern mit Synchrotronstrahlung mit einer Energie von 32eV konnten zwei Signale im Koinzidenzspektrum identifiziert werden. Das erste Signal tritt nur in Koinzidenz mit der Ar 3s Clusterlinie auf und ist das gesuchte ETMD(3) Signal. Ein Spektrum der kinetischen Energieverteilung des ETMD(3) Elektrons wird gezeigt. Das zweite Signal stammt von Elektron-Elektron Stößen im Cluster. In Ar-Xe Clustern sind sowohl ETMD(3) als auch ICD (interatomic coulombic decay) energetisch erlaubt. Mit Hilfe einer detaillierten Analyse der Valenzspektren von Ar-Xe Clustern, konnten die Struktur und die Zusammensetzung der Cluster bestimmt werden. Das Spektrum der Sekundärelektronen, die in Koinzidenz zu dem Ar 3s Band aufgenommen wurden, zeigt Beiträge von ICD und von ETMD. Die Intensität dieser Beiträge ist abhängig von der Zusammensetzung und Größe der untersuchten Cluster. Weiterhin wurden Struktur und Form der Photoelektronenspektren der Außenvalenzen homogener Argon und Krypton Cluster mit unterschiedlichen Größen untersucht. Beide Spezies zeigen in einem kleinen Bereich von Anregungsenergien ein dispergierendes Feature, was dem Außenvalenzband überlagert ist. Dieses Feature tritt ab Clustergrößen von ca. 230 Atomen bei Argon und unter ca. 270 Atomen bei Krypton auf. Es wird gezeigt, dass es auf Dispersion des Valenzbandes aufgrund der Kristallstruktur der untersuchten Cluster zurückzuführen ist. Es ist somit ein Indikator für die Entstehung von Festkörpereigenschaften.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-09-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3437</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36565</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36565</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3437/foerstel_marko.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
