<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2676">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2676</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Ellipsometric characterisation of anisotropic thin organic films</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ellipsometrische Charakterisierung von anisotropen dünnen organischen Schichten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rosu, Dana-Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The aim of the present work was to investigate the structural properties of organic molecules on different substrates using different optical spectroscopic techniques. The two studied systems were: self assembled monolayers of alkanethiols on GaAs and Au and cytosine thin films on H-passivated Si(111) surface. The studied organic molecules are very attractive due to their application in various fields, ranging from biosensors to optoelectronic devices. Characterisation of the molecular orientation and molecular packing in systems as biological sensors, electronic and optical organic devices, novel solid lubricants, corrosion inhibitors, as well as hydrophobic and hydrophilic coatings has gained considerable attention. The main investigation technique used to obtain the results presented in this work was infrared spectroscopic ellipsometry. Ellipsometric technique in the visible (VIS) as well as in the infrared (IR) spectral range is a typical method for thickness determination and structural investigation of thin films. The ellipsometric experiment is non-invasive, contact-free, and does not depend on special requirements such as (ultra-high) vacuum. Depending on the photon energy, electronic or vibrational properties are investigated. Since many organic compounds do not exhibit characteristic electronic transitions in the VIS spectral range, a detailed structural characterisation is often not possible from VIS ellipsometric spectra. On the other hand IR ellipsometry is extensively used for this purpose because characteristic IR bands associated with vibrations of specific molecular groups are noticed. The band amplitudes and shapes in the IR ellipsometric spectra are directly related with the directions of transition dipole moments of specific molecular vibrations, thus enabling determination of the molecular orientation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das Ziel der vorliegenden Studie war es, die strukturellen Eigenschaften von organischen Molekülen auf verschiedenen Substraten mit verschiedenen optischen spektroskopischen Methoden zu untersuchen. Die folgenden zwei Systeme wurden untersucht: Selbstorganisierende Monoschichten aus Alkanthiolen auf GaAs und Au, sowie dünne Cytosinschichten auf H-Si(111) Oberflächen. Die untersuchten organischen Moleküle sind aufgrund ihrer Anwendung in verschiedensten Bereichen, von Biosensoren bis hin zu optoelektronischen Bauelementen sehr attraktiv. Die Charakterisierung der molekularen Orientierung und Packung der Moleküle in biologischen Systemen wie Sensoren, elektronischen und optischen organischen Bauelementen, neuartigen Festschmierstoffen, Korrosionsinhibitoren, ebenso wie hydrophobe und hydrophile Beschichtungen hat beträchtliche Aufmerksamkeit gewonnen . Die Hauptuntersuchungstechnik, die verwendet wurde um die Ergebnisse dieser Arbeit zu erzielen war die spektroskopische Infrarotellipsometrie. Ellipsometrie im sichtbaren (VIS) als auch im infraroten (IR) Spektralbereich ist eine typische Methode zur Bestimmung der Dicke und zur strukturellen Untersuchung von dünnen Schichten. Die ellipsometrischen Messungen sind nicht-invasiv, berührungslos und nicht auf spezielle Anforderungen wie (ultra-hohes) Vakuum angewiesen. Abhängig von der Photonenenergie wurden elektronische Eigenschaften oder Schwingungseigenschaften untersucht. Weil viele organische Verbindungen keine charakteristischen elektronischen Übergänge im VIS-Spektralbereich zeigen, ist eine detaillierte strukturelle Charakterisierung durch VIS-ellipsometrische Spektren oft nicht möglich. Aus diesem Grund wird IR-Ellipsometrie hauptsächlich für diesen Zweck verwendet, weil charakteristische IR-Banden auftreten, welche den Vibrationen der spezifischen molekularen Gruppen zugeordnet sind. Die Amplituden und Formen der Absorptionsbanden in den IR-ellipsometrischen Spektren stehen in direktem Zusammenhang mit den Richtungen der Übergangsdipolmomente von spezifischen molekularen Schwingungen, wodurch die Bestimmung der molekularen Orientierung möglich ist .</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-10-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2676</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28037</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28037</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2676/rosu_dana.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
