<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:35Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2023">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2023</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Theory of Optical and Ultrafast Quantum Kinetic Properties of Carbon Nanotubes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Theorie der optischen und ultraschnellen quantenkinetischen Eigenschaften von Kohlenstoffnanoröhren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hirtschulz, Stefan Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work aims to theoretically model and examine the linear and nonlinear optical properties of single-wall carbon nanotubes (SWCNT). Because of their extraordinary mechanical, optical and electrical properties these systems have attracted a lot of scientific interest. In recent years several time-domain spectroscopic studies have been carried out, but a complete (theoretical) understanding is lacking and there are still several controversial results in ultrafast spectroscopy. To build future (opto-)electronic devices, however, a sound and fundamental understanding of ultrafast and non-linear properties of these nanoscale systems is necessary. This is the main focus of this work. The for CNT novel approach combines density matrix theory with the tight-binding method. It allowes to calculate the linear as well as the nonlinear response to optical pulses taking into account many-particle interactions. First of all, the Bloch equations for CNTs on a screened Hartree-Fock level have been derived. The carbon nanotube Bloch equations (CNBEs) contain excitons as elementary optical excitations for weak excitation and verify the importance of Coulomb effects in CNTs. The Hartree-Fock contributions lead to strong band renormalizations and exciton binding energies both in the order of magnitude of the band gap. Second, the optical response of various CNTs of different diameter in the quasi-equilibrium regime was calculated. As a result of the excitation-induced changes of the Hartree-Fock contributions and the plasma screening, strong optical nonlinearities, including gain for high excitation were found. The excitonic resonance experiences a bleaching and red shift. Both effects gradually increase with the strength of the optical excitation. At sufficiently high carrier densities optical Gain is observed. Such gain calculations are a prerequisite for future CNT lasers. The temporal response of CNTs to ultrashort pulses was modeled taking into account the time dependence of the carrier occupations. For non-resonant excitation below the excitonic resonance the total conduction band carrier density adiabatically follows the optical pulse. For these excitation conditions the pump-probe spectra for several CNTs have been obtained. Again, a bleaching and a strong red shift of the resonance (optical Stark effect) is found. To describe ultrafast carrier relaxation a mean-field theory is not sufficient. Hence the screened Hartree-Fock theory was extended to include carrier-carrier scattering. This results in the thermalization of non-equilibrium carrier populations. To accurately describe carrier dynamics on very short timescales below 100 fs a non-Markovian theory is necessary. Therefore, a correlation expansion was performed to account for memory effects that act on short timescales in the femtosecond regime. The intraband thermalization of carriers was described in a one-band and a two-band model. The calculations in the one-band model predict an ultrafast thermalization of the charge carriers on a 100 fs timescale. An effect of the non-Markovian dynamics are the oscillations of the electron plasma on the same timescale. The main characteristics of the relaxation dynamics are independent of chirality of the CNTs, but depend on their diameter (slower relaxation with increasing diameter, as the Coulomb interaction is weaker in larger diameter CNTs). Further influencing factors are the external dielectric screening (slower relaxation with increased screening, as scattering is less effective) and the total carrier density (faster relaxation with increasing excitation, as more scattering partners are present). The two-band calculations support the intraband carrier relaxation on a 100 fs timescale. The advantage of the model is the improved description of the carrier excitation. Furthermore, the excitation induced dephasing of the polarization can be described. On resonant excitation at the exciton the polarization dephases on a picosecond timescale (dephasing is faster for higher carrier densities).</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Doktorarbeit beschäftigt sich mit der theoretischen Modellierung und Untersuchung der linearen und nichtlinearen optischen Eigenschaften von Kohlenstoffnanoröhren (carbon nanotubes, CNT). Während die linearen optischen Eigenschaften dieser Systeme bereits eingehend untersucht wurden, sind die nichtlinearen und ultraschnellen Eigenschaften noch nicht ausreichend verstanden. Hier setzt diese Arbeit an. Ziel ist es, insbesondere nichtlineare optische Phänomene und die ultraschnelle Ladungsträgerdynamik beschreiben zu können. Der in dieser Arbeit verwendete für CNT neuartige Ansatz kombiniert die Dichtematrix-Theorie mit der Tight-Binding-Methode. Vorteil dieses Ansatzes ist die Möglichkeit, sowohl das lineare als auch das nichtlineare Antwortverhalten unter Berücksichtigung von Vielteilcheneffekten für eine Vielzahl von Nanoröhren berechnen zu können. Im ersten Schritt wurden die Bloch-Gleichungen für Kohlenstoffnanoröhren abgeleitet - zunächst auf dem Niveau der abgeschirmten Hartree-Fock Näherung. Bemerkenswerterweise sind sowohl die Bandrenormalisierung als auch die Exziton-Bindungsenergie in der Größenordnung der Bandlücke. Während die Bandrenormalisierung zu einer starken Blauverschiebung der Bandlücke führt, verändert der exzitonische Beitrag die Form der Resonanz (neue Quasi-Teilchen sind Exzitonen). Im zweiten Schritt wurde die optische Antwort des Systems nach Anregung mit einem starken Pump-Puls im Quasigleichgewicht beschrieben. Aufgrund der anregungsbedingten Veränderung der Hartree-Fock Beiträge und der verstärkten Plasma-Abschirmung findet man eine Rotverschiebung und Sättigung der exzitonischen Resonanz. Die Rotverschiebung nimmt mit zunehmendem Durchmesser der Nanoröhren ab. Bei ausreichender Ladungsträgerdichte wurde optischer Gewinn festgestellt. Solche Gewinn-Rechnungen sind die Voraussetzung für die mögliche Realisierung von CNT Lasern. Weiterhin wurde im Rahmen der Hartree-Fock Theorie auch die Ladungsträgerdynamik in die Modellbeschreibung integriert. Für nicht-resonante Anregung unterhalb der exzitonischen Resonanz folgt die Leitungsband-Ladungsträgerdichte dem Pulse adiabatisch. Für diese Anregungsbedingungen wurden auch Pump-Probe Experimente berechnet. Das Zusammenspiel der einzelnen Hartree-Fock Beiträge und der Plasma-Abschirmung führen hierbei zu einer mit der Stärke des Pump-Pulses zunehmenden Rotverschiebung und Sättigung der Exziton-Resonanz (optischer Stark Effekt). Zur Beschreibung nichtlinearer, resonanter Anregungen muss die IntrabandLadungsträgerrelaxation in das Modell integriert werden. Daher wurde im dritten Schritt eine Korrelationsentwicklung der Coulomb-Wechselwirkung durchgeführt. Da im Rahmen dieser Arbeit die Dynamik auf sehr kurzen Zeitskalen beschrieben werden soll, wurde keine Markov-Näherung durchgeführt. Dies erlaubt die Analyse der Ladungsträgerdynamik im Femtosekunden-Bereich auf nicht-markovschem Niveau, d.h. Gedächtniseffekte sind voll berücksichtigt. Die Intrabandthermalisierung wurde sowohl in einem 1-Band- als auch in einem 2-Band-Modell beschrieben. Man findet eine ultraschnelle Relaxation der Ladungsträger im 100 fs Bereich. Die wesentlichen Charakteristika der Relaxationsdynamik sind unabhängig von der Chiralität der CNTs und werden vor allem vom Durchmesser bestimmt (langsamere Relaxation mit zunehmendem Durchmesser). Weitere Einflussgrößen der Relaxationsdynamik sind die externe Abschirmung und die Ladungsträgerdichte. Ein Effekt der nicht-markovschen Dynamik sind die Oszillationen des Elektronenplasmas auf der selben Zeitskala (Periode der Oszillationen nimmt mit dem Durchmesser zu). Die Berechnungen des Zweiband-System bestätigen die Intrabandthermalisierung auf einer 100 fs Zeitskala. Vorteil dieses Ansatzes ist die bessere Modellierung der Anregung von Ladungsträgern. Außerdem kann die anregungsbedingte Dephasierung der Polarisation beschrieben werden, die mit der Stärke der Anregung zunimmt. Bei resonanter Anregung an der exzitonischen Resonanz dephasiert die Polarisation auf einer Picosekunden Zeitskala.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-01-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>text/x-tex</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21292</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21292</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2023/original_Doktor.tex</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2023/hirtschulz_matthias.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
