<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2061">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2061</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Orientational Dynamics and Flow Properties of Polar and Non-Polar Hard-Rod Fluids</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Orientierungsdynamik und Strömungseigenschaften von Flüssigkeiten bestehend aus unpolaren und polaren stäbchenförmigen Teilchen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Heidenreich, Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The dynamical behavior of molecular alignment strongly affects the flow properties of anisotropic fluids. A theoretical description can be made by a nonlinear relaxation equation of the order parameter. The generic model used in this thesis ignores the molecular details and is applicable to fluids that in principle consists of hard rods or hard disks. Representative examples are liquid crystals (low molecular weight liquid crystals as used in liquid-crystal displays), nano-composites, liquid crystal polymers, worm-like micelles, tobacco mosaic virus suspensions and inorganic nano-crystals. In each of these materials, orientational degrees of freedom and the possibility to form different mesoscopic phases (isotropic and nematic) leads to surprising and fascinating flow phenomena. In this thesis the orientational behavior and flow properties of polar and non-polar hard-rod fluids subjected to a flow were investigated. The effect of the presence of walls onto the orientational and flow dynamics was studied. First, the effect of time-dependent derivations of the shear rate on the bulk orientational dynamics was studied. It could be shown that without exceptions the bulk dynamics is very robust against shear rate perturbations. Especially, it was surprising that even chaotic solutions are very sensitive against the change of averaged shear rate but not against perturbations. Second, the flow properties of the inhomogeneous system of non-polar hard-rod fluids in the isotropic phase subjected to weak flows was investigated. The boundary conditions for the alignment flux tensor are derived within the framework of non-equilibrium thermodynamics and lead to an apparent slip in different flow geometries. In a plane Couette flow as well as in a cylindrical Couette flow, the velocity in the bulk extrapolated towards the wall is slower than the wall velocity. The cylindrical Couette flow is influenced by the radial geometry leading to non symmetrical flow profile, but qualitatively the effect of the alignment flow at the boundary give the same apparent slip and coincides in the limit for large radii with the plane Couette flow profile. On the other hand, for Poiseuille flow and the flow down an inclined plane, the flow in the bulk becomes faster caused by boundary effects. Furthermore, an interesting and surprising non-Newtonian flow feedback effect was found. Pulsating jet layers (local spurts of the velocity) arise in the model, where the flow profile across the shear gap is non-monotonic. The jet layer forms precisely at the location and time when neighboring orbits of the orientational distribution transition from tumbling to wagging, i.e., monotonic rotation versus oscillation in the principal director. The orientational distribution forms an oblate defect phase that coincides with the jet layer "pulse", which occurs when nearby tumbling and wagging orbits develop director phase incoherence. When the local axes of orientation regain phase coherence, the flow returns to monotonic shear profiles. For the investigation of polar hard-rod fluids the model equations for two spatially inhomogeneous tensorial order parameters, the dipole vector (modeling average dipole moments) and the alignment tensor are derived within the framework of non-equilibrium thermodynamics. The hydrodynamical properties of polar flexoelectric and non-flexoelectric hard-rod fluids are investigated. For non-flexoelectric polar hard-rod fluids no shear-induced polarization was detectable. However, flexoelectric hard-rods fluids show spontaneous dynamical and steady polarization that generates magnetic fields. The hydrodynamic model for structured suspensions of polar hard-rod fluids predicts spontaneous time-dependent polarization. For special parameters the magnetic fields are of an measurable magnitude. The polarization effect discovered here may have potential for several applications.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das Strömungsverhalten anisotroper Fluide ist durch seine Komplexität ausgezeichnet. Aus der inneren mikroskopischen Orientierungsdynamik resultieren interessante Strömungseffekte. Bekannt ist beispielsweise das Auftreten von Bandstrukturen in Scherströmungen (shear banding), oszillatorisches (tumbling) und chaotisches (rheo-chaos) Strömungsverhalten. Eine einfache theoretische Beschreibung von anisotropen Flüssigkeiten, wie z.B. Flüssigkristalle, flüssigkristalline Polymere, nanokristalline Stäbchen oder Scheiben, kann durch die Betrachtung von polaren und unpolaren harten Stäbchen erfolgen. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurde das Strömungsverhalten und die Orientierungsdynamik von Flüssigkeiten bestehend aus polaren und unpolaren harten Stäbchen untersucht. Die Beschreibung der Orientierung erfolgte durch Mittelung der mikroskopischen Orientierungen über mesoskopische Bereiche. Gemittelte molekulare Orientierungen sind durch einen symmetrisch spurlosen Carthesischen Tensor der Stufe zwei (Ausrichtungstensor) und die der Dipolmomente durch einen Vektor (Dipolvektor) charakterisiert. Die raum-zeitliche Dynamik des Ausrichtungstensors und des Dipolvektors sind durch Relaxationsgleichungen, die an den Strömungsgradienten angekoppelt sind, gegeben. Die Orientierungen bzw. gemittelten Dipolmomente beeinflussen über den Reibungsdruck des Fluids und über Randbedingungen die Strömungseigenschaften erheblich. In dieser Arbeit konnte durch numerische und analytische Untersuchungen zum Teil gezeigt werden, wie das Stömungsverhalten mit der Orientierungsdynamik zusammenhängt. Insbesondere zeigt sich für den Bereich der Mikrofluidik, dass die raum-zeitliche Orientierungsstruktur durch Randbedingungen gegeben ist. Hierfür wurde eine Flüssigkeit zwischen zwei Platten einer einfachen Scherströmung ausgesetzt. Je nach der Bedingung des Orientierungsstroms am Rand kommt es beispielsweise zu einem Geschwindigkeitsschlupf. Das Auftreten eines scheinbaren Schlupfes und deren Auswrikungen auf die Scherviskosität wurde für verschiedene Geometrien untersucht. Ein weiterer bemerkenswerter Effekt resultiert aus der nicht-Newtonschen Strömungsrückkopplung, der Orientierunsdynamik und den Randbedingungen. Hierbei bilden sich in der Flüssigkeit Orientierungsdefekte (planar biaxiale Ausrichtungen) die widerum zu einen pulsierenden lokalen hervorschnellen der Strömungsgeschwindigkeit führen. Polare harte Stäbchen zeigen ein sehr komplexes raum-zeitliches Orientierungsverhalten. Für flexoelektrische Flüssigkeiten (aus Deformationen des Ausrichtungstensorfeldes resultiert eine Polarisation) konnte eine scherströmungsinduzierte spontane dynamische Polarisation nachgewiesen werden. Das Auftreten von Magnetfeldern, deren Meßmöglichkeiten und mögliche Anwendungen des Effekts wurden diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-02-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>text/x-tex</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2061</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21467</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21467</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2061/original_thesisfinal_dez.tex</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2061/heidenreich_sebastian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
