<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3051">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3051</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Microscopic properties of grain boundaries in Cu(In,Ga)Se2 and CuInS2 thin-film solar cells studied by transmission electron microscopy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Mikroskopische Eigenschaften von Korngrenzen in Cu(In,Ga)Se2 und CuInS2 Dünnschichtsolarzellen untersucht mittels Transmissionselektronenmikroskopie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmidt, Sebastian Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Polycrystalline Cu(In,Ga)Se2 and Cu(In,Ga)S2 thin films are employed as absorber layers in highly efficient thin-film solar cells. The impact of grain boundaries on the electronic properties of these thin films and consequently on the conversion efficiency of the corresponding solar cells is not sufficiently understood. In the present work, methods in transmission electron microscopy were employed in order to study the microscopic properties of grain boundaries in Cu(In,Ga)(Se,S)2 layers with varying integral compositions. Electron holography measurements show that the electrostatic potential caused by atomic nuclei and electrons, averaged parallel to the plane of the grain boundary, is lower in an about 1 nm wide region at grain boundaries by up to 3V. The depths of these potential wells varies between individual grain boundaries, even within the same Cu(In,Ga)(Se,S)2 layer, and with the integral composition of the investigated layer. The potential well depths increase from Sigma 3 twin boundaries to Sigma 9 twin boundaries and further to grain boundaries with even lower symmetry. A bound excess charge at grain boundaries and a resulting redistribution of free charge carriers in the vicinity is ruled out as sole origin of the potential wells. Based on this result, it is concluded that major contributions to the measured potential wells may arise from a local change in the crystal structure with respect to the atomic density and the composition. The individual contributions are discussed in the present work. By use of electron energy-loss spectroscopy, the presence of the potential wells at grain boundaries is correlated with the presence of a local change in composition. The changes in composition are found to depend strongly on the integral composition of the investigated layers. In the case of Cu(In,Ga)Se2 thin films with a composition of [Cu]/([In] + [Ga]) = 0.83, a Cu deficiency and an In enrichment is found at grain boundaries, while the opposite effect is found in the case of thin films exhibiting [Cu]/([In] + [Ga]) = 0.43. The local changes in the atomic Cu and In concentrations always show an anticorrelated behavior. Based on these results, it is estimated that a local change in composition contributes significantly to the lowering of the electrostatic potential at grain boundaries. A model for the band diagram at grain boundaries within Cu(In,Ga)Se2 is proposed. This model comprises a local offset of the valence-band maximum towards lower energies in an about 1 − 2 nm wide region at the grain boundary in Cu(In,Ga)Se2 thin films with a composition of [Cu]/([In] + [Ga]) = 0.83. The magnitude of the offset decreases with increasing grain boundary symmetry. For grain boundaries in Cu(In,Ga)Se2 thin films with a composition of [Cu]/([In] + [Ga]) = 0.43, an offset of the valence-band maximum towards higher energies is proposed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Polykristalline Cu(In,Ga)Se2- und Cu(In,Ga)S2-Dünnschichten werden als Absorbermaterial in hocheffizienten Dünnschichtsolarzellen eingesetzt. Die Auswirkungen von Korngrenzen auf die elektronischen Eigenschaften dieser Dünnschichten und damit auf die Effizienz der entsprechenden Solarzellen sind nicht ausreichend verstanden. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurden Methoden der Transmissionselektronenmikroskopie genutzt, um die mikroskopischen Eigenschaften von Korngrenzen in polykristallinen Cu(In,Ga)(Se,S)2 Schichten zu untersuchen. Dazu wurde die integrale Zusammensetzung der Dünnschichten variiert. Mittels Elektronenholographie wurde gemessen, dass das parallel zur Korngrenze gemittelte elektrostatische Potential, welches sowohl durch Atomkerne als auch durch Elektronen verursacht wird, in einem etwa 1 nm breiten Bereich um die Korngrenze um bis zu 3V verringert ist. Die Tiefe dieser Potentialtöpfe unterscheidet sich von Korngrenze zu Korngrenze, sogar innerhalb derselben Cu(In,Ga)(Se,S)2 Schicht, und ändert sich mit der integralen Zusammensetzung der Dünnschichten. Des Weiteren nimmt die Tiefe der Potentialtöpfe mit sinkender Symmetrie der Korngrenzen von Sigma 3 Zwillings-, über Sigma 9 Zwillingskorngrenzen bis hin zu Korngrenzen mit noch niedrigerer Symmetrie zu. Eine gebundene Überschussladung an Korngrenzen und eine daraus resultierende Umverteilung von freien Ladungsträgern in der Umgebung, kann als alleinige Ursache der Potentialtöpfe ausgeschlossen werden. Deshalb kommen als Hauptursachen für die Potentialtöpfe eine lokale Änderung der Kristallstruktur bezüglich der Dichte und der Zusammensetzung in Frage. Die entsprechenden Beiträge werden in der vorliegenden Arbeit diskutiert. Mit Hilfe von Elektronenenergieverlustspektroskopie wird ein Zusammenhang zwischen dem Auftreten der Potentialtöpfe und einer lokalen Änderung der Zusammensetzung an Korngrenzen aufgezeigt. Die gemessenen Zusammensetzungsänderungen hängen dabei stark von der integralen Zusammensetzung der Dünnschichten ab. In Cu(In,Ga)Se2 Schichten mit [Cu]/([In] + [Ga]) = 0.83 wurde eine verringerte Cu- und eine erhöhte In-Konzentration an Korngrenzen gemessen, während in Schichten mit [Cu]/([In] + [Ga]) = 0.43 der umgekehrte Effekt beobachtet wird. Die gemessenen Unterschiede in den lokalen Cu- und In-Konzentrationen verhalten sich dabei immer entgegengesetzt. Basierend auf diesen Ergebnissen wird gezeigt, dass die gemessene Zusammensetzungsänderung einen großen Beitrag zu der Verringerung des elektrostatischen Potentials an Korngrenzen darstellen kann. Ein Modell für das Banddiagramm an Korngrenzen in Cu(In,Ga)Se2-Dünnschichten wird vorgestellt. Es basiert auf einer Verschiebung des Valenzbands zu niedrigeren Energien in einem etwa 1 nm breiten Bereich um die Korngrenze im Fall von Schichten mit einem Cu-Gehalt von [Cu]/([In] + [Ga]) = 0.83, wobei das Ausmaß der Verschiebung mit zunehmender Symmetrie der Korngrenzen kleiner wird. Im Fall von Korngrenzen in Schichten mit [Cu]/([In] + [Ga]) = 0.43 wird eine Verschiebung des Valenzbands zu höheren Energien vorgeschlagen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-10-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3051</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3051/schmidt_sebastian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
