<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:48:32Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:960">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:960</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Formation and disintegration of small-scale concentration gradients of trace metals on aggregate scale</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Safronov, Grigory</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Luftbürtige Schwermetalle, die sich auf Aggregatoberflächen ablagern, bilden kleinräumige Konzentrationsgradienten aus. Cadmium, Cu, Zn und Pb-Konzentrationen wurden im äußeren und inneren von Aggregaten aus archivierten (1910-1954) und neu gesammelten Bodenproben bestimmt. Die Schwermetallgehalte im inneren der Aggregate und die Schwermetallanreicherung auf der Aggregatschale waren in den neuen Bodenproben höher als in den archivierten. Geprüft wurde die Umverteilung der Schwermetalle innerhalb der Aggregate durch Diffusion. Die Diffusion von Zn, Cd, Ba and Cs wurde in gepackten, wassergesättigten Säulen untersucht. Es wurden 4 verschiedene Böden verwendet: (Probe A) aus dem Al Horizont und (Probe B) Bt Horizont eines Luvisols, (Probe Ch) aus dem Ah Horizont einer Schwarzerde und (Probe C) aus Aggregatüberzügen des Bt Horizont des Luvisols. Die vier Bodenproben wurden mit destilliertem Wasser gesättigt und in Säulen mit 1,8 cm Durchmesser und 1 cm Länge gepackt und separat in 45 ml Lösung getaucht (C(Zn)=10 mg l-1, C(Cd) =1 mg l-1, C(Ba) =10 mg l-1 und C(Cs) =40 mg l-1). Die Kationen der Lösung wurden mit den korrespondierenden radioaktiven Isotopen 65Zn, 109Cd, 133Ba und 137Cs markiert. Nach 4-40 Tagen Exposition wurden die Säulen entnommen und in 0,1 mm Scheiben geschnitten um die Diffusionsprofile mittels Gamma-Spektroskopie zu bestimmen. Gleichartige Säulen wurden für 18 - 22 Stunden in 600 ml 3,510-3 M NaCl (markiert mit 36Cl) getaucht. Die Säulen wurden nach der Entnahme umgehen in 0.4 mm dicke Scheiben geschnitten. Die lineare Diffusionsgleichung wurde an die Konzentrationsprofile angepasst, um die Tortuosität der Säulen zu bestimmen. Der korrespondierende Impedanzfaktor wurde für die Proben A und B mit 0.57, für die Probe Ch mit 0,54 und für die Probe C mit 0,52 ermittelt. Die Impedanzfaktoren als auch die Wassergehalte und die Diffusionskoeffizienten der Schwermetalle in Wasser wurden in ein Modell eingearbeitet. Aus den Koeffizienten der angepassten Adsorptionsisothermen (linear, Freundlich und Langmuir) wurde die reziproke Pufferung abgeleitet, die den experimentell ermittelten Diffusionskurven am besten entspricht. Dabei ließen sich die Konzentrationsprofile von Ca, Zn und Ba gut durch Freundlich-Isothermen beschreiben (Ausnahme: Probe A). Die Diffusionsprofile von Ba wurden am besten durch Langmuir-Isothermen widergegeben (Ausnahme: Probe C). Für Cd korrelierte der Verteilungskoeffizient kd der linearen Isotherme gut mit dem Corg Gehalt der Proben, während die Koeffizienten für Zn, Ba und Cs mit der KAK korrelierten. Das Modell war gut geeignet, Diffusionsprozesse im Boden zu beschreiben. Der Abbau der kleinräumigen Schwermetallkonzentrationsgradienten auf Aggregatebene durch Diffusionsprozesse ist unwahrscheinlich.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Airborne heavy metals are deposited on aggregate surfaces, forming small-scale concentration gradients. Cadmium, Cu, Zn and Pb concentrations were measured in inner and outer aggregate parts in archived soil samples from 1910-1954 and in recently collected soil samples from the same locations. Concentration gradients were higher in recent soil samples, and concentrations of all heavy metals inside aggregates in recent soils were higher than in archived ones. A hypothesis of heavy metal redistribution inside aggregates due to diffusion process has been examined. Diffusion of Zn, Cd, Ba and Cs cations in repacked soil samples under water-saturated conditions has been studied. Four soil samples from Al (sample A) and Bt (sample B) horizons of a luvisol, Ah horizon of a chernozem (sample (Ch), and aggregate coatings from Bt horizon of the luvisol (sample C) were saturated with distilled water, packed into columns of 1.8 cm in diameter and 1 cm long, and exposed separately to 45 ml of a solution with one of the studied cations (C(Zn)=10 mg l-1, C(Cd)=1 mg l-1, C(Ba)=10 mg l-1 and C(Cs)=40 mg l-1). The cations were labeled with the corresponding radioactive isotopes 65Zn, 109Cd, 133Ba and 137Cs. After the exposition time (4 to 40 days) the columns were removed from solution and sliced into 0.1 mm slices. Concentrations of the cations in the slices were found by means of gamma-spectroscopy, and the diffusion profiles of the cations were obtained. The same repacked and water-saturated soil samples were exposed to 600 ml of 3.510-3 M NaCl solution labeled with 36Cl isotope from 18 to 22 hours. The columns were immediately cut into approximately 0.4 mm slices. Linear diffusion equation of non-adsorbing substance was fitted to the diffusion profiles in order to find the tortuousity of the soil. The corresponding parameter - impedance factor was found 0.57 for samples A and B, 0.54 for sample Ch, and 0.52 for sample C. The factor values, as well as soil water content and diffusion coefficients of the cations in water were used in mathematical model of adsorption hindered diffusion of cations. The coefficients of linear, Langmuir and Freundlich adsorption isotherms were fit to obtain such reciprocal buffer power, at which the modeled diffusion curves are most close to the experiment. The model based on Freundlich adsorption isotherm described the profiles of Cd, Zn and Cs (except sample A) the best. The diffusion profiles of Ba (except sample C) were best approximated with the model based on Langmuir adsorption isotherm. Distribution coefficient Kd from linear adsorption isotherm for Cd correlated well with Corg, whereas Kd for Zn, Ba and Cs correlated well with soil CEC. The model was found suitable for describing cation diffusion in soils. Disintegration of small-scale gradients of heavy metals on aggregate scale because of diffusion process is unlikely.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2005-03-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/960</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-9534</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-9534</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/960/safronov_grigory.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
