<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:58Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2519">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2519</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Vorkommen und Bewertung von Pharmakarückständen im Berliner Gewässerkreislauf</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Occurrence and assessment of pharmaceutical residues in the Berlin water cycle </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Adam, Marc Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurde das Vorkommen von 37 Pharmakarückständen über einen Zeitraum von 19 Monaten an sieben exponierten Messstellen des Berliner Oberflächengewässersystems mittels zweier Multimethoden bestimmt. Ergänzend wurde ein dreimonatiges Sondermessprogramm zur Bestimmung von 18 Antibiotikarückständen durchgeführt. Anhand der gemessenen Konzentrationen und der messstellenspezifischen Durchflussraten wurden die Tages- bzw. Jahresfrachten der einzelnen Pharmaka und deren Abflüsse aus dem Berliner Stadtgebiet berechnet. Diese liegen im Bereich von 7 kg/Jahr (Ibuprofen) bis 383 kg/Jahr (Carbamazepin). Zur Abschätzung der Umweltrelevanz, der in den Berliner Oberflächengewässern gemessenen Arzneistoffe, wurde eine Umweltrisikobewertung von acht Pharmaka- und sechs Antibiotikarückständen nach der EMEA Richtlinie „Guideline on the Environmental Risk Assessment of Medicinal Products for Human Use“ [EMEA, 2006] erstellt. Dazu wurden für vier Messstellen durch Bestimmung der durchschnittlichen PEC-Werte Expositionsabschätzungen ermittelt. Anschließend erfolgte ein Vergleich mit den Daten zur stoffspezifischen umwelttoxikologischen Wirkung (PNEC-Daten) zur Bestimmung eines potentiellen Umweltrisikos ausgehend von den betrachteten Arzneimitteln für die jeweilige Messstelle. Aufgrund der unterschiedlichen Einleitungssituation der KA Ruhleben wurde zusätzlich eine saisonal abhängige Umweltrisikobewertung (Sommer/Winter) durchgeführt.Insgesamt konnte für drei Arzneimittel Diclofenac, Clarithromycin und Sulfamethoxazol in jeder der vier betrachteten Messstellen (325, 345, 355 und 430) unabhängig der saisonalen Bedingungen ein potentielles Umweltrisiko ermittelt werden. Für die Arzneimittel Carbamazepin und Erythromycin gelang die Ermittlung eines Umweltrisikos für die Messstellen 355 und 430, wobei sich für Carbamazepin der Einfluss der saisonalen Bedingungen bemerkbar machte. Neben der PEC-Berechnung wurden die realen Umweltkonzentrationen zum Vergleich und zur Verifizierung der theoretischen PEC-Werte einer MEC/PNEC-Betrachtung unterzogen.Für die meisten betrachteten Arzneimittel ergaben sich dabei gute Übereinstimmungen. Die MEC/PNEC-Betrachtungen für Carbamazepin ergaben hingegen an jeder Messstelle ein Unterschreiten der Risikoschwelle von 1. Des Weiteren wurde ein potentielles Umweltrisiko ausgehend vom Sulfamethoxazol nur noch in den Messstellen 355 und 430 statt in allen vier Messstellen im Vergleich zur PEC/PNEC-Betrachtung ermittelt. Für den Wirkstoff Propyphenazon, der nach der PEC/PNEC-Betrachtung kein Anzeichen für ein Umweltrisiko aufwies, wurde nach MEC/PNEC-Betrachtung an den Messstellen 325 und 355 die Risikoschwelle von 1 nur knapp unterschritten, bei der Messstelle 430 sogar überschritten und somit ein potentielles Umweltrisiko aufgezeigt.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The occurrence of 37 pharmaceutical residues in the surface water of Berlin, Germany, was examined over a time period of 19 months. The investigations were carried out at seven sampling locations selected to comprehend the loads of these compounds mainly entering the environment by discharges of municipal sewage. Analysis of the drug residues was conducted by solid-phase extraction and capillary gas chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry applying two multi-methods. In addition, a 3-month special measuring program was carried out at the same sites to analyse 18 antibiotic residues by high-performance liquid chromato¬graphy coupled to tandem mass spectrometry. The annual loads of each pharmaceutical residue and its runoff from the Berlin municipal area were calculated based upon their surface water concentrations at the specific sampling sites and the related flow rates. The individual loads were within the range of 7 kg/a for ibuprofen and up to 383 kg/a for carbamazepine. In order to evaluate their environmental relevance, an environmental risk assessment (ERA) was conducted for the 14 pharmaceutical residues including six antibiotics that were detected in the Berlin surface water system. ERA was conducted according to the "Guideline on the Environmental Risk Assessment of Medicinal Products for Human Use" [EMEA, 2006]. Therefore, the exposition by pharmaceutical residues was determined at four most-relevant sampling sites calculating the average values for the predicted environmental concentrations (PECs). These values were then compared with the corresponding predicted no effect levels (PNEC) to determine potential environmental risks caused by the observed pharmaceutical substances at the respective sampling site. In addition, a season-dependent environmental risk assessment (summer/winter) was carried out taking into account differences in the distribution of sewage discharges within the Berlin water cycle. In conclusion, a potential environmental risk was determined for three pharmaceutical substances (diclofenac, clarithromycin and sulfamethoxazole) at each of the four observed sampling sites (325, 345, 355 and 430). These observations were independent from seasonal conditions or changes. The pharmaceutical substances carbamazepine and erythromycin pose an environmental risk at the sampling sites 355 and 430. Besides the PEC to PNEC calculation an additional calculation based on the real measured environmental concentrations (MECs) was conducted to compare and to verify the theoretical assumptions. A good correlation for almost all observed pharmaceutical substances was seen. However, the ratio MEC/PNEC for carbamazepine, determined at each sampling location, was always below the risk threshold value of 1. In addition, a potential environmental risk by sulfamethoxazole was only determined at sampling sites 355 and 430 which was different compared to the PEC/PNEC-calculations indicating a risk at all four sampling sites under investigation. A potential environmental risk by propyphenazone was not indicated on basis of the PEC/PNEC-calculations, whereas the MEC/PNEC-ratio exceeded the risk threshold of 1 at sampling site 430 indicating a potential environmental risk caused by propyphenazone residues.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-05-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2519</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26414</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26414</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2519/adam_marc.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
