<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:05Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2783">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2783</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Purification, crystallization and structural analysis of the monomeric Photosystem II core complex from Thermosynechococcus elongatus</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Aufreinigung, Kristallisation und Strukturanalyse des monomeren Photosystem II core Komplexes aus Thermosynechococcus elongatus</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Broser, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The membrane-embedded Photosystem II core complex (PSIIcc) is one of the key enzymes in oxygenic photosynthesis and uses light energy to oxidize water. To understand the functional mode of this enzyme knowledge of its molecular structure is necessary. So far, the information about the spatial structure of PSIIcc obtained from X-ray crystallography has been restricted to the homodimeric form of the PSIIcc from thermophilic cyanobacteria. This work describes the first crystallization and structural analysis of the monomeric PSIIcc isolated from the thermophilic cyanobacteria Thermosynechococcus elongatus. Based on an improved preparation protocol, it was possible to obtain a highly pure fraction of PSIIcc monomer with high oxygen evolution activity. The PSIIcc monomer consists of all 20 protein subunits known to be present in the complete functional complex. Dynamic light scattering on this PSIIcc monomer fraction revealed the homogeneity needed for protein crystallization. First protein crystals could be obtained, which belong to the space group C2221 and contain one monomer per asymmetric unit. The X-ray diffraction data derived from these crystals yielded a first structural model of the PSIIcc monomer at a resolution of 3.6 Å. This model includes the assignment of 19 protein subunits, 35 chlorophylls, two pheophytins, two heme groups, the non-heme iron, eleven carotenoids, the primary plastoquinone QA, 22 lipids and the Mn4Ca cluster of the water-oxidizing complex (WOC). As expected, the overall structure of the PSIIcc monomer is essentially identical to its dimeric counterpart. Nevertheless, this structure provides a new basis for the discussion of the role of lipids and protein subunits in the oligomerization of PSIIcc and the assembly/disassembly during the repair cycle of photodamaged subunit D1. For the first time, a significantly different packing of PSIIcc could be obtained that features the following advantages: (I) lower anisotropy of the X-ray diffraction (dependence of resolution on crystal orientation), (II) a reduced number of orientations of PSIIcc within the unit cell and (III) the orientation of the membrane normal perpendicular to one of the crystallographic axes. Point (I) is crucial for further improving the quality of X-ray diffraction data, whereas (II) and (III) make this crystal form more suitable for orientation-dependent spectroscopy. This opens novel possibilities to elucidate the structure and function of the WOC. Preliminary measurements of polarized X-ray absorption spectroscopy confirmed the applicability of this method on the new crystal form. The acceptor side of PSIIcc is the target for many commercially used herbicides, but direct information about herbicide interactions with PSIIcc is lacking. In this work, the first structural model of a triazine-type herbicide bound to PSIIcc at a resolution of 3.4 Å could be obtained by crystallizing PSIIcc dimer in the presence of terbutryn. The structure reveals a similar binding mode of triazines to the QB site of PSIIcc to that observed for the reaction center of purple bacteria. The analysis of terbutryn-binding to PSIIcc using isothermal titration calorimetry and fluorescence spectroscopy suggests that herbicide binding is affected by the functional state of the acceptor side. Furthermore, initial structural data on the binding of a urea-type herbicide (chlorbromuron) to PSIIcc dimer at 3.7 Å resolution suggests two different binding conformations of this herbicide at the QB site. On the donor side, one halide binding site could be located 6.4 Å away from the Mn4Ca cluster by using crystals of PSIIcc dimer, in which the naturally occurring chloride was functionally replaced by bromide. This result confirmed the hypothesis that bromide (and concomitantly chloride) is not a direct ligand of the Mn4Ca cluster, despite its role in the proper functioning of water oxidation. The stoichiometry of one bromide per reaction center could be further supported by X-ray spectroscopy. Due to the location of the halide at the entrance of two putative proton channels, a functional role in proton transfer during the catalytic cycle is likely.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der in der Thylakoidmembran vorkommene Photosystem II-core Komplex (PSIIcc) ist eines der Schlüsselenzyme der oxygenen Photosynthese. Er katalysiert die lichtinduzierte Oxidation von Wasser. Bislang waren die zur Aufklärung der Funktionsweise notwendigen und mittels Röngtenkristallographie gewonnenen Strukturinformationen auf die Verwendung der homodimeren Form des PSIIcc beschränkt. In dieser Arbeit wird erstmalig die Kristallisation und Strukturanalyse des monomeren PSIIcc aus dem thermophilen Cyanobaterium Thermosynechococcus elongatus beschrieben. Aufgrund eines verbesserten Präparations-Protokolls konnten hochreine, monomere PSIIcc erhalten werden, die eine hohe Sauerstoffentwicklungsaktivität aufweisen. Das PSIIcc Monomer weist alle 20 Protein-Untereinheiten auf, die in vollständigen, funktionellen Komplexen vorkommen. Mittels dynamischer Lichtstreuung konnte die Homogenität der PSIIcc Monomer Fraktion nachgewiesen werden. Erste Proteinkristalle konnten gezüchtet werden, die zur orthorhombischen Raumgruppe C2221 gehören und ein PSIIcc Monomer in der asymmetrischen Einheit aufweisen. Die Analyse der Röntgen-Diffraktionsdaten erlaubte es, ein erstes Strukturmodell des PSIIcc Monomers bei einer Auflösung von 3.6 Å zu erstellen. Das Modell beinhaltet 19 Protein-Untereinheiten, 35 Chlorophyll a- und zwei Pheophytin a-Moleküle, zwei Häm-Gruppen, das Nicht-Häm Eisen, elf Karotinoide, das primäre Plastochinon QA, 22 Lipide und den Mn4Ca Cluster des Wasser-oxidierenden Komplexes (WOC). Erwartungsgemäß ist die Struktur des PSIIcc Monomers im Wesentlichen identisch mit der des dimeren Komplexes. Dennoch bilden die Strukturdaten eine neue Grundlage, um die Rolle der Lipide und Protein-Untereinheiten im Zusammenhang mit der Oligomerisierung des PSIIcc und dem Austausch des D1-Proteins zu diskutieren. Erstmalig konnte eine deutlich andere Kristall-Packung des PSIIcc erhalten werden, die folgende Vorzüge aufweist: (I) geringere Anisotropie der Röntgen-Diffraktion (Abhängig-keit der Auflösung von der Kristallorientierung), (II) die Reduzierung der Orientierungen des PSIIcc innerhalb der Einheitszelle und (III) die senkrechte Orientierung der Membran-Normalen zu einer Kristallachse. Punkt (I) ist ein Vorteil für die Verbesserung der Röntgen-Diffraktionsdaten, während (II) und (III) die Eignung von orientierungsanhängigen, spektro-skopischen Methoden erhöht. Letzteres eröffnet neue Möglichkeiten die Struktur und Funktionsweise des WOC aufzuklären. Erste Messungen bestätigen die Anwendbarkeit von polarisierter Röntgenabsorptions-Spektroskopie auf diese neue Kristallform. Die Akzeptorseite des PSIIcc ist das Wirkungsziel vieler kommerziell genutzter Herbizide, jedoch fehlen bislang direkte Informationen über die Interaktion von Herbiziden mit PSIIcc. In dieser Arbeit konnte, mittels Kristallen des dimeren PSIIcc, ein erstes Struktur-modell von an PSIIcc gebundenen Terbutryn bei einer Auflösung von 3.4 Å erhalten werden. Dieses Modell belegt, dass Triazin-Derivate in gleicher Art an den PSIIcc binden, wie an das Reaktionszentrum aus Purpurbakterien. Bindungsstudien zeigen eine Abhängigkeit der Terbutryn-Bindung vom funktionellen Zustand der Akzeptorseite des PSIIcc. Des Weiteren weisen erste Strukturdaten eines Herbizids der Harnstoff-Klasse (Chlorbromuron) bei 3.7 Å Auflösung, auf zwei unterschiedliche Bindungskonformationen dieses Herbizids hin. An der Donorseite konnte eine Halogenid-Bindungsstelle im Abstand von 6.4 Å zum Mn4Ca Cluster lokalisiert werden. Dazu wurden Kristalle des dimeren PSIIcc verwendet, bei denen das natürlich vorkommende Chlorid durch Bromid funktionell ersetzt wurde. Diese Ergebnisse bestätigen, dass Bromid (und somit auch Chlorid) kein direkter Ligand des Mn4Ca Clusters ist, trotz der funktionellen Rolle bei der Wasser-Oxidation. Röngtenspektroskopische Untersuchungen weisen auf eine Stöchiometrie von einem Bromid pro Mn4Ca Cluster hin. Aufgrund der Bromid-Position am Eingang zweier vermeintlicher Protonenkanäle ist eine Funktion im Zusammenhang mit dem Proton-Transfer naheliegend.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-02-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2783</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29235</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29235</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2783/broser_matthias.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
