<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:34Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1562">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1562</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Molekularbiologische und biochemische Untersuchungen zum Typ IV Sekretion-ähnlichen System (T4SLS) des konjugativen Antibiotikaresistenzplasmids pIP501 in Enterococcus faecalis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Molecular and biochemical studies of the type IV secretion-like system (T4SLS) encoded by the conjugative antibiotic resistance plasmid pIP501 in Enterococcus faecalis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Abajy, Mohammad Yaser</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In den letzten Jahren hat die Resistenz von Bakterien gegenüber Antibiotika so massiv zugenommen, dass die Bakterien immer lebensgefährlicher geworden sind. Der konjugative Plasmidtransfer stellt einen der wichtigsten Mechanismen für die Ausbreitung der Antibiotikaresistenzen in den Bakterien dar. Während die Konjugation in Gram-negativen (G−) Bakterien sehr intensiv untersucht worden ist, weiss man sehr wenig über die Mechanismen des konjugativen Plasmidtransfers in Gram-positiven (G+) Bakterien. Die Konjugation in G+ Bakterien wurde in dieser Arbeit am Beispiel des Multiresistenzplasmids pIP501 untersucht. pIP501 kodiert für drei Proteine ORF5, ORF7 und ORF10, die sehr große Ähnlichkeit mit Typ IV Sekretionskomponenten aus dem G− Bakterium Agrobacterium tumefaciens zeigen. In dieser Arbeit wurden die Protein-Protein Wechselwirkungen der pIP501-Transferproteine (Tra) in vivo und in vitro untersucht. Für die in vivo Studien wurden die 15 tra-Gene der pIP501-Transferregion in die Yeast Two-Hybrid (Y-2H) Plasmide pBTM117c und pGAD426 kloniert und in Saccharomyces cerevisiae L40ccU Hefezellen transformiert. Die Protein-Protein Wechselwirkungen wurden mit dem Y-2H System untersucht. Die Y-2H Studie ergab 18 Protein-Protein Wechselwirkungen. Die Intensitäten der in vivo Interaktionen wurden mit einem quantitativen β-Galaktosidase Assay gemessen. Für die in vitro Protein-Protein Wechselwirkungsstudien wurden die 15 tra-Gene in die Expressionsplasmide pQTEV, pGEX-6P-2 oder pMAL-c2x kloniert. Die Tra Proteine wurden als His-, GST- oder MBP-Fusionsproteine in E. coli Zellen exprimiert und solubilisiert. Protein-Protein Bindungsstudien zwischen den solubilisierten Proteinen wurden durchgeführt und die entsprechenden Proteinkomplexe wurden mittels Affinitätschromatographie isoliert und immunologisch mit Western Blot nachgewiesen. Anhand der in vivo und in vitro Ergebnisse und der Computervorhersagen für die Lokalisierung der Tra Proteine wurde eine Protein-Protein Interaktionskarte für die pIP501 Transferproteine erstellt. Für die Proteine ORF5 und ORF10 wurden ATP-Bindung-/Hydrolyse Studien durchgeführt. ORF5 und ORF10 konnten ATP in vitro binden und hydrolysieren. Mittels einer modifizierten Zymogramm Methode wurde lytische Transglykosylase Aktivität für ORF7 und die ORF7 Domänen SLT und CHAP nachgewiesen. Zusätzlich zum Hauptthema „Konjugativer Transfer in G+ Bakterien“ wurden Protein-Protein Wechselwirkungen zwischen ausgewählten Virulenzproteinen des pathogenen Bakteriums Enterococcus faecalis V583 und humanen Proteinen mittels eines automatisierten Yeast-Two-Hybrid Systems untersucht. Es konnten keine Interaktionen zwischen den Virulenzproteinen und den humanen Proteinen festgestellt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In the last decades the resistance of pathogenic bacteria towards antibiotics increased so massively, that they became even more life-threatening and more difficult to treat with antibacterial agents. The conjugative plasmid transfer represents one of the most important mechanisms for the spread of antibiotic resistance among bacteria. While the conjugative transfer in gram-negative (G−) bacteria has been examined very intensively, we know very little about the mechanisms of the conjugative plasmid transfer in gram-positive (G+) bacteria. Conjugative transfer in G+ bacteria was studied in this work with the resistance plasmid pIP501. At the beginning of this work it was known, that pIP501 encodes three gene products ORF5, ORF7 and ORF10, which show high similarities with components from the type IV secretion system of the G− bacterium A. tumefaciens. In this work the protein-protein interactions of the pIP501 transfer proteins (Tra) were tested with in vivo and in vitro methods. For the in vivo studies the 15 tra-genes were cloned in the yeast two-hybrid (Y-2H) plasmids pBTM117c and pGAD426. Saccharomyces cerevisiae L40ccU cells were then transformed with the recombinant plasmids. The Y-2H study showed 18 protein-protein interactions between the pIP501-encoded Tra proteins. The intensities of the interactions were measured with a quantitative β-galactosidase assay. For the in vitro studies the 15 tra-genes were cloned in the expression plasmids, pQTEV, pGEX-6P-2 or pMAL-c2x. The Tra proteins required for the in vitro studies were expressed and solubilized in E. coli as 7xHis-, GST- or MBP-fusions. Protein-protein binding between the soluble Tra proteins was then tested by pull-down assays. The corresponding protein complexes were isolated by means of affinity chromatography and detected immunologically by Western blot. On the basis of the in vivo and in vitro studies and computer-assisted prediction of the cellular location of the Tra proteins, a model for the first type IV secretion-like system encoded by a conjugative plasmid from G+ bacteria was postulated. For the proteins ORF5 and ORF10 ATP-binding/hydrolysis studies were performed. ORF5 and ORF10 could bind and hydrolyse ATP in vitro. By means of a modified zymogramm method lytic transglycosylase activity was proved for ORF7 and its domains SLT and CHAP. In addition to the main topic „Conjugative plasmid transfer in G+ bacteria“, protein-protein interactions between selected virulence proteins from the G+ pathogen E. faecalis V583 and human proteins were tested with an automated Y-2H system. No interactions between the virulence proteins and the human proteins could be determined.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-07-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1562</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16204</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16204</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1562/original_Abajy_Dissertation.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1562/abajy_mohammad.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
