<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:02Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2973">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2973</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Struktur-Funktions-Analysen regulatorischer C-terminaler Domänen und Charakterisierung der Bindungsstelle des Antikonvulsivums Retigabin von spannungsgesteuerten K+-Kanälen der Kv7-Familie</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Structure-function-analysis of C-terminal regulatory domains and characterization of the binding site of the anticonvulsant retigabine of voltage-gated K+-channels of the Kv7 family </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Geißendörfer, Jan Kaspar</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die auf der Erde vorkommenden Organismen weisen ein äußerst breites Spektrum an Transmembranproteinen auf. Dennoch finden sich zwischen den verschiedensten Arten zahlreiche Homologien, die auf eine gemeinsame evolutive Vergangenheit hinweisen. So handelt es sich beispielsweise bei den membranständigen Kaliumkanälen um Proteine, die in nahezu allen Organismen nachweisbar sind. Diese Ionenkanäle ermöglichen den selektiven Transport von positiv geladenen Kaliumionen durch die ansonsten für geladene Teilchen impermeable Zellmembran. Die vorliegende Dissertation beschäftigt sich mit einer Gruppe dieser großen K+-Kanal-Superfamilie, den humanen spannungsgesteuerten KV7-Kanälen. Trotz ausgeprägter Ähnlichkeiten unterscheiden sich die fünf humanen KV7-Isoformen deutlich hinsichtlich ihrer Sensitivität gegenüber K+-Kanal-Blockern oder -Aktivatoren, außerdem beeinflussen diverse Sequenzabschnitte innerhalb des ungewöhnlich langen C-Terminus der KV7-Kanäle, der ca. die Hälfte des Molekulargewichts einer Untereinheit ausmacht, das Assemblierungsverhalten, die Regulation der Kanalaktivität und die biophysikalischen Kanaleigenschaften steuert. Um die Sequenzunterschiede zwischen den KV7-Untereinheiten mit den spezifischen Eigenschaften der funktionellen Kanäle zu korrelieren, wurden innerhalb dieser Arbeit mit molekularbiologischen Methoden eine Reihe chimärer KV7-Untereinheiten hergestellt und heterolog in Xenopus laevis-Oozyten exprimiert. Anschließend erfolgten mittels der Zwei-Elektroden-Spannungsklemme zum einen die Analyse C terminaler KV7 Kanalstrukturen und zum anderen die Charakterisierung der Bindestelle für das Antikonvulsivum Retigabin (RGB). Basierend auf vorangegangenen Untersuchungen von Maljevic und Kollegen wurde hier die durch den Transfer homologer C terminaler Strukturen von KV7.3 auf KV7.1 bedingte stromverstärkende Wirkung auf einen Bereich von 23 Aminosäuren (Cpp-Sequenz) zurückgeführt, der sich cytoplasmatisch an das sechste Transmembransegment (S6) des Proteins anschließt (Maljevic et al., 2003). Als Ursache für die etwa fünffache Erhöhung der makroskopischen Ströme des KV7.1-(Cpp:7.3)-Konstrukts gegenüber dem KV7.1-Wildtyp konnte dabei eine erhöhte Plasmamembranexpression ausgeschlossen werden. In den von KV7.3 auf KV7.1 transferierten C-terminalen Sequenzen, die für die Stromerhöhung verantwortlich waren, wurde für diverse Aminosäuren eine wichtige Bedeutung für die PIP2-Sensitivität nachgewiesen (Hernandez et al., 2008; Matavel et al., 2010; Thomas et al., 2011). Ein Zusammenhang der vergrößerten Stromamplituden mit einer Beeinflussung der PIP2-Bindestellen ließ sich für die untersuchten KV7-Chimären im Rahmen dieser Arbeit jedoch nicht bestätigen. Die in enger räumlicher Nähe zur Porenregion gelegene Cpp-Sequenz aus KV7.3 führte in KV7.1-(Cpp:7.3) vermutlich durch Modifikation der Einzelkanalleitfähigkeit und der maximalen Offenwahrscheinlichkeit zu der beobachteten Stromerhöhung. In parallel durchgeführten detaillierten Studien zu der positiven Verschiebung der Spannungsabhängigkeit der Kanalaktivierung bei verschiedenen KV7.1/7.3-Chimären gelang es, den Effekt mit der Punktmutation KV7.1-Phe-351-Leu zu erklären. Das Antikonvulsivum Retigabin stellt einen vielversprechenden Wirkstoff für die Therapie verschiedener Erkrankungen, die mit einer neuronalen Hypererregbarkeit einhergehen, wie z. B. Epilepsie, chronische Schmerzen oder Migräne dar (Rundfeldt, 1997; Rundfeldt und Netzer, 2000). In Übereinstimmung mit der Vorhersage eines KV7.3-Strukturmodells ergab sich aus den Ergebnissen dieser Arbeit die Beteiligung von fünf Aminosäureeresten an der Bildung einer Retigabin-Bindungstasche (Lange et al., 2009). Bemerkenswert ist dabei, dass das separat auf einer Untereinheit gelegene KV7.3-Leu-338 zusammen mit den vier anderen Aminosäuren einer benachbarten Untereinheit zur Ausbildung einer der vier Retigabin-Bindungsstellen beiträgt, die sich jeweils an der Grenzfläche zweier Untereinheiten befinden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The organisms on earth exhibit an extremely wide spectrum of transmembrane proteins. Despite the huge variety of species, there is a large degree of homology among even distantly related species, referring to a common evolutionary past. Membrane potassium channels, for instance, are proteins that are found in almost all organisms. These ion channels enable the selective transport of potassium ions across cell membranes, which are otherwise impermeable for charged molecules. The present doctoral thesis focuses one subgroup of this large K+ channel super family, the human voltage-gated KV7 channels. Despite strong similarities in sequence the five human KV7 isoforms differ considerably in terms of the sensitivity to K+ channel inhibitors and activators. Moreover, assembly behavior, regulation of the channel activity and the biophysical channel characteristics are influenced by miscellaneous sequences of the long C-terminus of the KV7 channels, which accounts for about half of the molecular weight of one subunit. Using molecular biological methods, a range of chimeric KV7 subunits was constructed and heterologously expressed in Xenopus laevis oocytes in order to correlate sequence differences between the KV7 subunits with specific properties of functional channels. Subsequently, analyses of C-terminal KV7 channel structures on the one hand, and a characterization of the binding site for the anticonvulsive drug retigabine (RGB) on the other hand was conducted using the two-electrode-voltage-clamp technique (TEVC). In previous investigations, Maljevic and colleagues described a marked current increase and a simultaneously strong positive shift of the voltage dependence of channel activation for one KV7 chimera, which carried the C-terminus of KV7.3 in the backbone of KV7.1 (Maljevic et al., 2003). Starting from these observations, the current enhancing effect due to the transfer of homologous C-terminal structures from KV7.3 into KV7.1 could be narrowed down to a stretch of 23 amino acids (Cpp-sequence) at the cytoplasmic interface of transmembrane segment S6. In contrast to studies addressing the role of assembly domains of the KV7 channels (Schwake et al., 2000, 2003 and 2006; Schenzer et al., 2005), an increased plasma membrane expression could be excluded here as the cause for the about five-fold enhancement of the macroscopic currents of the KV7.1-(Cpp:7.3) construct in comparison to wild type KV7.1. For various amino acids present in the C-terminal region, which was responsible for the current augmentation after transfer from KV7.3 to KV7.1, a significant importance for the PIP2 sensitivity has been demonstrated (Hernandez et al., 2008; Matavel et al., 2010; Thomas et al., 2011). PIP2 is an essential cofactor for the KV7 channel function and has a stimulating impact on the currents of the various KV7 isoforms with subunit-specific concentration dependencies. However, a direct correlation between the enhanced current amplitudes and an altered interaction with PIP2 could not be confirmed. Located in close spatial proximity to the pore region, the KV7.3 Cpp sequence in KV7.1-(Cpp:7.3) led to the observed current augmentations, presumably via modifications of the single-channel conductance and the maximal open probability, respectively, which remains to be investigated in future studies. Regarding the positive shift of the voltage dependence of channel activation of several KV7.1/7.3 chimeras, one single point mutation KV7.1-Phe-351-Leu emerged to be responsible for the effect. Obviously, even together with additional mutations the shift of the voltage dependence caused by this substitution did not affect the current amplitudes of the respective chimeras. The anticonvulsant retigabine is a promising drug for the treatment of different diseases involving neuronal hyperexcitability such as epilepsy, chronic pain or migraine (Rundfeldt, 1997; Rundfeldt and Netzer, 2000). The compound activates all KV7 isoforms besides the cardiac KV7.1 channel (Wickenden et al., 2000; Tatulian et al., 2001), probably by cooperative binding to the four binding sites per channel tetramer (Schenzer et al., 2005). In agreement with predictions from a KV7.3 structural model, five amino acid residues emerged to contribute to the formation of a retigabine binding pocket (Lange et al., 2009). These include the KV7.3 amino acids Trp-265, Thr 271, Leu 272 in the transmembrane segment S5, Leu-314 within the inner pore loop and Leu-338 in the S6 segment. Of note, besides the four aforementioned amino acids, which all reside on the same subunit, KV7.3-Leu-338 of a neighboring subunit also contributes to the binding pocket, such that each of the four retigabine binding sites is located at the interface between two adjacent channel subunits. Compared to the other amino acids involved, the role of KV7.3-Thr-271 is more indirect, as the interaction of this residue with the retigabine molecule takes place only via its backbone.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-07-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2973</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31680</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31680</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2973/geissendoerfer_jan.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
