<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:47:06Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:653">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:653</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Fluorescence lifetime imaging at video rate  a new technique in photosynthesis research</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Bildgebende Messung von Fluoreszenzlebensdauern im Phasenbereich mit Video-Rate  eine neue Technik in der Photosynthese Forschung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Holub, Oliver</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit beschreibt: (1) Entwicklung und Aufbau einer Apparatur zur bildgebenden Messung von Fluoreszenzlebensdauern (FLI: Fluorescence Lifetime Imaging), die Bilder von Fluoreszenzlebendauern mit Video-Rate liefert. (2) Anwendung der schnellen Meßmöglichkeiten des neuen Gerätes auf die Untersuchung von Photosynthese betreibenden Proben, um Einsichten in die Photoschutzmechanismen während der Photosynthese zu erhalten. Die im Rahmen dieser Arbeit entwickelte Apparatur ist die erste betriebene Anlage zur Aufnahme, Berechnung und Visualisierung von Fluoreszenzlebensdauerbildern mit Video-Rate. Bildwiederholraten von 26 Lebensdauerbildern pro Sekunde für Bilder mit 320 x 220 Pixeln wurden erreicht. Dies konnte durch eine konzeptionell neue Kombination von instrumentellen Systemkomponenten, die neuste optoelektronische Elemente enthalten, und speziell entwickelten Programmen für Personal Computer erreicht werden. Die Apparatur beruht auf dem Prinzip der Phasen-und-Modulationsmethode im Homodyn-Modus: Hochfrequent moduliertes Anregungslicht löst in einer fluoreszierenden Probe ein mit der gleichen Frequenz moduliertes Emissionssignal aus, das gegenüber der Anregung eine lebensdauerbedingte Phasenverschiebung und Demodulation aufweist. Mit Hilfe eines modulierbaren Bildverstärkers werden diese beiden Meßgrößen der Detektion durch eine schnelle CCD-Kamera zugänglich gemacht. Die neuen Möglichkeiten für schnelle bildgebende Messungen von Fluoreszenzlebensdauern wurden genutzt, um Unterschiede zwischen der Chl a Fluoreszenz von dem Wildtyp (WT) und den Xanthophyll-Zyklus-Mutanten, npq1 und npq2 der photosynthetischen Alge Chlamydomonas reinhardtii zu untersuchen. Der WT und die Mutante npq1, die Violaxanthin akkumuliert, weisen ähnliche Fluoreszenzintensitäten und Lebensdauern auf, während die npq2 Mutante, die Zeaxanthin akkumuliert, im Vergleich zu WT/npq1 eine deutlich reduzierte Fluoreszenzintensität aufweist (etwa 25-35% am P-Level). Diese Reduktion in der Fluoreszenzintensität ist mit 20-30% kürzeren Fluoreszenzlebensdauern von Phase und Modulation (den scheinbaren Fluoreszenzlebensdauern, berechnet für eine einzelne Lebensdauerkomponente) verbunden. Diese Ergebnisse sind im Einklang mit einer Vielzahl von Messungen, die zeigen, daß Zeaxanthin im Photoschutzmechanismus während der Photosynthese eine wichtige Rolle zukommt. Auch Zellen die mit dem Elektroneninhibitor DCMU (3-(3,4-dichlorophenyl)-1,1-dimethylurea), dem Protonophor Nigericin und dem effizienten PSI Elektronenakzeptor Metyl Viologen behandelt wurden, wiesen ähnlich reduzierte Fluoreszenzintensität und Lebensdauern für die npq2 Mutante (im Vergleich zu WT/npq1) auf. Diese Ergebnisse könnten darauf hindeuten, dass zusätzliche, von dem gewöhnlichen npq Mechanismus unabhängige, Prozesse an dem Fluoreszenzlöschvorgang beteiligt sind. Die ersten Fluorezenzlebensdauer-Transienten konnten gemessen werden: Während in einer gewöhnlichen Fluoreszenz Transienten Messung nur die Fluoreszenzintensität aufgenommen wird, konnten Intensität und Lebensdauern während des Verlaufs der Fluoreszenzinduktion für den WT und die Mutanten gemessen werden. Lebensdauer-Heterogenitäten konnten sowohl in Ensemble-Messungen (gemittelt über eine Vielzahl von Zellen) als auch auf der Ebene von einzelnen Zellen festgestellt werden. Zellen im Zustand negativer Geotaxis (ausgelöst von einigen Stunden Dunkelheit), weisen deutlich verkürzte Fluoreszenzlebensdauern auf.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The achievements of this work are twofold: (1) An instrument was designed and constructed for fast Fluorescence Lifetime-resolved Imaging (FLI)  it can provide fluorescence lifetime images at video-rate. (2) The rapid image acquisition capabilities afforded by the new instrument were used to answer important questions concerning the photoprotection mechanisms of photosynthetic samples. The first of its kind, the FLI instrument described in this work enables continuous image acquisition with concurrent data analysis and visualization of fluorescence lifetime images at video-rate. Sustained rates of up to 26 fluorescence lifetime images per second can be obtained for images of 320 x 220 pixels. This was achieved by a combination of new and conceptually different hardware and software design, which integrates modern opto-electronic components and custom built software for personal computers. The instrument is based on the principle of the phase and modulation method in homodyne operation mode: In a fluorescent sample, high frequency modulated light excites an emission signal that is modulated at the same frequency, but that exhibits a lifetime dependent phase shift and demodulation. Using a modulatable image intensifier, it is possible to detect both measurement parameters with a fast charge-coupled device (CCD)-camera. Under intense irradiation, plants and photosynthetic algae activate photoprotection mechanisms to thermally dissipate potentially harmful energy that exceeds their photosynthetic capacity. Photoprotection of this kind can be monitored by non-photochemical quenching (npq) of the chlorophyll (Chl) a fluorescence produced in photosystem II. The so-called xanthophyll-cycle is known to be involved in photoprotection by conversion of violaxanthin to zeaxanthin under intense irradiation. The new capabilities for rapid fluorescence lifetime-resolved imaging microscopy were used to investigate differences between the Chl a fluorescence of wild type (WT) and xanthophyll-cycle npq mutants, npq1 and npq2 of the photosynthetic alga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii. When photosynthetic samples are brought from darkness to constant irradiation, fluorescence intensity undergoes large changes with time. Rapid measurements are necessary to determine the fluorescence lifetimes during this so-called Chl a fluorescence transient (induction). WT and the mutant npq1, (which accumulates violaxanthin), show similar fluorescence intensities and lifetimes while the npq2 mutant, (which accumulates zeaxanthin), displays reduced fluorescence intensity, (about 25-35% at P-level), compared to WT/npq1 cells. This reduction in fluorescence intensity is correlated with 20-30% shorter apparent single lifetimes from phase and modulation. These results support the important function of zeaxanthin in the photoprotection mechanism of photosynthetic samples. Similar reductions at P-level and P-to-S decay in fluorescence intensities and lifetimes for the npq2 mutant compared to WT/npq1 are also found for cells that were treated with the electron inhibitor DCMU (3-(3,4-dichlorophenyl)-1,1-dimethylurea), the protonophore nigericin and the efficient PSI electron acceptor methyl viologen. These results might imply that the quenching process includes contributions from additional processes not dependent on the npq mechanisms. We present the first fluorescence lifetime transients: the simultaneous measurements of transient changes of fluorescence intensity and lifetime during the fluorescence induction for the WT as well as for the mutants. Lifetime heterogeneities were observed in ensemble experiments (averaged over multiple cells) as well as at the single cell level. Cells in the state of negative geotaxis, (induced by several hours of darkness), show shortened lifetimes.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2003-05-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/653</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-6471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-6471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/653/holub_oliver.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
