<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3284">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3284</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Experimentelle Untersuchung der Modensynchronisation in Multisegment-Laserdioden zur Erzeugung kurzer optischer Pulse bei einer Wellenlänge von 920 nm</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Experimental investigation of mode-locking in multi-segment Laser-diodes for generation of short optical pulses at a wavelength of 920 nm </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schwertfeger, Sven</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wurden monolithische modengekoppelte Halbleiterlaser zur Kurzpulserzeugung auf GaAs-Basis für eine Emissionswellenlänge von 920 nm entwickelt und experimentell charakterisiert. Die emittierten Pulse sollten eine Pulslänge unter 20 ps aufweisen und eine möglichst hohe Pulsenergie haben. So wurden zunächst mit dem Softwaretool LDSL Mehrsegmentlaser simuliert, um das erreichbare Potential in Bezug auf Pulslänge und -leistung zu ergründen. Ausgehend von diesen Simulationen wurden 4-Sektionslaser mit einer Wellenleiterdicke von 3.6 µm und einem Zweifachquantumwell als aktive Zone mittels metallorganischer Gasphasenepitaxie (MOVPE) hergestellt. Die gesamte Resonatorlänge betrug konstant 10mm, um die angestrebte Repetitionsfrequenz von 4GHz zu erreichen. Die 4 Sektionen unterscheiden sich durch ihre Funktion wie folgt. Die Absorbersektion ermöglicht durch die sättigbare Absorption das nötige synchronisieren der Resonatormoden. Die Gewinnsektion sorgt für die nötige Verstärkung der Resonatormoden. Die Kavitätssektion ist besonders lang (ca. 8 mm) und dient als aktiver Wellenleiter, um die nötige Umlaufzeit zu erreichen. Die vierte Sektion beinhaltet ein Bragggitter, welches die spektrale Lage der Emissionswellenlänge definiert. In der Arbeit werden Details zu den Messmethoden, der Laseransteuerung und der experimentellen Verfahrensweise dargelegt. Durch umfangreiche experimentelle Charakterisierung der Laser konnte gezeigt werden, dass die Laser unter fast allen Anregungsbedingungen passive Modenkopplung aufweisen. Es zeigte sich, das die Größe der Sperrspannung an der Absorbersektion entscheidenden Einfluss auf die Emissionseigenschaften des Lasers hat. So bewirkt eine Erhöhung der Sperrspannung eine Reduktion der Pulslänge und wirkt sich stabilisierend in Bezug auf das Rauschverhalten aus. Das Erreichen der Laserschwelle war nur möglich, wenn die Stromdichte in der Kavitätssektion oberhalb der Transparenzstromdichte lag. Eine Erhöhung über die Transparenzstromdichte hinaus führt zu einer Leistungszunahme einerseits und bewirkt andererseits eine Verbreiterung der Pulse bei gleichzeitiger Zunahme des Rauschens. Für sehr hohe Kavitätsströme wird das Modenkoppeln instabil. Die Länge der Gewinnsektion hat direkten Einfluss auf die erzielbare Pulsenergie, die Pulslänge und damit auch auf die Pulsspitzenleistung. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass für niedrige Pulsenergien bis etwa 3.7 pJ die Laser nahezu fourierlimitierte sech² förmige Pulse mit einer Pulslänge unter 10 ps emittieren. Die maximal erreichte Pulsenergie betrug 25 pJ. Außer passivem Modenkoppeln wurde auch hybrides Modenkoppeln untersucht, dass durch das Anlegen einer hochfrequenten Wechselspannung an die Absorbersektion realisiert wurde. Die Frequenz der Wechselspannung muss hierbei der Umlauffrequenz entsprechen und sehr frequenzstabil sein. Die Umlauffrequenz des modengekoppelten Lasers passt sich der externen Frequenz an womit sich die zeitliche Stabilität erhöht. Hier zeigte sich, dass bei einer maximalen HF-Leistung von 30 dBm, für Frequenzen innerhalb des Fangbereiches, der zeitliche Jitter durch die hochpräzise externe HF-Quelle bis auf etwa 1 ps verringert werden konnte. Eine Besonderheit der hier prozessierten Laser ergibt sich daraus, dass die lichterzeugende aktive Zone sich unterbrechungsfrei über alle 4 Sektionen erstreckt. Damit besteht die Möglichkeit, die Gittersektion mit einem Strom in Vorwärtsrichtung zu betreiben und so die Reflexionseigenschaften entscheidend zu verändern. Die Speisung des Bragg-Gitters führte bei allen Geometrien zu einer signifikanten Steigerung der Leistung und einer deutlichen Reduktion der Rauschparameter. So konnte die Pulsspitzenleistung für einen Laser mit 1000 µm langer Gewinnsektion auf über 2W gesteigert werden, was in diesem Fall einer Verdoppelung der Leistung entsprach. Die in dieser Arbeit erzielten Ergebnisse bezüglich der Pulsenergie und Spitzenleistung zeigen deutlich das Potential des verwendeten GaAs-Materialsystems. Im Vergleich zu den monolithischen Beispielen aus der Literatur konnte die Pulsenergie deutlich gesteigert werden. Die hier gewonnenen Erkenntnisse bilden die Grundlage für das vollständige Verständnis GaAs basierender modengekoppelter Laser und bieten das Handwerkszeug für die Realisierung ähnlicher Laser bei anderen Wellenlängen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work deals with the development and experimental investigation of a highpower short laser-pulse source that emits at a wavelength of 920 nm. The laser source consists of a monolithic multi-section mode-locked laser based on the GaAs material system. The main focus lies on the achievement of high pulse energies at pulse durations below 20 ps. First, simulations of a four section DBR laser were carried out with the software tool LDSL in order to determine their potential in terms of pulse duration and output power. Based on the simulation results four section lasers with a waveguide thickness of 3.6 μm and a double quantum well acting as active region were realized. The four sections of the laser work as follows: The section at the front facet acts as a saturable absorber allowing the synchronization of the resonator modes and thus enable passive mode-locking. The second section, the gain section, provides the required power. The third section is a long active cavity section (length approx. 8000 μm) which is required to reach an overall laser length of 10 mm. The round trip time for the overall length of 10mm corresponds to 250 ps resulting in the desired repetition rate of 4GHz. The fourth section adjacent to the rear facet is a DBR section that defines the emission wavelength. The length of the gain section was varied while keeping the overall laser length fixed by a corresponding variation of the cavity section length. The lasers were grown by a two step metal organic vapor phase epitaxy (MOVPE). In order to characterize the laser devices an appropriate mount including the driving electronics was developed. Furthermore a measurement setup consisting of a streak camera, an autocorrelator, and an electrical spectrum analyzer was realized and a corresponding controlling and evaluation software has been developed. These DBR lasers were systematically analyzed by measuring the average power and the spectral and temporal behavior of the generated pulses. In order to obtain hybrid mode-locking a high frequency sinusoidal shaped voltage was applied to the absorber section. The extensive experimental investigations showed that the lasers feature passive mode locking for nearly all operating parameters. The emission power scaled with the injection current through the gain as well as the cavity section. An increased voltage at the absorber section leads to shorter pulses and reduced phase noise. In order to reach laser emission the current through the cavity section is required to exceed the transparency current density. A further increase of the current through the cavity section increases the pulse energy, however, the pulse duration and the noise level are also increased. For very high cavity currents modelocking will finally be instable. The length of the gain section influences the achievable pulse energy and pulse duration directly and thus influences the peak pulse level as well. For lasers with a 1500 μm long gain section the achieved pulse energy was 25 pJ. With a shorter gain section of 1000 μm a pulse energy of 12 pJ was reached. The lasers with the shortest gain section of 750 μm delivered a maximum pulse energy of 10 pJ. For pulse energies below 3.7 pJ the measured pulses are transform limited with a pulse duration below 10 ps and a sech2 pulse shape. The sech2 shape is observed for pulse energies up to 7 pJ, however these pulses are not transform limited any more. The maximum achievable peak power at these power levels corresponds to 900mW. For higher powers an increase of the pulse duration is observed and a definite determination of the pulse shape with the autocorrelation function can no longer be obtained. As a result, the calculated pulse parameters like peak power and time-bandwidth product become defective. Besides passive mode-locking, hybrid mode-locking, realized by applying a high frequency AC voltage to the absorber section, has been investigated as well. If the frequency of the external voltage source lies in the range of the roundtrip time of the mode-locked laser, then the laser locks to the high frequency signal. Under hybrid mode-locking the round trip time of the laser is fixed to the external frequency and thus the long term frequency stability is increased. For a maximum external RF-power of 30 dBm the timing jitter measured by a phase noise measurement was reduced to about 1 ps. The specific design of these laser chips with the active region extending over all sections allows for an electrical pumping of the Bragg-grating section. The pumping of the Bragg grating with a current up to 100mA leads to a significant increase of the output power and a reduction of phase noise for all three geometries presented. With this method the pulse peak power of a 1000 μm device was increased to values beyond 2W corresponding to twice the power obtained without pumping of the Bragg grating section. The pulse energy corresponds to 16.5 pJ. The pulse length of 7 ps was well below the aim of 20 ps. The timing jitter was reduced to 1.5 ps at passive operation. With hybrid mode-locking the timing jitter was even below 1 ps. The results reached in this work regarding pulse energies and maximum pulse power, shows the potential of the GaAs material system. Compared to the monolithic lasers presented in the literature the pulse energies were significantly increased. Electrical pumping of the Bragg-section resulted in an increased emission power and a significant reduction of the timing jitter. This work provides a deep insight into the physics and performance of GaAs based mode-locked lasers and can be used as a groundwork for the realization of mode-locked lasers at other wavelengths.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-04-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3284</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34619</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34619</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3284/schwertfeger_sven.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
