<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:09Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3220">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3220</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Development and Validation of a Risk Score predicting substantial Weight Gain over 5 Years in middle-aged European Men and Women</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Entwicklung und Validierung eines Risikoscores zur Prädiktion einer starken Gewichtszunahme in den nächsten 5 Jahren bei Männern und Frauen in Europa</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Steffen, Annika</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Given the rapid rise in obesity prevalence around the world in recent years and the considerable strains involved with the treatment of overweight and obesity, primary prevention of weight gain is of paramount public health importance. Due to limited resources, prevention efforts might be particularly targeted to individuals at high risk of excess weight gain that may result in overweight and obesity. Therefore, the aim of the present thesis was to develop a risk score predicting risk of substantial weight gain (SWG) within the following 5 years. Because this objective was addressed using data of the large-scale, multi-centre European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC), the present study offered the unique opportunity to simultaneously investigate whether such a risk score is equally well applicable to different European populations and to evaluate the idea of one universal, transnational risk prediction model for weight gain. Data from six cohorts (47,203 men and women) of the EPIC study were used to develop a risk prediction model for SWG (training sample). Substantial weight gain was defined as gaining ≥10% of baseline weight during follow-up. Significant predictors of SWG were identified using Cox Proportional Hazards regression. Multivariable regression model coefficients were used to assign weights for each predictor and the risk score was calculated as a linear combination of the single predictors. The validity of the risk score was assessed by means of discrimination (area under a receiver operating characteristic curve, aROC) and calibration in the training sample and in external validation samples, comprising eight independent cohorts of the EPIC study (115,099 men and women). During an average follow-up of 6.2 years (291,748 person-years), a total of 6,471 men and women gained ≥10% of baseline weight in the training sample. The final prediction model was defined on the basis of the following factors: age, sex, baseline body weight and height, technical school, secondary school, university, cessation of smoking, sports, non-consumption of alcohol, moderate consumption of alcohol, intake of fruits and vegetables, red and processed meat, poultry, bread, butter and margarine, cake and cookies, and soft drinks. The probability of experiencing SWG within 5 years increased from 2.0% for 100 to 33.6% for 400 score points. The discriminatory ability of the model measured by the aROC (95% CI) was 0.67 (0.66–0.68) in the training sample and 0.57 (0.566–0.578) in the external validation sample. Variations in discrimination between cohorts were observed, ranging from 0.65 to 0.76 in the training and from 0.56 to 0.66 in the validation sample. Calibration was very good and good in cohorts of the training and validation sample, respectively. The present thesis could demonstrate that it was possible to develop a risk score predicting SWG over 5 years among European adults using easily assessable information on several socio-demographic, dietary and lifestyle factors. The score was found to exhibit moderate discriminatory accuracy and to accurately predict risk of experiencing SWG during the following 5 years. The results of the present thesis highlight that the prediction of weight gain is complex and may be limited in general. Within these limits, the findings of the thesis further suggest the appropriateness of one universal, transnational risk score to predict weight gain among European adults.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Primärprävention von Übergewicht und Adipositas ist von hoher gesamtgesellschaftlicher Bedeutung. Angesichts limitierter Ressourcen könnten Interventionsmaßnahmen zur Prävention vorrangig an jene Personen gerichtet werden, die ein hohes absolutes Risiko für die Entwicklung übermäßigen Körpergewichts aufweisen. Daher war das Ziel der vorliegenden Dissertation, einen Risikoscore zu entwickeln, der das absolute Risiko für eine starke Gewichtszunahme (SGZ) in den folgenden 5 Jahren vorhersagt. Da die multizentrische European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC)-Studie die Datengrundlage dieser Arbeit darstellte, konnte überdies der Frage nachgegangen werden, ob ein Risikoscore zur Prädiktion einer SGZ gleichermaßen in unterschiedlichen europäischen Populationen einsetzbar ist und ob es ein universelles, länderübergreifendes Risikoprädiktionsmodell für SGZ gibt. Für die Ableitung des Prädiktionsmodells wurden die Daten von 47.203 Männern und Frauen aus sechs Kohorten der EPIC-Studie verwendet (Lernstudienpopulation). Eine starke Gewichtszunahme war definiert als eine Zunahme von ≥10% des Ausgangsgewichts während der Nachbeobachtung. Signifikante Prädiktoren wurden mit Hilfe der Cox Regression identifiziert. Multivariable Regressionskoeffizienten dienten der Gewichtung der einzelnen Prädiktoren in der Berechnung des Risikoscores. Die Validität des Risikoscores wurde anhand von Diskrimination (Fläche unter der Receiver Operating Characteristic-Kurve, aROC) und Kalibrierung bewertet. Die externe Validität wurde mit Hilfe von acht unabhängigen EPIC-Kohorten beurteilt (Teststudienpopulation, 115.099 Männer und Frauen). Während einer mittleren Nachbeobachtungszeit von 6,2 Jahren (291.748 Personenjahre) verzeichneten 6.471 Männer und Frauen in der Lernstudienpopulation eine SGZ. Das finale Prädiktionsmodell wurde auf Basis der folgenden Prädiktoren definiert: Alter, Geschlecht, Körpergewicht und –höhe, Bildung, Aufgabe des Rauchens, Sport, Alkoholabstinenz, moderater Alkoholkonsum, Verzehr von Obst und Gemüse, rotem und verarbeitetem Fleisch, Geflügel, Brot, Butter und Margarine, Kuchen und Keksen und von Softgetränken. Das Risiko für eine SGZ in den nächsten 5 Jahren stieg von 2.0% bei 100 auf 33.6% bei 400 Score-Punkten. Die Fähigkeit zur Diskrimination des Modells gemessen anhand der aROC (95% Konfidenzintervall, KI) betrug 0,67 (0,66–0,68) in der Lernstudienpopulation und 0,57 (0,566–0,578) in der Teststudienpopulation. Die Diskriminationsfähigkeit variierte dabei zwischen den einzelnen Studienkohorten und schwankte von 0,65 bis 0,76 in der Lern- und von 0,56 bis 0,66 in der Teststudienpopulation. In den Kohorten der Lern- bzw. Teststudienpopulation wies das Modell eine sehr gute bzw. gute Kalibrierung auf. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurde erstmalig ein Risikoscore zur Prädiktion von Gewichtszunahmen entwickelt. Dieser Score basiert auf einfach zu erhebenden Informationen zu soziodemographischen, Ernährungs- und Lebensstilfaktoren und wies eine moderate Diskriminationsfähigkeit auf. Die Ergebnisse der vorliegenden Arbeit stellen die Komplexität der Prädiktion von Gewichtszunahmen heraus und weisen darauf hin, dass deren Prädiktion im Allgemeinen begrenzt sein könnte. Innerhalb dieser Grenzen scheint ein universeller Risikoscore zur Prädiktion von Gewichtszunahmen bei europäischen Erwachsenen jedoch geeignet zu sein.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-02-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3220/steffen_annika.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
