<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:53Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1628">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1628</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Screening und Charakterisierung von   anti-Œ≤-Herpesvirus-Aktivit√§ten in Substanzen aus phototrophen, aquatischen Mikroorganismmen</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Screening and characterisation of anti-Œ≤-herpesvirus activities in substances from phototrophic, aquatic microorganisms.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Thulke, Stefanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Infektionen mit den Œ≤-Herpesviren humanes Cytomegalievirus (HCMV) und humanes Herpesvirus-6 (HHV-6) sind mit bis zu 90 % Seroposititvit√§t aller Erwachsenen sehr weit verbreitet. Sie verlaufen in der Regel asymptomatisch, k√∂nnen jedoch bei immunsupprimierten Patienten zum Teil lebensbedrohliche Erkrankungen hervorrufen, z.B. Entz√ºndungen der Lunge, des Gehirns oder der Netzhaut. Gegenw√§rtig werden verschiedene antiherpale Medikamente verwendet, die partiell ernsthafte Nebenwirkungen hervorrufen. Au√üerdem ist die Verbreitung resistenter St√§mme zu beobachten. Daher existiert ein verst√§rktes Interesse an der Entwicklung neuartiger antiviraler Substanzen. Naturstoffe spielen dabei wegen ihrer gro√üen Strukturvielfalt eine zentrale Rolle, wobei Verbindungen aus aquatischen, phototrophen Mikroorganismen (pMO, Mikroalgen und Cyanobakterien), ein bisher unzureichend genutztes Potential darstellen. Die vorliegende Arbeit war Teil eines Projektes mit dem Ziel, antivirale Substanzen aus pMO zu identifizieren und zu isolieren. Die Substanzen wurden aus monoseptischen pMO-Kulturen in sterilisierbaren Photobioreaktoren aufgearbeitet, ihre chemische Struktur bestimmt und im Rahmen der vorliegenden Arbeit hinsichtlich einer antiviralen Aktivit√§t gegen√ºber HCMV getestet. Antiviral aktive Substanzen wurden ferner hinsichtlich ihrer Wirkungsweise untersucht. Zun√§chst wurden die Screeningmethoden zur Bestimmung der Zellvitalit√§t von MRC-5-Fibroblasten (WST-1-Test) und der anti-HCMV-Aktivit√§t (Peroxidasef√§rbung viraler Antigene) etabliert und mit dem bei HCMV-Infektionen klinisch eingesetzten Basenanalogon Ganciclovir (GCV) als Referenzsubstanz getestet. Im entwickelten Screeningsystem inhibiert es bei einer Konzentration von etwa 6 mg/ml die Zellvitalit√§t um 50 % (CC50) und bei einer Konzentration von 14 ¬µg/ml die HCMV-Replikation um 50 % (IC50). Aus fast 500 unterschiedlich gewonnenen Extrakten wurden die folgenden wirksamen Substanzen erfolgreich identifiziert und charakterisiert: 1. Das anionische Exopolysaccharid (EPS) aus dem Rhodophyten Porphyridium purpureum weist im Screeningsystem eine anti-HCMV-Aktivit√§t von IC50 = 90 ¬µg/ml auf (CC50 &gt; 5 mg/ml). Die Substanz ist au√üerdem wirksam gegen HHV-6 und Vacciniavirus (VV). Damit werden erstmals Aktivit√§ten aus P. purpureum gegen Ô?¢-Herpesviren und VV beschrieben. 2. F√ºr das intrazellul√§re aPS TK V2 aus der Biomasse des Cyanobakteriums Arthrospira platensis wurde eine Wirksamkeit von IC50 = 39 ¬µg/ml nachgewiesen (CC50 &gt; 5 mg/ml). In diesem Extrakt ist wahrscheinlich das bereits beschriebene Ca-Spirulan enthalten. 3. Das davon zu unterscheidende, bisher unbekannte anionische Exopolysaccharid TK V3 aus A. platensis zeigt sogar eine 10fach h√∂here antivirale Aktivit√§t (IC50 = 4 ¬µg/ml, CC50 &gt; 5 mg/ml) als TK V2 und ist dar√ºber hinaus etwa 3,5fach besser als das herk√∂mmlich verwendete GCV. Hervorzuheben ist weiterhin die 100 %ige Inhibierung der HCMV-Replikation mit lediglich 20 ¬µg/ml TK V3, was mit 250 ¬µg/ml EPS, 40 ¬µg/ml TK V2 und ebenso mit 40 ¬µg/ml GCV nicht erzielt werden konnte. Sowohl TK V2 als auch TK V3 besitzen au√üerdem eine Wirksamkeit gegen HHV-6, VV, das Herpes Simplex-Virus-1 und das Humane Immundefizienz-Virus-1. Anhand von in vitro Infektionskinetiken wurde f√ºr EPS, TK V2 und TK V3 weiterhin veranschaulicht, dass sie zu einer signifikanten Reduktion der viralen DNA- und RNA-Replikation f√ºhren. Das herausragende Charakteristikum der aPS ist die Verminderung der Virusreplikation durch Inhibierung der Adsorption und/oder Fusion der Viruspartikel an die Zellmembran. Im Gegensatz dazu hemmen herk√∂mmliche Virostatika direkt die DNA-Replikation, zum Beispiel Basenanaloga. Die mikrobiellen aPS stellen somit eine Erfolg versprechende Basis f√ºr die Entwicklung von Virostatika mit neuartigem Wirkmechanismus und dar√ºber hinaus mit einem sehr breiten antiviralen Wirkungsspektrum dar.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Infections with human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) and human herpesvirus-6 (HHV-6), both belonging to the Œ≤-subfamily of herpesviruses, are very widespread with a rate up to 90 % of seropositive adults. Usually, no infection related symptoms can be detected. Nevertheless, these infections can cause life-threatening diseases in immunosuppressed patients, for instance, pneumonitis, encephalitis or retinitis. Nowadays, several different therapeutic agents are used against herpesvirus infections but still this way of treatment can come up with severe partial side effects. Furthermore, the spreading out of resistant strains can be watched, and so there is a great need for and an increasing interest in the development of novel substances. As natural products exhibit a great structural diversity, they play a central role in this process. In fact, concerning antiviral drug development, there should have been paid more attention to phototrophic microorganisms providing many different metabolic substances. All data presented here were achieved by a project work aiming at the isolation and chemical characterisation of anti-herpetic drugs produced by phototrophic microorganisms (pMO, micro algae and cyanobacteria). Therefore, metabolically synthesised sulphated polysaccharides and sulpholipides were selectively extracted from pMO-culture and their chemical structures were determined. Also screening and characterisation of their antiviral activity were performed. Substances positively tested for antiviral action were further analysed in view of their mode of action. Initially, screening methods to ensure cytotoxicity against MRC-5-fibroblasts (WST-1 test) and anti-HCMV activity (peroxidase staining of viral antigens) were established. The therapeutically exerted base analogue ganciclovir (GCV) was used as reference substance. It inhibits cellular vitality by 50 % (CC50) at a concentration of about 6 mg/ml and leads to 50 % inhibition of viral replication (IC50) at a concentration of 14 ¬µg/ml. After having screened nearly 500 extracts, the following agents were successfully identified and characterised: 1. The anionic exopolysaccharide EPS of rhodophyte Porphyridium purpureum exhibits a low cytotoxicity (CC50 &gt; 5 mg/ml) and a significant anti-HCMV activity (IC50 = 90 ¬µg/ml). EPS is also active against HHV-6 and vaccinia virus (VV). So this is the first report about P. purpureum showing activities against Ô?¢-herpesviruses and VV. 2. Furthermore, the anionic polysaccharide TK V2 was isolated from the biomass of the cyanobacterium Arthrospira platensis exhibiting an anti-HCMV activity of IC50 = 39 ¬µg/ml. TK V2 presumably contains the already known Ca-Spirulan. 3. In contrast to TK V2, the structurally differing anionic exopolysaccharide TK V3, also isolated from Arthrospira platensis, demonstrated a 10fold higher antiviral activity (IC50 = 4 ¬µg/ml). Compared to clinically used GCV, TK V3 is 3.5fold more active. It is to emphasise, that using the screening system only 20 g/ml TK V3 completely inhibited HCMV-replication, whereas 250 ¬µg/ml EPS, 40 ¬µg/ml TK V2 or 40 ¬µg/ml GCV did not achieve 100 % inhibition of HCMV-replication. TK V2 and TK V3 possess low cytotoxicities (CC50 &gt; 5 mg/ml) and are also active against HHV-6, VV, HSV-1 and human immunodeficiency virus-1 (HIV-1). Performing in vitro infection kinetics, anionic polysaccharides EPS, TK V2 and TK V3 were shown to reduce viral DNA- and RNA-replication. Compared to antiherpal therapeutical agents, these agents were demonstrated to act by inhibiting the adsorption of viral particles to the cellular membrane. Because of the different mode of action of clinically used agents, which directly inhibit the viral DNA-replication, this has to be considered as an outstanding attribute. Due their broad antiviral activity and their novel mode of action, the identified anionic polysaccharides constitute a fundamental potential for the development of antiviral agents.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-12-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1628</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1628/original_Dissertation_Stefanie_Thulke_Nov_2007.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1628/thulke_stefanie.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
