<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:38Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2668">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2668</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Adigrat Sandstone in Northern and Central Ethiopia: Stratigraphy, Facies, Depositional Environments and Palynology</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Adigrat Sandstein in Nord- und Zentral-Äthiopien: Stratigraphie, Fazies, Ablagerungsmilieu und Palynologie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Enkurie, Dawit Lebenie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In northern and central Ethiopia, continental to shallow-marine siliciclastic sediments of up to 430 m thick are exposed. These sediments are referred to as the ‘Adigrat Sandstone’. This study provides a detailed investigation of the stratigraphy, sedimentary facies, depositional environments and palynology of the ‘Adigrat Sandstone’ succession in the Mekelle and Blue Nile basins in order to obtain a complete picture of the large-scale spatial/temporal stacking patterns of depositional systems, whereby a new knowledge of the mode of evolution of the basins and the mechanisms controlling their formation can be obtained. The study also provides a more reliable stratigraphic position for the sandstone succession based on palynological data. Three unconformity bounded stratigraphic units have been identified within the Late Triassic to Middle Jurassic ‘Adigrat Sandstone’ succession. Unit I that represents the lower stratigraphic unit in both basins is Late Triassic (Late Carnian–Early Rhaetian) in age. It is composed of transgressive tide-dominated estuarine and prograding storm-dominated shoreface deposits. The overall northeastward-thickening wedge-shaped geometry of the depositional body and the palaeocurrent patterns in both basins suggest that the sediments accumulated on a vast slowly subsiding passive continental margin in a shallow gulf, which extended northeast into the Neotethys. This indicates that the Late Triassic shallow gulf, which encroached into the Arabian platform from the northeast, had most probably reached the northern and central parts of Ethiopia. A Neotethyan seaway through Saudi Arabia into Ethiopia has an important bearing on the palaeotectonic and palaeogeographic scenario of the region at that time. The second stratigraphic unit (Unit II) is Late Liassic (Early Toarcian) in age. No direct similarity can be inferred regarding facies successions and depositional systems within Unit II in the two basins. In the Mekelle Basin, the unit is composed of coarse-grained sandstones and conglomerates of fluvial and deltaic origin whereas in the Blue Nile Basin the unit is of barrier/inlet-spit origin. The fluvio-deltaic deposits in the Mekelle Basin have been accumulated in an active rift basin. The key similarity in the strata of Unit II in both basins is their similar palaeocurrent patterns, indicating deposition on a SE-dipping divergent continental margin. The abandonment of the previously existing NE-dipping continental margin and its replacement by a SE-dipping one can be best explained by rifting and basin inversion, which is most probably associated with the break-up of East and West Gondwana that commenced during the Toarcian. The uppermost stratigraphic unit (Unit III), which is recognised only in the Mekelle Basin, is Middle Jurassic (Late Toarcian to Early Callovian) in age. This phase corresponds to delta abandonment and the inception of transgressive barrier-lagoon system, which is most probably related to the continuous crustal thinning and subsidence along the evolving rift between East and West Gondwana. The transition from a ‘Gilbert-type’ delta to a barrier-lagoon system suggests that the basin has evolved from a possibly fault-controlled, broadly downwarping basin to a cratonic seaway characterised by a low gradient coastal to nearshore profile. The landward migration of the barrier-lagoon complex is attributed to the marine transgression progressing from the southeast as the rate of sea level rise exceeds the rate of sediment supply. As relative sea level started to fall, the elongate shoestring sand bodies of the uppermost barrier were destructed and cannibalised by a number of tidal inlet channels, which cut through them. Barrier destruction was concomitantly accompanied by the establishment of prograding open-coast tidal flats and strandplains. Based on 16 productive samples collected at different stratigraphic levels, three informal palynological assemblage zones have been identified within the Adigrat Sandstone succession in the Mekelle and Blue Nile basins. These assemblage zones, in ascending order, are: AZ I, Late Triassic (Late Carnian–Early Rhaetian); AZ II, latest Early Jurassic (Early Toarcian); and AZ III, latest Early–Middle Jurassic (Late Toarcian–Early Callovian). These palynological results allow for the first time a better biostratigraphic subdivision of the Adigrat Sandstone succession and its correlation with equivalent units in the region.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In Nord- und Zentral-Äthiopien sind bis zu 430 m mächtige, kontinentale und flachmarine klastische Sedimentfolgen aufgeschlossen, die als ‘Adigrat-Sandstein’ bezeichnet werden. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurde auf Grundlage detaillierter stratigraphischer, sedimentfazieller und palynologischer Untersuchungen dieser Schichtenfolgen im Mekelle- und Blauen-Nil- Becken ein umfassendes Bild des zeitlichen und räumlichen Aufbaus der ‘Adigrat-Sandsteine’ erarbeitet, wobei auch neue Erkenntnisse über die Entwicklungsgeschichte dieser Sedimentbecken gewonnen wurden. Darüber hinaus wurde die stratigraphische Stellung der Sedimentfolge mit Hilfe von Palynomorphen geklärt. Die Schichtenfolge des ‘Adigrat-Sandsteins’ (Obertrias–Mitteljura) wird in drei durch Diskordanzen (Hiaten) voneinander getrennte stratigraphische Einheiten gegliedert. Die unterste Einheit (Einheit I) wurde im Keuper (oberstes Karn–unterstes Rhät) unter tidal-ästuarinen und sturm-dominierten Bedingungen flachmarin abgelagert. Die Transport-richtungen der Sedimente und die nach Nordosten hin zunehmende Mächtigkeit des keilförmigen Sedimentkörpers weisen darauf hin, dass die Sedimente in einem weiträumigen, flachen, nach Nordosten zur Neotethys hin geöffneten Golf abgelagert wurden. Dies bedeutet, dass sich in der Obertrias von Nordosten her ein flacher Meeresgolf über die arabische Plattform und Nord-Äthiopien höchstwahrscheinlich bis nach Zentral-Äthiopien hinein erstreckt hat. Diese sich in der oberen Trias über Südarabien bis nach Äthiopien erstreckende Meeresbucht der Neotethys ist eine wesentliche Neuerkenntnis zur Paläogeographie der Region. Die nächstjüngere stratigraphische Einheit (Einheit II) wurde im Untertoarcium abgelagert. In Bezug auf Sedimentfazies und Ablagerungssysteme besteht diese Einheit im Mekelle-Becken aus fluvio-deltaischen Sedimenten, die in einem aktiven Riftbecken abgelagert wurden. Im Blauen-Nil-Becken bestehen die Sedimente dagegen aus Ablagerungen von Barriere-Inseln und Gezeitenkanälen eines ‚barrier/inlet-spit’-Systems. Die gleichbleibende Transportrichtung der Schichtenfolge der Einheit II in den voneinander getrennten Sedimentbecken belegt einen generell nach Südosten geneigten Kontinentalrand. Die Änderung der nach Nordosten gerichteten Sedimentschüttungen nach Südosten deutet auf den Einfluß des beginnenden Riftings zwischen Ost- und Westgondwana während des Toarciums und eine lokale Beckeninversion hin. Die oberste stratigraphische Einheit (Einheit III) - die nur im Mekelle-Becken ausgebildet ist - wurde im Obertoarcium–Untercallovium abgelagert, während sich im Blauen-Nil-Becken in dieser Zeit Evaporite bildeten. Die zu dieser Zeit einsetzende Entwicklung eines transgressiven Barrieren-Lagunen-Systems im Mekelle-Becken steht vermutlich in Verbindung mit dem fortschreitenden Rifting zwischen Ost- und West-gondwana. Der Wechsel von einem ‘Gilbert-Typ’-Delta zu einem Barrieren-Lagunen-System deutet darauf hin, dass hierbei ein störungskontrolliertes, sich rasch vertiefendes Becken in eine Meeresstraße mit einem geringen Küstengradienten überging. Die landwärtige Verlagerung der Barrieren-Lagunen-Komplexe wird auf die von Südosten her vorgreifende Transgression zurückgeführt, wobei vermutlich der Meeresspiegelanstieg die Sedimentzufuhr überstieg. Mit dem danach erneut einsetzenden relativen Abfall des Meeresspiegels wurden die zuvor abgelagerten barriere-formenden Sandsteine zunehmend durch zahlreiche Gezeitenkanäle eingeschnitten. Gleichzeitig entstanden daneben progradierende Gezeiten- und Strandebenen. Pollen und Sporen aus 16 produktiven Oberflächenproben des ‘Adigrat-Sandsteins’ wurden drei informellen Sporomorph-Vergesellschaftungen zugeordnet. In aufsteigender Reihenfolge sind dies die Vergesellschaftungszonen AZ I: Obertrias (oberstes Karn–unterstes Rhät); AZ II: später Unterjura (Untertoarcium) und AZ III: später Unterjura–Mitteljura (Obertoarcium–Untercallovium). Mit diesem Ergebnis konnte erstmals palynologisch eine stratigraphische Gliederung der Sedimentabfolge erzielt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-10-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2668</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2668/enkurie_dawit.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
