<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2363">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2363</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Climate and Energy Responsive Housing in Continental Climates : the Suitability of Passive Houses for Iran‚Äôs Dry and Cold Climate</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Klima- und energiegerechter Wohnungsbau im kontinentalen Klima : die Eignung von Passivh√§usern f√ºr das kalt-trockene Klima im Iran</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nasrollahi, Farshad</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In spite of worldwide climate change problems caused by fossil fuel use, energy consumption levels in Iran, while already high, continue to rise each year. About 97% of the total energy consumption of Iran, and 98.8% of energy consumed by the building sector in this country is fossil fuel-derived, with residential and commercial buildings being responsible for over 40% of this amount. The present dissertation focuses on the cold climatic region in Iran, which is characterised by a continental climate, and it examines the city of Tabriz as a case study. The primary aim was to study the suitability of passive houses in Iran‚Äôs cold climatic region and to identify those architectural factors most relevant for reducing building energy consumption. Because of present economic conditions in Iran, notably the subsidised cost of fossil fuels, energy savings in buildings through expensive conservation methods are not economically viable. Thus, there is little social interest in energy saving, especially where such measures increase building costs. Therefore this thesis argues that the use of cost-neutral building methods and cheaper architectural solutions is the most realistic and pragmatic approach. This dissertation also briefly examines theoretical aspects of climate and of the effect of climatic factors on buildings, as well as examining the climatic response of various building types, passive solar heating systems and various passive and hybrid cooling methods. In addition, the work compares the energy situation, climate and residential architecture in Iran and Germany, and it introduces German concepts of energy efficient building and standards, with an emphasis on passive houses. The analysis section of dissertation is organised as follows: "Comparison of Iran and Germany" this first part of the analysis compares these two countries, with an emphasis on climatic conditions, and studies the feasibility of applying German passive house techniques and standards to Iran. In order to provide accurate and detailed results, this dissertation uses several different building energy software tools to evaluate climate data, building and system components and the economics of energy conservation. Dynamic simulation software tools and hourly weather data are also used to calculate the energy consumption of buildings. The energy software tools used in different parts of this analysis match the requirements for different stages of the research. They include EnergyPlus, DesignBuilder, Passive House Planning Package, Climate Consultant, GAEA and Economic Evaluation. ‚ÄúClimate data analysis‚Ä? analyses the local climatic data of Tabriz, to suggest the most appropriate passive design strategies for this city. ‚ÄúPassive houses in Iran‚Äôs climate‚Ä? simulates passive houses in Iran‚Äôs cold climatic region to suggest suitable features for passive houses and the effect of architectural design on passive house energy requirements in this region. It indicates that not only are passive houses climatically suitable for winter conditions in this region, but that they are also more easily achievable, requiring less insulation. However, they do need additional cooling systems. ‚ÄúSimulation of subsoil heat exchanger‚Ä? shows the energy saving potential and economic efficiency of subsoil heat exchangers in Iranian passive houses. To present a simulation of different architectural factors and building elements, "Simulation of architectural elements" searches for the optimal case and the most appropriate application of each of these factors and elements under given conditions. An analysis of the simulations provided in this section shows the behaviour of energy efficiency in relation to different measures or quantities of various architectural factors and building elements. This section offers an explanation and rationalisation of the complex relationships between building energy use and architectural design. ‚ÄúSimulation of Buildings with different Architectural Designs" simulates and compares the energy consumption of a typical building with some other newly designed buildings. The energy demand of the most efficient building is 63% less than the least efficient building available in similar control conditions, but with architectural design as the only variable. This shows that architectural design profoundly affects heating, cooling and therefore the total energy consumption of buildings. This section introduces those architectural factors which reduce the energy consumption of buildings in Iran‚Äôs cold climatic region. There is a big difference in the construction costs (about 50%) for passive and non-passive houses in Iran. Nonetheless, based on the economic evaluation done in ‚ÄúEconomic Analysis‚Ä?, if the passive houses have an energy efficient architectural design, the use of these kinds of buildings is economically very viable when based on international energy costs. However, in view of current subsidisation of fuel, investment for passive houses in Iran is economically not viable at present. The section ‚ÄúMechanical Equipment‚Ä? outlines specifications for heating and cooling equipment which is climatically, economically and technologically appropriate for energy efficient and passive housing in Iran. Gas heat pumps can be integral to mechanical systems for heating and cooling both energy efficient houses and passive houses in Iran. Heater-cooler unit systems are also particularly suitable in this country. In Iran‚Äôs cold climatic region, the energy consumption of a well-insulated, suitably-designed building is only 8.3% of an uninsulated normal house, so the potential for energy saving in buildings is very high. Therefore, to solve this problem the present research strongly suggests using both architectural techniques and insulation materials. Printed version available: Universit√§tsverlag der TU Berlin (www.univerlag.tu-berlin.de)</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der Energieverbrauch in Wohn- und Gesch√§ftsgeb√§uden im Iran betr√§gt mehr als 40 Prozent des gesamten Energieverbrauchs. Die Einf√ºhrung von energieeffizienten H√§usern im Iran h√§tte einen wesentlichen Einfluss auf den Gesamtenergieverbrauch des Landes. Die vorliegende Dissertation konzentriert sich auf die kalte Klimazone des Irans mit kontinentalem Klima und auf die Stadt Tabriz als Fallstudie. Aufgrund der wirtschaftlichen Bedingungen im Iran und insbesondere aufgrund der hochsubventionierten Energiekosten sind Ma√ünahmen zur Energieeinsparung in Geb√§uden durch kostenintensive Verfahren heute nicht wirtschaftlich. Vor diesem Hintergrund liegt der Schwerpunkt dieser Arbeit auf der Verwendung kostenneutraler Methoden sowie kosteng√ºnstiger Energiesparma√ünahmen, insbesondere durch Anwendung architektonischer Ma√ünahmen. Der theoretischeTeil der vorliegenden Dissertation zeigt den Stand der Technik zu den Themengebieten klimagerechte Geb√§ude, passive solare Heizsysteme und zu verschiedenen passiven und hybriden K√ºhlmethoden auf. Anschlie√üend werden die Energiesituation, das Klima und die Architektur im Bereich des Wohnungsbaus im Iran und in Deutschland aufgezeigt und verglichen sowie deutsche Baustandards f√ºr den energieeffizienten Wohnungsbau mit dem Schwerpunkt Passivh√§user vorgestellt. ‚ÄûVergleich Iran - Deutschland‚Äú √ºberschreibt den ersten Schritt der Analyse, die diese beiden L√§nder vergleicht und die Anwendbarkeit deutscher Passivhauskonzepte im Iran untersucht. Als Untersuchungsmethode f√ºr genaue und detaillierte Aussagen nutzt die vorliegende Dissertation verschiedene Softwareprogramme zur dynamischen Simulation und zur Auswertung von Klimadaten, Bau- und Systemkomponenten sowie f√ºr die Ermittlung der Wirtschaftlichkeit in Bezug auf Energiesparma√ünahmen. In den verschiedenen Abschnitten der Untersuchung wurden hierf√ºr je nach Anforderung die Programme EnergyPlus, DesignBuilder, Climate Consultant, PHPP, GAEA und √ñKO-RAT verwendet. Im Abschnitt ‚ÄûKlimadaten Analyse‚Äú wurden sowohl die lokalen Klimadaten wie auch ein psychrometrisches Diagramm verwendet, um die am besten geeigneten passiven Entwurfstrategien f√ºr die Stadt Tabriz zu finden. Der Abschnitt ‚ÄûPassivh√§user f√ºr das Klima des Irans‚Äú simuliert Passivh√§user in der kalten Klimazone des Irans um geeignete Passivh√§user zu entwickeln und die Wirkung des architektonischen Entwurfs auf den Energieverbrauch zu untersuchen. Es deutet darauf hin, dass nicht nur Passivh√§user f√ºr die winterlichen klimatischen Bedingungen dieser Region geeignet sind, sondern dass die Einsparziele im Vergleich zu den deutschen Vorbildern auch leichter erreichbar sind. Allerdings werden zus√§tzliche Ma√ünahmen zur Geb√§udek√ºhlung ben√∂tigt. Im Abschnitt ‚ÄûSimulation von Erdw√§rmetauschern‚Äú wurden die Energieeinsparpotenziale und die Wirtschaftlichkeit von Erdw√§rmetauschern aufgezeigt. Im Abschnitt ‚ÄûSimulation der architektonischen Elemente‚Äú werden verschiedene architektonische Faktoren und Bauelemente untersucht, um deren optimale Konfiguration zu ermitteln. Die Analyse der Simulationen in diesem Abschnitt zeigt das Verhalten der Energieeffizienz in Bezug auf die jeweils verwendeten, unterschiedlichen baulichen Ma√ünahmen und Entwurfsvarianten. Im Abschnitt ‚ÄûSimulation von Geb√§uden mit unterschiedlichem architektonischen Entwurf‚Äú wird bei vergleichender Durchf√ºhrung von Geb√§udesimulationen der Energieverbrauch eines typischen Geb√§udes der Region mit einigen anderen prototypisch neu gestalteten Geb√§uden verglichen. Der Energiebedarf der am effizientesten gestalteten Geb√§ude liegt bei ausschlie√ülicher Ver√§nderung der architektonischen Gestaltung unter sonst vergleichbaren Bedingungen um 64% niedriger als der der aufgef√ºhrten Bestandsgeb√§ude. Es beweist, dass die architektonische Gestaltung den Energieverbrauch von Geb√§uden stark beeinflusst. Es gibt einen gro√üen Unterschied bei den Baukosten (ca. 50%) zwischen Passivh√§usern und der konventionellen Bauweise im Iran. Die Wirtschaftlichkeitsberechnung im Abschnitt ‚Äû√∂konomische Bewertung‚Äú zeigt aber, dass bei Annahme von Weltmarktpreisen f√ºr die zugrundegelegten Energiekosten die Verwendung von Passivh√§usern mit energieeffizienter Architektur eindeutig wirtschaftlich ist. Bei den gegenw√§rtig niedrigen Energiekosten sind aber Investitionen f√ºr Passivh√§user im Iran heute nicht wirtschaftlich. Der Abschnitt ‚ÄûHeiz- und K√ºhlanlage‚Äú schl√§gt Gasw√§rmepumpen und insbesondere ‚ÄûHeater-Cooler-Systems‚Äú als klimatisch, wirtschaftlich und technologisch geeignete Klimaanlagen f√ºr energieeffiziente Geb√§ude im Iran vor. In der kalten Klimaregion des Irans liegt der Energieverbrauch eines wie empfohlen gut isolierten und gut konzipierten Geb√§udes bei nur 8,3% eines konventionellen, nicht isolierten Objektes. Energieeffizientes Bauen weist somit f√ºr diese Region ein au√üergew√∂hnlich hohes Einsparpotenzial auf. Als Kernaussage der Arbeit werden f√ºr diese Region die architektonische Optimierung und die erh√∂hten Nutzung von D√§mmstoffen in Kombination mit einer ge√§nderten F√∂rderstrategie besonders empfohlen. Gedruckte Version im Universit√§tsverlag der TU Berlin (www.univerlag.tu-berlin.de) erschienen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-11-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2363</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22597</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22597</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-7983-2144-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2363/2144_Nasrollahi.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2363/2144_Nasrollahi_US.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
