<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:44:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:195">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:195</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Entwicklung und Anwendung geostatistischer Verfahren zur strukturellen Klassifizierung von Forstbeständen in hochauflösenden Daten der HRSC-A</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Development and application of geostatistical methods for forest structure classification in high resolution data of the HRSC-A</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hese, Sören Mathias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Auf dem Gebiet der flugzeuggestützten Fernerkundungssensoren sehr hoher geometrischer Auflösung vollzieht sich eine Umorientierung von der Luftbildkamera hin zu digitalen Stereokamerasystemen mit multispektralen Kanälen. Mit der vollautomatischen Ableitung orthoprojizierter Multispektraldaten und digitaler Oberflächenmodelle stehen in Zukunft Datensätze zur Verfügung, die in den Bereichen Fernerkundung, Geographische Informationssysteme, Photogrammetrie und Kartographie zu erheblichen Veränderungen führen werden. Automatische Klassifikationsmethoden oder Objekterkennungsverfahren für geometrisch sehr hochauflösende Fernerkundungsdaten im Bereich von 15 bis 40 cm sind jedoch bisher für viele Anwendungen, so auch für die Forstfernerkundung, nur ansatzweise verfügbar. Bekannte pixelorientierte Klassifizierungsverfahren, die bisher in der Forstfernerkundung genutzt wurden und aus Entwicklungen für geringer auflösende Satellitenbilddaten hervorgegangen sind, können nur bedingt erfolgreich für die Auswertung sehr hochauflösender Daten eingesetzt werden. Einzelne Pixel stellen nicht mehr eine Mischung unterschiedlicher Objekte dar, sondern bilden vielmehr Teile eines einzigen Objektes. Diese Komponenten weisen oft keine objektspezifischen spektralen Charakteristika auf. Dagegen hat die räumliche Anordnung der Bildelemente einen sehr hohen Beschreibungswert für die Ableitung der im Forstanwendungsbereich relevanten Objekteigenschaften wie z.B. Bestandsdichte, Kronendurchmesser, Bestandsstruktur oder Bestandsart. Es besteht daher für viele Anwendungsbereiche ein hoher Entwicklungsbedarf für Verfahren, die Nachbarschaften von Pixelwerten in hohem Maße berücksichtigen, um Objekte zu erfassen, die außerdem objektorientiert vorgehen und die hohe spektrale Variabilität von Objekten und Klassen in geometrisch sehr hochauflösenden Bilddatensätzen bei einer Auswertung untersuchen und nutzen. In dieser Arbeit werden die multispektralen Daten, die Stereodaten und die digitalen Oberflächenmodelle des digitalen Stereozeilenscanners HRSC-A (High Resolution Stereo Camera-Airborne) hinsichtlich der Eignung für eine Beschreibung der strukturellen Eigenschaften von Forstbeständen untersucht. Digitale Oberflächenmodelle, die mit stereoabbildenden Sensoren ableitbar sind, stellen für die Forstwirtschaft potentiell eine sehr hochwertige Informationsquelle dar, da die vertikalen Bestandsstrukturen wirtschaftlich wichtige Parameter (z.B. Bestandshöhe und Holzvolumen) ableitbar machen können. In dieser Arbeit wird das Potential digitaler Bestandsoberflächenmodelle daher hinsichtlich einer derartigen Anwendung im direkten Vergleich mit Laserscannerdatensätzen untersucht. Ergebnisse zeigen, daß Oberflächenmodelle von Nadelbeständen nicht mit ausreichend hoher Genauigkeit aus HRSC-A Daten ableitbar sind, um die Wuchshöhe von einzelnen Bäumen und Beständen automatisch festzustellen. Die Geländehöhe in älteren Nadelbeständen ist nur im Bereich größerer Bestandslücken erkennbar, was die Berechnung eines Bestandshöhenmodells mit nur wenigen, inhomogen verteilten Stützpunkten bedingt. Auch durch das indirekte photogrammetrische Verfahren der Bestimmung von Objekthöhen treten bei Forstoberflächen Ungenauigkeiten bei der Wiedergabe von Kronenhöhen auf. Eine Ableitung bestandsspezifischer Eigenschaften der vertikalen Strukturen eines Forstgebietes aus HRSC-A Bestandsoberflächenmodellen ist daher nur sehr eingeschränkt möglich. Aufgrund dieser Einschränkungen wird ein erweitertes Verfahren entwickelt, das die hochauflösenden Multiblickwinkeldaten und Multispektraldaten des Kamerasystems HRSC-A nutzt, um bestandsstrukturspezifische Texturparameter abzuleiten. Die Beleuchtungsbedingungen und die Blickwinkel der Stereo- und Multispektralkanäle bestimmen die Textureigenschaften und die Geometrieveränderungen in Bilddatensätzen von Forstbeständen in erheblichem Maße. Die so verursachten richtungsabhängigen Eigenschaften sind bei der Ableitung von Texturparametern zu berücksichtigen. Zur Untersuchung der Pixelnachbarschaften wird die geostatistische Variogrammfunktion genutzt. Eine Miteinbeziehung von Beleuchtungsrichtung und blickwinkelbedingten Objektgeometrieveränderungen bei der Berücksichtigung richtungsabhängiger Eigenschaften für eine Bestandsstrukturklassifikation wird über die gesonderte Untersuchung der entsprechenden Winkel für Beleuchtungsrichtung (Azimut) und Flugrichtung bzw. den Objektversatz in allen Stereokanälen ermöglicht. Trennbare und hochdimensionale Merkmalssignaturen, bestehend aus modellierten Variogramm-rangewerten, können so für einzelne Bestandsstrukturen abgeleitet werden. Dies führt zu hohen Klassifikationsgenauigkeiten für Bestandsstrukturen von bis zu 93%. Durch die Reduzierung auf geometrische Merkmale ist auch eine Ableitung von Bestandsobjekten durch eine Segmentierung der Texturmerkmale zu Bestandsregionen möglich. Das so entwickelte Verfahren zeigt ein hohes Anwendungspotential in der Beschreibung der strukturellen Diversität von Beständen, in der Ableitung von Bestandesgrenzen und der Differenzierung der Bestandsdichte. So ist der Einsatz in den Anwendungsbereichen Forstinventur und Biodiversitätserfassung denkbar. Durch die Integration des Verfahrens in das Geoinformationssystem GRASS (Geographic Resources Analysis Support System) können externe Informationen (z.B. Bestandesgrenzen aus der Forstinventur) genutzt werden. So kann das entwickelte Verfahren der Variogramm Textur Klassifikation für die Erfassung von Wachstumsunterschieden oder Strukturdiversitätsveränderungen über bereits bestehende Informationen der Bestandesgrenzen genutzt werden. Dies zeigt auch Anwendungsmöglichkeiten im Bereich der Landschaftsstrukturerfassung. Geometrisch hochauflösende Zeilenscannerdaten zeigen somit durch die konstante Multiblickwinkel-geometrie und auch durch den geringen öffnungswinkel des optischen Systems der HRSC-A ein hohes Potential bei der Ableitung von Forstbestandseigenschaften über Textur erfassende Methoden. Mit der Operationalisierung derartiger anwendungsspezifischer Methoden können aus hochauflösenden Fernerkundungsdaten in Zukunft Informationen bereitgestellt werden, die bisher terrestrisch erstellt oder visuell aus Luftbilddaten generiert wurden. Ein entscheidender Schritt in diese Richtung wird die Integration von Methoden der Geoinformationssysteme und anwendungsspezifischen Verfahren der Fernerkundung in Form von hybriden und objektorientierten Ansätzen darstellen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In the field of airborne high-resolution remote sensing a paradigm shift from analogue aerial photographic systems towards digital sensor systems with stereo and multispectral imaging capabilities is recognisable. In addition there is a trend towards the use of high-resolution data of orbital remote-sensing systems. New strategies and adapted tools for the analyses of high-resolution remote sensing data for different applications and in the field of forest remote sensing are up to now not available. There is however an increased interest of the scientific community in relating textural information to biophysical properties ever since the appearance of the first airborne stereo line scanners in the 80's. The problem which dominates the analysis of high-resolution data and which confuses most traditional methodologies is the very much increased interclass spectral variability compared with low-resolution satellite scanner data. Well known pixel-based supervised and unsupervised classification methods used for the analysis of low-resolution satellite data cannot be applied with much success. Pixels in very high resolution data do not represent a mixture of objects anymore. In fact pixels now represent a small portion of one object which is not a representative measure of reflectance for the object or a forest stand attribute anymore as reflectance depends also on illumination direction, sensor viewing geometry, object shape, object structure and surface. In contrast the spatial distribution and neighbourhood of pixels is now of increased interest. The spatial information can be used to measure important forest stand characteristics (for example stand density, crown diameter and structural information of forest stands). This leads to image processing methods which focus on the investigation of neighbourhood relationships of pixel values by analysing and classifying texture or which define object geometry and location at first (segmentation) and analyse their spectral properties thereafter (classification). In this work a new methodology is developed in order to use high-resolution stereo scanner data in the applicational field of forestry. Main purpose is the classification and differentiation of forest stands. High-resolution data shows a potential for the differentiation of stand properties, which is of interest for forest inventory, monitoring and applications of landscape structure analysis. Digital stereo line scanner cameras also provide panchromatic stereo information which is used to derive digital surface models which could be valuable information source for stand height and for the prediction of timber volume. In this work the potential of HRSC-A digital stand surface models is analysed. Tree heights and stand surface information of laser scanner surface models and HRSC-A surface models are compared with terrestrial measurements. One finding is that indirect measurements of object heights in photogrammetric generated HRSC-A digital surface models do not reproduce tree height of spruce stands with adequate accuracy. Besides terrain height in medium dense stands is not observable. This reduces the applicational potential of digital surface models in forestry as absolute stand height models cannot be derived with sufficient accuracy. Analysis of vertical properties of stand surfaces and attribution to specific stand structures and species is therefore complicated. Due to this restriction a new enhanced method of texture classification is developed that uses the multiviewangle data characteristics of the HRSC-A stereo and multispectral data. The basis of the textural analysis of the multiviewangle data is the variogram and its characteristic parameters: "range" and "sill". The range parameter of the variogram as a measure of auto correlation and textural coarseness is calculated for variograms in illumination direction, in flight direction and perpendicular to these directions. This captures the viewangle and sun azimuth dependent texture anisotropy in high resolution HRSC-A stereo data. Stand structure can be differentiated and classified using these modelled multidirectional variogram parameters with success. This is performed using range values as n-dimensional geometrical signatures generated from a multi-layer range raster data set (in a similar way as hyperspectral data spectra are used). This method shows potential for a supervised stand structure classification using range signatures (with up to 93% accuracy) (variogram texture classification -VTC). Variogram texture measures can also be used with success for a stand segmentation when range values are used for a region growing and region merging strategy. Possible applications are forest inventory, estimation of biodiversity and as a measure for structural stand diversity in the context of landscape metrics methodologies. By integrating this method into the geographic information system GRASS (Geographic Resources Analysis Support System) enhanced capabilities of map operations following the concept of Tomlin (1990) and zonal functionality can be applied (area thresholding). This increases the attribution accuracy furthermore and allows the integration of vector data formats into application scenarios of the proposed method. This opens the perspective for applications of variogram texture classification for monitoring purposes or change detection of structural diversity of forest stands. If forest stands can be investigated as objects using external information about stand borders than structural homogeneity can be analysed with success. Another advantage of the integration of the presented method for forest stand structure mapping into GRASS is the combined use with landscape metrics tools. High-resolution multispectral and stereo scanner data of the HRSC-A show a high potential for textural analysis of forest stands. This is explained with high geometric accuracy of the data correction, low across-track viewing angles, stereo viewing-angles with a defined geometry and multispectral image information. The application-specific analysis of high-resolution remote sensing data (including the data from high-resolution orbital sensor systems) will benefit from the development of integrated RS/GIS systems that use GIS functionality together with specialised image processing tools (e.g. the VTC) in a hybrid and object oriented style.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2002-05-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/195</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-1902</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-1902</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/195/hese_soeren.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
