<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2088">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2088</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:150</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Reactive Embitterment. Conceptualization, Relevancy and Differentiation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Reaktive Verbitterung. Konzeptualisierung, Relevanz und Differenzierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rotter, Max</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:150</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Exceptional, though normal negative life events like severe illness, divorce, occupational strain, or unemployment can lead to severe and prolonged psychological disorders. One specific emotional reaction to stressful live events is embitterment, a feeling known to most people (Alexander, 1966). The feeling of bitterness is always associated with a burning sense of unfairness or injustice, a protesting feeling of having been wronged without cause. It signifies an aggressive protest against a felt and perceived injustice, and is a goad to desperate, sometimes reckless, efforts to gain redress. Prolonged embitterment can become pathological when it reaches greater intensity and is accompanied by additional symptoms. Linden (2003) coined the term ‚Äúposttraumatic embitterment disorder (PTED)‚Ä? to conceptualize this specific reaction type as a distinct sub-class of adjustment disorder. The present theses is a compilation of studies which were carried out with the aim to obtain objective information on reactive embitterment and PTED. In a first step, the PTED Self-Rating Scale (PTED Scale) which asks for prolonged and disabling embitterment reactions in the aftermath of negative life events was developed. The aim was to provide an instrument which allows screening for reactive embitterment in the wake of stressful life events. Moreover, data on the epidemiology of reactive embitterment in clinical and nonclinical populations are presented. In addition, the prevalence of reactive embitterment in an administrative sample was explored. The event job loss was used as a common negative life event for all participants. Furthermore, empirically derived diagnostic criteria and an instrument which allows a standardised diagnosis of PTED were introduced. In a next step, the continuum from reactive embitterment as an unspecific symptom towards reactive embitterment as a self-contained disorder (PTED) was analyzed, and the context (triggered vs. unspecific) in which embitterment arises was investigated in a large psychosomatic inpatient sample. Subsequently, the psychological and emotional profile of patients with PTED was described, and PTED patients were compared with patients with other mental disorders as regards quality, distinguishability and intensity of psychopathology as well as posttraumatic symptoms. In all, the results show that reactive embitterment is a frequent emotion that deserves more scientific and clinical attention. Individuals who react with prolonged embitterment to a negative life event can develop impressive psychological symptoms. Embitterment is an emotion which in many cases does not cease via self-regulation, and can continue unabated. It is a distinct state of mood, which differs from depression, hopelessness, and also anger as such, though it can share common emotional features or go parallel with each of these other emotions. Similar to anxiety and depression, embitterment must be understood as a dimensional phenomenon, which becomes pathological when reaching greater intensities, when it is associated with additional symptoms, and when daily role performance is impaired. The concept of PTED can help further subclassify and specify adjustment and reactive disorders. With the PTED Scale a reliable and valid measure for embitterment as an emotional reaction to a negative life event is provided, which can be used as a screening instrument in large populations. Moreover, the diagnostic interview for PTED fulfils the need for a standardized diagnostic instrument.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Belastende, wenn auch lebenstypische Ereignisse wie schwere Krankheit, Scheidung, berufliche Probleme oder Arbeitslosigkeit k√∂nnen zu erheblichen und prolongierten psychischen St√∂rungen f√ºhren. Ein Beispiel sind anhaltende Verbitterungszust√§nde. Verbitterung erw√§chst aus Gef√ºhlen und Gedanken der Ungerechtigkeit, Herabw√ºrdigung und Benachteiligung zusammen mit dem Impuls, zur√ºckzuschlagen bzw. Rache zu √ºben. Betroffene k√∂nnen sich gedanklich nicht vom kritischen Lebensereignis l√∂sen und tragen durch die st√§ndige kognitive Wiederholung des Erlebnisses zu einer Verfestigung ihres Zustandes bei. Verbitterung muss dann als pathologisch angesehen werden, wenn sie lange anh√§lt, eine hohe Intensit√§t erreicht und von zus√§tzlichen Symptomen begleitet wird. Linden (2003) konzeptualisierte die ‚Äûposttraumatische Verbitterungsst√∂rung (engl.: posttraumatic embitterment disorder; PTED)‚Äú um diesen spezifischen Reaktionstyp zu beschreiben. Bei der vorliegende Arbeit handelt es sich um eine Zusammenstellung von Studien die alle mit dem Ziel durchgef√ºhrt wurden, empirische Information √ºber reaktive Verbitterung und PTED zu erheben. Die PTED Skala wird als ein Screening- Instrument zur Erfassung von reaktiver Verbitterung vorgestellt. Au√üerdem werden epidemiologische Daten zur Pr√§valenz reaktiver Verbitterung in klinischen und nicht klinischen Stichproben dargestellt und Verbitterung als Reaktion auf einen Arbeitsplatzverlust und Arbeitslosigkeit untersucht. Des weiteren werden empirisch abgeleitete diagnostische Kriterien und ein standardisiertes diagnostisches Interview f√ºr PTED eingef√ºhrt und das Kontinuum von Verbitterung als emotionaler Zustand bis hin zu einer eigenst√§ndigen St√∂rung in einer klinischen Stichprobe untersucht. Anschlie√üend wird das emotionale und psychopathologische Profil von PTED- Patienten beschrieben und dem von Patienten mit anderen psychischen St√∂rungen gegen√ºber gestellt. Die Ergebnisse zeigen, dass reaktive Verbitterung ein weit verbreitetes und h√§ufiges Ph√§nomen ist, das mehr wissenschaftliche und klinische Aufmerksamkeit verdient. Verbitterung ist eine Emotion eigener Qualit√§t, die sich deutlich von Depressivit√§t, Hoffnungslosigkeit oder √Ñrger abgrenzen l√§sst. Personen die mit chronischer Verbitterung auf ein negatives Lebensereignis reagieren, k√∂nnen schwere psychopathologische Symptome entwickeln. √Ñhnlich wie Angst oder Depression muss man Verbitterung als ein dimensionales Ph√§nomen verstehen, das bei hoher Intensit√§t, zus√§tzlichen Symptomen und Einschr√§nkungen in der Alltagsbew√§ltigung, pathologische Ausma√üe annehmen kann. Verbitterung ist, √§hnlich wie z.B. Angst, ein h√§ufiges unspezifisch Symptom bei verschiedenen psychischen St√∂rungen. Nur wenn die Verbitterungsreaktion kausal einem spezifischen Ereignis zugeordnet werden kann und weitere Bedingungen erf√ºllt sind, stellt reaktive Verbitterung eine eigenst√§ndige St√∂rung i.S. der posttraumatischen Verbitterungsst√∂rung dar. Das Konzept der PTED kann helfen, die unscharfe Kategorie der Anpassungsst√∂rungen weiter zu spezifizieren. Mit der PTED Skale wird ein reliables und valides Instrument zur Erfassung von reaktiver Verbitterung bereitgestellt und das Diagnostische Interview f√ºr PTED erf√ºllt den Bedarf nach einem standardisierten diagnostischen Instrument f√ºr PTED.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/vnd.ms-excel</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2088</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21933</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21933</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2088/original_rotter_max.doc.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2088/rotter_max.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
