<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:44Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3796">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3796</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-05</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:150</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Designing Speech Output for In-car Infotainment Applications Based on a Cognitive Model of Attention Allocation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Gestaltung von Sprachausgaben für automotive Anwendungen basierend auf einem kognitionspsychologischen Modell für Aufmerksamkeitsausrichtung </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Niemann, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:150</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Drivers tend to glance at the display of in-car infotainment systems despite the presence of speech output. The SEEV Model by Wickens et al. (2003) defines parameters influencing attention allocation towards events in dynamic environments. Analysing the SEEV Model provides insights on which of the parameters of speech output have disadvantages compared to visual output. In two driving simulator experiments, it was tested whether increasing or decreasing the deducted parameters of the SEEV Model for speech output by means of improving the speech output in various respects actually decreases attention allocation to the display. It was shown that increasing the relevant information content (corresponding to the parameters expectancy and value) for speech as well as decreasing the time effort (which corresponds to the parameter effort) of speech compared to a baseline condition leads towards lower percentage dwell time to the display. Next, it was shown that a conscious motor action performed to request for speech output (corresponding to the parameter effort) decreases attention allocation towards the display in situations whereby the secondary task gets interrupted by a highly demanding driving task. Based on theses insights, design recommendations for speech output were deducted and implemented in a prototype with several infotainment applications. In another driving simulator experiment, it was observed that the design recommendations actually reduced attention allocation towards the display compared to a common speech output design of in-car infotainment systems. The design recommendations to reduce the time effort of speech output were again evaluated regarding their influence on the development of users’ mental models. Finally, it was tested whether increasing the hedonic quality of speech output also leads towards less time glancing at the display. On the one hand, the conducted experiments showed which parameters of the SEEV Model could be influenced for speech output to decrease attention allocation to the display of a multimodal in-car infotainment system. On the other hand, the results provided insights regarding the applicability of specific SEEV Model parameters to the auditory modality since so far the model had only been evaluated with respect to the visual modality. Finally, it was shown that also hedonic aspects of speech output do indeed influence attention allocation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Trotz Verfügbarkeit von Sprachausgaben schauen Fahrer vermehrt auf das Display von Infotainmentsystemen im Fahrzeug. Das SEEV-Modell von Wickens et al. (2003) definiert Parameter, welche die Aufmerksamkeitsausrichtung in dynamischen Umgebungen vohersagen sollen. Eine Analyse des SEEV-Modells liefert Hinweise darauf, welche dieser Parameter als Indikatoren für Nachteile einer Sprachausgabe gegenüber einer visuellen Darstellung herangezogen werden können. In zwei Fahrsimulatorstudien wurde getestet, ob durch eine Veränderung der Parameterwerte des SEEV-Modells in Richtung einer Verbesserung der Sprachausgabe, die Aufmerksamkeitsausrichtung zum Display gesenkt werden kann. Es hat sich gezeigt, dass eine Erhöhung des relevanten Informationsgehalts (entspricht den Parametern Expectancy und Value) sowie eine Verringerung des zeitlichen Aufwands (entspricht dem Parameter Effort) bei Sprachausgaben tatsächlich die prozentuale Blickdauer zum Display gegenüber einer Baseline-Bedingung reduzieren können. Darüber hinaus wurde gezeigt, dass eine bewusste motorische Handlung, um die Sprachausgabe anzufordern (entspricht dem Parameter Effort), ebenfalls die Aufmerksamkeitsausrichtung auf das Display minimieren kann. Dies zeigt sich allerdings nur in Situationen in denen die Zweitaufgabe durch eine hoch beanspruchende Fahraufgabe unterbrochen wird. Basierend auf den gewonnenen Erkenntnissen wurden Gestaltungshinweise für Sprachausgaben abgeleitet und in einem Prototyp mit unterschiedlichen Infotainmentapplikationen implementiert. In einer weiteren Fahrsimulatorstudie wurde nachgewiesen, dass die Integration der Gestaltungshinweise gegenüber der herkömmlichen Auslegung von Sprachausgaben bei Infotainmentsystemen im Fahrzeug, die Blickzuwendungen zu einem Display reduzieren können. Die Gestaltungshinweise zur Reduzierung des zeitlichen Aufwands von Sprache wurden darüber hinaus hinsichtlich ihres Einflusses auf die Entwicklung des mentalen Modells von Nutzern evaluiert. Schlussendlich wurde getestet ob die Verbesserung hedonischer Aspekte (entspricht dem Parameter Value) ebenfalls dazu führt, dass prozentual weniger Zeit auf das Display des Prototypen geschaut wird. Einerseits zeigen die durchgeführten Experimente welche Parameter des SEEV-Modells für Sprachausgaben beeinflusst werden können, um die Aufmerksamkeitsausrichtung auf visuelle Ausgaben von multimodalen Infotainmentsystemen im Fahrzeug zu minimieren. Andererseits liefern die Ergebnisse den Beweis, dass einzelne Parameter des SEEV-Modells auch auf die akustische Modalität anwendbar sind. Außerdem wurde gezeigt, dass hedonische Aspekte die Aufmerksamkeitsausrichtung beeinflussen können.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-06-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3796</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-37963</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-37963</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3796/niemann_julia.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
