<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:24Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2850">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2850</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Environmental Assessment and the Greening of NAFTA</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Das Instrument der Umweltprüfung in der Ökologisierung des NAFTA</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Podhora, Aranka</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In 1994, the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) between Canada, the US and Mexico entered into force. For the first time, a trade agreement was accompanied by an environmental side agreement, the North American Agreement on Environmental Cooperation (NAAEC). The NAAEC is an agreement of trinational environmental cooperation, mainly covering different aspects and ideas of cooperation. It is implemented by the trilateral Commission for Environmental Cooperation (CEC). NAAEC and CEC do not have any supranational powers, e.g. concerning the development of environmental instruments. Further, their tasks are not necessarily linked with greening NAFTA. The NAAEC refers to environmental assessment, to its importance and to its objectives with respect to: - domestic environmental assessment as self-commitment of the nation states on the domestic level (here interpreted as project environmental impact assessment and strategic environmental assessment for policies, plans and programs) - transboundary environmental impact assessment with tasks for the CEC Council nd the nation states and - as analysis for the NAFTA as trade agreement guided by the CEC (ex-post NAFTA environmental assessment). The dissertation analysed a) the interaction of the three types of environmental assessment and NAFTA as trade agreement and b) the individual influence of the governance level (with view to multi-level governance). The thesis built on extensive literature and internet search, expert interviews mainly in Canada and Mexico and two case studies from the NAFTA environmental assessment. The results showed that the NAAEC creates a link between NAFTA and NAFTA environmental assessment. The analysis of the case studies, however, also illustrated an interaction between project environmental impact assessment/ strategic environmental assessment and NAFTA. Therefore, the dissertation developed the three-step analytic, adaptation and monitoring cycle "NAFTA's Green Impact". On the one side, the results of the studies of NAFTA environmental assessment can be integrated into project environmental impact assessment/ strategic environmental assessment. On the other hand, both instruments may gather further data related to NAFTA to fill analytic gaps within the NAFTA environmental assessment. The strong interaction among the three types of environmental assessment and a back up through various governance levels allows for a contribution to greening NAFTA.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das Nordamerikanische Freihandelsabkommen (NAFTA) trat 1994 zwischen Kanada, den USA und Mexiko in Kraft. Erstmals wurde dabei ein Handelsabkommen durch ein Umweltabkommen ergänzt, dem North American Agreement on Environmental Cooperation (NAAEC 1993). Das NAAEC widmet sich der Umweltkooperation zwischen den drei Unterzeichnerstaaten, die durch die Commission for Environmetnal Cooperation (CEC) als trinationaler Kommission geleitet wird. NAAEC und CEC machen dabei keine verbindlichen Vorgaben für nationale Entwicklungen oder Instrumente. Auch stehen die Aufgaben nicht notwendigerweise mit der ökologischen Gestaltung des NAFTA in Bezug. Die Instrumente der Umweltprüfung sind auf drei Ebenen in das Umweltabkommen eingebunden: • als Selbstverpflichtung für die Nationalstaaten im Hinblick auf allgemeine Ansätze der Umweltprüfung (hier interpretiert als Ex-ante-Umweltverträglichkeitsprüfung und Strategische Umweltprüfung – UVP und SUP) • als Rahmen zur grenzüberschreitenden Ex-ante-Umweltverträglichkeitsprüfung mit Aufgaben für die CEC und die Nationalstaaten sowie • als Prüfansatz für die Analyse der Umweltfolgen des NAFTA (Ex-post-Handelsprüfung) unter Federführung der CEC. Die Dissertation analysierte dabei a) das Zusammenspiel dieser drei Arten von Umweltprüfung mit dem NAFTA als Handelsabkommen und b) den jeweiligen Einfluss der Staatsebenen auf der Grundlage von Multi-level Governance. Die Arbeit baute dabei auf umfangreichen Literatur- und Internetrecherchen, zahlreichen Expert/innen-Interviews v.a. in Kanada und Mexiko sowie zwei Fallstudien der NAFTA-Umweltprüfung auf. Die Dissertation kam dabei zu dem Ergebnis, dass die Vorgaben im NAAEC lediglich bei der NAFTA-Umweltprüfung einen Zusammenhang mit dem Handelsabkommen selbst herstellen. In der Analyse der Fallstudien zeigte sich jedoch zudem eine deutliche Korrelation zwischen NAFTA und Strategischer Umweltprüfung sowie Umweltverträglichkeitsprüfung. Das Ergebnis der Arbeit ist daher der dreistufige Analyse-Anpassungs- und Monitoring-Kreislauf „NAFTA’S GREEN IMPACT“. Darin werden die Ergebnisse der NAFTA-Umweltprüfung einerseits in die Analyse der SUP sowie der UVP einbezogen. Andererseits können im Rahmen der SUP und UVP weitere handelsrelevante Daten erhoben werden, um Analyselücken der NAFTA-Umweltprüfung zu schließen. Durch die enge Verzahnung der drei Arten der Umweltprüfung und die Rückkopplung zu verschiedenen Governance-Ebenen können diese gezielt zur Ökologisierung des NAFTA einsetzt werden. Das Konzept wird auf verschiedenen Staatsebenen im Rahmen von Multi-level Governance umgesetzt. Die CEC bildet hierbei v.a. den übergeordneten strukturgebenden Rahmen für „NAFTA’S GREEN IMPACT“ und die Nationalstaaten unterstützen die Anwendung des Konzepts im Rahmen der SUP und UVP. Zudem tragen die regionale Ebene und öffentliche Sphäre mit Expert/innenwissen bei.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-04-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2850</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2850/podhora_aranka.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
