<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:11Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2108">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2108</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Acid buffering and sulfate retention in SO2-impacted Andosols - a multi-methodological approach</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Säurepufferung und Sulfatretention in SO2-beeinflussten Andosolen - eine Kombination unterschiedlicher Methoden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Herre, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Large deposition of sulfuric acid to soils in close vicinity of active volcanoes affects the dynamics of sulfur and other nutrients and can have toxic effects on animals, plants and microorganisms. Both acid buffering and sulfur retention processes are hardly investigated for Andosols of the (sub-)tropics, however. The objectives of my study were (i) to estimate the contributions of different processes to the effective acid neutralization capacity and (ii) to determine the relevance of adsorption and basic aluminum sulfate (BAS) precipitation for the total sulfate retention in SO2-impacted Andosols. Acid buffering was studied in short-term pHstat laboratory experiments with samples taken at two sites which differ in climatic conditions and soils (Masaya: wet-dry cycles; vitric Andosols developing towards the sil-andic subtype; Poás: perhumid; vitric Andosols developing towards the alu-andic subtype). Additionally, samples from a transect of increasing acid input at Poás were analyzed by infrared spectroscopy (IR) and scanning electron microscopy with energy dispersive X-ray analysis (SEM-EDX) to identify the processes which are relevant for the long-term acid buffering under field conditions. For the identification of S retention processes a combination of macroscopic field and laboratory experiments with synthetic allophane and glass were combined with microscopic and spectroscopic techniques (SEM-EDX; S K-edge X-ray absorption near edge spectroscopy, XANES; simultaneous thermal analysis coupled with mass spectrometry, STA-MS; IR). The suitability of STA-MS to differentiate S pools in samples was evaluated before by the analysis of synthetic reference compounds in pure form and in mixtures with simple matrix components (allophane, SiO2, Al2O3). Thereby I could show that organically bound sulfur, basaluminite, alunite and adsorbed sulfate can be distinguished from each other in pure form by STA-MS. However, matrix components distort STA-MS signals thus limiting this method to samples of simple and known matrix composition. The protonation of variable charge of organic matter and mineral / glass dissolution dominate the short-term acid buffering at pH 3.0 in vitric Andosols. Protonation of variable charge is of larger relevance in Poás than in Masaya samples due to larger contents of organic matter at Poás. Accumulation of base cations and aluminum in solution hamper mineral weathering. This is likely the case during the dry season at Masaya leading to a decrease in the effective acid neutralization capacity for this site. Under field conditions, protonation of variable charge is effectively reversed by cation and aluminum release from mineral / glass weathering which is thus the dominant long-term acid buffering process at both study sites. After an 18 months field experiment close to Masaya and Poás Volcanoes no measurable in situ BAS formation could be detected on surfaces of glass particles. Contrastingly, BAS contributed with 11% and 19% to the total sulfur retention by synthetic allophane exposed in soils close to Masaya and Poás Volcanoes, respectively. The presence of BAS in allophane samples exposed at Poás showed that large organic matter contents and perhumid climatic conditions do not impede BAS formation. Laboratory pHstat experiments showed that decreasing pH, increasing sulfate load and increasing time tend to increase the relevance of BAS for S retention by allophane but the effects were small and adsorption processes dominated with 86% to 98% the total sulfate retention. The observed slow increase in sulfate adsorption at pH 4.5 within 6 months could be attributed to an increased availability of existing adsorption sites due to silica depolymerization and desorption and to the formation of new adsorption sites due to an increase in defect sites of the allophane spherules. Although BAS precipitation increases the S retention capacity of SO2-impacted allophane containing Andosols, no measurable effect on the S extractability could be identified in laboratory experiments. Whether in situ formed BAS decrease the sulfate extractability deserves further investigation. Additionally, the elucidation of the process underlying BAS precipitation, i.e. surface precipitation or solution supersaturation in void spaces, would help to predict the effects of further parameters – as e.g. the concentrations of fluoride, DOC or phosphate or the allophane aggregation degree – on BAS formation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Deposition von Schwefelsäure auf Böden in der Umgebung aktiver Vulkane beeinflusst den S-Haushalt sowie die Dynamik anderer Nährelemente und kann toxisch auf Tiere, Pflanzen und Mikroorganismen wirken. Die Prozesse der Säurepufferung und der S-Retention sind für vulkanische Böden der (Sub)tropen kaum untersucht. Die Ziele meiner Arbeit waren deshalb, (i) die Relevanz verschiedener Prozesse für die Säurepufferung abzuschätzen und (ii) die Bedeutung der Sulfatadsorption und der Fällung von basischen Aluminium-Hydroxosulfaten (BAS) für die S-Retention in SO2-beeinflussten vulkanischen Böden zu bestimmen. Pufferprozesse wurden mithilfe von Kurzzeit-pHstat-Versuchen an Bodenproben zweier klimatisch und bodenkundlich unterschiedlicher Standorte identifiziert (Masaya: wechselfeucht; Präsenz von Allophan; Poás: perhumid; Dominanz von Al-Humus-Komplexen). Zusätzlich wurden für den Standort Poás Bodenproben entlang eines Transektes abnehmender Säuredeposition mithilfe von IR-Spektroskopie (IR) und Rasterelektronenmikroskopie (SEM-EDX) untersucht, um die Relevanz der zuvor identifizierten Pufferprozesse für die Säureneutralisation unter Freilandbedingungen zu prüfen. Für die Untersuchung der S-Retentionsprozesse habe ich makroskopische Freiland- und Laborexperimente mit synthetischem Allophan und Glas mit spektroskopischen und mikroskopischen Methoden kombiniert (SEM-EDX; Röntgenabsorptionsspektroskopie, S K-edge XANES; Thermische Analyse gekoppelt mit Massenspektroskopie, STA-MS; IR). Die Eignung von STA-MS für die Identifizierung verschiedener S-Pools in Böden habe ich zuvor anhand der Analyse synthetischer Referenzsubstanzen in Reinform und in Mischung mit Mineralen (Allophan, SiO2, Al2O3) getestet. Dabei zeigte sich, dass mit dieser Methode Basaluminit, Alunit, Estersulfate und an Allophan adsorbiertes Sulfat in Reinform voneinander unterschieden werden können, die Methode jedoch auf Proben sehr einfacher und bekannter Matrixzusammensetzung beschränkt ist. Die Protonierung funktioneller Gruppen der organischen Substanz und die Auflösung von silikatischen Mineralen und Glas dominieren die schnelle Säurepufferung in vitric Andosolen. Aufgrund höherer Gehalte an organischer Substanz ist deren Protonierung für den Standort Poás bedeutender als am Masaya. Die Anreicherung von basischen Kationen und Aluminium in der Bodenlösung hemmt die Mineralverwitterung, was insbesondere während der Trockenzeit am Standort Masaya zu einer Erniedrigung der Säurepufferkapazität führen kann. Unter Freilandbedingungen wird die kurzzeitige Protonierung variabler Ladungen durch die Freisetzung von basischen Kationen und Aluminium bei der Mineral- oder Glasverwitterung rückgängig gemacht, so dass Verwitterungsprozesse die Langzeitpufferung von Säureeinträgen an diesen Standorten dominieren. In situ gebildete BAS konnten nach 18-monatiger Exposition von synthetischem Allophan und Glas in Böden nahe der Vulkane Masaya und Poás nur an Allophanproben identifiziert werden, in denen sie mit 11% (Masaya) und 19% (Poás) zur Gesamt-S-Retention beitrugen. Perhumide Bedingungen und hohe Gehalte an organischer Substanz, wie sie am Standort Poás vorliegen, verhindern somit die BAS-Bildung nicht. Obwohl pH-Erniedrigung, höhere Sulfatkonzentrationen und längere Versuchszeiten in pHstat-Laborversuchen mit synthetischem Allophan tendenziell zu einer Zunahme von BAS führten, waren die Effekte als gering einzustufen und Adsorption dominierte die Sulfatretention mit 86% - 98%. Eine langsame Zunahme der Sulfatadsorption bei pH 4.5 im Laufe von 6 Monaten konnte ich auf eine Freilegung existierender Adsorptionsplätze (durch die Depolymerisierung und Desorption von Si) und die Bildung neuer Adsorptionsplätze (durch die Zunahme der Allophan-Fehlstellen) zurückführen. Die Fällung von BAS erhöht die Sulfatretentionskapazität SO2-beeinflusster vulkanischer Böden, die Sulfatextrahierbarkeit wird dadurch zumindest in Laborversuchen jedoch nicht beeinflusst. Ob in situ gebildete BAS die Sulfatextrahierbarkeit erniedrigen, bedarf weiterer Untersuchungen. Zusätzlich sollte der Mechanismus, der der BAS-Bildung zugrunde liegt (Bildung von Oberflächenpräzipitaten oder Lösungsübersättigung in Mikro- und Mesoporen), aufgeklärt werden. Dadurch könnte der Einfluss weiterer Faktoren auf die BAS-Bildung, wie z.B. der Präsenz von Fluorid, DOC oder Phosphat oder des Allophan-Aggregierungsgrades, abgeschätzt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-04-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22115</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22115</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2108/herre_andrea.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
