<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3049">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3049</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Reaction rim growth in the systems MgO-SiO2 and CaO-MgO-SiO2: Diffusion pathways and the effect of water</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Wachstum von Reaktionss√§umen in den Systemen MgO-SiO2 und CaO-MgO-SiO2: Diffusionswege und der Einfluss von Wasser</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Joachim, Bastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Growth of reaction rims and metamorphic coronas is recorded in many metamorphic rocks. Various parameters such as pressure, temperature, time, the chemical composition of a system and the presence of fluids may affect reaction rim growth. Laboratory experiments are the method of choice to derive transport mechanisms, reaction rates and component mobilities in polycrystalline rims as a function of these parameters. The major goal of this study is to derive component mobilities in rim growth experiments in the ternary system CaO-MgO-SiO2 and get a better understanding of the growth of complex natural coronas. In the first part, growth of a monomineralic, polycrystalline √•kermanite (Ca2MgSi2O7) reaction rim between monticellite (CaMgSiO4) and wollastonite (CaSiO3) is investigated. Rim growth is solely controlled by MgO-diffusion with D(eff,MgO,Ak) = 10^(-15.8 +/- 0.1 m^2s^(-1)) at 1200¬∞C and 0.5 GPa. Between 1000¬∞C and 1200¬∞C, the effective bulk diffusion coefficient follows an Arrhenius law with Ea = 204 ¬± 18 kJ/mol and D0 = 10^(-8.6 +/- 1.6 m^2s^(-1)). With increasing run duration, growth of √•kermanite grains led to a successive decrease of the grain boundary area fraction. This does not affect , which implies that rim growth is essentially controlled by volume diffusion. The second part focuses on the effect of small, undefined amounts of water on the microstructure of bimineralic diopside (CaMgSi2O6) - merwinite (Ca3MgSi2O8) reaction rims growing between monticellite and wollastonite at 900¬∞C and 1.2 GPa. Overall rim growth rates are solely controlled by diffusion of MgO with D(eff,bulk,MgO,di+mer) = 10^(-16.3 +/- 0.2 m^2s^(-1)) and are not affected by an increasing water concentration, at least in the range of the conditions used in this study. A ‚Äúcellular‚Ä? microstructure of alternating palisade-shaped diopside and merwinite grains elongated normal to the reaction front develops at relatively dry conditions, if MgO is substantially more mobile than the other components CaO and SiO2. A ‚Äúsegregated multilayer‚Ä? microstructure with almost perfectly separated monomineralic merwinite | diopside | merwinite layers oriented parallel to the reaction fronts develops, if either CaO or SiO2 or both have relatively high diffusivities that are comparable to MgO-diffusivities. The fact that a segregated microstructure develops at more humid conditions implies that small amounts of water may significantly change relative component mobilities and, consequently, the internal rim organization. In the third part, the effect of small amounts of water on multilayered reaction rim growth is discussed. The usage of OH-doped periclase (MgO) as starting material provides a method to introduce very small controlled amounts of water on the ppm-level in rim growth experiments. Growth of a forsterite (Mg2SiO4)-enstatite (MgSiO3) double-layered reaction rim between periclase and quartz (SiO2) in presence or absence of minute amounts of water shows that changes in the present water concentration affect the forsterite-enstatite thickness ratio and therefore the relative mobility of the growth rate controlling component(s) between the layers of a reaction rim. Rim growth reactions between periclase and wollastonite in presence of various water concentrations show that small amounts of water are a necessary catalyst to nucleate metamorphic reaction products. The water concentration that is required to nucleate √•kermanite is smaller than for forsterite, followed by monticellite and finally merwinite. The final succession in presence of a water concentration allowing the nucleation of all product phases gives reaction rims with the sequence periclase | forsterite | monticellite | merwinite | √•kermanite | wollastonite. This study shows that minute amounts of water do not only affect the overall growth rate but also the microstructure, the relative thickness ratios and the sequences and overall organization of reaction rims.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Metamorphe Koronen sind ein typisches Merkmal metamorpher Gesteine. Das Saumwachstum wird von zahlreichen Parametern wie Druck, Temperatur, der Zeit, der chemischen Zusammensetzung und der Anwesenheit von Fluiden beeinflusst. Anhand von Laborexperimenten lassen sich Transportmechanismen, Reaktionsraten und Komponentenmobilit√§ten in Reaktionss√§umen als Funktion dieser Parameter bestimmen. Das Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, Komponentenmobilit√§ten im tern√§ren System CaO-MgO-SiO2 zu bestimmen und anhand dessen ein besseres Verst√§ndnis f√ºr das Wachstum komplexer nat√ºrlicher Koronen zu erlangen. Der erste Teil behandelt das Wachstum eines monomineralischen, polykristallinen √Ökermanitsaumes (Ca2MgSi2O7) zwischen Monticellit (CaMgSiO4) und Wollastonit (CaSiO3). Das Saumwachstum wird bei 1200¬∞C und 0.5 GPa ausschlie√ülich durch die Diffusion von MgO kontrolliert und l√§sst sich mit D(eff,MgO,Ak) = 10^(-15.8 +/- 0.1 m^2s^(-1)) beschreiben. Zwischen 1000¬∞C und 1200¬∞C folgt einer Arrheniusbeziehung mit Ea = 204¬±18 kJ/mol und D0 = 10^(-8.6 +/- 1.6 m^2s^(-1)). Mit zunehmender Reaktionsdauer f√ºhrt Kornwachstum zu einer Abnahme der Korngrenzdichte im Saum. Die Tatsache, dass dies keine Auswirkungen auf hat weist darauf hin, dass es sich beim Transport von MgO im Saum √ºberwiegend um Volumendiffusion handelt. Im zweiten Teil wird der Einfluss sehr kleiner Wassermengen auf die Mikrostruktur bimineralischer Diopsid (CaMgSi2O6) - Merwinit (Ca3MgSi2O8) Reaktionss√§ume diskutiert, die sich bei 900¬∞C und 1.2 GPa zwischen Monticellit und Wollastonit bilden. Das Gesamtsaumwachstum wird ausschlie√ülich durch die Diffusion von MgO D(eff,bulk,MgO,di+mer) = 10^(-16.3 +/- 0.2 m^2s^(-1)) kontrolliert, wobei die Reaktionsrate nicht durch zunehmende Wasserkonzentrationen, zumindest von solchen im Rahmen dieser Studie angewendeten, ,beeinflusst. Eine zellul√§re Mikrostruktur, die sich durch pallisadenf√∂rmige, alternierende senkrecht zur Reaktionsfront angeordnete, Diopsid-, und Merwinitk√∂rner auszeichnet, bildet sich ausschlie√ülich, wenn MgO deutlich mobiler ist als CaO und SiO2. Eine lagige Mikrostruktur, die sich durch eine parallel zu den Reaktionsfronten angeordnete Abfolge Merwinit | Diopsid | Merwinit auszeichnet, bildet sich, wenn entweder CaO oder SiO2 oder beide eine √§hnliche Diffusivit√§t aufweisen wie MgO. Die Tatsache, dass sich eine lagige Mikrostruktur bevorzugt bildet, wenn h√∂here Wasserkonzentrationen vorliegen, l√§sst darauf schlie√üen, dass die Verf√ºgbarkeit von kleinen Wassermengen entscheidenden Einfluss auf die relativen Komponentenmobilit√§ten und folglich die Mikrostruktur von Reaktionss√§umen hat. Der dritte Teil behandelt den Einfluss kleiner Wassermengen auf mehrlagige Saumabfolgen. Die Verwendung von OH-gedoptem Periklas (MgO) als Ausgangsmaterial gibt uns die M√∂glichkeit sehr kleine, quantifizierbare Wassermengen in Saumwachstumsexperimente einzubringen. Anhand des Wachstums eines Forsterit (Mg2SiO4) - Enstatit (MgSiO3) Doppelsaumes l√§sst sich zeigen, dass √Ñnderungen in der Wasserkonzentration das Dickenverh√§ltnis der beiden Phasen und folglich das Verh√§ltnis der relativen Mobilit√§t der saumwachstumskontrollierenden Komponente(n) zwischen den einzelnen Phasen beeinflussen. Saumwachstumsexperimente zwischen Periklas und Wollastonit bei variierenden Wasserverf√ºgbarkeiten zeigen, dass Wasser f√ºr die Nukleation metamorpher Reaktionsprodukte als Katalysator ben√∂tigt wird. Die minimale Wasserkonzentration, welche f√ºr die Nukleation von √Ökermanit ben√∂tigt wird, ist kleiner als diejenige f√ºr Forsterit, gefolgt von Monticellit und Merwinit. Bei ausreichend hoher Wasserkonzentration ergibt sich die Abfolge Periklas | Forsterit | Monticellit | Merwinit | √Ökermanit | Wollastonit. In dieser Arbeit wird gezeigt, dass Wasser nicht nur die Reaktionsrate, sondern auch die Mikrostruktur, das relative Dickenverh√§ltnis und die Saumabfolge von Reaktionss√§umen beeinflusst.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-10-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3049</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32198</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32198</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3049/joachim_bastian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
