<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1539">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1539</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:300</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Chilean Housing Policy:A Case of Social and Spatial Exclusion?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Chilenische Sozialwohnungspolitik: Ein Fall f眉r Soziale und R盲umliche Trennung?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jimenez-Cavieres, Fernando</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:300</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The main hypotheses underlying this work are that current Chilean housing policy has contributed to processes of social and spatial exclusion, and that the already known phenomenon of "exclusion through housing" can also take place in Chile. Current Chilean housing policy is widely known for its success in providing affordable dwellings for most of the population, and therefore even promoted by international agencies such as the World Bank, as a system to be copied by other countries in the "south". Nevertheless, its quantitative approach has disregard its role in shaping social outcomes such as health problems, low education attainment, and delinquency, as well as other "intangibles" such as deprecate identity, low-self-esteem and lack of sense of belonging, among others. The principal assumption is that urban inequalities hamper social integration because prevent the equal access to urban opportunities for all citizens. In other words, part of the population is "excluded" from having equal access to economic, cultural or institutional privileges and benefits, goods and rights that are supposed to be recognised as "universal" in this society. This exclusion, on the other hand, is represented in the housing arena by the concept of "exclusion through housing". Yet, The main aim of this work is to explore the extent to which current Chilean housing policy affects urban spatial and social inequalities and, in particular, to find out whether the phenomenon of exclusion through housing is also taken place in the Chilean case. The main problems addressed by this study are the early physical and social decay of complete neighbourhoods, as well as the lack of policies aiming to upgrade these areas; with particular emphasis on neighbourhoods with three to four-storey estates that have been a result of the "Programa de Vivienda B谩sica" in the city of Santiago. To tackle these problems interpretative and analytical approaches are used. While the interpretative approach aims to understand which factors have determined the structure of the Chilean housing model, the analytical approach pursues to closely observe its impacts, results and its prospects of improvement. Therefore, besides of the revision of relevant literature and the development of a conceptual framework, this work confers special attention to both the interpretation of historical policies and the analysis of a concrete case study carried out in the city of Santiago, in three compounds of estates. The theoretical framework aims at developing parameters to interpret and analyse social and spatial exclusion in Chile, which can be applied methodologically through combined approaches. A first approach aims at reviewing the historical patterns of public interventions through housing policies in the city of Santiago, in order to interpret the shifts in paradigms, and the roots of social and spatial exclusion. A second approach is to analyse current housing policy and its implementation in the city of Santiago through the development and use of diverse indicators such access to infrastructure, distribution of poverty and physical aspects, among others. The third and final approach aims at closely observing and comparing three cases studies located in districts that should present different both differences and similarities. The analysis of these cases studies aims at evaluating both the factors that creates social and spatial exclusion as well as the possible main outcomes. As a result of this discussion and analysis the main conclusions are presented, as well as some interpretations and new insights.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="spa">Resumen La principal hip贸tesis que subyace en este trabajo es que la actual pol铆tica habitacional chilena ha contribuido a procesos de exclusi贸n social y espacial y que el fen贸meno ya conocido en Europa como exclusi贸n por medio de la vivienda? tambi茅n puede encontrarse en pa铆ses como Chile. La pol铆tica de vivienda chilena vigente es mundialmente conocida por su 茅xito cuantitativo en la provisi贸n masiva de viviendas baratas para la mayor铆a de la poblaci贸n, y por consiguiente incluso promovida por instituciones globales como el Banco Mundial como un modelo a ser copiado en otros pa铆ses del Sur?. No obstante, el enfoque cuantitativo de dicha pol铆tica ha ignorado su rol en la configuraci贸n tambi茅n de impactos sociales negativos tales como problemas de salud, bajo rendimiento escolar y delincuencia tanto como otros intangibles como las identidades devaluadas, la baja autoestima y la falta de un sentido de pertenencia entre otros. El supuesto principal es que las inequidades urbanas amenazan la integraci贸n social porque impiden el acceso equitativo a las oportunidades urbanas para todos los ciudadanos. En otras palabras, parte de la poblaci贸n esta excluida de tener acceso a los privilegios y beneficios econ贸micos, culturales e institucionales que se supone son reconocidos com,o universales en esa sociedad. Esa exclusi贸n, por otra parte, se representa en la arena de la vivienda por el concepto de exclusi贸n por medio de la vivienda?. As铆, este trabajo busca explorar hasta que medida la pol铆tica de vivienda chilena vigente afecta las inequidades espaciales y sociales y, en particular, verificar si el fen贸meno de exclusi贸n por medio de la vivienda est谩 presente. Los principales problemas que abarca este estudio son la temprana decadencia de los barrios y conjuntos de vivienda social, as铆 como la falta de pol铆ticas integrales que permitan mejorar esas 谩reas, en particular aquellos barrios de vivienda en media altura que han sido implementados a trav茅s del Programa de Vivienda B谩sica? en la ciudad de Santiago. Para enfrentar esos problemas se usaron enfoques anal铆ticos e interpretativos. Mientras el enfoque interpretativo busca entender que factores han determinado la estructura del modelo de vivienda chileno, el enfoque anal铆tico persigue observar de cerca sus impactos, resultados y posibilidades de mejoramiento. Por ello, adem谩s de la revisi贸n de literatura relevante y el desarrollo de un marco conceptual especifico, este trabajo pone especial atenci贸n en la interpretaci贸n de las pol铆ticas hist贸ricas y el an谩lisis de tres casos de estudio concretos en la ciudad de Santiago. El marco conceptual apunta a desarrollar par谩metros que permitan interpretar y analizar la exclusi贸n espacial y social en Chile y que puedan ser aplicados metodol贸gicamente a trav茅s de enfoques combinados. Un primer enfoque se orienta a la revisi贸n de patrones hist贸ricos de la intervenci贸n p煤blica en vivienda en la ciudad a fin de interpretar los principales hitos, los cambios de paradigma y los or铆genes de la exclusi贸n social y espacial. El segundo enfoque se centra en el an谩lisis de la implementaci贸n de la pol铆tica actual por medio de una serie de indicadores tales como la relaci贸n entre vivienda y la distribuci贸n de la pobreza, la infraestructura y el equipamiento en la ciudad. El tercer enfoque a combinar por su parte se focaliza en tres casos particulares que permitan una comparaci贸n a partir de sus diferencias y similitudes. Para terminar, este trabajo presenta algunas conclusiones finales as铆 como algunas sugerencias y propuestas de interpretaci贸n</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-07-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-13950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-13950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1539/jimenez_fernando.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f眉r Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
