<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:10Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2106">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2106</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:300</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Implications of future EU policy on the provision of medicines and on actors in the European pharmaceutical sector</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Implikationen der EU-Regulierung auf Arzneimittelversorgung und Akteure im europäischen Arzneimittelmarkt</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ginneken, Ewout Johan Marius van</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:300</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The European pharmaceutical sector has been an area of continuing political attention for many years. On a national level, the rising expenditures on drugs are posing a threat to the financing and accessibility of health care. Often faster growing than GDP and the health sector as a whole, the pharmaceutical sector has been subject of many national cost containment strategies. On a supranational level, the EU has an increasing role. Not only does the EU ensure the satisfactory delivery of public health, it is also concerned how to encourage innovation and competitiveness of the strategically important sector. The main objective of thesis is to examine the impact of future EU regulation and policy on the various stakeholders in the European pharmaceutical market, focusing on industry and Member States. To achieve this goal, the thesis research has been conducted in three steps. The first step consists of a review of the roles, historic context and trends of the actors of the European pharmaceutical market, including the European Union and Member States, using a conceptual model of the European pharmaceutical market. The second step contains of future scenarios for EU pharmaceutical policy. To this end, key issues and variables of European pharmaceutical policy were selected from published literature after which a Delphi questionnaire was developed in which 41 selected European experts were questioned on these issues. The results of the Delphi questionnaire were used as building stones to fill in the ‘Expert Scenario’. This scenario was then contrasted with a more ‘pessimistic’ scenario and a more ‘optimistic’ scenario. As a last step an analysis of the impact of these scenarios on the various stakeholders in the EU pharmaceutical sector was made.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der europäische Arzneimittelmarkt steht seit vielen Jahren im Fokus der Politik. Sowohl die Finanzierung von Gesundheitssystemen als auch der Zugang zu solchen werden auf nationaler Ebene durch steigende Ausgaben für Arzneimittel gefährdet. Der pharmazeutische Sektor ist häufig Gegenstand nationaler Interventionen zur Kostendämpfung, da dieser in der Regel schneller als das Bruttoinlandsprodukt und der gesamte Gesundheitsmarkt wächst. Nationenübergreifend wächst die Rolle der Europäischen Union, die versucht, die Innovations- und Wettbewerbsfähigkeit der strategisch wichtigen europäischen Pharmaindustrie zu stärken. Ziel dieser Dissertation ist es, die wachsende Rolle der EU im europäischen Arzneimittelmarkt, insbesondere in Hinblick auf Akteure und Mitgliedstaaten zu untersuchen. Dies erfolgt in drei Schritten: (1) ein Review der Rollen und Trends der Akteure des europäischen pharmazeutischen Marktes, einschließlich der EU und ihrer Mitgliedsstaaten; (2) Entwicklung von Zukunftsszenarien für die europäische pharmazeutische Politik; und (3) eine Analyse der Auswirkung dieser Szenarien auf die verschiedenen Akteure im europäischen Arzneimittelmarkt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-04-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/vnd.ms-office</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2106</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21756</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21756</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2106/original_vanginneken_ewout.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2106/vanginneken_ewout.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
