<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:41Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3550">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3550</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Einfluss des Heterostrukturdesigns auf die Effizienz und die optische Polarisation von (In)AlGaN-basierten Leuchtdioden im ultravioletten Spektralbereich</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Influence of the heterostructure design on the efficiency and the optical polarization of (In)AlGaN-based light emitting diodes in the ultraviolet spectral region</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kolbe, Tim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wird der Einfluss des Heterostrukturdesigns auf die externe Quanteneffizienz (EQE) von ultravioletten (UV) Leuchtdioden (LEDs) untersucht. Durch Simulationen der LED-Heterostruktur in Kombination mit Elektrolumineszenzmessungen an 320nm LEDs konnte eine gezielte Verbesserung der Heterostruktur und damit der internen Quanteneffizienz (IQE) der LEDs erreicht werden. Neben der IQE spielt auch die Extraktionseffizienz eine wichtige Rolle, um LEDs mit einer möglichst hohen EQE zu realisieren. Daher wurde im zweiten Teil der Arbeit die Änderung der Polarisation der senkrecht zur c-Achse emittierten Elektrolumineszenz mit steigendem Aluminiumgehalt der aktiven Zone weltweit erstmals systematisch untersucht, da sie eine entscheidende Rolle für die Extraktionseffizienz der LEDs spielt. Für eine Erhöhung der IQE sind die Reduzierung der Defektdichte in den einzelnen Schichten sowie das Design der aktiven Zone und der Elektronensperrschichten von entscheidender Bedeutung. Durch eine gezielte Verbesserung dieser Parameter konnte die nichtstrahlende Rekombination der Ladungsträger an Defekten reduziert, die Ladungsträgerinjektion und der Ladungsträgereinschluss gesteigert werden, was die IQE der LEDs deutlich erhöht hat. Bei der Untersuchung des Einflusses der Defektdichte konnte eine Reduzierung der Lichtleistung um einen Faktor von 4,6 bei einer Zunahme der Defektdichte um rund eine Größenordnung in 380nm LEDs beobachtet werden. Der gleiche tendenzielle Verlauf ergab sich auch für 320nm LEDs in Simulationen. Zudem zeigten Untersuchungen an 320nm LEDs, dass die höchste Lichtleistung für LEDs mit einer Quantenfilmbreite von 2nm und einer AlGaN:Mg-Elektronensperrschicht mit einer Aluminiumkonzentration zwischen 42% und 45% erzielt werden konnte. Außerdem wurde deutlich, dass aufgrund der sehr asymmetrischen Verteilung der Ladungsträger in den Quantenfilmen die Lichtleistung unabhängig von der Quantenfilmanzahl der LEDs ist. Im zweiten Teil der Arbeit wurde die optische Polarisation der senkrecht zur c-Achse emittierten Elektrolumineszenz von UVA-, UVB- und UVC-LEDs untersucht. Dabei konnte für die LEDs auf den Saphirsubstraten eine nahezu lineare Abhängigkeit des Polarisationsgrades von der Wellenlänge beobachtet werden. Eine Änderung der dominanten Polarisation ließ sich für LEDs mit einer Wellenlänge um 300nm nachweisen. Für größere Wellenlängen wurde eine dominante transversal elektrisch (TE) und für kleinere Wellenlängen eine dominante transversal magnetisch (TM) polarisierte Emission beobachtet. Dies konnte durch temperaturabhängige Polarisationsmessungen bestätigt werden. Zudem wurde gezeigt, dass eine Kontrolle des Polarisationsgrades durch eine gezielte Verspannung der LED-Heterostuktur möglich ist. So konnte für 253nm LEDs durch einen Wechsel der Substrate eine Änderung der dominanten Polarisation von einer hauptsächlich TM-polarisierten Emission für LEDs auf den Saphirsubstraten zu einer hauptsächlich TE-polarisierten Emission für pseudomorph gewachsene LEDs auf AlN-Substraten beobachtet werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this work the influence of the heterostructure design on the external quantum efficiency (EQE) of ultraviolet (UV) light emitting diodes (LEDs) has been investigated. By simulations of the LED heterostructure in combination with electroluminescence measurements on 320nm LEDs a systematic improvement of the heterostructure and therefore a systematic improvement of the internal quantum efficiency (IQE) of the LEDs could be achieved. In addition to the IQE, the extraction efficiency plays also an important role in realising LEDs with a high EQE. Therefore, in the second part of this work the polarisation of the in-plane emitted electroluminescence has been investigated, with increasing aluminium content of the active region, for the first time worldwide because the polarisation of the light plays a decisive role in the extraction efficiency of the LEDs. For an increase in the IQE, a reduction of the dislocation density in specific layers as well as the design of the active region and of the electron blocking layer is vitally important. By a systematic improvement of these parameters the non-radiative recombination of the carriers at the defects could be reduced, the carrier injection and carrier confinement could be increased which clearly improved the IQE of the LEDs. During the investigation of the influence of the dislocation density in 380nm LEDs, a reduction of the light output power by a factor of 4.6 was found if the dislocation density increases by around one order of magnitude. The same trend was observed in 320nm LEDs by simulations. Furthermore, the investigations on 320nm LEDs have shown that the highest light output power can be found for LEDs with 2nm thick quantum wells and an AlGaN:Mg electron blocking layer with aluminium content between 42% and 45%. Additional, it was observed that the output power of the 320nm LEDs is independent of the number of quantum wells because of the asymmetric distribution of the carriers. In the second part of this work the in-plane electroluminescence of UVA-, UVB- and UVC-LEDs has been investigated. For the LEDs on sapphire substrates, a nearly linear dependency of the degree of polarisation on the wavelength could be observed. A change of the dominant polarisation could be demonstrated for a wavelength of around 300nm. For larger wavelengths a dominant transversal electric (TE) and for smaller wavelengths a dominant transversal magnetic (TM) polarised emission could be observed. This could be also confirmed by temperature dependent measurements. Additionally, it could be shown that the degree of polarisation can be controlled by a systematic strain in the LED heterostructure. Thus, for 253nm LEDs a change of the dominant polarisation from a mainly TM polarised emission, for LEDs on sapphire substrates, to a mainly TE polarised emission, for pseudomorphically grown LEDs on AlN-substrates, could be observed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-12-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3550</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3550/kolbe_tim.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
