<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:03:06Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:4743">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:4743</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-04-22</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:5</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Nicht-enzymatische Bräunung von Pektin und Oligogalacturonsäuren im Modell und im Apfelsaft</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Non-enzymatic browning of pectin and oligogalacturonic acids in model and in apple juice</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Richter, Janine Jennifer</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:5</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In Verarbeitungsprozessen oder während der Lagerung pektinreicher Lebenmittel kann es sowohl zum chemisch als auch enzymatisch katalysierten Abbau der polymeren Strukturen kommen, so dass gesättigte und 4,5-ungesättigte, partiell methylveresterte Oligogalacturonsäuren entstehen. Da D-Galacturonsäure als reaktive Carbonylkomponente für die nicht-enzymatische Bräunung vom Maillard-Typ angesehen wird, kann sich das Farb- und Aromabild des prozessierten Lebensmittels unerwünscht verändern. Daher ist es von Bedeutung, die beim Pektinabbau auftretenden Intermediate der Bildung von D-Galacturonsäure zu trennen, um den Einfluss dieser Oligogalacturonide und somit des Homogalacturonans auf die nicht-enzymatische Bräunung in Modellsystemen und in Lebensmittelmatrices analysieren zu können. Die Gewinnung von gesättigten und 4,5-ungesättigten, teilweise methylveresterten Oligogalacturonsäuren erfolgt durch gezielten Enzymeinsatz. Anschließend werden die Oligomere mittels präparativen HILIC-UV getrennt und mittels LC-ESI/MS sowie NMR-Spektroskopie gesättigte (Di-/Trigalacturonsäure, Trigalacturonsäure-methylester, Tetragalacturonsäure-dimethylester) und 4,5-ungesättigte Verbindungen (Trigalacturonsäure-methylester, Tetragalacturonsäure-di-/trimethylester, Pentagalacturonsäure-di/tri-/tetramethylester) identifiziert und strukturell aufgeklärt. Diese Oligomere wurden in wässrigen Modellsystemen in An- oder Abwesenheit von DL-Alanin umgesetzt und während des Apfelsaftprozesses verfolgt. Zudem wurden hoch- und niederveresterte sowie amidierte Pektine unterschiedlicher Herkunft mit und ohne DL-Alanin in Modellsystemen mit verschiedener absoluter Gutsfeuchte sowie im wässrigen Milieu bei pH 3 und pH 6 thermisch behandelt. Neben der Verfolgung des thermisch induzierten Abbaus erfolgte die Charakterisierung der nicht-enzymatischen Bräunung über den Bräunungsindex bei 420 nm, die Farbe im CIE-L*a*b*-System und die typischen, bräunungsrelevanten Abbauprodukte wie 2-Furfural und Reduktinsäure. Die Modelle der einzelnen Komponenten lassen Rückschlüsse auf den Beitrag des Homogalacturonans auf die nicht-enzymatische Bräunung zu. Die quantifizierten Abbauprodukte des Homogalacturonans überwiegen gegenüber jenen des Rhamnogalacturonans, insbesondere im wässrigen System, wobei die Summe der gebildeten Pyrrole sowie Reduktinsäure teilweise mit dem a*-Wert und die Furane mit dem b*-Wert korrelieren. Hinsichtlich der untersuchten Parameter weisen Citrus- das geringste und Apfelpektine das höchste nicht-enzymatische Bräunungsverhalten auf. Darüber hinaus konnte der stärkere Abbau von nieder- gegenüber hochveresterten Pektinen im sauren Milieu bestätigt und mit den Modellen der Oligogalacturonsäuren erklärt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">During storage and processing of pectin-containing foods, both chemically- and enzymatically induced degradation of the pectin polymeric structure can occur. This results in the formation of saturated, 4,5-unsaturated, partially methyl esterified oligogalacturonic acids. D-Galacturonic acid is regarded as the reactive carbonyl component taking part in the non-enzymatic Maillard type of browning in foods. This phenomenon, occurring during processing and storage of foodstuffs is obviously undesirable in its effects on the overall quality that is, aroma and appearance of such foods. Therefore it becomes important to be able to separate the galacturonic acid degradation intermediates formed as part of the decomposition of the pectins, so that the influence of such oligogalacturonides can be analysed in laboratory studies of non-enzymatic Maillard browning of both pure, modelled systems as well as in laboratory studies of actual foodstuffs. Application of specific enzymes was used to yield saturated, 4,5-unsaturated and partially methyl esterified oligogalacturonic acids. Subsequent separation of the oligomers was achieved by use of preparative HILIC-UV. Identification of the target compounds – saturated di/tri-galacturonic acids, tri-galacturonic acid methyl ester and unsaturated tri-galacturonic acid methyl ester, tetragalacturonic acid di- and tri-methyl esters, pentagalacturonic acid di/tri/tetramethyl esters – was by HILIC-ESI/MS, while NMR spectroscopy were used for the elucidation of their structures. These samples were treated by heating in model aqueous media with and without addition of DL-alanine and monitored during the apple juicing process. Additionally high and low methoxylated, as well as amidated pectins derived from diverse raw materials, were thermally treated in model systems at varying water contents and at acidities of pH 3 and pH 6. These experiments were repeated both with and without addition of DL-alanine. Further studies were carried out, by measuring the browning index at 420 nm, the colour in the CIE-L*a*b*-colour space and determining typical degradation products such as 2-furfural and reductic acid. These measurements allowed further characterization of the process of browning. From these studies further conclusions could be drawn about the contributions of pectic homogalact¬uronas on the non-enzymatic browning. Quantitatively, the homogalacturonan degradation products are more significant than contributions from Rhamnogalacturonan, especially in aqueous systems. Pyrrole and reductic acid contents correlated directly with the a*-value while furan derivatives correlated more with the value of b*. With regard to the parameters studied in this work, citrus pectins showed the least tendency towards non-enzymatic browning while apple pectins showed the greatest tendency to do so. As expected, low methoxylated pectins are strongly reduced in comparison to high methoxylated pectins at acidic conditions. This could be explained by models of oligogalacturonic acids. </dc:description>
          <dc:date>2014-03-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/4743</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-47432</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-47432</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/4743/Richter_Janine.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
