<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:46:00Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:402">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:402</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:004</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Computer aided image segmentation and graph construction of nerve cells from 3D confocal microscopy scans</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Computer unterstützte Bildsegmentierung und Graph-Rekonstruktion von Nervenzellen aus 3D konfokalen Mikroskopaufnahmen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dima, Anca</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:004</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Computer unterstützte, automatische dreidimensionale Rekonstruktion von Nervenzellen aus Mikroskopaufnahmen würde die Analyse der Abhängigkeit der physiologischen Eigenschaften der Neuronen von ihrer Morphologie erleichtern. Dies würde die Untersuchung der kortikalen Verschaltungen und der entwicklungsabhängigen oder experimentell induzierten plastischen Verformungen, sowie die Untersuchung der Auswirkungen von genetischen Fehlern oder degenerativen Veränderungen und eine Frühdiagnose von degenarativen Prozessen im zentralen Nervensystem ermöglichen. Zur Zeit kann die neuronale Segmentierung nur von Hand durchgeführt werden. Die vorliegende Arbeit hat als Hauptziel die Konstruktion von Graphen, die das Skelett (also die topologische Struktur) einzeln gefärbter Nervenzellen beschreiben. Die für diese Arbeit verwendeten Präparate sind intrazellulär gefärbte Zellen die von konfokalen Mikroskopen aufgenommen werden. Diese ermöglichen eine volumetrische Datenerfassung, ohne daß das Gewebe physikalisch geschnitten werden muß. Damit die Methoden möglichst tolerant gegenüber von Aufnahmeartefakten sind, werden mehrere Vorverarbeitungsschritte wie folgt durchgeführt: i) Die Entrauschung wurde multiskalar, mit Hilfe der orthogonalen 3D Wavelettransformation implementiert. Dabei wurden Donoho's adaptive Schrankenwertauswahlmethode "SURE Shrink" für den dreidimensionalen Raum erweitert. Die Bewertung der Resultate, erzielt durch die Anwendung der verschiedenen Entrauschungsvarianten und der Wavelet Filter unterschiedlicher Glätte, wird durch das Fehlen von einem "ideellen" Vergleichsbild erschwert. Es wird gezeigt, daß herkömmlich verwendete einfache Qualitätsmaße, wie z.B der quadratische Fehler (MSE) oder die Entropie nicht aussagekräftig sind. Deshalb wird hier ein zusammengesetztes Qualitätsmaß entwickelt, und gezeigt, daß dessen Bewertung besser mit der menschlichen Beurteilung der Entrauschungsresultate übereinstimmt. ii) Im nächsten Schritt werden Objektkanten auf mehreren Auflösungsstufen mit Hilfe der Translationsinvarianten Wavelettransformation erkannt. Danach wurde in dieser Arbeit eine interskalare Validierungsmethode der Kanten entwickelt. Diese hat sich als gut geeignet erwiesen für die fast blinde Trennung der neuronalen Kanten von den verauschten Kanten. iii) Die so erhaltenen, bereinigten Kanten werden anschließend für die Segmentierung verwendet. Das hier neu entwickelte Segmentierungsverfahren - "Gradient Tracing" genannt - hat den Vorteil, daß es weniger kontrastabhängig ist als herkömmliche Methoden. Dadurch, daß es die multiskalare Kanteninformation aus dem ganzen Bild verwendet, anstatt - wie üblich - iterativ eine bereits segmentierte Zone "wachsen" zu lassen, verliert dieses Verfahren keine Information, so daß sogar die schwächsten neuronalen Strukturen segmentiert werden. iv) Multiskalare Differentialoperatoren können anschließend auf dem segmentierten Neuron angewendet werden um eine von der Skelettkonstruktion unabhängige Detektion von Verzweigungspunkten und starken Krümmungspunkten zu entwickeln. Es wird gezeigt, daß die übliche, direkte Anwendung der Operatoren auf den neuronalen Aufnahmen fehlschlägt und daß die vorab Segmentierung notwendig ist, um sinnvolle Resultate zu erzielen. Dies stellt die erste erfolgreiche Anwendung dieser Operatoren auf reelen dreidimensionalen Grauwertdatensätzen dar. v) Das oben erwähnte Segmentierungsverfahren berechnet im gleichen Schritt (also recheneffizient) die inneren Symmetriepunkte und schätzt in diesen Punkten den lokalen axialen Verlauf der neuronalen Äste. Dies resultiert in einem groben Skelett des Neurons, das im nächsten Schritt, zusammen mit den detektierten Verzweigungspunkten, zu einem Graphen, das die neuronale Topologie wiedergibt, weiterverarbeitet wird. Die Graphenrekonstruktion ist wiederum eine in dieser Arbeit entwickelte Methode, die möglichst stabil gegenüber Rauschen und Bildartefakten (wie z.B. Kontrastschwankungen innerhalb der neuronalen Äste) zu bleiben versucht. vi) Nicht zuletzt zeigt diese Arbeit, daß die hier entwickelten Methoden, generell sind und dehalb auch für andere Bildverarbeitungszwecke angewendet werden können, wie zum Beispiel für die automatische Segmentierung von Gehirnregionen (gezeigt am Beispiel eines Gerbilgehirns) oder die Detektion von Vesikeln im optischen Neuropil der Fruchtfliege (Drosophila melanogaster). Die einzelnen Methoden dieser Arbeit bilden ein modulares System, daß aus einem 3D Grauwertbild, vorab einen Graphen konstruiert. Das ganze System benötigt außer von ein paar Parameter -und Schwellwerteinstellungen sonst keinen zusätzlichen Eingriff von Seiten des Benutzers und ist also fast automatisch.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Exact knowledge about the morphology of neuronal cells is essential in neurobiology and in medicine. The main goal of these disciplines is to study the influence of morphology upon the physiology of the neuronal cells. Comparative studies on a high number of cells, would thus facilitate the better understanding of cortical circuitry, as well as the study of the consequences of genetic defects and degenerative modifications. Thus an automated procedure for the neuronal reconstruction is needed, since the currently available computer-aided segmentation and tracing procedures still necessitate the manual drawing of an expert - a time consuming task. Therefore the so obtained results are not objectively quantifiable. The goal of automatic 3D-reconstructions of neuronal cells is hard to achieve. Due to the large variety of existing neuronal cell types and probe characteristics (differences in staining, mounting and scanning procedures) no general solution can be given. The current work focuses on the construction of a neuronal graph from confocal microscopy scans of intracellularly stained neurons. This facilitates a subsequent automatic three-dimensional high-resolution geometric reconstruction of the cell, which is needed for the precise geometrical measurement of the neurons. The here developed neuronal graph construction algorithm relies on several pre-processing steps: i) Image denoising is performed in the current work by means of the orthogonal wavelet shrinkage paradigm, first introduced by David Donoho. The 3D extension of Donoho's wavelet shrinkage, introduced here for the first time, gives rise to several variants. An objective evaluation of the performance of these variants (generated by the application of different wavelet filters and shrinkage modalities) on the same initial image is very difficult, since there is no "ground truth" noiseless image available for comparison. This work shows, that the usually employed quality measures, such as the mean squared error (MSE), the entropy or the density of nonzero wavelet coefficients are not giving meaningful rankings, which are comparable with human judgment. Therefore a new intercale wavelet coefficients' correlation measure is introduced, which is related to the scene scanning mechanism of the human visual system. This interscale correlation measure is then combined with other simple measures to quantify more of the conditions imposed to a well denoised image. The rankings given by the obtained new composed measures are compared with human evaluation. It is shown, that any of these measures perform better than the simple ones and a winner measure is determined. ii) Boundary detection is performed employing Mallat's efficient multiscale "A Trous" algorithm (based on the Translation Invariant Wavelet Transform - TIWT). This algorithm is extended here to 3D. However, since it finds even the lowest contrasted edges, it detects also small background fluctuations and noise. Therefore an edge selection method is needed. The current work develops a new across-scales edge validation method which computes a confidence measure of edge points corresponding to object boundaries. This validation strongly enhances coherent edges which are present on neighboring scales and have similar gradient direction. Therefore coefficients corresponding to noisy edges can be suppressed almost blindly by thresholding those having low confidence values. iii) The segmentation is based on a new paradigm called "Gradient Tracing" which uses the cleaned edges from the previous step and the associated gradient directions to determine the inside of the foreground objects. Since edge detection finds edges of even the finest and lowest contrasted objects, and Gradient Tracing considers all available edge information, smallest and weakest neuronal signal is retrieved. This is in contrast to currently available segmentation techniques, which either are based on thresholding or start from initially set points and grow a region based on the assumption of low contrast variations - a premise, which is almost never given in recordings of neuronal tissue - leading thus to the loss of significant data at regions of strong contrast decrease. Additionally, the "Gradient Tracing" paradigm computes in the same step branch symmetry points which lie along the central branch axes and estimates the axial direction at these points. These points form a raw skeleton of the analyzed objects and are further used for the graph construction along the neuronal branches. iv) Feature extraction is computed also in a multiscalar fashion, basing on the efficient TIWT to implement second order differential operators. The wavelet filter needed for this operator is derived in this work. These operators are then employed for the detection of branching and bending points of the neuron (n.b. independently from the skeletonization, which is in contrast to currently available branching point detection methods) and for the detection of circular objects. It is shown here, that the direct application of multiscale differential operators to noisy biological data does not give meaningful results. Instead, combined with the segmentation by Gradient Tracing, a correct feature detection is obtained for the first time on 3D neuronal data. v) Graph construction is finally implemented basing on all previous pre-processing results. This novel graph construction method uses thus the most available information, unlike any similar method has used before. This allows it to be more tolerant to image artifacts such as background noise or boundary irregularities and therefore to capture much more details of the underlying structure. The here presented system is constructed modularly as several independent algorithms, and thus it is a general image processing toolkit, which gives total freedom to the user. It was completely implemented in C++ and is therefore easy to extend or modify. The processing chain for neuronal graph construction needs the setting of two thresholds, and two neighborhood parameters and is thus almost automatic, without demanding any online user interaction. Even if the final goal of the here presented algorithms is the graph construction, the single modules, such as the segmentation or the feature extraction do have a general character, such that the algorithms can be used also on other kinds of data. The two different segmentation and detection examples on the brain structures of a gerbil and the detection of neurotransmitter vesicles in the optic neuropil of the Drosophilamelanogaster demonstrate the general applicability of the proposed Gradient and Seed-Fill segmentation methods to extremely different data (w.r.t image contrast, shapes and sizes of foreground objects).</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2003-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/402</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/402/dima_anca.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
