<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2945">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2945</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:004</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">An Integrated, Interactive Application Environment for Session-Oriented IPTV Systems, Enabling Shared User Experiences</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Eine integrierte, interaktive Applikationsumgebung für sitzungsbasierte IPTV-Systeme.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Friedrich, Oliver</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:004</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The Internet is continuously developing in the direction of becoming a platform for the delivery of video and entertainment services. Internet Protocol Television (IPTV) services, including Video-on-Demand (VoD), Linear TV and corresponding interactive TV services are already part of nearly all current Internet service offerings. Due to consumers’ rising demands for Internet video portals like YouTube, which are not necessarily part of operators’ edge networks, the entire Internet is currently heading towards an end-to-end media delivery platform. Current IPTV offerings provide services already known from Digital TV. In addition to Linear TV and Video on Demand, a certain amount of interactivity using the IP back-channel is provided. In contrast to those, innovative services like Social Networking come from the Internet. What has been missing so far is an integrated approach combining both worlds, including the above-mentioned common streaming services, interactivity, rich media communications and novel aspects of Over-The-Top services like Social Networking. In this thesis, such an extended approach to IPTV is introduced. Herewith the consumer, as well as third-party service providers will be enabled to create, manipulate and enhance services and interact with other consumers and services in the end. Based on a profound state-of-the-art and requirements analysis, the author proposes a novel session-oriented core system for IPTV. The platform therefore reuses concepts from session-oriented conversational services specified for Next Generation Networks (NGNs), incorporating the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP). First, different approaches for so-called Interactive Application Environments are analyzed. Then two Interactive Application Environments are selected for integration into the proposed system called the Open IPTV Ecosystem Core. Second, the corresponding architecture will be derived through the specification of functional entities, interfaces and protocols, which allow for the consumption, creation, manipulation and interaction with other consumers and services. Furthermore, the described architecture and exemplary interactive services are implemented. Finally, the resulting infrastructure is validated through different case studies. The work on this thesis was carried out at the Fraunhofer Institute for Open Communication Systems (FOKUS). The results have been used within the scope of multiple international research projects either funded by the European Commission or research partners from industry. Furthermore, they have partly contributed to the IPTV standardization process within the Open IPTV Forum and ETSI TISPAN.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das Internet entwickelt sich derzeit zu einer Plattform für multimediale, hochauflösende Video- und Unterhaltungsdienste. Fernsehen über das Internetprotokoll, sog. Internet Protocol Television (IPTV), ist bereits heute Bestandteil vieler Internetpakete. Dies beinhaltet sowohl klassische lineare TV-Inhalte, als auch Video-on-Demand–Angebote, kombiniert mit ersten interaktiven Diensten. Die derzeit verfügbaren Angebote für IPTV unterscheiden sich kaum von klassischen Digital-TV-Angeboten, da diese derzeit nur bedingt von dem über das Internet verfügbaren Rückkanal für interaktive Dienste Gebrauch machen. Im Gegensatz hierzu entwickeln sich im Internet neue und innovative Dienste, die vornehmlich unter dem Stichwort Social Media zusammengefasst werden. Eine Verschmelzung beider Ansätze erfolgt derzeit nur zögerlich, wobei der Kombination von Bewegtbild, Interaktivität, Kommunikationsdiensten und Sozialen Medien eine erfolgversprechende Zukunft vorausgesagt wird. Die vorliegende Arbeit beschreibt einen solchen kombinierten Ansatz, mit dem der Nutzer und der Dienstanbieter in die Lage versetzt werden, kombinierte Mediendienste zu nutzen und bereitzustellen, sowie mit Kommunikationsdiensten anzureichern und zu beeinflussen. Die technische Basis bilden hierbei Konzepte, abgeleitet von sog. Next-Generation-Networks (NGNs) zur Bereitstellung von multimedialen Diensten über das Internetprotokoll. Das sog. Session-Initiation-Protokoll (SIP) stellt die entsprechenden Funktionalitäten zur Kontrolle und Signalisierung der Dienste bereit. Das im Rahmen der Arbeit entwickelte Kernsystem – der sog. Open IPTV Ecosystem Core – besteht weiterhin aus einer integrierten Laufzeitumgebung für interaktive Dienste, die aus existierenden Ansätzen abgeleitet und zu einem neuen und innovativen System erweitert wird. Die hierbei entwickelte Architektur spezifiziert funktionale Komponenten, Schnittstellen und Protokolle, die den oben beschriebenen Konsum und die Erstellung von interaktiven Inhalten, sowie die Interaktion mit anderen Nutzern und Diensten erlauben. Des Weiteren erfolgt die exemplarische Entwicklung von neuen interaktiven Diensten, sowie deren Validierung durch mehrere Fallstudien. Die vorliegende Arbeit wurde im Rahmen der Tätigkeit des Autors als wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter am Fraunhofer Institut für Offene Kommunikationssysteme (FOKUS) erstellt. Die Ergebnisse wurden hierbei im Rahmen mehrerer internationaler Forschungsprojekte erarbeitet und publiziert. Die Projekte wurden durch Partner aus der Industrie bzw. der Europäischen Kommission gefördert. Des Weiteren flossen Ergebnisse in offene Standards für interaktives IPTV der ETSI und des Open IPTV Forums (OIPF) ein.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-06-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2945</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31406</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31406</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2945/friedrich_oliver.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
