<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:24Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2163">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2163</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:400</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Alphabetisation in Spanish-German bilinguals</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Alphabetisierung bei spanisch-deutscher Zweisprachigkeit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bonillo, Robert</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:400</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This study deals with three characteristic differences of bilingual acquisition compared with monolingual acquisition: earlier semantic-based, holistic processing, minor-rule delay and levelling. The influence of these bilingual factors on alphabetisation and literacy development is analysed multidimensionally: comparison of bilingual data with monolingual data, contrastive aspects of Spanish and German, error analysis, etc. The bilingual data of this study consist of text of appr. 20000 predominantly written words produced by 17 simultaneously alphabetised third graders to ninth graders from a German school in Madrid. Out of this sample, four early Spanish-German bilinguals are selected, whose development was studied between 2 and 5 years. Comparison with monolingual peers shows that these bilingual subjects rely more heavily on memory-based word processing and less on analytic control by spelling rules. This result confirms the assumption that bilinguals rely strongly on holistic strategies even in the first stages of alphabetisation where processing of alphabetic scripts should be predominantly analytic (bottom up). This amounts to a delay in the development of a balanced double-checking strategy (slower bottom-up processing controls the result of faster holistic processing). One minor-rule delay from the data is an insecurity with phoneme-grapheme correspondences in contexts where language-specific major rules of stop discrimination are not distinctive. Finally many language-contact phenomena are visible in the data. Two of them are a) a tendency towards phonetic-based spelling and b) dative overgeneralisation in animate accusative objects. Morphosyntactic levelling is slowly overcome, but reoccurring interferences until the end of the survey indicate that ‚Äúnew‚Ä? language-specific knowledge cannot be activated yet without conscious monitoring. Automatised transfer routines still intrude, when this cognitively demanding process fails. The error analysis shows that three strategies are productive in bilinguals: reliance on general, non-language-specific patterns, on interlingual and on language-specific analogies. This confirms the view that multilinguals use a linguistic system, which contains common, language-specific and relational components. Hence strict language separation in simultaneous alphabetisation and literacy development misses the point of possible bilingual problems, such as fossilisation of transfer phenomena. It can be concluded that closer attention to bilingual factors can have a positive effect on the development of language-specific literacy.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Hauptziel der Studie ist es festzustellen, ob Faktoren des mehrsprachigen Erwerbs Alphabetisierung und Entwicklung der Schriftsprache ver√§ndern k√∂nnen. Die untersuchten bilingualen Faktoren sind ‚Äûfr√ºhere holistische, bedeutungsorientierte Verarbeitung‚Äú, ‚Äûverz√∂gerter Erwerb von Nebenregeln‚Äú (minor-rule delay) und ‚Äûtempor√§re Einebnung sprachspezifischer Unterschiede‚Äú (levelling). Ihr Einfluss auf die schriftsprachliche Entwicklung und Verarbeitung wird mehrdimensional analysiert, z.B. durch Vergleich mit monolingualen Daten, kontrastiven Aspekten des Deutschen und des Spanischen, durch eine Fehleranalyse, usw. Das Untersuchungskorpus besteht aus vorwiegend geschriebenen Texten von ca. 20000 Worten L√§nge, produziert von 17 simultan alphabetisierten Sch√ºlern der Klassen 3 bis 9 einer deutschen Schule in Madrid. Haupts√§chlich stammen die Daten aus vier Fallstudien (2 bis 5 Jahre lang). Ergebnisse: Die spanisch-deutschen Kinder der Untersuchung produzieren eher Schreib- und Lesefehler, die auf zu wenig analytische Kontrolle zur√ºckzuf√ºhren sind, als deutsche peers. Das spricht daf√ºr, dass sie bereits in den Anfangsphasen der Alphabetisierung verst√§rkt holistisch verarbeiten. M√∂gliche Folge sind Verz√∂gerungen bei der Automatisierung einer ausgewogenen doppelten Kontrolle des Geschriebenen, ganzheitlich und regelgeleitet. Der Einfluss von minor-rule delay auf die Alphabetisierung zeigt sich z.B. in Unsicherheiten mit Phonem-Graphem-Korrespondenzen in Kontexten, in denen sprachspezifische Hauptmerkmale zur Plosivdiskrimination nicht distinktiv sind. Schlie√ülich treten bei allen Teilnehmern Sprachkontaktph√§nomene in der Schriftlichkeit auf, z.B. a) eine Tendenz zu phonetisch bedingten Oberfl√§chenschreibungen und b) Dativ√ºbergeneralisierung bei belebten Akkusativobjekten. Dieses Levelling wird in der Beobachtungszeit langsam √ºberwunden, aber regelm√§√üig wiederkehrende Interferenzen bis zum Ende der Beobachtungszeit zeigen, dass ‚Äûneues‚Äú sprachspezifisches Wissen ohne bewusstes Monitoring noch nicht aktiviert werden kann. Die Fehleranalyse verdeutlicht, dass Mehrsprachige au√üer sprachspezifischen auch sprach√ºbergreifende Analogien einsetzen. Dies best√§tigt die Ansicht, dass sie ein gemeinsames Sprachsystem mit sprachspezifischen Auspr√§gungen und den Beziehungen zwischen diesen Sprachkomponenten verwenden. Dementsprechend zielt eine strikte Trennung der Sprachen im Schriftspracherwerb an m√∂glichen bilingualen Erwerbsproblemen, wie Fossilisierung von Transferph√§nomenen, vorbei. Die Ergebnisse der Dissertation sprechen daf√ºr, dass die Ber√ºcksichtigung bilingualer Faktoren sich g√ºnstig auf die Entwicklung der einzelsprachlichen Literalit√§t auswirken kann.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2163</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22764</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22764</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2163/original_bonillo_robert.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2163/bonillo_robert.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
