<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2621">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2621</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">On a mathematical model for case hardening of steel</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Zu einem mathematischen Modell für das Einsatzhärten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Panizzi, Lucia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Despite the creation of numerous new functional materials, steel is still the basic material for the sustainable development of modern industrial society. Its applications are very diverse and widespread in all major branches of industry. The basic principle involved in heat treatment is the process of heating and cooling. In steel for example, hardness can be achieved by heating followed by rapid cooling. In general, two important properties of ferrous materials are contact fatigue strength and wear resistance, which depend mainly on the physical and chemical properties of a superficial layer. A special treatment acting on a relatively thin superficial layer of steel workpieces is called case hardening, because its aim is to harden just the workpiece case (i.e an encasing layer), letting the inner part softer. In nowadays high-technology industry the approach to case hardening often involves trial and error methods, based on previous experiences and empirical analysis. This kind of procedure requires costly and time-consuming experiments. Due to its importance, there is a huge technical literature on the subject of heat treatment of steel, mostly of engineering type. On the other hand, the thermal processing of steel has also attracted the attention of mathematicians. The amount of works dedicated to the modelling of the phase transitions in steel has been increasing in the last decades, due to the numerous applications in industry. From the modelling point of view, heat treatments of steel include heat transfer and transition processes involving the many different crystalline species in steel. Occasionally, as in the specific case of carburizing processes, more equations are needed to describe the evolution of added chemicals. From the mathematical point of view, heat treatments can be ascribed among the numerous phenomena describable through evolutionary problems. Their mathematical modelling includes, in fact, the equations for the evolution of the phases present in steel, the heat equation to follow the thermal process, and, according to the aim, additional PDEs to describe the evolution of other relevant quantities. The heat treatment that we want to investigate in the present work is the most widely used variant of case hardening, named gas carburizing. Carbon is indeed the key to the hardening of steel by the heating and quick cooling mechanism. If the used steel does not contain sufficient carbon to provide the required hardness, then its composition is altered only on the surface layer so that it can become hard during subsequent cooling. In carburizing, the workpiece is heated up to a certain temperature, then it is brought in contact with an environment of sufficient carbon potential to cause the carbon absorption at the surface and, by diffusion favoured by the high temperature, to create a carbon concentration gradient inside the workpiece. Then the workpiece is rapidly cooled down, so that the carbon diffusivity drops practically to zero and carbon atoms remain frozen within the iron lattice. This causes an atomic disorder and results in distortion of the lattice which manifests itself in the form of hardness and/or strength. %Gas carburizing can be shortly described as follows: first, a workpiece is heated up until a certain temperature is attained, at this temperature the concentration of carbon is increased, up to a certain value, in the surface layer of the component, sometimes only over a limited area by diffusion of carbon. The workpiece is kept in the furnace until the desired amount of carbon is diffused, then it is rapidly cooled down. When steel is cooled suddenly, the carbon atoms cannot make an orderly 'escape' from the iron lattice. This causes an atomic disorder and results in distortion of the lattice which manifests itself in the form of hardness and/or strength. Regarding this process, we do not know any reference to previously formulated models. We are aware of the amount of works dedicated to the modelling of the phase transitions in steel in their applications to heat treatments (like induction or flame hardening) which do not count for the variation of the carbon content Within the engineering literature, the process of gas carburizing is divided and investigated in two distinct parts: first carburization, then cooling. In the studies regarding the carburization stage, the focus is almost exclusively on the carbon evolution, described through a diffusion equation often with constant coefficients and disregarding of the coupling with temperature. This approach does not permit, for instance, to take into account further diffusion of carbon into the workpiece in a lower temperature range during the stage preceding quenching, which nevertheless is very important for the control of the carbon profile and the accuracy of the whole process. To the best of our knowledge a complete model including all the possible effects has not yet been examined.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Stahl ist, obwohl die Entwicklung und Nutzung neuer vielseitiger Werkstoffe und Materialen immer bedeutsamer wird, nach wie vor der Grundwerkstoff einer modernen industriellen Gesellschaft. Die grundsätzliche Bedeutung des Kohlenstoffs ergibt sich aus seinem Einfluss auf das Phasenumwandlungsverhalten und damit auf die mechanischen Eigenschaften des Stahls, was vor allem man sich in der Wärmebehandlung zu Nutze macht. Die Grundidee bei der Wärmebehandlung besteht darin, einen Stahl mit bestimmten gewünschten Eigenschaften durch eine geeignete Kombination von kontrollierter Erhitzung und Abkühlung zu erzeugen. Ein spezielles Verfahren, das sich auf eine relative dünne, oberflächennahe Schicht beschränkt, heißt 'Randschichthärten'. Bei diesem Verfahren wird nur die äußerste Schicht des Werkstücks gehärtet, was den Verschleiß bei mechanischer Beanspruchung deutlich verringert. Das Innere hingegen behält seine Duktilität was insbesondere für die Dauerfestigkeit eines Bauteils von Vorteil ist. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wird eine spezielle verfahren des Randschichthärten untersucht, dass so genannte 'Einsatzhärten'. Bei diesem Verfahren wird in die Oberfläche von Werkstücken aus kohlenstoffarmen Stahl von außen durch Diffusion Kohlenstoff eingebracht. Das Werkstück bezieht dabei den zur Diffusion notwendigen Kohlenstoff aus einer kohlenstoffreichen Gasatmosphäre. Auch in der heutigen hoch technologisierten Industrie ist es gängige Methode die Prozessparameter für das Einsatzhärten experimentell zu ermitteln. In der Regel werden Erfahrungswerte mit zusätzlichen experimentellen Studien kombiniert um eine optimale Wärmebehandlungstrategie für ein bestimmtes Bauteil zu entwickeln. Ein großer Nachteil hierbei ist, dass trotz aller Optimierungsversuche oft viele kostspielige und zeitaufwändige Experimente notwendig sind. Die mathematische Beschreibung von fest-fest-Phasenumwandlungen in Stahl, die in den dreißiger Jahren des letzten Jahrhunderts seinen Anfang nahm, ist bis heute Gegenstand weitreichender Untersuchungen. Aus Sicht der mathematischen Modellierung lässt sich die Wärmebehandlung von Stahl als eine Kombination von Wärmeleitungs- und Phasenentwicklungsprozessen verstehen, die letztendlich für die Entstehung der verschiedenen Kristallsorten im Stahl verantwortlich sind. Diese Vorgänge werden in der Regel durch ein System von Evolutionsgleichungen beschrieben, das im Wesentlichen aus Gleichungen für die zeitliche Entwicklung der verschiedenen Phasen, der Temperatur und, im Falle des Einsatzhärtens, aus einer Diffusionsgleichung für den Kohlenstoff besteht. Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit ist die mathematische Beschreibung des Einsatzhärtens auf makroskopischer Ebene, die mathematische Untersuchung der Modellgleichungen und numerische Simulationen, die die Eigenschaften des Modells illustrieren. Im ersten Kapitel werden die grundsätzlichen physikalischen Phänomene beschrieben, die im Stahl bei Variation der Temperatur ablaufen, was schliesslich auf die Modellgleichungen führt, die ein nichlineares, gekoppeltes System von gewönlichen und partiellen Differentialgleichungen darstellen. Die beiden partiellen Differentialgleichungen parabolischen Typs beschreiben die Temperaturentwicklung und die Evolution der Kohlenstoffkonzentration im Bauteil. Die gewöhnlichen Differentialgleichungen modellieren die Phasenentwicklung. Im zweiten Kapitel wird die Frage nach der Existenz einer eindeutigen Lösung des Rand-Anfangswertproblems diskutiert, das aus den Modellgleichungen zusammen mit Randbedingungen dritter Art entsteht. Um die für den Beweis der Eindeutigkeit einer Lösung des Gesamtmodells relativ starken Voraussetzungen abschwächen zu können, wird zusätzlich ein Teilproblem eingeführt und analysiert, das aus einem quasilinearen, parabolischen System von nur zwei gekoppelten, partiellen Differentialgleichungen besteht. Für dieses System konnte eine Technik entwickelt werden, die auf einer Methode von J. Neças basiert. Ursprünglich war diese Methode zur Lösung von elliptischen Differentialgleichungen mit linearen Randbedingungen gedacht, sie konnte aber auf den parabolischen Fall mit einer nichtlinearen Randbedingung für die Temperatur erweitert werden. Ein weiteres wichtiges Werkzeug zur Behandlung der Frage der Eindeutigkeit der Lösung und deren stetiger Abhängikeit von den Daten sind die anisotropischen Sobolev-Räume die von O.V. Besov eingeführt wurden. Sie ermöglichen es Probleme mit unterschiedlichenRegularitäten in tangentialer und normaler Richtung zu behandeln. Die bewiesenen Existenz- und Eindeutigkeitssätze gelten für Raumdimensionen kleiner gleich drei, wobei der dreidimensionale Fall aus Anwendungsicht die grösste Relevanz besitzt. Die numerischen Simulationen am Ende der Arbeit, die durch einen Vergleich mit experimentellen Ergebnissen noch validiert werden können, belegen die prinzipielle Anwendbarkeit des entwickelten Modells.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-09-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25928</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25928</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2621/panizzi_lucia.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
