<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3684">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3684</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Frobenius-stable lattices in rigid cohomology of curves</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Frobenius-stabile Gitter in rigider Kohomologie von Kurven</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Minzlaff, Moritz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This thesis considers three aspects of computing zeta functions of algebraic varieties over finite fields of characteristic p, with a particular focus on curves. They are: 1) Approximating proper lifts of curves. A central ingredient to computing zeta functions with p-adic cohomology is a comparison theorem with de Rham cohomology: Given a pair consisting of a smooth, proper, geometrically irreducible scheme over the Witt vectors of the finite field together and a sufficiently "nice" divisor, the log de Rham cohomology of the pair is naturally isomorphic to the p-adic cohomology of the pair of closed fibres. The first contribution of the thesis answers the question how a proper lift of a given curve over a finite field to the Witt vectors can be effectively approximated so that this comparison theorem can be used to compute the zeta function: To this end, it is sufficient to lift a plane model of the curve in an equisingular fashion. If the model only has ordinary singuarities, then the lifting process is shown to reduce to an solving linear systems of equations over the finite field. These LSEs are moreover shown to always allow a solution if "most" of the singularities are nodes. 2) An explicit description of Frobenius-stable lattices. The zeta function can be directly deduced when given the Frobenius action on the p-adic cohomology. Frobenius-stable lattices in the p-adic cohomology are therefore of particular interest: In case a proper lifting of a curve is only approximated over Witt vectors of finite length, the action on a Frobenius-stable lattice naturallly induces a Frobenius action on a module over these Witt vectors of finite lengths which can be computed without further loss of precision. The second contribution of this thesis is an explicit description of the Frobenius-stable lattice given by log de Rham cohomology inside p-adic cohomology (using the above mentioned comparison theorem). 3) Computing zeta functions in larger characteristic. Usually computing zeta functions with the help of p-adic cohomology leads to a quasi-linear runtime in p, whereas input and output size are logarithmic in p. For hyperelliptic curves, Harvey introduced an algorithm whose runtime is only quasi-linear in the root of p. The third contribution of this thesis is an extension of this algorithm to more general cyclic covers of the projective line. The speed up of root of p is mainly due to a baby-step/giant-step approach to compute "normal forms" of differentials modulo exact differentials. In addition to a complete theoretical description, this thesis reports on an open source implementation that was written by the author and which confirms the improved runtime behaviour with respect to p in experiments.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Dissertationsschrift befasst sich mit drei Aspekten des Berechnens von Zetafunktionen algebraischer Varietäten, insbesondere Kurven, über einem endlichen Körper der Charakteristik p. Im Einzelnen sind dies: 1) Approximation eigentlicher Lifts von Kurven. Eine zentrale Zutat zum Berechnen von Zetafunktionen mit p-adischer Kohomologie ist ein Vergleich von p-adischer und de Rham Kohomologie: Gegeben ein Paar bestehend aus einem glatten, eigentlichen, geometrisch irreduzible Schema über den Witt Vektoren und einem hinreichend "netten" Divisor, so existiert ein funktorieller Isomorphismus zwischen der log de Rham Kohomologie des Paares und der p-adischen Kohomologie des Paares der geschlossenen Fasern. Der erste Beitrag der Dissertationsschrift löst die Frage, wie ein eigentlicher Lift einer gegebenen Kurve zu den Witt Vektoren effektiv approximiert werden kann: Es ist hierfür hinreichend ein ebenes Modell der Kurve equisingulär zu liften. Für Modelle mit ausschließlich gewöhnlichen Singularitäten wird gezeigt, dass sich der Liftungsprozess mit formaler Deformationstheorie auf ein iteriertes Lösen von Gleichungssystemen über dem endlichen Körper zurückführen läßt. Dabei lassen sich die auftretenden Gleichungssysteme stets lösen, wenn die Singularitäten bis auf "wenige" Ausnahmen sämtlich Knoten sind. 2) Eine explizite Beschreibung Frobenius-stabiler Gitter. Die Zetafunktion läßt sich direkt von der Frobeniusoperation auf der p-adischen Kohomologie ablesen. Frobenius-stabile Gitter über den Witt Vektoren sind daher von großem Interesse: Ist ein eigentlicher Lift einer Kurve nur über den Wittvektoren endlicher Länge gegeben, so induziert ein Frobenius-stabiles Gitter auf natürliche Weise einen Modul über diesen Vektoren endliche Länge, auf dem man die Frobeniusoperation ohne weiteren Präzisionsverlust approximiert kann. Der zweite Beitrag der Arbeit ist eine explizite Beschreibung des Frobenius-stabilen Gitters, das durch die log de Rham Kohomologie in der p-adischen Kohomologie gegeben ist. 3) Berechnen der Zetafunktion in größerer Charakeristik. Algorithmen, die auf p-adischer Kohomologie basieren, haben üblicherweise eine quasi-lineare Laufzeit in p und sind daher bei "großer" Charakteristik ungeeignet. Harvey gelang es, die Laufzeit im Falle von hyperelliptischen Kurven um einen Faktor von p zu verbessern. Der dritte Beitrag der vorliegenden Dissertationsschrift ist eine Erweiterung dieses Algorithmus auf allgemeinere zyklische Überlagerungen der projektiven Gerade. Der Gewinn im Umfang von Wurzel von p beruht im Wesentlichen auf einem Baby-Step/Giant-Step Ansatz um Normalformen von Differentialen modulo exakter Differential zu berechnen. Zusätzlich zur vollständigen theoretischen Beschreibung des Algorithmus weist eine Open Source Implementierung das bewiesene bezüglich p verbesserte Laufzeitverhalten auch experimentell nach.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-04-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3684</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-39342</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-39342</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3684/minzlaff_moritz.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-SA: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, Weitergabe zu gleichen Bedingungen</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
