<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3066">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3066</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The production of urban space through mobilty: The Case of the Stadtbahn in Berlin </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die Produktion von urbanen Räumen durch Mobilität: Fallstudie Berliner Stadtbahn</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alfaro d´Alençon, Paola</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Across several major cities in Europe and North America, railway spaces have once again become a central topic in urban development. In recent initiatives such as the ‘Renaissance of the Railway Station’ in Berlin, the ‘Highline’ in New York or the ‘Promenade Plantée’ in Paris, railway spaces have been the subjects of massive changes and radical redevelopment strategies. Inner-city urban regeneration strategies, such as the ‘Planwerk Innenstadt’ in Berlin, have put a new focus on railway spaces that were erected in peripheral spaces during the course of 19th century industrialization and are now surrounded by a dense urban fabric. The contemporary planning strategies - as the Berlin case shows – present three perspectives. Firstly, to serve the increased demand for transportation integration the intermodality concept of concentrated network hubs in renovated stations was developed. Secondly, from the urban development perspective, there is an attempt to ‘properly’ integrate the increased flows of mobility in the city area, thereby creating urban space of higher quality. Thirdly, beyond in Berlin and other European cities, railway spaces have been redeveloped as ‘Flagship Projects.’ Hereby the intention is to catalyze the transformation of a whole neighborhood or district by converting the railway station or line to serve commercial, recreational and other uses beyond the original transportation function. During the nineteenth century its heyday, the construction of railway space entailed radical spatial enlargement through networks while new spatial configurations simultaneously developed at specific points around stations and station squares and neighboring areas. Today, railway space plays a role in ‘place making,’ which involves intensifying the development of areas of the greater metropolis in the multi-centered geography of emerging urban development. Against this background, railway space redevelopment has become an increasingly important and controversial subject among scholars from the fields of urban research, planning and architecture, as well as among the public voices of the cities affected by the projects. Railway space redevelopment debates criticize single-sector based approaches and demand that multi-actor principles be incorporated into the planning process. However the planning and realization of railway space redevelopments continues to be marked by the railway space management’s focus on profitable commercial outcomes along with providing public transportation services. Therefore, railway space redevelopment can be seen as a complex field, combining commercial redevelopment strategies, transport infrastructure and public interest in a building process that lacks clear concepts or models. Comprehensive research on national or international case studies is needed to understand the meanings and implications of the emerging railway space from a social perspective, and the Berlin-based case study contributes to this. The research conceptualizes the emerging redevelopment as two key aspects: • Firstly, there has been a significant shift by the railway management from a network extension approach to specific railway space development. The previous focus on specialized train network configurations and stations has moved to a concentration on strategically designed responses to new demands for additional services and consumption. • Secondly, formerly diverse social-physical station space configurations are becoming increasingly uniform as redevelopment initiatives follow goals of strategic and commercial ‘place making.’ By means of theoric discussion, case studies and empirical surveys on the Stadtbahn in Berlin, the work brings together European and American experiences paralleling Berlin’s railway redevelopment strategies. The aim of the research is: • To advance on the understanding of inner city-railway space as a crucial site for post-fordist development and urban entrepreneurship. • To understand the complex dynamics of contemporary urban social-physical changes caused by railway space redevelopments. • To provide a deep understanding of the redevelopment strategies in terms of participation and power relations.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In Infrastrukturumbauprojekten wie die "Renaissance der Bahnhöfe" in Berlin oder die "Promenade Plantée" in Paris werden Bahnräume wie Bahnhöfe oder (Viadukt)strecken Gegenstand massiver Veränderungen und radikaler Restrukturierungsstrategien. Innerstädtische Stadterneuerungsprojekte, wie das "Planwerk Innenstadt" in Berlin, setzten zudem Ihren Fokus auf Eisenbahnräume, ehemalige periphere Stadtlagen die im Zuge der Industrialisierung und des starken Stadtwachstums im 19. und frühen 20. Jahrhundert nun von einem dichten Stadtgefüge umgeben sind. Während die Eisenbahnentwicklung in dieser Blütezeit von einer radikalen räumlichen Erweiterung der Eisenbahnnetze mit einer gleichzeitigen Verdichtung städtischer Räume um spezifische Bahnhöfe geprägt war, lassen sich heutige Ansätze als eine grundsätzliche Redefinition des Bahnraums erklären. Dabei können aktuelle Planungsstrategien für Bahnräume zunächst grob in drei von einander verschieden aber zentralen Perspektiven betrachtet werden: Bahnräume sollen aktuell zunächst als restrukturierte Bahnhöfe neuen hoch konzentrierten verkehrlichen Netzknotenpunkten (Hub´s) mit integrativen Verkehrskonzepten wie der Intermodalität entsprechen. Aus einer städtebaulichen Perspektive besteht das Bemühen erhöhtes Verkehrsaufkommen und Mobilität an wichtigen Verkehrsknotenpunkten adäquat in den Stadtraum zu integrieren und dabei Räume mit hoher urbaner Qualität auszubilden. Von einer ökonomischen Projektmanagement Vision, lassen sich Bahnräume aktuell mit sogenannten „Flagship“ Projekten assoziieren. Für den Umbau werden Projektansätze entwickelt, die perspektivisch als Katalysatoren der Entwicklung des umliegenden Stadtraums fungieren sollen, aber zunächst als restrukturierter Bahnhof oder Infrastrukturlinie mit Zusatzfunktionen wie Einzelhandel und Dienstleistungen über das eigentliche verkehrliche Konzept hinaus ausgeprägt werden. Vor diesem Hintergrund sind Bahnraumrestrukturierungsprojekte wie es bürgerliche Protestbewegungen in Städten wie Stuttgart zeigen durch kontroverse Diskussionen in ihrem Umbauprozess beeinträchtigt. Restrukturierungen werden in Bürgerinitiativen als sektoriale Ansätze kritisiert, welche mit einem öffentlichen Service, wie der Bereitstellung von Verkehrsangebot Multi-Akteursprinzipien einer integrativen Stadtentwicklung außer Acht lassen zu Gunsten eines profitablen Bahnraumkonzepts. Die Stadtforschung bemängelt fehlende Analysen die den Bahnraum als ein komplexes Feld verschiedener Ansätze betrachten, bei dem das öffentliche Interesse, die verkehrlichen Optimierungskonzepte und zusätzlichen bahnräumlichen Vermarktungskonzepte stark verwoben sind. Aus dieser Forschungslücke heraus entwickelt sich diese Arbeit, die eine Reflektion von Bahnumbauprozessen in Berlin anhand der Stadtbahn aus einem integrativen Forschungsansatz vornimmt, die sowohl sozialräumliche, verkehrliche als auch ökonomische Aspekte der Restrukturierung herausarbeitet. Inhaltlich beinhaltet die Arbeit einen theoretischen Ansatz über sozialräumliche, verkehrliche und kommerzielle Aspekte der aktuellen Bahnrestrukturierung in vergleichenden Studien von der Berliner Fallstudie der Stadtbahn zu nationalen und internationale Projekten. Eine historische Studie der Stadtbahnentwicklung stellt die wesentlichen Grundzüge der Strukturierungsprinzipien dar. Eine empirische sozial-räumliche Erhebung mit unterstützender Primärliteratur zu ökonomischen Analysen der derzeitigen Stadtbahnentwicklung gibt ein integratives Bild ihrer Ausprägung als Verkehrsträger und städtebauliches Projekt in den Stationen und Bahnviadukten wieder. Zielsetzung der Forschungsarbeit ist: • zum Verständnis innerstädtischer Verkehrsräume als wichtige Räume einer post-fordistischen Stadtentwicklung und dem „urban entrepreneurship“ beizutragen. • Komplexe Dynamiken zeitgenössischer urbaner Bahnraumumgestaltungen in Stationen und Viaduktbereichen und ihre sozial-räumlichen Konsequenzen zu verstehen. • Einen fundierten Überblick über Partizipationsprozesse und Aneignungen von städtischen Räumen bei Bahnraumrestrukturierungsprozessen zu verschaffen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-11-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3066</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33069</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33069</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3066/1_alfaro_paola_Text.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3066/2_alfaro_paola_Text_Plan_S_176.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3066/3_alfaro_paola_Anhang.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3066/4_alfaro_paola_Anhang_Plan.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
