<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:13Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3663">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3663</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Development of Hydropower in India: Between Global Norms and Local Actions</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Entwicklung der Wasserkraft in Indien: Zwischen globalen Normen und lokalen Maßnahmen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Choudhury, Nirmalya</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Hydropower is an important source of renewable energy. At the same time hydropower projects are prone to adverse environmental and social impacts. This makes responsible hydropower development an important area of research. This thesis addresses the process governing hydropower development in India through an analysis of the importance of environment impact assessment (EIA) and EIA follow-up in the overall decision-making, existence of resettlement and rehabilitation (R&amp;R) norms to mitigate social impacts, and the scope and importance of public involvement in hydropower decision-making. Subsequently this thesis analyses the implications of an increasing private sector involvement on responsible hydropower development. The thesis followed a qualitative research design with a case-oriented approach. This thesis found that requirement of an environmental clearance through an EIA is now legally mandatory for hydropower projects. The process of issuing an environmental clearance has also been standardized over the years. But at the same time the environmental clearance process is perceived to delay projects and constrain infrastructure growth. The reforms in this arena in recent years have been influenced by this perception. The importance of EIA follow-up – measured by compliance and effect monitoring – has declined over the last three decades. Public involvement – in general – resembles as an arena for public information. But this limited legal mandate, not seen as a legitimate public involvement over hydropower projects, results in conflict escalation during post-public involvement stage. The cross-case analysis over hydropower projects showed that presence of an international actor is necessary for diffusion of superior public involvement, while a combination of social mobilization and presence of international actors is sufficient for superior public involvement. In India the R&amp;R of the displaced population in India is guided by the National Resettlement and Rehabilitation Policy in 2007. This policy does espouse for minimizing displacement, comprehensive option assessment and social impact assessment. But their implementation is made subject to discretion of the state government and project developer. While there is an increase in the importance of the private sector in hydropower business, a majority of private sector actors are not equipped to address the social and environmental risks typical to hydropower projects. In future new regulatory agencies like the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) and their guidelines of Business Responsibility Reports, could open-up new arenas through which practices towards responsible hydropower development can be promoted.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Wasserkraft ist eine wichtige Form erneuerbarer Energie, die allerdings erhebliche Umweltrisiken und soziales Konfliktpotential birgt. Die vorliegende Dissertation untersucht den Prozess der Entwicklung von Wasserkraft in Indien durch die Analyse der Rolle von Umweltverträglichkeitsprüfungen (UVP), UVP Follow-ups, internationalen Normen für Umsiedlung und Wiederherstellung der Lebensbedingungen sowie von Öffentlichkeitsbeteiligung in den Entscheidungsprozessen für Staudämme. Zudem werden die Auswirkungen der wachsenden Bedeutung des Privatsektors analysiert. Dieser Arbeit liegen eine qualitative Methodologie sowie eine Fallstudienanalyse zu Grunde. Ein zentrales Ergebnis ist die Erkenntnis, dass in den letzten Jahren bestimmte Komponenten des Entscheidungsverfahrens gestärkt wurden, andere aber geschwächt. So ist die UVP nun gesetzlich vorgeschrieben und UVP-relevante Prozesse sind standardisiert. Jedoch betrachten Teile der Regierung sowie diverse Projektentwickler die UVP als Hindernis im Entscheidungsverfahren und als Hemmnis für die wirtschaftliche Entwicklung. Das UVP Follow-up – im Sinne von Compliance und Monitoring – hat in den letzten drei Jahrzehnten an Bedeutung verloren. Die Art der Öffentlichkeitsbeteiligung ähnelt zwar einem Forum zur Informierung der Öffentlichkeit, allerdings wird dieses bereits eingeschränkte Mandat nicht als legitim für die Entscheidungsfindung bei Wasserkraftprojekten anerkannt. Das erste Gesetz zu Umsiedlung und Wiederherstellung der Lebensbedingungen in Indien trat im Jahr 2004 in Kraft und wurde im Jahr 2007 geändert. Dem geänderten Gesetz liegen eine Reihe progressiver Normen wie die Minimierung von Umsiedlungen zu Grunde. Die Umsetzung dieser Normen liegt allerdings im Ermessen der jeweiligen Regierung und des Projektentwicklers. Die vergleichende Fallanalyse zeigt, dass die Präsenz internationaler Akteure für die Umsetzung einer hochqualitativen Öffentlichkeitsbeteiligung notwendig ist. Die Kombination von sozialer Mobilisierung und der Präsenz internationaler Akteure ist für die Umsetzung einer hochqualitativen Öffentlichkeitsbeteiligung ausreichend. Zudem hat die Mehrheit der Privatinvestoren keine ausreichende Erfahrung im Umgang mit sozialen und Umweltauswirkungen. Die Entwicklung von Wasserkraft ist daher eine Herausforderung für die Zukunft. Jedoch entstehen mit der zunehmenden Bedeutung des Privatsektors auch neue Regulierungsbehörden, wie zum Beispiel das Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) mit seinen Richtlinien, den Business Responsibility Reports. Hierdurch könnten sich neue Wege für die die Entwicklung von Wasserkraft eröffnen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-03-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3663</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-39071</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-39071</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3663/choudhury_nirmalya.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
