<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:26Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1767">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1767</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Integration of Climate Information into Spatial Planning in Seoul, South Korea</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Integration klimatischer Information in die räumliche Planung in Seoul, Südkorea</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eum, Jeong-Hee</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In recent years, demands on urban climate information for various planning purposes have increased in South Korea. However, spatial and environmental planners are still not in possession of comprehensive and spatially distributed information covering large areas. This dissertation explores ways to integrate urban climate information in spatial planning of Seoul by focusing on the following main research questions: how to generate comprehensive and spatially distributed information on urban climate for planning usages in Seoul, and how to apply this information to spatial planning. In order to examine these questions, an already existing methodology is applied to Seoul, which was developed for generating maps of climate analysis/evaluation and planning recommendations in European cities. The application of this methodology to Seoul is called CAMPUS (Climate Analysis Maps for Planning Usage in Seoul) in this study. By performing CAMPUS, spatially distributed and qualitatively evaluated information on climate and air quality is generated: function-related Areal Types, wind and temperature fields simulated by a mesoscale meteorological model ‘MetPhoMod’, and simulations of local atmospheric/thermal loads. In addition, spatial information on the ventilation situation, such as local cold air production, transport, and stagnation, local surface influence, local wind exposition, and mesoscale wind circumstances, is also generated. Based on this climate analysis and evaluation information, spatial information on planning recommendations is further produced for the three targets ‘ventilation, air quality and thermal situation’. Finally, this information provided by CAMPUS is applied to suggest what new planning strategies can be recommended in relation to climate and air quality situations at the three levels of spatial planning in Seoul: the comprehensive urban plan (regional level), the urban master plan (urban level), and the urban management plan (district level). This study comes to the following conclusions: - It is important to generate land cover classes (‘pixel classes’ in this study) suitable for Seoul and to estimate their structural and ground parameters. They permit a more exact representation of the urban structure and surface characteristics of Seoul. - The existing biotope dataset is useful as supplementary data to generate pixel classes and to estimate parameters. The Digital Elevation Model with high resolution in flat areas is needed to reduce misrepresentations of ground surface in flat areas. - The modification of evaluation formulas for establishing maps with planning recommendations enhances spatial differentiation in maps representing the densely built-up area of Seoul. - The potential to integrate information generated by CAMPUS varies according to the level of planning. The information is most suitable for the two levels of the comprehensive urban plan and the urban master plan. For the urban management plan, the information can offer only general overviews of the climate situation. More detailed climate analysis and measurements will enhance the usefulness of the information at the district level of spatial planning.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der dicht bebauten Stadt Seoul mit ihren typischen klimatischen Problemen einer Megacity sind Klima und Lufthygiene heutzutage von großer Bedeutung für ihre Bewohner. Die bisher getroffenen Maßnahmen, z.B. Nutzungsbeschränkungen für den Verkehr, reichen nicht aus, die Belüftungsprobleme zu lösen, die aus der Land- nutzungssituation (dichte Bebauung) und den ungünstigen topographischen Verhältnissen resultieren. Der planerischen Steuerung der Raumentwicklung kommt in Seoul also eine besondere Bedeutung für die Unterstützung einer für den Menschen günstigen Klimasituation zu. Das allgemeine Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit besteht darin, klimatische und luft-hygienische Information in die räumliche Planung Seouls zu integrieren, mit den folgenden Hauptforschungsfragen: wie die räumlich differenzierte und zur räumlichen Planung verwendbare Information der relevanten klimatischen und lufthygienischen Sachverhalte in Seoul erstellt werden, und wie die Information in die räumliche Planungen umgesetzt wird. Um die benötige flächendeckende Information zu Seoul bereit zu stellen, wird das „Regelbasierte Klimaanalyse- und Bewertungsmodell“ auf Seoul angewandt. Die Anwendung des Modells auf Seoul, das ursprünglich für mitteleuropäische Städte entwickelt wurde, wird als CAMPUS (Climate Analysis Maps for Planning Usage in Seoul) bezeichnet. Die Ergebnisse von CAMPUS liegen als räumlich und zeitlich homogene, flächen-deckende Informationen vor. Bezüglich der Klimaanalyse und -bewertung liegen die folgende Informationen vor: Arealtypen, mesoskalige Wind- und Temperatur- feldmodellierung, lokale Luft- und Wärmebelastungsrisiken und Durchlüftungs- situationen (darunter lokale Kaltluftproduktion, -stau und -transport, lokaler Ober-flächeneinfluss und lokale Windexposition, mesoskalige Windverhältnisse). Auf diesen räumlich differenzierten Grundlagen werden drei weitere flächendeckende Datensätze erstellt, die jeweils Planungsziele und -maßnahmen beinhalten: Durchlüftung, Lufthygiene und thermische Situation. Anschließend wird überprüft, wie die mit CAMPUS erstellten Informationen auf den drei Planungsebenen (Regionalebene, Stadtebene und Stadtteilebene) von Seoul umgesetzt werden können. Im Ergebnis der Arbeit zeigt sich die folgendes: - Es ist wichtig, für Seoul passende Landbedeckungsklassen (Pixelklassen in dieser Arbeit) zu erstellen, und ihre Strukturparameter und Parameter zu den Oberflächeneigenschaften zu berechnen. Sie erlauben eine genauere Wieder-gabe der städtischen Struktur und der Oberflächeneigenschaften von Seoul. - Der bestehende Biotop-Datensatz bietet zusätzliche Informationen für Pixel- klassen zu generieren und ihre Parameter zu berechnen. Das digitale Höhen- modell mit hoher Auflösung in flachen Gebieten wird benötigt, um Fehl- darstellungen der Oberfläche in flachen Gebieten zu reduzieren. - Die Modifizierung der Bewertungsformeln zur Herstellung von Planungs- hinweiskarten verbessert die räumliche Differenzierung in Karten, die dicht bebaute Gebiete von Seoul wiedergeben. - Das Integrationspotential der Informationen, die von CAMPUS erstellt wurde, variiert je nach Planungsebene. Die erstellen Klima- und Lufthygiene- informationen eignen sich am besten für die regionale und gesamtstädtische Ebene. Auf der Stadtteilebene geben die Ergebnisse nur einen allgemeinen Überblick zur klimatischen und lufthygienischen Situation. Zur Verstärkung der Anwendbarkeit auf die Stadtteilebene bedarf es weiterer Ansätze inkl. detaillierte Klimaanalyse und Klimamessungen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-05-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1767</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18557</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18557</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1767/eum_jeonghee.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
