<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:44:48Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:160">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:160</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Traditional agroforestry and ecological, social, and economic sustainability on small tropical islands : a dynamic land-use system and its potentials for community-based development in Tioor and Rhun, Central Maluku, Indonesia</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Traditionelle Agroforstwirtschaft und ökologische, soziale sowie ökonomische Nachhaltigkeit auf kleinen tropischen Inseln</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stubenvoll, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Obwohl sie viele Gemeinsamkeiten mit kontinentalen, peripheren Landschaften der Tropen aufweisen, sind kleine tropische Inseln mit zusätzlichen, spezifischen Umwelt- und Entwicklungsproblemen belastet. Für die menschliche Nutzung stehen auf diesen kleinsten Landeinheiten nur sehr begrenzte Ressourcen  wie z.B. Süsswasser, Vegetation und Land  zur Verfügung. Darüber hinaus werden die fragilen, auf engem Raum vernetzten terrestrischen und marinen Ökosysteme durch unangepasstes Ressourcenmanagement nachhaltig und z.T. irreversibel gestört. So hat vielerorts die Praxis der Rodung von Wäldern zur Urbarmachung von Ackerland zu Bodenerosion und zu Sedimentation geführt  mit nachteiligen Folgen für die Landwirtschaft sowie für die subsistenzorientierte Fischerei im Küstenbereich, welche zur Deckung des Proteinbedarfs der lokalen Bevölkerung von Bedeutung ist. Aufgrund der Bindung von Kohlendioxid durch die Karbonatbildung der sie umgebenden Korallenriffe spielen kleine tropische Inseln zudem eine wichtige Rolle im globalen Klimahaushalt. Die Arbeit hat zum Ziel, traditionelle Land- und Ressourcennutzung auf kleinen tropischen Inseln anhand zweier Inseln im östlichen Indonesien zu analysieren, deren Stärken zu identifizieren sowie diese, zusammen mit Verbesserungspotenzialen hinsichtlich ihrer Schwächen, in auszuarbeitende und von der Dorfgemeinschaft getragene (d.h. kommunale) Land- und Ressourcennutzungspläne einzubringen. Damit soll ein Beitrag zu der Frage geleistet werden, ob und unter welchen Bedingungen nachhaltige, ländliche Entwicklung auf kleinen tropischen Inseln erreicht werden kann. Über ein induktives Verfahren  mit Methoden der qualitativen Sozialforschung, des RRA und PRA, und der Kartierung, sowie mit der Erhebung von boden- und vegetationskundlichen Daten und der Auswertung von Sekundärquellen  wird gezeigt, dass die in beiden Inseln praktizierte traditionelle Agroforstwirtschaft sowohl den Bedürfnissen und Möglichkeiten der Bevölkerung weitgehend entgegenkommt, als auch ökologisch nachhaltig ist (Bodenschutz, Küstenschutz, Stabilisierung des Wasserhaushalts). Allerdings stösst die Erweiterung der Agroforstwirtschaft auf Hindernisse, u.a. weil andere Landnutzungssysteme (z.B. Brandrodungs-Wanderfeldbau, permanenter Trockenfeldbau) mit ihr konkurrieren. Deshalb wird analog der FAO 'Guidelines for Land-use Planning'(1993) ein Planungsverfahren vorgestellt, mit dem Agroforstwirtschaft auf kommunaler Basis ausgeweitet werden kann. Des weiteren werden die Nutzung der Küstengewässer (mit 'sea-use planning', verstanden als Erweiterung des FAO-Ansatzes) und institutionelle Gesichtspunkte (z.B. Landrecht, Regelungen, traditionelle Institutionen) bei der Entwicklung von kommunalen Landnutzungsplänen berücksichtigt. Die Studie kommt zur Schlussfolgerung, dass nachhaltige Entwicklung auf kleinen tropischen Inseln nur über kommunale Landnutzungsplanung, mit der gleichzeitigen Sicherung der exklusiven Nutzungsrechte von Ressourcen in traditionellem Dorfterritorium einschließlich der Küstengewässer, erreichbar ist. Mit partizipativer Planung können lokal spezifische Problemlösungsmöglichkeiten identifiziert werden, weil einerseits indigenes Wissen eingebracht wird, und andererseits die lokale Bevölkerung Zugang zu externem Wissen erhält. Ausserdem wird mit Partizipation die Akzeptanz der Bevölkerung für eine veränderte, nachhaltige Land- und Ressourcennutzung erhöht.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Although small tropical islands share many characteristics with continental, peripheral landscapes of the tropics, they are confronted with additional, specific environmental and development constraints. On these smallest land units only very limited resources  such as fresh water, vegetation and land  are present to draw on for human utilisation. Furthermore, their fragile, interdependent terrestrial and marine ecosystems, that are co-existing in a limited area, will be severely, and partly irreversibly disturbed by unsuitable resource management. In many places, for instance, the usual practice of clearing forests to reclaim arable land has caused soil erosion and sedimentation  with adverse impacts on both agriculture and subsistence-oriented fisheries in coastal waters, which is important for islanders as these resources are the major source of proteins. Moreover, small tropical islands have a significant function for global climate as carbon dioxide is being fixed in the calcium carbonate of the islands' coral reefs. The purpose of this thesis is to analyse traditional land and resource utilisation on small tropical islands with the help of two island case studies in East Indonesia. Furthermore, merits of traditional resource management as well as potentials to deal with its shortcomings are identified and discussed concerning its inclusion in community-based land and resource management plans. Thus, it is intended to contribute to a clarification of the question, if and under which conditions sustainable rural development on small tropical islands can be achieved. For this purpose an inductive approach is chosen, which includes methods of qualitative social research, RRA and PRA, as well as the collection of soil and vegetation data and the evaluation of secondary sources. It is shown that traditional agroforestry is practised on both islands. These land-use systems are adapted to the needs and capacities of the local population, while being ecologically sustainable (soil conservation, coastal protection, protection of freshwater resources). However, the extension of agroforestry runs into difficulties, also because other land-use practices (e.g., shifting cultivation, permanent dry field agriculture) are competing with it. Therefore, a planning process, derived from the FAO's 'Guidelines for Land-use Planning' (1993), is presented, by which agroforestry can be extended on a community level. Additionally, the utilisation of coastal waters (with 'sea-use planning', understood as an extension of the FAO's approach) and institutional aspects (land tenure, regulations, traditional institutions) are discussed and considered for the development of community-based land-use plans. The study concludes that sustainable development on small tropical islands can only be achieved with community-based land-use planning, along with the islanders' exclusive access to resources in customary territory including coastal waters. With community participation in planning, locally specific conditions and possibilities to tackle problems are easier to be identified: On the hand indigenous knowledge can be tapped by local participation, and on the other hand the local population gets access to external knowledge. Furthermore, locals' acceptability of modified, sustainable land and resource management is increased by participation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2001-07-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/160</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-1553</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-1553</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/160/stubenvoll_stefan.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
