<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3377">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3377</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Recreational use of protected areas in Germany: Evaluating visitors’ perception of crowding in the Wadden Sea National Park</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Erholungsnutzung in Schutzgebieten in Deutschland: Erfassung der Crowding-Wahrnehmung im Nationalpark Schleswig-Holsteinisches Wattenmeer</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kalisch, Dennis</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Unspoiled natural environments are the backbone for various recreational activities. In recent years, visits to large scale protected areas continue to increase or at least be maintained at a high level. At the same time these areas provide important, sometimes competing landscape functions such as the protection of natural resources. Starting point of this work is that popular tourist sites in Germany such as the North Sea coast and the Alps attract numerous visitors annually and have to cope with a great demand for outdoor recreation activities. The high number of people visiting natural areas has generated a number of concerns about the ability of these areas to sustain appropriate levels of social impacts, especially in the summer season. Growing demand for access and participation in outdoor leisure activities can damage the ecological integrity of sensitive environments, and reduce the quality of visitor experiences at the same time. These social aspects are framed in terms of carrying capacity, which characterises the ability of a site or region to absorb recreational use without deterioration. Detailed knowledge of crowding issues in national parks in Europe and especially in Germany is rather limited. While the ecological impacts of tourism in protected areas in Germany are well documented, studies on social impacts in terms of social carrying capacity and how visitors perceive their recreation experience are rare. Primary purpose of this dissertation is to explore the interrelationships of visitor encounters and related perception of crowding and thus the identification of appropriate social indicators to measure recreation quality. A case study research design with several methodological approaches is applied in a comparative manner to assess the social carrying capacity of recreation use in a popular German coastal recreation area. The empirical data has been collected in an on-site survey on the Hamburger Hallig located in the Wadden Sea National Park to identify various determinants of visitor’s crowding perception. A combination of visitor survey and direct observation data is applied to simulate the visitor use patterns and respondents’ reported encounter associated with areas’ actual density. This approach was used to analyse the perception of contacts with others (reported encounters), congestion (perceived crowding) and preferences for certain visitor numbers within the study area.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Intakte, naturnahe Landschaften bilden die Grundlage und Kulisse für zahlreiche Erholungsaktivitäten. Naturtourismus und Ausflüge in die deutschen Nationalparks haben in den letzten Jahren kontinuierlich Zulauf erhalten. Dabei kommt es durch die Erschließung der Gebiete für ein breites Publikum zu einer Steigerung der Besucherzahlen und des Störungspotenzials durch den Tourismus. Ausgangspunkt der vorliegenden Arbeit sind zumeist hohe Besucherzahlen in den Sommermonaten in populären Erholungsgebieten wie z.B. an der deutschen Nordseeküste oder im Alpenraum. Innerhalb dieser Destinationen sind bestimmte Landschaftsräume als Nationalparke ausgewiesen, die durch Besucherströme in der Region einem hohen Nutzungsdruck unterliegen und in ihrer Tragfähigkeit begrenzt sind. Neben Belastung und Störung der ökosystemaren Zusammenhänge durch die Erholungsaktivitäten stellt sich zusätzlich die Frage nach einer sozialen Tragfähigkeit des Gebietes. Während die ökologische Tragfähigkeit in zahlreichen Untersuchungen thematisiert worden ist, sind Untersuchungen zu Belastungsgrenzen aus einer sozialen Perspektive in Deutschland nur vereinzelt zum Einsatz gekommen. Das konzeptionelle und empirische Wissen darüber, wie hohe Besucherzahlen auf die individuelle Besuchsqualität wirken und wie die Besucher auf diese steigende Frequentierung der Gebiete reagieren, ist im Vergleich zur Forschung in Nordamerika sehr begrenzt. Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit ist es, die vielschichtigen Beziehungen zwischen absoluten Besucherzahlen, Begegnungen zwischen Besuchern im Gebiet und Wahrnehmung der daraus resultierenden Störungen des individuellen Erholungserlebnisses zu erfassen und zu bewerten. In der kumulativen Dissertation wird in einer Fallstudie auf der Hamburger Hallig im Nationalpark Schleswig-Holsteinisches Wattenmeer die Wahrnehmung von Übernutzungen durch verschiedene Besuchergruppen unter Verwendung einer Vorort-Befragung und etablierter und standardisierter Messverfahren erhoben. Zusätzlich bildet das Datenmaterial, welches in einer parallel durchgeführten Besucherzählung erhoben wird, die Grundlage für eine Simulation der Besucherströme und direkte Kontakte zwischen den Besuchern auf dem Weg zur Hallig während des Befragungszeitraumes. Mit Hilfe dieser Methodenkombination sollen Zusammenhänge zwischen der Anzahl von Begegnungen der Besucher (Reported encounter) und daraus resultierende potentielle Störungen (Perceived crowding) bzw. Präferenzen für bestimmte Nutzungslevels aufgedeckt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-06-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3377</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35900</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35900</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3377/kalisch_dennis.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
