<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:41Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2045">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2045</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Kulturlandschaft als planerisches Konzept. Die Einbindung des Schutzgutes "historische Kulturlandschaft" in der Planungsregion Oberfranken-West</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Cultural landscape as a planning concept. The integration of the preservation object historical cultural landscape at the regional planning level in Upper Franconia-West</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>B√ºttner, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Vielf√§ltige Kulturlandschaften sind ein Markenzeichen Bayerns. Als Schmelztiegel des reichhaltigen Natur- und Kulturerbes bilden sie die Basis f√ºr die regionale Identit√§t in einem zusammenwachsenden Europa. Im Europ√§ischen Raumentwicklungskonzept (EUREK) von 1999 und in der am 01.03.2004 in Kraft getretenen Europ√§ischen Landschaftskonvention (European Landscape Convention) wird ‚ÄûKulturlandschaft‚Äú bzw. ‚ÄûLandschaft‚Äú als ein wesentliches Leit- und Rahmenkonzept f√ºr die r√§umliche Planung hervorgehoben. Die Forderung nach der Tradierung von in der Landschaft ablesbarer Geschichte spiegelt sich auch in den gesetzlichen Auftr√§gen des Bayerischen Denkmalschutzgesetzes, des Bundesnaturschutzgesetzes und Bayerischen Naturschutzgesetzes, des Gesetzes zur Umweltvertr√§glichkeitspr√ºfung wie auch des Bundesraumordnungsgesetzes wieder. Im Kern geht es darum, die geschichtlichen und kulturellen Zusammenh√§nge der Kulturlandschaften in ihrer pr√§genden Aussagekraft zu bewahren und Substanz schonend zu entwickeln. Die spezifische Auspr√§gung und das Zusammenspiel der in der Kulturlandschaft verorteten historischen Kulturlandschaftselemente bringt eine an den Raum gebundene Eigenart und Historie hervor, die die Identifikationskraft und die Heimatverbundenheit der Menschen mit ihrer Region f√∂rdern. Die Bewahrung und Entwicklung der Kulturlandschaften Bayerns ist eine Aufgabe, die sich nicht nur an die Raum- und Landschaftsplanung richtet, sondern dazu sind alle aufgerufen. Mit diesem Ansinnen wurde im Jahr 2002 das Pilotprojekt ‚ÄûDie historische Kulturlandschaft in der Region Oberfranken-West‚Äú als ein Gemeinschaftsprojekt der Bayerischen Landes√§mter f√ºr Umwelt und f√ºr Denkmalpflege begonnen, um den kulturhistorischen Bedeutungsgehalt dieser 3675 km¬≤ gro√üen und im Norden Bayerns gelegenen Region aufzuzeigen und in den regionalen Planungsprozess einzubringen. Ein besonderes Anliegen war die Bewusstseinsbildung in der √ñffentlichkeit f√ºr den Wert dieser Kulturlandschaft. Ende 2003 wurde das Modellvorhaben erfolgreich abgeschlossen. Es wurden √ºber 1500 historische Kulturlandschaftselemente und -elementkomplexe erhoben und 112 Kulturlandschaftsr√§ume verschiedener Wertstufen abgegrenzt. Aufgrund ihrer sehr hohen Bedeutung wurden 26 Kulturlandschaftsr√§ume als historische Kulturlandschaften angesprochen. Das Schutzgut ‚Äûhistorische Kulturlandschaft‚Äú fand Eingang in das Landschaftsentwicklungskonzept der Region Oberfranken-West. Erstmalig in Deutschland wurde hier neben den biotischen, abiotischen und √§sthetischen Schutzaspekten auch der kulturhistorische Belang gleichwertig in der Landschaftsplanung auf regionaler Ebene behandelt und fand auch in den Ziel- und Ma√ünahmenkonzepten seinen Ausdruck. Die vorliegende Dissertation schildert die im Modellvorhaben angewandte methodische Vorgehensweise, die Bewertungssystematik und die Darstellungsform der erzielten Ergebnisse. Ferner wird die Frage diskutiert, wie das Schutzgut ‚Äûhistorische Kulturlandschaft‚Äú auf der regionalen Planungsebene integriert werden kann. Letztendlich muss die Bewahrung und Weiterentwicklung der historischen Kulturlandschaft und ihrer Bestandteile als gesamtgesellschaftliche Aufgabe begriffen werden. Als wesentliche Voraussetzung hierf√ºr bedarf es in Bayern einer landesweiten Erfassung der historischen Kulturlandschaftselemente √ºber√∂rtlicher Bedeutung. Einhergehend muss Netzwerkbildung und Bewusstseinsbildung betrieben werden, um auf diesem Wege ein B√ºndnis f√ºr die Kulturlandschaften Bayerns zu schmieden, das sich der √§sthetischen und kulturhistorischen Werte der Kulturlandschaften Bayerns bewusst ist und im Sinne eines planerischen Konzeptes in k√ºnftige Entwicklungsstrategien einzubinden versucht.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Varied cultural landscapes are a trademark of Bavaria. Their particular richness of cultural historical substance and structures is an expression of the interaction between man and nature over many centuries. In the last decades there has been a dynamic inherent change of our perception of landscapes. The loss of historicity and landscape diversity has established a wide range of landscape initiatives in Bavaria. The European Landscape Convention (ELC) and the European Spatial Development Perspective (ESDP) ask for specific measures aiming at the protection, preservation, management and planning of landscapes, acknowledging that landscape is a communal asset, an important part of the quality of life. German laws like the Federal Nature Protection Act (BNatSchG), the Bavarian Federal State Preservation of Historic Monuments Act (BayDSchG), the Environmental Impact Assessment Act (UVPG) and the Federal Spatial Planning Act (ROG) are reflecting these aims. The preservation and development oft this unique treasure of cultural land is a task which is not only associated with spatial and landscape planning, but everyone is called for in this regard. Based on this awareness the demonstration project ‚ÄúThe Historical Cultural Landscape in the Region Upper Franconia-West‚Ä? was begun in 2002. The joint project of the Bavarian Environment Agency and the Bavarian State Department of Historical Monuments set itself the objective to indicate the cultural landscape and historical significance of this region and to contribute to its preservation and development. The main idea of the project was to identify, to assess and to evaluate the cultural landscape elements and structures of regional importance. The next step was to designate cultural landscapes displaying a specific combination of historic landscape elements and structures. One of the important intentions was to create a common awareness of the man-made landscape and its cultural heritage. At the end of 2003 the project was sucessfully completed. In the planning region Upper Franconia-West, which covers an area of 3675 km¬≤, more than 1500 regionally significant elements of the culural landscape and 112 cultural landscape areas were registered, evaluated and characterized. Due to their immense cultural historical importance 26 cultural landscape areas were labelled historical cultural landscapes. The results of the project have been integrated in the Landscape Development Concept (LDC). The LDC is the landscape planning concept of the nature conservation authorities, but is not legally binding. It is also a nature conservation contribution towards the review and extrapolation of the Upper Franconia West Regional Plan. For the first time in Germany the cultural heritage of landscape was treated next to the biotic, abiotic and aesthetic aspects in landscape planning with their own aims and management concepts. The dissertation describes the methodical procedure adopted in the demonstration project, the system of evaluation and the form of the presentation of the gained results. Finally the question is discussed how the preservation object historical cultural landscape can be integrated at the regional planning level. The protection and cultivation of cultural landscapes require suitable partners to be identified from the fields of enviromental protection and landscape preservation, rural development and spatial planning. The management and planning of landscapes is an interdisciplinary task preferably embedded in a local network. It is very important to initiate a cultural landscape register and information system for Bavaria, which contains the cultural heritage of rural and urban spaces. We should agree that cultural landscape in its historic and aesthetic dimension is a communal asset, which has to be used as a planning concept for the future development. The preservation and development oft this unique treasure of cultural land is a task which is not only associated with spatial and landscape planning, but everyone is called for in this regard.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-02-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2045</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2045/original_buettner_thomas_org.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2045/buettner_thomas.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2045/buettner_thomas_anhang.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
