<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:44:22Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:72">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:72</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Radiolysis Products in Gamma-Irradiated Plastics by Thermal Desorption-Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Radiolyseprodukte in gamma-bestrahlten Kunststoffen durch Thermodesorption-Gaschromatographie-Massenspektrometrie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Buchalla, Rainer</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Niedermolekulare ('flüchtige') Radiolyseprodukte von Kunststoffen wurden mittels Thermodesorption-Gaschromatographie-Massenspektrometrie untersucht. Nach einem qualitativen Screening von sechs medizinisch verwendeten Kunststoffen und Untersuchungen an LDPE- und Polypropylen-Folien lag der Schwerpunkt auf der quantitativen Bestimmung der Radiolyseprodukte von Polystyrol. Eine Sterilisationsdosis von ca. 25 kGy erzeugte in allen untersuchten medizinischen Kunststoffen -- Spritzgußtypen von PS, MABS, PA-6, PVC, HDPE und PP -- nachweisbare Mengen von niedermolekularen Radiolyseprodukten, die für beträchtliche Zeit in der polymeren Matrix eingeschlossen bleiben. Diese Produkte und ihre Konzentrationen sind charakteristisch für die einzelnen Kunststoffe. Die Hauptprodukte von Polystyrol (PS) sind Acetophenon, Benzaldehyd, Phenol, 1-Phenylethanol und Phenylacetaldehyd; ihre Konzentrationen liegen um etwa eine Größenordnung unter denen des Reststyrols und Styrol-Dimers. Die Produkte werden (neben aliphatischen Verbindungen) auch in MABS, einem Styrol-Copolymeren, gebildet. Das Hauptprodukt von Polyamid-6 ist Pentanamid, die wichtigsten Radiolyseprodukte von PVC und Polypropylen sind Fragmente von Additiven, d. h. von Organozinn-Stabilisatoren bzw. Phenol-Antioxidantien. In HDPE entstehen nur Spuren von Kohlenwasserstoffen, Aldehyden, Ketonen und Carbonsäuren. Im Gegensatz zu früheren Berichten werden flüchtige Produkte auch in LDPE-Folien für längere Zeit zurückgehalten und in PP-Folien wesentlich länger als erwartet. Die Folien liefern Fingerprint-Chromatogramme mit sehr charakteristischen Mustern von strahlen-induzierten Peaks; nach 25 kGy liegen die Konzentrationen der Produkte um etwa eine Größenordnung unter der der Ethylenoligomere. Neben der Identifizierung der Produkte wurden Versuche zum Einfluß der absorbierten Dosis und der Desorptionstemperatur durchgeführt. Die Frage, ob die mit der TDS analysierten Produkte genuin sind oder strahlen-induzierte Artefakte, wird diskutiert, außerdem die mögliche Existenz zyklischer Produkte, der Nachweis einer Bestrahlung nach niedrigen Dosen (1 kGy) sowie die Entstehung von Fragmenten von Antioxidantien mit atypischer Struktur. Die Quantifizierung basiert auf der Annahme, daß flüchtige Verbindungen -- unter dynamischen Bedingungen und oberhalb der Glasübergangstemperatur Tg -- vollständig aus einer polymeren Matrix desorbiert werden können. Quantitative Desorptionsbedingungen wurden für die Hauptprodukte von PS etabliert, die Kalibrierung erfolgte durch Injektion externer Standards. Nach ca. 25 kGy liegen die Konzentrationen von 1-Phenylethanol (1-Pet) und Acetophenon (Acp) bei ca. 6-8 ppm bzw. 30-40 ppm (mg/kg), ihre strahlenchemischen Ausbeuten liegen im Bereich von 2.5 bis 3.5 nmol/J (1-Pet; G 0.03) und 10 bis 15 nmol/J (Acp; G 0.13). Die Konzentrationen der anderen Hauptprodukte -- Benzaldehyd, Phenol, Phenylacetaldehyd und Benzoesäure -- sind von vergleichbarer Größenordnung; sie scheinen sich während mehrjähriger Lagerung nicht zu verändern und die Ergebnisse mit einigen 'realen' Proben (bestrahlten Petrischalen etc.) zeigen, daß es zumindest nach Sterilisationsdosen möglich ist, eine Bestrahlung von Polystyrol nachzuweisen. Zur Kontrolle des analytischen Systems wurde ein umfassendes Testprogramm entwickelt, bestehend aus Sensitivitäts-, Wiederfindungs- (Recovery) und TDS-'Performance'-Tests. Außerdem wurde eine neue Desorptionstechnik, die Desorption von Polymerlösungen mit Lösungsmittelausblendung, erfolgreich getestet; Versuche zur Identifizierung von Spuren-Radiolyseprodukten in PS ergaben einen weiteren potentiellen 'Marker' für den Bestrahlungsnachweis (1-Phenyl-1-propanon). Schließlich wurden mit einer eigens entwickelten GC-Methode zur splitlos-Injektion von Benzol-Standards die Konzentrationen von Benzol in bestrahltem PS bestimmt. Die Ergebnisse werden kurz unter analytischen und strahlenchemischen Gesichtspunkten betrachtet, und ihre Implikationen für einen Bestrahlungsnachweis und für die Sicherheit von Medikalprodukten und Verpackungsmaterialien werden diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Low-molecular-weight ('volatile') radiolysis products of polymers were investigated by thermal desorption-gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (TDS-GC-MS), a technique comparable to dynamic headspace analysis. The experiments have a two-fold background, namely, radiation sterilization of medical products and packaging in food irradiation; the main objectives were (1) to allow a better assessment of the risks potentially associated with these techniques (safety evaluation), and (2) to evaluate whether thermal desorption allows to distinguish between irradiated and non-irradiated materials (irradiation detection). The volatiles were analyzed with commercially available equipment that uses a cooled injection system (CIS; a PTV-type split/splitless injector) to interface the TDS-unit with the GC column. After a qualitative screening of six medical polymers aimed at identifying the volatiles produced by a sterilizing dose of ca. 25 kGy, and a digression into LDPE and polypropylene films (inspired by some rather unexpected results), it was decided to focus the investigation on polystyrene (PS), and -- as a third major objective -- to quantify the major radiolysis products of PS. All the medical polymers -- PS, MABS, PA-6, PVC, PE, and PP -- produce detectable amounts of volatiles which remain trapped in the polymer matrix for considerable times; the products and their concentrations are characteristic for each plastic. The main products of PS are acetophenone, benzaldehyde, phenol, 1-phenylethanol, and phenylacetaldehyde; their concentrations are ca. one order of magnitude below the residual styrene/styrene dimer levels. Some trace components are formed with still lower yields -- with the exception of benzene these are also oxidized aromatic structures. The same compounds are observed in MABS, which additionally gives some aliphatic radiolysis products. PA-6 yields pentanamide as the main product, plus traces of some homologous amides. The main products of PVC and of PP are fragments of additives, i. e., of organotin stabilizers and of phenol-type antioxidants, respectively. The medical PE produces only traces of hydrocarbons, aldehydes, ketones, and carboxylic acids, which largely disappear within weeks. The effects of irradiation on non-processed polymer pellets and on parts injection-molded from these granulates are comparable. Turning -- half by accident -- to LDPE and polypropylene films, it was found that, contrary to previous reports, low-MW radiolysis products are retained in LDPE films for considerable times, and in PP films much longer than expected. The films produce fingerprint chromatograms with highly characteristic patterns of groups of radiation-induced peaks; these are mainly hydrocarbons, aldehydes, ketones, and carboxylic acids with concentrations (after 25 kGy) ca. one order of magnitude below that of the residual hydrocarbons (oligomers). PP additionally produces very substantial amounts of three degradation products of phenol-type antioxidants. Besides product identification, the following topics were addressed in these series of measurements: Effects of the absorbed dose and the desorption temperature; comparison of several commercial (proprietary) films; high-temperature thermal desorption; the question whether TDS analyzes radiation-induced artifacts rather than genuine products; the possible existence of cyclic radiolysis products; the possibility of identifying an LDPE film as irradiated after a dose of only 1 kGy; and atypical trace fragments of antioxidants. Quantitation is based on the assumption that -- under dynamic (continuous) extraction conditions -- volatile compounds can be desorbed quantitatively from polymer matrices at temperatures above the polymer's glass transition temperature, Tg. Total desorption conditions (TDS-temperature and time) were established for the main radiolysis products of PS, and calibration was achieved by injecting external standards into the CIS. After sterilizing doses of ca. 25 kGy 60Co-gamma-radiation, the concentrations of 1-phenylethanol (1-Pet) and acetophenone (Acp) were determined as ca. 6-8 ppm (mg/kg) and ca. 30-40 ppm, respectively; their radiation-chemical yields (G-values) are in the range of 2.5 to 3.5 nmol/J (1-Pet; G A comprehensive parallel test program, consisting of system sensitivity, analyte recovery, and TDS performance tests was developed to monitor the analytical system. A new desorption technique was successfully tested, namely, thermal desorption of polymer solutions with solvent evaporation (initially called the 'DSC-Method'), which requires almost no sample pre-treatment; and it is suggested to directly inject polymer solutions into the CIS (i. e., to use a PTV-type injector for thermal desorption). One of several minor projects was the identification of trace products; experiments with relatively high sample loads yielded another potential 'marker' for irradiation detection. Finally, a GC-method was developed that allows the splitless-injection of parts-per-million standards of benzene. The method was used to quantify benzene in some high dose-irradiated PS samples, and benzene concentrations at sterilizing doses can be expected to be in the range of 1 to 2 ppm. The overall findings are briefly examined from an analytical point of view, and their implications for irradiation detection, and for the safety of medical devices and packaging materials are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2000-07-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/72</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-670</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-670</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/72/buchalla_rainer.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
