<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3604">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3604</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-10-15</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Structure-function relationships of membrane proteins - spectroelectrochemical investigation of artificial membranes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Struktur-Funktionsbeziehungen von Membranproteinen - Spektroelektrochemische Untersuchung von artifiziellen Membranen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kozuch, Jacek Artur</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Membrane proteins exert a variety of fundamental functions, such as proton and electron transfer, voltage-gated ion translocation and enzymatic reactions. Since most of these processes can be monitored and controlled by electrochemical techniques, substantial efforts have been made to engineer membrane models on electrodes, providing a biocompatible environment for membrane proteins, e.g. tethered bilayer lipid membranes (tBLMs). To date, electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS) has been extensively used to study integral proteins in such devices. However, this methodology cannot provide structural insights, which are required to understand the molecular basis of the proteins' functions. To overcome this limitation, in this work, surface-enhanced infrared absorption (SEIRA) spectroscopy, combined with EIS, was applied. Here a nanostructured Au film, the supporting material for the tBLM, served as the IR signal amplifier of adsorbed molecules and as the working electrode in the same setup. In this work, for the first time, the assembly of stable tBLMs on nanostructured Au films is demonstrated, allowing for the structural and functional spectroelectrochemical characterization of a membrane-embedded protein. The tBLM, composed of (cholesterylpolyethylenoxy)thiol (CPEO3), 6-mercaptohexanol (6MH), and 1-palmitoyl-2- oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (POPC), showed a capacitance of C(tBLM) = 0.6 - 0.7 µF cm−2 and, due to the presence of inevitable defects, a moderate resistance of R(Bilayer) = (21 ± 2) kΩ cm2. The combined spectroscopic and electrochemical analysis provided novel insight into molecular details of the formation process of the tBLM, revealing a two-step process of vesicle adsorption onto 6MH fragments and the spreading to cover the CPEO3 SAM. As a proof-of-concept, the cation-channel forming peptide gramicidin A (gA) was integrated into the tBLMs and analyzed in terms of specific cation-peptide and cation-lipid interactions that are essential for the function of the channel-forming gA and the membrane structure, respectively. On the basis of EIS and SEIRA spectroscopy, the functionality of gA, acting as an ion channel for monovalent cations, was analyzed and correlated to the structural alterations. The combined approach was further extended to the human voltage-gated anion channel (hVDAC) which, besides its central key role in apoptosis, is proposed to be involved in the voltage-controlled ion flux across the membrane. This protein was used to study the direct proteo-tBLM formation from hVDAC-containing vesicles, the suitability of this tBLM system for potential-dependent SEIRA difference spectroscopy, and the mechanism of voltage-gating. Fusion and spreading of hVDAC-containing vesicles result in tBLMs with capacitances and resistances of C(tBLM) = 0.6 - 0.7 µF cm−2 and R(Bilayer) = (14 ± 2) kΩ cm2, respectively, as well as in potential-dependent variations of the bilayer resistance. The results prove the presence of hVDAC within the POPC-POPC bilayer fragments of the tBLM. Potential-dependent SEIRA difference spectra demonstrate the motion of the bilayer towards or away from the Au surface for positive and negative potential differences, respectively. In addition, small potential-dependent changes of the protein structure were observed pointing at a mechanism of voltage-gating that involves a distortion of the β-barrel structure. This structural change may be caused either by elongation and compression (for positive and negative potentials) of the channel or by bending of the hVDAC-bilayer network leading to a cone-shaped structure. Both hypotheses are in line with the asymmetry of voltage-gating, however, only the latter describes the low gating probability reported previously. Altogether, the present study has demonstrated the great potential of the combined EIS/SEIRA approach for studying structure-function relationships of membrane proteins.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Membranproteine üben eine Vielzahl fundamentaler Funktionen, wie z. B. den Protonen- und Elektronentransfer, den spannungsgesteuerten Ionentransport oder enzymatische Reaktionen, aus. Da diese Prozesse in der Regel mit elektrochemischen Techniken untersucht werden können, wurden verschiedene Membranmodelle entwickelt, um eine biokompatible Umgebung für die Rekonstitution von Membranproteinen auf Elektroden zu schaffen. Besonders interessant sind dabei die trägerfixierten Lipiddoppelschichtmembranen (tethered bilayer lipid membranes - tBLMs). Bislang wurde überwiegend die elektrochemische Impedanzspektroskopie (EIS) für die Untersuchung von membrangebundenen Proteinen verwendet. Diese Methode liefert allerdings keine strukturellen Informationen, die für das Verständnis der molekularen Grundlagen der biologischen Prozesse erforderlich sind. In dieser Arbeit wurde daher, in Kombination mit der EIS, die oberflächenverstärkte Infrarotabsorptions-Spektroskopie (surface-enhanced infrared absorption – SEIRA) eingesetzt. Bei dieser Technik dient ein nanostrukturierter Au Film, der als Träger der tBLMs verwendet wird, sowohl als IR-Signalverstärker wie auch als Arbeitselektrode in einer elektrochemischen Zelle. Die vorliegende Arbeit zeigt erstmals den Aufbau einer stabilen tBLM auf einer nanostrukturierten Au-Schicht und ihre Verwendung für die spektroelektrochemische Charakterisierung der Struktur und Funktion von membrangebundenen Proteinen. Die tBLM, aufgebaut aus (Cholesterylpolyethyleneoxy)thiol (CPEO3), 6-Mercaptohexanol (6-MH) und 1-Palmitoyl-2-oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholin (POPC), wies eine spezifische Kapazität von 0.6 - 0.7 µF cm−2 und, aufgrund der unvermeidbaren Defekte, moderate Widerstände von (21 ± 2) kΩ cm2 auf. Die spektroelektrochemische Untersuchung der tBLMs lieferte neue Informationen zum Prozess der tBLM-Bildung, der mit der Adsorption der Vesikel auf 6MH-besetzten Bereichen und der nachfolgenden Spreitung und Benetzung des CPEO3-SAMs in zwei Schritten abläuft. Als "Proof-of-Concept" wurde das Peptid Gramicidin A (gA), das kationenselektive Kanäle bildet, in die tBLM eingebaut und EIS/SEIRA-spektroskopisch hinsichtlich der spezifischen Kation-Peptid- und Kation-Lipid-Wechselwirkungen untersucht, die essentiell für die Funktion des Ionenkanals und die Struktur der Membran sind. Dabei konnten die funktionellen und strukturellen Eigenschaften des gA korreliert werden. Der kombinierte spektroskopisch-elektrochemische Ansatz wurde zudem auf die Untersuchung des spannungsgesteuerten Anionenkanals (human voltage-gated anion channel - hVDAC) ausgedehnt, der neben seiner Rolle in der Apoptose den Ionentransport über die äußere Mitochondrienmembran spannungsabhängig zu steuern scheint. Die Arbeiten am hVDAC zielten darauf ab, die direkte Bildung von Proteo-tBLMs durch Spreiten von hVDAC-rekonstituierten Vesikeln, den Mechanismus des spannungsabhängigen Ionentransports und die Anwendbarkeit dieses tBLM-Systems für die spannungsabhängige SEIRA Differenzspektroskopie zu untersuchen. Das Spreiten der hVDAC-POPC-Vesikel resultierte in tBLMs mit Kapazitäten und Widerständen von 0.6 - 0.7 µF cm−2 und (14 ± 2) kΩ cm2 und spannungsabhängigen Variationen des tBLM Widerstandes. Die Ergebnisse beweisen die Integration von hVDAC in die POPC-POPC Doppelschichtfragmente der tBLM. Potentialabhängige SEIRA Differenzspektren zeigen die Bewegung der Doppelschichten bei positiven Potentialdifferenzen zur Au Elektrode hin und bei negativen von ihr weg. Zusätzlich lassen die SEIRA-spektroskopischen Resultate auf eine spannungsabhängige Verzerrung der β-Barrelstruktur schließen. Diese kann zum einen auf einer Dehnung bei positiven und einer Kompression bei negativen Potentialen des hVDAC-Doppelschichtnetzwerks oder zum anderen auf dessen Krümmung beruhen, welche zu einer keilförmigen Struktur des Kanals führt. Beide Hypothesen stimmen mit der Asymmetrie des spannungsabhängigen Schließens von hVDAC überein. Letztere erklärt zusätzlich auch die niedrige Schließwahrscheinlichkeit von hVDAC. Insgesamt demonstriert die vorliegende Arbeit das große Potential des kombinierten EIS/SEIRA-spektroskopischen Ansatzes für die Untersuchung von Struktur-Funktions-Beziehungen in Membranproteinen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-01-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3604</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38286</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38286</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3604/kozuch_jacek.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
