<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:02:28Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:4189">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:4189</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-10-09</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Reconstituted nonribosomal biosynthesis of the peptide antibiotic valinomycin in Escherichia coli as recombinant whole-cell biocatalyst</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Rekonstituierte nichtribosomale Biosynthese des Peptidantibiotikums Valinomycin in Escherichia coli als rekombinanter Ganzzell-Biokatalysator</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jaitzig, Jennifer</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Nonribosomal peptides (NRPs) cover a diverse group of microbial secondary metabolites with a wide range of significant biological activities. However, their industrial potential is diminished by the fact that the majority of potential source organisms are difficult or not at all cultivable or the compound of interest is only produced under complex environmental conditions that cannot be simulated in the laboratory. Furthermore, the structural complexity of many NRPs makes chemical synthesis hardly feasible. NRPs are assembled from simple building blocks by the coordinated reactions of large multi-modular enzymes, nonribosomal peptide synthetases (NRPSs). Heterologous expression of the required biosynthesis genes in a robust and genetically easy to manipulate host like Escherichia coli is a promising approach to make medicinally relevant NRPs more accessible. Nevertheless, until now only few examples of recombinant production of fully active NRPs have been reported. In this study the functional in vivo biosynthesis of valinomycin, a cyclodepsipeptide with antifungal, antibacterialand antiviral activities, was established in an engineered E. coli host strain. The relevant valinomycin biosynthesis pathway components from Streptomyces tsusimaensis, NRPS genes vlm1 (10.3 kb) and vlm2 (8.0 kb), were isolated and transferred into a library of cytoplasmic expression vectors, which combine molecular elements for expression fine-tuning. A small-scale expression screening of the constructs and relevant cultivation parameters in parallel led to soluble expression of the large, initially poorly expressed heterodimeric valinomycin synthetase (343 kDa + 266 kDa). Correct folding and activity of the adenylation domains of the purified NRPS apoenzymes were assayed in vitro. To provide the necessary posttranslational modification of valinomycin synthetase, the sfp gene for the promiscuous phosphopantetheinyl transferase from Bacillus subtilis was genomically integrated into the E. coli host. Co-expression of Vlm1 and Vlm2 in the engineered E. coli strain BJJ01 led to in vivo synthesis of valinomycin, which was monitored and quantified via HPLC-ESI-mass spectrometry. The conditions for valinomycin production were optimized with a design of experiments (DoE) based, semi-automated screening with enzyme-based glucose delivery (EnBase). Finally, high cell-density cultivation of the recombinant E. coli valinomycin producer with increasing glucose feeding was performed in a lab-scale bioreactor.  The reconstituted biosynthesis of valinomycin involving the expression of two large NRPS enzymes and genomic engineering of the host strain is another example for the versatility and feasibility of E. coli as a recombinant natural product producer. In vitro studies of A domain substrate specificities provide the first experimental proof of the previously ambiguous model of valinomycin biosynthesis. This study paves the way to rationally tailor the enzymatic valinomycin assembly line in order to produce non-natural valinomycin derivatives.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Nichtribosomale Peptide (NRPs) umfassen eine vielseitige Gruppe mikrobieller Sekundärmetabolite mit einem weiten Rahmen an biologischen Aktivitäten. Allerdings wird ihr industrielles Potential dadurch beschränkt, dass die Mehrzahl potentieller Ursprungsorganismen schlecht oder gar nicht kultivierbar sind oder den Wirkstoff nur unter komplexen Umweltbedingungen produzieren, die im Labor nicht simuliert werden können. Zudem macht die strukturelle Komplexität vieler NRPs eine chemische Synthese unattraktiv. NRPs werden aus einfachen Bausteinen durch multi-modulare Nichtribosomaler Peptidsynthetasen (NRPSs) zusammengesetzt. Die heterologe Expression von NRPSs in einem robusten und genetisch leicht manipulierbaren Wirt wie Escherichia coli ist ein vielversprechender Ansatz, um medizinisch bedeutsame NRPs zugänglicher zu machen. Jedoch wurden bis heute nur wenige Beispiele für die rekombinante Produktion vollständig aktiver NRPs veröffentlicht. In dieser Arbeit wurde die funktionelle in vivo Biosynthese von Valinomycin, einem Zyklodepsipeptid mit antifungaler, antibakterieller und antiviraler Wirkung, in E. coli etabliert.  Die nötigen Komponenten der Valinomycin Biosynthese aus Streptomyces tsusimaensis, die NRPS Gene vlm1 (10.3 kb) und vlm2 (8.0 kb), wurden isoliert und in eine Sammlung zytoplasmatischer Expressionsvektoren übertragen, die molekulare Elemente zur Expressions-Feineinstellung kombinieren. Ein parallelisiertes Expressionsscreening der Konstrukte und relevanter Kultivierungsparameter in kleinem Maßstab führte zu löslicher Expression der ursprünglich schlecht exprimierten heterodimeren Valinomycin-Synthetase (343 kDa + 266 kDa). Die korrekte Faltung und Aktivität der Adenylierungsdomänen der aufgereinigten NRPS Apoenzyme wurden in vitro untersucht. Um die notwendige posttranslationale Modifizierung zu gewährleisten, wurde das sfp Gen für die unselektive Phosphopantetheinyltransferase aus Bacillus subtilis genomisch in E. coli integriert. Koexpression von Vlm1 und Vlm2 in dem modifizierten E. coli Stamm BJJ01 führte zu der in vivo Synthese von Valinomycin, welche durch HPLC-ESI-Massenspektrometrie kontrolliert und quantifiziert wurde. Die Valinomycinproduktion wurde durch auf statistischer Versuchsplanung beruhender, halbautomatischer Screenings mit enzymbasierter Glukosefreisetzung (EnBase)optimiert. Schließlich wurde eine Hochzelldichtekultivierung des rekombinanten Valinomycin-Produzenten mit steigender Glukosefütterungsrate im Bioreaktor im Labormaßstab durchgeführt.  Die rekonstruierte Biosynthese von Valinomycin mit Expression zweier großer NRPS Enzyme und genomischer Modifizierung des Wirtsstammes ist ein weiteres Beispiel für die Vielseitigkeit und Anwendbarkeit von E. coli als rekombinantem Naturstoffproduzenten. Die in vitro Untersuchungen zur Substratspezifität der A-Domänen lieferte erstmalig den experimentellen Beleg für das vormals uneindeutige Modell der Valinomycin Biosynthese. Diese Arbeit schafft die Grundlage, um den Biosyntheseweg in E. coli maßzuschneidern und so neue Valinomycin-Derivate zu produzieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-09-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/4189</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-41898</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-41898</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/4189/jaitzig_jennifer.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
