<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:12Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3660">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3660</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Hybrid interface engineering in ZnPc/C60 bi-layer heterojunction organic solar cells</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Hybrid-Grenzfläche engineering in ZnPc\C60 organischen Doppelschicht Solarzellen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bochukov, Ivelin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Bilayer heterojunction organic solar cells (OSCs) consisting of Zn-phthalocyanine (ZnPc) as electron donor and fullerene (C60) as electron acceptor material were optimized in this thesis. The research was focused on the chemistry and morphology of the hybrid interface between the transparent conductive oxide (TCO) anode, in the particular case indium-tin oxide (ITO) and the first organic layer ZnPc. Three approaches were pursued: 1. The interface was chemically engineered by simple dip-coating techniques that terminate ITO prior to ZnPc absorber deposition with synthesized novel axially substituted metal-phthalocyanine molecules. From collected near edge x-ray fine structure spectroscopy (NEXAFS) data the presence of a molecular monolayer termination on the ITO substrate was proved. Photovoltaic devices were prepared using vacuum thermal deposition techniques and applying the new termination concept with modified absorber molecules. Thus the hybrid interface was transformed into a band aligned π-π interface with improved transport properties yielding 2.0 % power conversion efficiency η, with 67% higher than the reference device. 2. As another approach TCO substrates with morphology were investigated for organic solar cell applications. ZnO nanostructures with different length were electrochemically grown on commercial ITO. Additionally, mesoporous ITO with specific pores of 10 nm and 30 nm was examined. Due to light scattering ZnPc absorber deposited on those morphological substrates absorbed up to 20 % more light. Transferred to the device, this effect enhanced short circuit current density (Jsc) by up to 17 %. Efficiency of devices with both morphologies reached 1.6 %. 3. Moreover, in the present dissertation CuI was introduced on ITO as template for oriented growth of the absorber molecules. Analysis on the NEXAFS structure profile of ZnPc films showed decreased molecular tilt angle from 70° on non-templated substrate to 45° on CuI template. With that molecular rearrangement ZnPc absorber layer had 30 % higher absorption coefficient than in conventional α-phase film structure. Bilayer devices produced on 0.032 cm2 active area yielded Jsc as high as 7.3 A/cm2 and 65 % fill factor, thus record efficiency of 2.6 % was achieved.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Dissertation wurden organische Zweischichtsolarzellen mit einem Heterokontakt bestehend aus Zink-Phthalocyanin (ZnPc) als Elektronendonator- und Fulleren (C60) als Elektronenakzeptormaterial optimiert. Im Vordergrund der Forschung stand dabei die Hybrid-Grenzfläche zwischen der Elektrode aus einem transparenten leitfähigen Oxid (TCO), hier Indium-Zinnoxid (ITO), und der ersten organischen Absorberschicht aus ZnPc. Drei Ansätze wurden verfolgt: 1. Die Grenzfläche wurde durch einfaches Tauchbeschichten chemisch angepasst. Dabei wurde das ITO vor Deposition des ZnPc Absorbers mit neuen synthetisierten axial substituierten Metall-Phthalocyaninmolekülen terminiert. Dass die molekulare Monolage auf dem ITO Substrat vorhanden ist, konnte mit Röntgen-Nahkanten-Absorptions-Spektroskopie (NEXAFS) bewiesen werden. Solarzellen wurden unter Verwendung thermischer Vakuumdeposition und dem neuen Konzept der Terminierung mit modifizierten Absorbermolekülen hergestellt. Damit wurde die Hybridgrenzfläche in eine bandangepasste π-π Grenzfläche mit verbesserten Transportfähigkeiten umgewandelt womit ein Wirkungsgrad η von 2% Wirkungsgrad erreicht wurde, der 67% höher ist als für die Referenzzelle. 2. Als weiterer Ansatz wurden TCO Substrate mit nanostrukturierter Morphologie für die Anwendung in organischen Solarzellen untersucht. ZnO Nanostrukturen mit verschiedenen Längen wurden elektrochemisch auf kommerzielle ITO Substrate deponiert. Zusätzlich wurde mesoporöses ITO mit spezifischen Porengrößen von 10 und 30 nm untersucht. Austrittsarbeiten von 3,9 eV für ZnO und 4,0 eV für mesoporöses ITO wurden unabhängig von der Größe der Nanostrukturen gemessen. Auf Grund von Lichtstreuung absorbierten ZnPc Schichten, die auf solche strukturierten Substrate deponiert wurden, bis zu 20% mehr Licht. In Solarzellen führte dieser Effekt zu einer 17% höheren Kurzschlussstromdichte (JSC). Mit beiden Morphologien wurden Wirkungsgrade von 1,6% erreicht. 3. In der vorliegenden Dissertation wurde außerdem CuI auf ITO als Unterlage für ein orientiertes Wachstum der Absorbermoleküle eingeführt. Die Analyse des NEXAFS Strukturprofils von ZnPc zeigte einen Kippwinkel, der sich von 70° für Substrate ohne CuI auf 45° mit CuI verringerte. Mit dieser molekularen Umordnung wurde für die ZnPc Schicht ein 30% höherer Absorptionskoeffizient erzielt als mit der konventionellen α-Phasen- Filmstruktur. Zweischichtsolarzellen mit einer aktiven Zellfläche von 0,032 cm2 erreichten eine typische JSC von 7,3 mA/cm2, einen Füllfaktor von 65% und damit einen Rekordwirkungsgrad von 2,6%.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-03-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3660</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38729</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38729</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3660/bochukov_ivelin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
