<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2593">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2593</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Theoretical studies on structural, dynamic and spectroscopic properties of phytochrome photoreceptors</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Theoretische Studien zu strukturellen, dynamischen und spektroskopischen Eigenschaften von Phytochromen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kaminski, Steve</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Phytochromes (Phy) constitute a family of photosensory receptors, found in plants, bacteria and fungi. Phys are homodimeric complexes with each polypeptide containing three main domains: an N-terminal chromophore binding domain (CBD) with photosensing activity, the phytochrome domain (PHY) which is required for the formation and stability of the physiologically active state, and the C-terminal domain which is essential for signal transduction processes. Through a unique interaction between the chromophore, a linear methine-bridged tetrapyrrole (bilin), and the protein matrix (mainly the CBD and PHY domains), phytochromes can interconvert upon light absorption between two stable states: a physiologically inactive red-absorbing (Pr) form and an active far-red-absorbing (Pfr) form. The underlying molecular events controlling this process are still not fully understood and despite the numerous studies in this field, the elucidation of the photointerconversion mechanism is still a matter of debate. In this context, several RR and NMR experimental studies revealed the existence of two or more stable conformations of the chromophore in each of the parent states. This structural heterogeneity of the bilin chromophore seems to be an intrinsic property of phytochromes in general, which were not yet captured by crystallographic techniques. Therefore, identification and characterization of possible chromophore conformers in the Pr state and their influence on the photoactivation mechanism remain an open question. Furthermore, novel results were obtained from three-dimensional structures of a small fragment of SyB phytochrome from Synechococcus based on NMR measurements in solution, especially concerning the structural and dynamic properties of the cofactor and adjacent residues in the binding pocket. These experimental results, however, were, for both parent states, in disagreement with results obtained from crystallographic and spectroscopic measurements of similar phytochrome species, and with some established concepts concerning photoconversion processes in phytochromes. In the first part of this work, those questions were addressed from a theoretical point of view, by analyzing the structural stability and conformational flexibility of bilin cofactors inside the protein binding pocket of several phytochromes. All-atoms molecular dynamics (MD) simulations with newly derived molecular mechanics force field parameters for bilin cofactors were used for this purpose. The developed parameters accurately reproduce various target data, calculated on higher levels of theory. Furthermore, the derived parameters allow for generating structural properties in an overall good agreement with most experimental phytochrome structures of the Pr state. For the wild type of Deinococcus radiodurans bacteriophytochrome, the parameters also revealed a possible origin of structural heterogeneity at the A-B methine bridge of the chromophore, in agreement with experimental observations. Evidences for strutural heterogeneity, however, could not be observed for any other of the investigated phytochromes, although RR spectroscopic measurements indicate high structural similarities between different phytochrome systems. Therefore it remains uncertain, whether simulations on the nanosecond time scale are generally sufficient to identify all possible forms of structural heterogeneity in the binding pocket of phytochromes. The structural and dynamic properties of SyB phytochrome from Synechococcus, especially in the binding pocket, as obtained from recent NMR solution studies in both parent states, could not be reproduced by molecular simulations with the derived empirical force fields. From a theoretical point of view, the experimental NMR structures do not represent stable protein conformations in the binding pocket, in contrast to the investigated crystallographic structures. Besides NMR and x-ray crystallography, resonance Raman spectroscopy is one of the most valuable methodologies to extract structural information of cofactors in their native protein environment, since the spectrum of the cofactor can be selectively obtained under resonance conditions. To extract structural information as decoded in the Raman spectrum, a proper assignment of the observed vibrational bands is needed and requires a sound theoretical vibrational analysis. Established approaches for vibrational spectra calculations via a standard normal mode analysis (NMA), however, do not systematically consider the influence of molecular dynamics, which turned out to be an important aspect in the interpretation of experimental vibrational spectra. Therefore, as a second project of this work, a methodology for the calculation of vibrational Raman spectra of large systems via a time-correlation function formalism (FTTCF) was implemented into an efficient semiempirical code (SCC-DFTB).</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Phytochrome bilden eine Familie von Fotorezeptorproteinen, die vielfältige biologische Prozesse in Pflanzen, Bakterien und Pilzen steuern. Phytochrome treten hierbei als homodimere Komplexe auf, welche in drei funktionell unterschiedliche Domänen unterteilt werden können. Hierzu zählen die N-terminale Kofaktorbindungsdomäne (CBD), welche die spektrale Qualität des Lichts bewertet, die Phytochromdomäne, deren Funktion die Ausbildung und Stabilisierung des durch Licht aktivierten Proteinzustandes ist, sowie eine C-terminale Domäne, welche Prozesse der weitergehenden Signaltransduktion steuert. Durch Lichtanregung im roten Spektralbereich können Phytochrome reversibel zwischen zwei stabilen Proteinzuständen hin- und herschalten, dem physiologisch inaktiven Pr und dem aktiven Pfr-Zustand. Ausgelöst wird diese Fotokonversion durch spezifische und trotz einer Vielzahl wissenschaftlicher Studien noch weitgehend unverstandene Wechselwirkungen zwischen dem Kofaktor, einem linearen methinverbrückten Tetrapyrrol und der Kofaktorbindungsdomäne. In diesem Zusammenhang scheint nach neueren spektroskopischen (RR und NMR) Untersuchungen der Kofaktor in beiden Zuständen (Pr/Pfr) in zwei oder mehreren verschiedenen Konformationen vorzuliegen. Bei dieser strukturellen Heterogenität handelt es sich vermutlich um eine allgemeine, intrinsische Eigenschaft von Phytochromen. Zum Verständnis dieses Phänomens auf molekularer Ebene konnten experimentelle Methoden zur Strukturbestimmung (NMR und Röntgen) bisher keinen entscheidenden Beitrag leisten. Darüber hinaus führten neuere NMR-spektroskopische Untersuchen an einem Fragment von SyB Phytochrom der Spezies Synechococcus zu Schlussfolgerungen im Hinblick auf Struktur und Flexibilität in der Kofaktorbindungstasche, welche im Widerspruch zu Röntgenstrukturen und schwinggungsspektroskopischen Daten verwandter Phytochrome stehen und zudem nicht im Einklang mit gängigen Konzepten über Fotokonversionsprozesse in Phytochromen sind. Im ersten Teil der vorliegenden Arbeit wurde versucht, diese und ähnliche Fragestellungen zur Struktur und Dynamik von Kofaktoren in Phytochromen mit Hilfe von Moleküldynamiksimulationen zu beantworten. Die speziell hierfür entwickelten inter- und intramolekularen Kraftfeldparameter für methinverbrückte Tetrapyrrole reproduzieren mit ausreichender Genauigkeit Moleküleigenschaften im Vakuum, wie sie mit genaueren theoretischen Methoden ermittelt wurden. Darüber hinaus konnten mit Hilfe dieser Parameter strukturellen Eigenschaften der meisten untersuchten Phytochrome im Pr-Zustand sehr gut reproduziert werden. Für den Wildtyp von Bakteriophytochrom der Spezies Deinococcus radiodurans konnte außerdem eine mögliche Ursache für strukturelle Heterogenität gefunden werden, welche im Einklang mit experimentellen spektroskopischen Untersuchungen steht. Strukturelle Heterogenitäten konnten jedoch bei keinem der anderen untersuchten Phytochrome beobachtet werden. Da RR spektroskopische Untersuchungen jedoch eine grosse strukturelle ähnlichkeiten unter den verschiedenen Systemen belegen, bleibt es fraglich, ob Moleküldynamiksimulationen auf der Zeitskala von Nanosekunden im Allgemeinen ausreichend sind, um sämtliche Formen struktureller Heterogenitäten in der Bindungstasche von Phytochromen aufzuklären. Die mittels NMR Spektroskopie ermittelten strukturellen und dynamischen Eigenschaften einer Phytochromspezies in ihrer Bindungstasche, konnten mit Hilfe von Moleküldynamiksimulationen für beide stationären Zustände (Pr/Pfr) nicht reproduziert werden. Im Rahmen der verwendeten Kraftfelder stellten die experimentellen NMR Strukturen keine stabilen Proteinkonformationen dar, im Gegensatz zu allen untersuchten Kristallstrukturen. Neben den Röntgen- und Magnetresonanzmethoden, spielt die Resonanz-Ramanspektroskopie eine wichtige Rolle in der Strukturbestimmung von Kofaktoren in Proteinen, da das Spektrum des Kofaktors unter Resonanzbedingungen selektiv intensitätsverstärkt gegenüber der Proteinmatrix gemessen werden kann. Um die in den Spektren codierten strukturellen Informationen zu erhalten, ist eine genaue Zuordnung der Schwingungsbanden zu intramolekularen Bewegungen nötig, welche nur mit einer computergestützten Schwingungsanalyse möglich ist. Etablierte Methoden für die Berechnung von Schwingungsspektren, basierend auf der Technik der Normalmodenanalyse (NMA), beziehen jedoch nicht auf systematische Weise den Einfluss der Moleküldynamik eines Systems bei Raumtemperatur in die Berechnung des Spektrums mit ein. Dieser Aspekt hat sich jedoch bezüglich der Interpretation experimenteller Spektren als unabdingbar erwiesen. Aus dieser Notwendigkeit heraus, wurde im Ramen dieser Arbeit eine Methode zur Berechnung von Ramanspektren großer Moleküle nach dem Formalismus der Zeitkorrelationsfunktion (FTTCF) in ein bestehendes, effizientes semiempirisches Programm (SCC-DFTB) implementiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-08-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2593</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27332</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27332</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2593/kaminski_steve.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
