<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:58Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1649">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1649</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die Bedeutung des lokalen und zirkulierenden Renin-Angiotensin Systems in der Präeklampsie</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The significance of local and circulating renin-angiotensin systems in preeclampsia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Herse, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Präeklampsie ist verheerend für Mutter und Kind. Der Ursprung der Krankheit liegt in der utero-plazentären Einheit (upE). Auswirkungen sind bis in die Zirkulation der Mutter messbar. Das Renin-Angiotensin System (RAS) ist in die Präeklampsie involviert, obwohl nicht geklärt ist, wie das zirkulatorische und das gewebespezifische utero-plazentäre RAS miteinander interagieren. Diese Arbeit sollte die Dysregulation in der upE und der maternalen und fetalen Zirkulation, insbesondere des RAS, zeigen. Es wurden Expressionsanalysen der Decidua, Plazenta (als upE), Fett- und Muskelgewebe von 10 Kontroll-Schwangeren und 10 präeklamptischen Schwangeren durchgeführt und auf Proteinebene verifiziert. Außerdem wurden die Plasma-Renin Aktivität (PRA) und der Angiotensin II-Rezeptor Typ 1-Autoantikörper (AT1-AA) in der Zirkulation untersucht und die Aktivität des AT1-AA charakterisiert. Die meisten Gene waren in der Decidua dysreguliert. Der Angiotensin II-Rezeptor Typ 1 (AT1-R) war um den Faktor 5,0 in der präeklamptischen Decidua hochreguliert, der AT2-R in der präeklamptischen Plazenta runterreguliert. Der AT1-AA wurde in maternalem Serum und im transplazentaren Transfer detektiert und zeigte sich befähigt den MAPK-Weg spezifisch zu aktivieren. Die PRA war in der Präeklampsie um den Faktor 3 reduziert. Die RAS-Komponenten Renin (35-fach), Angiotensin converting enzyme (2,8-fach) und Angiotensinogen (9-fach) waren unabhängig der Präeklampsie in der Decidua höher expremiert als in der Plazenta, wohingegen der AT1-R in der Plazenta höher expremiert wurde. Diese Ergebnisse verdeutlichen die Dysregulation des lokalen und zirkulierenden RAS während der Präeklampsie und beschreiben das RAS in der upE. Diese neuen Faktoren könnten zum besseren Verständnis der Pathologie von Präeklampsie beitragen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Preeclampsia is devasting for Mother and Fetus. The origin of this disease is located in the utero-placental unit and effects the maternal circulation. The renin-angiotensin system (RAS) participates in preeclampsia, however, the relative contributions from the circulating RAS and the tissue-based, uteroplacental RAS are unknown. My hypothesis is, that the tissue-based uteroplacental RAS is dysregulated in preeclampsia, as well as the circulating RAS. I performed microarray and gene expression studies and confirmed the findings on the protein level by immunohistochemistry in decidual-, placental-, fat- and muscle-tissue from 10 preeclamptic women and 10 women with uneventful pregnancies. I also analyzed plasma-renin activity (PRA) and the circulating angiotensin II-receptor type 1- autoantibodies (AT1-AA). In preeclampsia, most of dysregulated genes were find in decidual-tissue. The angiotensin II-receptor typ 1 (AT1-R) was significantly upregulated in the decidual-tissue by a factor of 5.0. The angiotensin II-receptor typ 2 was downregulated in placental-tissue. The AT1-AA was detectable in maternal serum and serum from umbilical-vein. The AT1-AA was able to activate cell-signaling via map-kinase. PRA was significantly reduced in preeclamptic group by a factor of 3. Gene expression for renin (35-fold), angiotensin-converting enzyme (2.8-fold) and angiotensinogen (9-fold) were higher in decidua than placenta in both preeclamptic and control women, while AT1-R was higher expressed in placenta. These results characterize the dysregulation of local and circulating RAS in preeclampsia and the RAS of the utero-placental unit in uneventful pregnancies. These findings could help to understand the pathology of preeclampsia.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-01-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1649</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17301</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17301</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1649/original_herse_florian.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1649/herse_florian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
