<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:47Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2703">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2703</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Structural Analysis of an Essential Core Component of the Nuclear Pore Complex</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Strukturanalyse eines essenziellen Bausteins des Kernporenkomplexes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nagy, Vivien</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In eukaryotic cells, the nuclear envelope segregates the nucleoplasm from the cytoplasm. To allow communication between these compartments, huge proteinaceous macromolecular assemblies termed nuclear pore complexes (NPCs), are embedded into perforations of the nuclear envelope and selectively mediate nucleocytoplasmic transport. Multiple copies of approximately 30 different proteins known as nucleoporins are organized in subcomplexes and assemble the NPC with a molecular weight of around 60 MDa in yeast. While the NPC’s general composition is well characterized, its molecular architecture, as well as the functional and mechanistic details of nucleocytoplasmic transport through the NPC are still enigmatic. However, several crystal structures have provided valuable insight into the NPC architecture and its dynamic nature. The structure of the Nup84 complex, an essential subcomplex of the NPC that consists of seven proteins, has been especially well characterized by X-ray crystallography in combination with electron microscopy. In an effort to advance our understanding of the architecture of the Nup84 complex and the NPC, the crystal structure of the hetero-trimeric Sec13•Nup145C•Nup84 NTD complex, the centerpiece of the heptameric Nup84 complex, was determined. Overall, the trimeric complex forms an elongated Z-shaped assembly. Nup84 NTD binding to the Sec13•Nup145C nucleoporin pair is achieved by the head-to-head interaction of two kink regions of the U-shaped α-helical solenoid domains of Nup145C and Nup84 NTD. The docking of the hetero-trimer and crystal structures of other Nup84 complex components into EM envelopes now provides a nearly complete atomic picture of the Nup84 complex. Furthermore, this structure, together with a previously determined structure of hSec13•Nup145C, suggests promiscuous binding of Nup145C. Biochemical and biophysical analyses of the Sec13•Nup145C•Nup84 NTD complex and its components suggest that these proteins are capable of engaging in different assembly states. In the future, the observed assembly states need to be placed into a functional context to resolve the dynamic four-dimensional structure of the NPC in an interdisciplinary approach.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In eukaryotischen Zellen ist der Zellkern durch die Kernhülle vom Cytoplasma getrennt. Jeglicher molekularer Austausch zwischen beiden Kompartimenten wird deshalb selektiv von Kernporenkomplexen (NPCs) vermittelt. NPCs sind Proteinkomplexe, die in Perforationen der Kernhülle eingebettet sind. Ein NPC wird von 30 verschiedenen Proteinen aufgebaut, wobei jedes einzelne Protein in mehreren Kopien vorliegt. Zusammen ergibt sich ein Molekulargewicht von circa 60 MDa pro NPC in Hefezellen. Die Zusammensetzung des NPCs wurde bereits gut charakterisiert, allerdings sind die genaue Anordnung der Proteine im NPC sowie die molekularen Mechanismen des Transportvorganges noch immer ungeklärt. Kristallstrukturen einzelner Proteine und kleinerer Proteinkomplexe des NPCs haben wertvolle Informationen über die Bauweise und dynamische Beschaffenheit des NPCs geliefert. Bisher am besten charakterisiert wurde die Struktur des heptameren Nup84 Komplexes, eines essentiellen Bausteins des NPCs, mittels Röntgenstrukturanalysen und elektronenmikroskopischer (EM) Studien. Um unseren derzeitigen Wissensstand bezüglich des Aufbaus des NPCs zu erweitern, wurde die Kristallstruktur des trimeren Sec13•Nup145C•Nup84 NTD Komplexes bestimmt. Dieser stellt das Kernstück des Nup84 Komplexes dar. Die drei Proteine sind Z-förmig angeordnet, wobei Nup84 und das Sec13•Nup145C Proteinpaar Kopf an Kopf aneinander binden. Diese Kristallstruktur konnte, ebenso wie die Strukturen weiterer Proteine des Nup84 Komplexes, in eine EM-Struktur gedockt werden. Dadurch entstand ein nahezu vollständiges atomares Bild vom gesamten Nup84 Komplex. Eine vergleichende Analyse mit einer zuvor bestimmten Struktur von hSec13•Nup145C lässt auf ein promiskuitives Bindeverhalten von Nup145C schließen. Auch die biochemische und biophysikalische Untersuchung des Sec13•Nup145C•Nup84 NTD Komplexes deutet darauf hin, dass diese Proteine in verschiedenen Bindungszuständen vorliegen können. Es ist von großer Bedeutung, diese Bindungszustände in der Zukunft mittels interdisziplinärer Studien in den zellulären Zusammenhang einzuordnen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-11-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2703</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28457</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28457</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2703/nagy_vivien.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
