<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:48Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2068">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2068</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Insulin Effect Phenotype 1 protein (Iep1p): a putative Protein Phosphatase 1 modulator</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Insulin Effekt Ph√§notyp 1 Protein (Iep1p): ein putative Protein Phosphatase 1 Modulator</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mart√≠n Granados, Cristina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Saccharomyces cerevisiae is a good production host for eukaryotic proteins and has acquired the ‚Äúgenerally regarded as safe‚Ä? (GRAS) status. One of the disadvantages of the use of S. cerevisiae in the production of heterologous proteins is the inefficient secretion. Much effort has been applied to increase protein secretion in yeast by constructing strains overexpressing certain proteins that positively regulate secretion. The results obtained from overproduction cannot be generalized to all reporter proteins, being dependent of the protein used for the screening. This study presents data on Iep1p as a protein necessary for the efficient production of two reporter proteins, mouse Œ±-amylase and fungal polygalacturonase. Overexpression of Iep1p has been shown to increase reporter protein production in the both S. cerevisiae strains BY4741 and GRF18ura3. The plasmid stability assay results showed that IEP1 is necessary for mitotic plasmid stability and that overexpression of Iep1p conferred plasmids a higher stability in both cis and trans conformation. The data on plasmid stability helped elucidate the observed differences in protein production of the two expression systems, establishing a correlation between the observed enhancement in protein production occurring when IEP1 overexpression and the higher stability of the plasmids conferred by the overexpression. The bioinformatics investigation identified a possible functional role of Iep1p as a putative PP1 modulator and the phenotypic study determines Iep1p acting as an agonist of PP1 in glycogen accumulation. Furthermore, Iep1p is identified as an attenuator of pheromone response and different stress responses, such as growth at restrictive temperatures, glucose depletion and high osmolarity conditions, these are all biological processes where PP1 possess several substrates. A BLAST search in S. cerevisiae using Iep1p as query has found that deletion of AdoMet-dependent methyltransferases affects several cellular processes. For example, deletion of PPM1, encoding the methyltransferase of PP2Ac, has a similar effect as the deletion of IEP1 in some biological processes where the two phosphatases have a functional role, such as protein production, glycogen accumulation and cell growth. These findings open the innovative perspective of using PPP modulator AdoMet-dependent methyltransferases as a mechanism for modifying the phosphorylation state in the cell.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">S. cerevisiae ist ein gutes System zur Produktion von eukaryontischen Proteinen und kann generell als sicher angesehen werden (GRAS). Einer der Nachteile bei der Verwendung von S. cerevisiae zur Produktion heterologer Proteine ist die ineffiziente Sekretion. Es wurden bereits viele Anstrengungen unternommen um die Sekretion in Hefe zu erh√∂hen. Zum Beispiel durch die √úberexpression positiv in die Regulation der Sekretion involvierter Proteine. Die Ergebnisse der √úberexpression k√∂nnen nicht bez√ºglich aller Reporterproteine verallgemeinert werden, da sie abh√§ngig sind von dem f√ºr das Screening verwandten Proteins. In dieser Arbeit werden Daten vorgestellt bez√ºglich Iep1p als einem Protein welches n√∂tig ist f√ºr die effiziente Produktion zweier Reporterproteine, der Maus Œ±-Amylase und der fungalen Polygalakturonase. Die √úberexpression von Iep1p f√ºhrte in zwei Hefe-St√§mmen zu einem Anstieg der Reporterprotein-Produktion. Die Ergebnisse des Plasmidstabilit√§tstests zeigten, dass IEP1 n√∂tig ist f√ºr die mitotische Plasmidstabilit√§t, und dass die √úberexpression von Iep1p in beiden Konformationen, cis und trans, Plasmiden eine h√∂here Stabilit√§t verleiht. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass es bei √úberexpression von Iep1p und der dadurch vermittelten h√∂heren Plasmidstabilit√§t zu erh√∂hter Proteinproduktion kommt. Die bioinformatischen Untersuchungen zeigten eine m√∂gliche funktionelle Rolle von Iep1p als einem putativen PP1 Modulator auf und die ph√§notypischen Untersuchungen ergaben, dass Iep1p als Agonist von PP1 bei der Glykogenakkumulation agiert. Weiterhin wurde Iep1p als ein D√§mpfer der Pheromonantwort und verschiedener Stressantworten bestimmt, wie beispielsweise beim Wachstum bei restriktiven Temperaturen, unter Glukose-Mangelbedingungen und unter hoch osmolaren Bedingungen; dies sind alles biologische Prozesse, in denen PP1 mehrere Substrate hat. Eine BLAST-Untersuchung in S. cerevisiae mit Iep1p als Eingabe ergab, dass die Deletionen von AdoMet-abh√§ngigen Methyltransferasen viele zellul√§re Prozesse beeinflussen. Zum Beispiel hat die Deletion von PPM1, das f√ºr die Methyltransferase PP2Ac kodiert, in einigen biologischen Prozessen vergleichbare Effekte wie die Deletion von IEP1, da hier beide Phosphatasen eine funktionelle Rolle haben, wie bei der Proteinproduktion, der Glykogenakkumulation und dem Zellwachstum. Diese Erkenntnisse er√∂ffnen eine innovative Perspektive zur Nutzung von PPP-Modulator-AdoMet- abh√§ngigen Methyltransferasen als Mechanismus zur Modifizierung des zellul√§ren Phosphorylierungsstatuses.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-02-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2068</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-12626</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-12626</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2068/martingranados_cristina.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
