<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:45:37Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:324">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:324</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Sucrose responsiveness and behaviour in honey bees (Apis mellifera L.)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Zuckerwasserreaktion und Verhalten in Honigbienen (Apis mellifera L.)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scheiner, Ricarda</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wird bei der Honigbiene (Apis mellifera L.) analysiert, wie sich die individuelle Empfindlichkeit für Zuckerwasserreize auf verschiedene Formen der Verhaltensplastizität auswirkt. Die Versuche klären insbesondere die Rolle des Belohnungsreizes Zuckerwasser beim assoziativen und nicht-assoziativen Lernen auf. In den Untersuchungen werden Bienen verschiedenen Genotyps, verschiedenen Alters und mit verschiedener Sammelrolle verwendet. Die Funktion von potentiellen endogenen Modulatoren und von intrazellulären Signalmolekülen auf die Zuckerwasserempfindlichkeit wird analysiert. Die individuelle Empfindlichkeit für Zuckerwasserreize wird mit Hilfe des Rüsselreflexes oder durch Ableitungen am Proboscismuskels M17 bestimmt. Die Versuche zeigen, daß Pollensammlerinnen empfindlicher für Zuckerwassereize als Nicht-Pollensammlerinnen sind, Bienen der genetischen Linie "high pollen hoarding" sind empfindlicher als solche der Linie "low-pollen hoarding". Ältere Sammlerbienen sind empfindlicher als Jungbienen. Die individuelle Zuckerwasserempfindlichkeit bestimmt beim taktilen und olfaktorischen assoziativen Lernen in starkem Maße den Verlauf von Akquisition, Extinktion und Diskriminierung. Dabei ist die Zuckerwasserperzeption an der Proboscis für das Lernniveau entscheidender als die an der Antenne. Auch beim nicht-assoziativen Lernen determiniert die individuelle Zuckerwasserempfindlichkeit den Grad und den Verlauf von Habituation und Sensitisierung. Liganden für biogene Amin-Rezeptoren können die Zuckerwasserreaktion modulieren. Die Injektion von Oktopamin und Tyramin erhöht die Zuckerwasserempfindlichkeit, während Dopamin und der Dopamin-Rezeptor-Agonist 6,7-ADTN funktionell antagonistisch wirken. Die Aktivität der PKA im Antennallobus korreliert mit der Zuckerwasserempfindlichkeit. Bienen mit niedriger Empfindlichkeit zeigen eine signifikant niedrigere PKA-Aktivität als Bienen mit hoher Zuckerwasserempfindlichkeit. Die hier vorgestellten Experimente zeigen, daß die Zuckerwasserempfindlichkeit einer Biene alle untersuchten Formen des Lernens entscheidend beeinflußt. Damit ist ein wichtiger Faktor identifiziert worden, der durch biogene Amine moduliert werden kann und der Unterschiede der Verhaltensplastizität bei Bienen erklärt.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work shows the effects of individual sucrose responsiveness on two forms of associative and non-associative learning in the honey bee. In addition, the effects of genotype, foraging role and age on sucrose responsiveness, associative learning and discrimination are presented. It is tested whether myograms of the proboscis muscle 17 can determine sucrose responsiveness more accurately than behavioural tests. It is further analysed whether the three biogenic amines octopamine, tyramine and dopamine, and the dopamine receptor agonist ADTN can modulate sucrose responsiveness. In search of neuronal correlates for sucrose responsiveness the activity of cAMP-dependent protein kinase (PKA) in the antennal lobes of bees with different sucrose responsiveness is studied. Sucrose responsiveness varies between individuals of different genotypes, foraging roles or ages. Associative tactile and olfactory learning is strongly affected by individual sucrose responsiveness. Bees with high sucrose responsiveness show a higher acquisition level and less extinction than individuals with low sucrose responsiveness. Genotype or foraging role have no separate effects on associative learning or extinction. Age has an additional effect on acquisition, which cannot be explained by differences in sucrose responsiveness. Discrimination depends on acquisition and is thus indirectly related to sucrose responsiveness. Genotype has a separate effect on discrimination in foragers but not in preforagers. The short sucrose stimulation of the antenna during associative tactile learning only has a week effect on the learning performance. The sucrose concentration offered to the proboscis as reward strongly determines the level of acquisition and extinction. Discrimination is best when antenna and proboscis are stimulated with a low sucrose concentration. The degree of non-associative habituation and sensitisation is strongly determined by individual sucrose responsiveness. Bees with high sucrose responsiveness demonstrate weaker habituation and stronger sensitisation than bees with low sucrose responsiveness. The sucrose concentration of the habituating or sensitising stimuli strongly affects habituation and sensitisation. Age affects habituation but not sensitisation. Sucrose responsiveness can be exactly determined by myograms from the proboscis muscle 17, which differs in its spike rate when the antennae of a bee are stimulated with different sucrose concentrations, even when the bee responds with proboscis extension to all sucrose concentrations offered. Modulation of sucrose responsiveness by biogenic amines is possible. Octopamine and tyramine injections result in a dose-dependent increase in sucrose responsiveness. Dopamine and ADTN decrease sucrose responsiveness in a dose-dependent manner. This modulation of sucrose responsiveness is reversible. Sucrose responsiveness covaries with PKA activity in the antennal lobes. Bees with high sucrose responsiveness show higher PKA activity than bees with low sucrose responsiveness. Thirty minutes after feeding, PKA activity is higher than 90 min after feeding. These findings show that individual sucrose responsiveness is a very good indicator of the "physiological state" of a bee and can explain a large part of individual differences in non-associative and associative learning. The neuronal mechanisms regulating individual sucrose responsiveness are not yet known, but PKA activity in the antennal lobes and biogenic amines appear to be involved in these processes.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2001-10-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/324</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/324/scheiner_ricarda.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
