<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1537">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1537</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Physiologie nährstofflimitierter Bakterien in Membranbioreaktoren</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Physiology of substrate-limited bacteria in membrane bioreactors</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Keil, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Heterotrophe Bakterien sind sowohl in natürlichen wie in technischen Systemen vielfach oligotrophen Bedingungen ausgesetzt, auf die sie speziesspezifisch mit unterschiedlichen Überlebensstrategien reagieren. Eine mögliche Reaktion auf nährstofflimitierende Bedingungen ist das Einstellen der Zellteilung, so dass die zur Verfügung stehenden Substrate hauptsächlich für den Erhalt der Zelle genutzt werden (Erhaltungsstoffwechsel). Unser derzeitiges Verständnis der Anpassungsstrategien entstammt zumeist Untersuchungen an relativ kurzzeitigen Kultivierungen in Batch- oder Chemostatkulturen. Diese eignen sich für die Analyse kurzfristiger Stressantworten und deren Regulation, spiegeln jedoch nicht die langfristig nährstofflimitierenden Bedingungen wider, denen Bakterien in ihren natürlichen Habitaten und artifiziellen Systemen wie in der Abwasserreinigung ausgesetzt sind. In dieser Arbeit wurden die verfahrenstechnischen Voraussetzungen zur langfristigen Untersuchung von substratlimitierten, nicht-wachsenden Bakterien im Erhaltungsstoffwechsel geschaffen und das Wachstumsverhalten einer Reinkultur eines Escherichia coli Umweltisolates erstmals unter diesen Bedingungen detailliert beschrieben und dem von langfristig hungernden Zellen in Batch-Kulturen gegenübergestellt. Dazu wurde ein Membranbioreaktorsystem (MBR) etabliert, das die langfristige Kultivierung der Bakterien bei kontinuierlicher Versorgung mit gering konzentrierten Nährstoffen unter vollständigem Bakterienrückhalt ermöglichte. Die Bakterienpopulation im MBR zeigte nach einer vierwöchigen Wachstumsphase eine gleich bleibende Biomassekonzentration 6,6 g Trockengewicht pro Liter während die Wachstumsphase der Batch-Kultur bereits nach wenigen Tagen bei einer um 90 % geringeren Zellzahl abgeschlossen war. Ein gleich bleibend geringer Anteil an toten Zellen (10 %), ein geringer Gehalt an mikroskopisch detektierbaren Teilungsstadien sowie distinkte C2 und C4 Verteilungen der DNA und das Fehlen von mikroskopisch sichtbaren Lyseprodukten deuten auf ein Nicht-Wachstum der Zellen im MBR ab der fünften Woche hin. Im weiteren Verlauf der zehnwöchigen Kultivierung wurde die Ausbildung von Subpopulationen der nicht-wachsenden Zellen mit unterschiedlicher Aktivität observiert. Während der Anteil vermeintlich lebender Zellen (BacLight) im MBR über den Versuchszeitraum bei 90 % annähernd konstant blieb, nahmen die Anteile potentiell teilungsfähiger Zellen (DVC), der hybridisierbaren Zellen (FISH) und der metabolisch aktiven Zellen (CTC) sowie der kultivierbaren Zellen (KBE) ab. Demgegenüber stieg der Anteil der lebensfähigen, aber nicht kultivierbaren Zellen (VBNC) bis auf 60 % an. Der Batch-Ansatz zeigte einen im Vergleich zum MBR um gut 50 % verminderten Anteil an metabolisch aktiven Zellen (CTC), wohingegen der Anteil an kultivierbaren Zellen am Ende des Experimentes im Batch-Ansatz um gut ein Drittel höher war als im MBR. Mit Hilfe der Durchflusszytometrie wurde im MBR neben den auch im Batch-Ansatz auftretenden C2 und C4 Verteilungen der DNA, eine Subpopulation von Zellen (47 %) mit reduziertem DNA-Gehalt detektiert, die im Batch-Ansatz nicht auftrat. Weitere Hinweise auf eine veränderte Zellphysiologie der Bakterien im Langzeit-Erhaltungsstoffwechsel lieferte der Vergleich der mittels 2D-Gelelektrophorese bzw. mittels MALDI-TOF Massenspektrometrie visualisierten Proteinmuster von wachsenden sowie kurzzeitig und langfristig nicht-wachsenden Zellen im MBR. Insgesamt wurden beim Vergleich von wachsenden und nicht-wachsenden Zellen circa 146 Proteine und beim Vergleich von kurzzeitig und langfristig nicht-wachsenden Zellen circa 73 Proteine unterschiedlich exprimiert. Weiterhin konnten MBR- bzw. Batch-spezifische Proteine im niedermolekularen Bereich mit MALDI-TOF MS nachgewiesen werden. Die in Fraßversuchen ermittelte Verwertbarkeit der Bakterien aus dem MBR für den bakterivoren Ciliaten Tetrahymena thermophila war im Gegensatz zur Verwertbarkeit von Bakterien aus dem Batch-Ansatz und aus einer Übernachtkultur zudem vermindert. Zusammenfassend ist davon auszugehen, dass nicht-wachsende aber kontinuierlich mit geringen Substratkonzentrationen versorgte Bakterien im MBR unter Ausbildung von heterogenen Populationen komplexe Adaptionsstrategien verfolgen, die sich von hungernden Zellen in Batch-Kulturen unterscheiden. Die in dieser Arbeit an Reinkulturen durchgeführten Untersuchungen verdeutlichen die Vielschichtigkeit der bakteriellen Anpassungsmöglichkeiten und bilden die Grundlage für weitere Untersuchungen und das Verständnis der Vorgänge in komplexeren Systemen wie in technischen MBR-Anlagen zur Abwasserreinigung.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Heterotrophic bacteria face oligotrophic conditions in natural habitats to which they are able to respond in a species-specific manner. As one possible adaptation to nutrient limitation bacteria stop to proliferate and start using substrates just for maintenance purposes. Our current knowledge of bacterial adaptation to nutrient-limited conditions is primarily based on short-term experiments in batch culture or chemostats. These systems are suitable to study short-termed stress-responses and their regulation, but do not reflect the long-termed nutrient-limited conditions, which bacteria face in their natural habitats or in artificial systems like wastewater treatment MBRs. In this study, the procedural requirements for the long-termed examination of substrate-limited, non-growing bacteria displaying maintenance metabolism were established. A membrane bioreactor system (MBR) was set up, that allowed the cultivation of bacteria under continuous supply of low-concentrated nutrients and complete biomass retention over extended time periods. The growth characteristics of an environmental Escherichia coli A3 strain under these conditions were investigated for the first time over a period of 10 weeks and compared to long-term starving cells of the same strain in a batch system. After four weeks of growth, the biomass of the bacterial population in the membrane bioreactor remainted constant at 6.6 g dry weight l-1, while the growth period of the batch culture lasted for only a few days with a 90 % lower cell density. Dead cells comprised only a minor fraction of 10 % at most in the MBR population as indicated by the LIVE/DEAD® BacLightTM Kit. Only few dividing cells as well as no products of cell lysis were observed. Together with the distinct C2 and C4 subpopulations examined by flow cytometry these findings point to very slow or even no growth of the bacteria in the MBR from the 5th week on. During the following six weeks subpopulations of the non-growing cells displaying different cell activities were observed, which were monitored using different kinds of (fluorescence-) microscopy techniques such as DVC, CTC, BacLight, FISH and compared to the fraction of culturable cells (CFU). While the fraction of living cells (BacLight) remained constant at a high value of over 90 %, the fraction of cells potentially able to divide (DVC) and being culturable (CFU) as well as the fraction of cells showing metabolic activity (CTC) and the fraction of cells giving a positive signal after fluorescence in situ hybridisation (FISH) declined during the experiment. In contrast the fraction of viable but non-culturable cells (VBNC) increased up to 60 % during the continuous cultivation. Although bacteria in the MBR system and in batch culture showed similarities as the high fraction of living and hybridisable cells, some fundamental differences could be observed pointing to different physiological states of the substrate-limited, non-growing cells in the MBR system and the starving cells in batch culture. Compared to the MBR only half of the bacteria in batch culture showed metabolic activity (CTC) whereas the fraction of cells forming colonies on agar plates (CFU) was one third higher than in the MBR system. Flow cytometric analyses revealed, beside the two subpopulations C2 and C4 ermerging in both MBR and batch culture, a fraction of cells displaying a low DNA content of less then the DNA content of C1 cells. This fraction of &lt; C1 cells was only apparent in MBR and increased to a proportion of 47 % at the end of the continuous culture period. Proteomic studies revealed additional arguments for different physiological states in growing and non-growing substrate-limited E. coli cells in MBR and starved E. coli cells from batch culture. 2D-gelelectrophoresis showed an expected high number of 146 differentially expressed proteins in growing and long-term non-growing E. coli cells in the MBR. But even between bacteria that just had passed into the non-growing state and cells being in that state for about 30 days 73 differentially expressed proteins were observable. Moreover different MBR- and batch-specific proteins in the low molecular range could be observed by means of MALDI-TOF MS. Grazing experiments with the protist Tetrahymena thermophila were performed to examine the quality of E. coli cells in different metabolic states as prey organisms. Growth of T. thermophila was reduced when fed with non-growing E. coli cells from the MBR compared to cells from batch culture or overnight culture. Generally the results of this work indicate that long-term non-growing cells in MBR provided with limiting amount of nutrients display a different physiological mode than long-term starving cells in batch cultures. These findings illustrate the complexity of bacterial adaptations to nutrient limitation and create the basis for further investigations of more complex systems e. g. MBR-units for wastewater treatment.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-07-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1537</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15882</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15882</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1537/keil_claudia.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
