<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2641">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2641</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Environmental stress response in filamentous fungi: the impact of ion homeostasis on gene regulation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die Stressantwort filamentöser Pilze auf Umweltbedingungen: der Einfluss der Ionenhomöostase auf die Genregulation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Spielvogel, Anja</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">A fast adaptation of microorganisms to changing environmental conditions is essential for their survival and growth in different habitats. External signals such as altered ion concentrations within the medium are triggered into the cell and direct the regulation of transcription factors and their corresponding target genes. This work aimed to analyse the response of the model fungus Aspergillus nidulans to different environmental stress conditions. Two transcription factors, CrzA and SltA, have been isolated and characterised with regard to their DNA binding properties and to their role in cellular stress response. DNA-protein-binding assays demonstrated that both transcription factors, CrzA and SltA, recognise the same consensus sequences as their corresponding homologues in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (Crz1p) and Hypocrea jecorina (AceI), respectively. Furthermore, phenotypic analysis of the deletion strains ∆crzA, ∆sltA and the double deletion strain ∆crzA, ∆sltA revealed that both transcription factors are necessary for the adaptation to ambient alkaline pH and for ion homeostasis. Northern analyses, carried out in A. nidulans, revealed genes that are both commonly and independently regulated by CrzA and SltA. Genes encoding for ChsB (chitin synthase B) and VcxA (vacuolar calcium exchanger) are positively regulated by CrzA, whereas SltA is a negative regulator of vcxA gene and acts as a positive regulator in enaA gene expression (putative sodium and lithium exporter). Therefore, it can be postulated that both transcription factors, CrzA and SltA, interactively control or balance gene expression, essential in ion homeostasis and especially in Ca2+ homeostasis. Knowledge deduced in A. nidulans was subsequently transferred to A. giganteus to get acloser insight into the regulation of the afp gene expression (encoding the antifungal protein, AFP). Results indicate that genes homologous to crzA and sltA are also present in A. giganteus. Reporter assays indicate that CrzA and SltA regulate afp expression in an opposing manner. CrzA is an activator of afp expression, whereas SltA is acting as a repressor of afp expression. In vitro interactions between CrzA respectively SltA and afp promoter elements hint to a direct role in afp gene regulation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Eine schnelle Anpassung von Mikroorganismen auf schwankende Umweltbedingungen ist essentiell für das Überleben und die Besiedlung von verschiedensten Habitaten. ÄußereBedingungen, z.B. veränderte Ionenkonzentrationen im Medium, werden dabei über Signaltransduktionswege in die Zelle geleitet und führen unter anderem zur Regulation der Aktivität von Transkriptionsfaktoren und deren Zielgenen. Ziel dieser Arbeit war es, die Reaktion des Modelorganismus Aspergillus nidulans auf verschiedene äußere Stressbedingungen zu analysieren. Es wurden zwei Transkriptionsfaktoren, CrzA und SltA, aus A. nidulans isoliert und hinsichtlich ihrer DNA Bindungseigenschaften untersucht. Ferner wurde deren Funktion in der zellulären Stressantwort analysiert. DNA-Protein-Bindungsstudien zeigten, dass CrzA die gleiche Sequenzspezifität wie das homologe Protein Crz1p aus Saccharomyces cerevisiae aufweist, sowie dass SltA die gleiche DNA-Sequenz wie der Transkriptionsfaktor AceI aus Hypocrea jecorina erkennt. Die phenotypische Analyse von CrzA bzw. SltA Deletionsmutanten zeigte deutlich, dass beide Transkriptionsfaktoren für die Anpassung an alkalische Mediumbedingungen sowie für die Ionenhomöostase benötigt werden. Mit Hilfe von Northern-Analysen konnte gezeigt werden, dass beide Transkriptionsfaktoren die Expression unterschiedlicher als auch gemeinsamer Zielgene regulieren. Gene kodierend für die Chitinsynthase B und einem vakuolären Calciumtransporter, genannt VcxA, werden in positiver Weise durch CrzA reguliert. SltA agiert als negativer Regulator der vcxA sowie als positiver Regulator der enaA Genexpression (putativer zellmembranlokalisierter Natrium- und Lithiumtransporter). Es kann daher geschlussfolgert werden, dass CrzA und SltA interaktiv die Expression von Genen beeinflussen und teilweise ausbalancieren, die essentiell für dieIonenhomöostase, insbesondere in der Ca2+ Homöostase sind. Die Ergebnisse aus den Versuchen mit A. nidulans wurden daraufhin herangezogen, um die Expression des Gens zu analysieren, welches für das Antifungalprotein (AFP) in A. giganteus kodiert. Es wurde gezeigt, dass die Gene für beide Transkriptionsfaktoren in A. giganteus vorliegen und dass sie an der Regulation des afp - Gens beteiligt sind, wobei auch hier eine gegensätzliche Regulation vorliegt. CrzA ist ein Aktivator und SltA ist ein Repressor der afp Expression. In vitro Interaktionen von CrzA bzw. SltA mit Sequenzen aus dem afp Promoter weisen auf eine direkte Regulation hin.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2641</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18712</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18712</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2641/spielvogel_anja.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
