<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:19Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2830">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2830</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The role of TPL-2 - ERK signaling in inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Der TPL-2 - ERK Signalweg in chronisch entzündlichen Darmerkrankungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lawrenz, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Inflammatory bowel disease, namely Crohn’s disease and Ulcerative colitis, are characterized by dysregulated immune responses to the intestinal microbiota leading to chronic inflammation of the colon and small intestine. Prolonged and enhanced activation of NF-ĸB was shown in the intestinal lamina propria of Crohn's disease patients (Visekruna et al., 2006). This correlates with overproduction of the proinflammatory cytokines TNFα and IL-1β (Schreiber et al., 1999), which are among the most important cytokines that drive intestinal inflammation. In addition to NF-ĸB, the MAP kinase pathway TPL-2-ERK also regulates synthesis of TNFα and IL-1β. We found that the TPL-2-ERK pathway is activated in the inflamed intestinal tissue of patients with Crohn’s disease but not in Ulcerative colitis patients. Furthermore, by studying the murine DSS-colitis model we found that the absence of TPL-2-ERK signaling ameliorates intestinal inflammation. This was mainly due to inhibited production of the pro-inflammatory cytokines TNFα, IL-1β and IL-6 in response to bacterial components. Therefore, our results clearly show that in addition to NF-ĸB signaling increased TPL-2-ERK activation is responsible for enhanced production of pro-inflammatory cytokines leading to intestinal inflammation. Interestingly, we found that cytokine suppression in the absence of TPL-2 signals was at least partly mediated by accumulation of transcriptional inactive NF-ĸB p50 homodimers in the nucleus. NF-ĸB homodimer accumulation also occurs during LPS tolerance and displays an effective mechanism to block LPS induced transcription (Ziegler-Heitbrock et al., 1994). Thus, by targeting TPL-2, we found a new mechanism to modulate NF-ĸB activation after immune stimulation, while leaving NF-ĸB mediated protective cell functions undisturbed. These properties of TPL-2 kinase make it a promising new target for an anti-inflammatory drug that may have potential use in the treatment of Crohn’s disease patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Chronisch-entzündliche Darmerkrankungen wie Morbus Crohn und Colitis ulcerosa sind als unkontrollierte Immunreaktionen gegenüber der Darmflora beschrieben, die zur chronischen Entzündung des Darmes führen. In der Darmschleimhaut von Morbus Crohn Patienten wurde eine verstärkte NF-ĸB Aktivität nachgewiesen (Visekruna et al., 2006). In diesem Zusammenhang wurden auch erhöhte Mengen von pro-inflammatorische Zytokinen TNFα und IL-1β beschrieben (Schreiber et al., 1999), die ausschlaggebend an der Entzündung im Darm beteiligt sind. Neben NF-ĸB wird die Produktion von TNFα und IL-1β auch von dem MAP Kinase Signalweg TPL-2-ERK reguliert. Wir konnten zeigen, dass der TPL-2-ERK Signalweg im entzündeten Darmgewebe von Morbus Crohn Patienten aber nicht in Patienten mit Colitis ulcerosa aktiviert ist. Weiterhin konnten wir im Mausmodell zeigen, dass das Fehlen von TPL-2-ERK Signalen zu einer Verringerung der Darmentzündung führt. Dieser Effekt wurde vor allem durch die Unterdrückung der pro-inflammatorischen Zytokine TNFα, IL-1β und IL-6 herbeigeführt, dessen Produktion von bakteriellen Bestandteilen stimuliert wird. Unsere Ergebnisse zeigen deutlich, dass neben NF-ĸB Signalen die Aktivierung des TPL-2-ERK Signalweges zu einer verstärkten Produktion von pro-inflammatorischen Zytokinen und damit zur Darmentzündung führt. Weiterhin konnten wir zeigen, dass die Unterdrückung der Zytokinproduktion bei fehlenden TPL-2 Signale zum Teil durch die Anhäufung von inaktiven NF-ĸB p50 Homodimeren im Zellkern entsteht. LPS-Toleranz führt ebenfalls zu einer Akkumulation von NF-ĸB Homodimeren (Ziegler-Heitbrock et al., 1994) , die eine LPS-induzierte Transkription effektiv blockieren. Mit der Hemmung von TPL-2 Signalen zeigen wir also einen neuen Mechanismus mit dem NF-ĸB Aktivierung nach Immunstimulation moduliert werden kann und ohne die NF-ĸB vermittelten protektiven Zellfunktionen zu stören. Diese Eigenschaft macht die TPL-2 Kinase zu einem interessanten Zielprotein für entzündungshemmende Medikamente, die potentiell für die Behandlung von Morbus Crohn Patienten eingesetzt werden könnten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-03-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2830</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29884</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29884</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2830/lawrenz_maria.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
