<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1810">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1810</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Evaluation of novel vaccine candidates against tuberculosis in murine models of persistent and latent infection</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Evaluierung neuer Vakzine-Kandidaten gegen Tuberkulose in Maus-Modellen persistenter und latenter Infektion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Desel, Christiane Anna-Elisabeth</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this thesis, novel vaccine candidates against pulmonary tuberculosis (TB) were assessed in models of persistent and latent infection. In the first part, immunogenicity and protective capacity of plasmid DNA vaccines encoding the dormancy-associated antigens hspX, TB31.7, Rv1733c or Rv2628 was analysed in pre- and post-exposure vaccination experiments. In order to test the capability of these DNA vaccines to prevent reactivation of latent M.tb infection, short-duration drug-induced latency models were evaluated. However, none of the experimental setups yielded a working model for latent TB infection in mice. It was not possible to induce protection against pulmonary TB by plasmid DNA vaccines in any of the experiments. It is most likely that in none of the murine models for pulmonary TB infection tested here, bacteria were in a ‚Äútrue‚Ä? state of dormancy. If the bacteria are not dormant and thus not expressing dormancy-associated antigens, plasmid DNA vaccines encoding these antigens cannot confer protection against TB infection. In the second part, the immune response elicited by vaccination with BCG or recBCG, involved in the defence against infection with M.tb was analysed in detail. Vaccination with recBCG conferred superior protection against TB. After vaccination a strong TH1 polarised immune response was detected, regardless which strain of BCG was used. Splenocytes of mice vaccinated with recBCG were capable of producing more IL-17 in response to PPD stimulation. Post infection, cells isolated from the lungs of mice vaccinated with recBCG produced substantially more IL-2, IL-6, GM-CSF and TNF-a. Flow cytometry revealed mostly CD4 T cells responding and a higher percentage of them were poly-functional (secreting any combination of IL-2, IL-17, IFN-g and TNF-a) after vaccination with recBCG. Most likely these cells are indicative of a more sustained memory T cell response generated by vaccination with recBCG. Thus, the protective TH1 memory T cell response after vaccination with recBCG is maintained, whereas the memory response generated by vaccination with BCG wanes over time.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Ziel dieser Arbeit war es, experimentelle Impfstoffe gegen Tuberkulose (TB) in latenten und persistenten murinen Infektionsmodellen zu evaluieren. Im ersten Teil wurde die Immunogenit√§t, sowie das protektive Potential, von Plasmid-DNA Vakzinen, die die Dormanz-assoziierten Antigene hspX, TB31.7, Rv1733c oder Rv2628 kodieren, in Tiermodellen untersucht. Um eine Schutzfunktion von Dormanz-assoziierten DNA Vakzinen gegen Reaktivierung latenter TB untersuchen zu k√∂nnen, wurden Kurzzeit Antibiotika-induzierte Latenzmodelle getestet. Es konnte jedoch mit keiner Behandlung ein zuverl√§ssigens Tiermodell latenter TB etabliert werden. Da sich die Mykobakterien in keinem der untersuchten Tiermodelle in einem echten Dormanz-Zustand befanden und folglich auch keine Latenzassoziierten Antigene exprimierten, konnte in keinem der Versuche eine Schutzfunktion von Plasmid-DNA nachgewiesen werden. Im zweiten Teil dieser Arbeit sollte die sch√ºtzende Immunantwort gegen TB nach Vakzinierung mit BCG oder rekombinantem BCG (rekBCG) untersucht werden. Vakzinierung mit rekBCG vermittelte einen wesentlich st√§rkeren Schutz als BCG. Nach Vakzinierung mit beiden BCG St√§mmen konnte eine starke TH1 Immmunantwort nachgewiesen werden. Milzzellen von M√§usen, die mit rekBCG vakziniert wurden, sekretierten wesentlich mehr IL-17 nach Stimulation mit PPD. 90 Tage nach Infektion sekretierten Lymphozyten, die aus den Lungen von rekBCG vakzinierten M√§usen isoliert wurden, deutlich mehr IL-2, IL-6, GM-CSF und TNF-a. Mit Hilfe der Durchflu√üzytometrie konnten CD4 T-Zellen als Hauptquelle dieser Zytokine identifiziert werden. Au√üerdem konnte ein erh√∂hter Anteil von polyfunktionalen T-Zellen, die Kombinationen von IL-2, IL-17, IFN-g sowie TNF-a produzieren, nachgewiesen werden. Die hier durchgef√ºhrten Experimente lassen den Schlu√ü zu, da√ü die durch rekBCG vermittelte, sch√ºtzende TH1 Immunantwort, besser erhalten wird, wogegen die durch BCG vermittelte Immunantwort im Verlauf der TB Infektion nachl√§√üt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-07-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1810</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1810/original_desel_christiane.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1810/desel_christiane.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
