<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:02:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:4411">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:4411</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-05-28</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:book</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:710</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Entwurfsbasiert Forschen</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Design-Based Research</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aufmkolk, Fine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frank, Ute (Prof.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hahn, Achim (Prof. Dr.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hopstock, Lars</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jonas, Wolfgang (Prof. Dr.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Palz, Norbert (Prof. Dr.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sch√§ffner, Wolfgang (Prof. Dr.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schlaich, Mike (Prof. Dr.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmid, Volker (Prof. Dr.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tang, Huiran</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vogt, G√ºnther (Prof.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weidinger, J√ºrgen (Prof.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yocoub, Susanne Isabel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yong, Guo (Dr.)</dc:creator>
          <dc:contributor>Yacoub, Susanne Isabel</dc:contributor>
          <dc:subject>ddc:710</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Heute sind die Entwurfsdisziplinen Landschaftsarchitektur und Architektur an den Universit√§ten aufgefordert, wissenschaftliche Forschung zu betreiben, die sich an den Forschungsformaten der Natur- oder Geisteswissenschaft orientieren sollen. Ist das sinnvoll? Ist das m√∂glich? Wie ist das m√∂glich? Welche eigenst√§ndigen Methoden k√∂nnen die Entwurfsdisziplinen anwenden? Kann es der Methode der Entwurfsbasierten Forschung gelingen, ‚Äûindividuelles K√∂nnen‚Ä? erfahrener Entwerfer mit ‚Äûwissenschaftlich abgesichertem‚Ä? Wissen zusammenzuf√ºhren? F√ºhrt dieser Br√ºckenschlag zu einer besonderen Art des Entwurfswissens, das in st√§rkerer Weise durch Entwurfshaltung und Entwurfsprozess gepr√§gt ist? &#13;
&#13;
Unter den drei Rubriken Entwerfen und Wissenschaft, Atmosph√§ren entwerfen, Entwerfen und Konstruieren finden sich Antworten von Entwerfern und Theoretikern wie Wolfgang Jonas, Wolfgang Sch√§ffner, Achim Hahn, G√ºnther Vogt, Andr√© Kempe, Wolfgang Palz, Mike Schlaich, Volker Schmid und J√ºrgen Weidinger, die sich diesen Fragen aus individueller Perspektive n√§hern. Beitr√§ge von Promovierenden und Nachwuchsentwerfern suchen und untersuchen Forschungsfragen, die neue Wechselwirkungen von Entwurf und Wissenschaft ausloten.&#13;
</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Today design disciplines at universities like landscape architecture and architecture are asked to conduct research using methods which respond to research in the natural sciences and humanities. Is that reasonable? Is that possible? Which independent approach could design disciplines follow? Will the method of design-based research succeed in connecting ‚Äúindividual knowledge‚Ä? of experienced designers to ‚Äúscientifically verified knowledge‚Ä?? Could this integral approach lead to a type of designerly knowledge that is influenced by the design process and the individual attitude of the designer? Under the three captions Design and Science, Designing Atmospheres, Design and Construction, initial answers are given from the individual perspectives of designers and researchers, architecture critics, well-known landscape architects and architects. PhD candidates and young designers investigate potential research questions that explore interactions between design and science. &#13;
The authors manage an intense walk from theory to practice. Norbert Palz, for example, who teaches Experimental Design an University of Arts Berlin, describes how digitally contolled material properties support innovative architecture. Young researcher Guo Yong, inspired through analysing design theories, develops a design concept for an unautorized landfill near Beijing. Architect Andr√© Kempe from Dutch Atelier Kempe Thill explains, how building typologies promote architectural experimentation. Graphics and photos illustrate fields of research and applications.&#13;
</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2014-05-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>book</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:book</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/4411</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-44115</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-44115</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-7983-2653-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/4411/entwurfsbasiert_forschen.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
