<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3594">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3594</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:660</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Synthesis of novel polymeric hybrid nanoparticles with enhanced interfacial and colloidal properties for biomedical studies</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Synthese von neuartigen polymeren Hybridnanopartikeln mit verbesserten Grenzflächen-und Kolloidaleigenschaften für biomedizinische Studien</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Natte, Kishore</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:660</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The reduced size of nanoparticles (diameter &lt; 100 nm) confers them high specific surface areas and permeability through many biological pathways resulting in high interaction with biological systems. Therefore, in the recent years, nanoparticles (NPs) have increasingly found many applications in biomedical research. Herein, silica-based NPs are among the most promising candidates for biomedical studies due to their relative low toxicity and the possibility of functional variability. The main focus of this thesis work has been the synthesis and characterisation of novel hybrid NPs with enhanced properties for biomedical studies. More specifically, suppression of protein adsorption and achievement of highly fluorescent NPs in serum-rich media are well focused. First, a chemical strategy for the preparation of highly fluorescent silica nanoparticles by covalent attachment of Alexa dyes and subsequent shielding by an additional pure silica shell is well presented. These nanoparticles were investigated by Dynamic light scattering (DLS), Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) and fluorescence spectroscopy, the latter includes determination of absolute fluorescence quantum yields of such scattering suspensions with an integrating sphere setup and the assignment of fluorescence intensity values. At low shelling extension core-shell fluorescent silica nanoparticles show smooth surfaces and high quantum yields, even comparable to those for free dyes. However, by increasing the amount of shell precursor, nanoparticle surfaces show raspberry morphologies and decay of the quantum yields. Secondly, two different types of novel silica-poly(ethylene glycol) hybrid nanoparticles (H-SiO2-PEG and G- SiO2@PEG) have been synthesized by use of the same polymer precursor: Here the influence of concentration of the polymer precursor poly(ethylene glycol) methyl ether-3-(triethoxysilyl) propyl urethane (mPEG-IPTES) on the particle properties was scrutinised. For polymer grafted NPs, the concentration of polymer precursor increases the PEG density and the hydrophobicity of the NPs surface. On the other hand, for condensated NPs, the polymer precursor influences the size, but not the density of polymer chains on the NPs surface, which indicates that PEG on the surface of the NPs effectively reduces the adsorption of Bovine serum albumin (BSA). Finally, the influence of polymer length on the ability to repel BSA adsorption onto nanoparticles is reported. SNPs@PEG with different molecular weights (mPEG: 350, 2000 and 5000 g/mol) were synthesized by nucleophilic substitution of tosylated mPEG to aminated silica nanoparticles (chemical grafting). The resulted hybrid nanoparticles were consistently characterized by DLS, TEM, Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR), Thermogravimetric analysis (TGA) and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS). BSA at different concentrations was used as a model protein to study the protein-corona formation after adsorption onto the pristine and modified nanoparticles (SNPs@PEG). For pristine SNPs and SNPs@PEG (MW = 350 g/mol), zeta potential at different incubation times (0, 24 and 48 h) show a dynamic evolution of the nanoparticle-protein corona. Conversely, for SNPs@PEG with MW ≥ 2000 g/mol, a significant suppression of corona formation and time evolution was observed. In resume, protein corona is strongly influenced by the adsorption inhibition of PEG surfaces.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die geringe Größe von Nanopartikeln (Durchmesser &lt; 100 nm) gewährleistet sowohl eine hohe spezifische Oberfläche sowie Permeabilität durch eine Vielzahl biologischer Systeme. Als Folge weisen Nanopartikel (NP) eine starke Wechselwirkung mit biologischen Systemen auf, wodurch diese in den letzten Jahren zunehmend in der biomedizinischen Forschung Anwendung fanden. Aufgrund der relativ geringen Toxizität sowie der Möglichkeit zur Einführung unterschiedlicher funktioneller Gruppen eignen sich besonders auf Siliziumdioxid (Silica) basierende Nanopartikel für biomedizinische Studien. Der Schwerpunkt dieser Doktorarbeit lag in der Synthese und Charakterisierung von neuartigen Hybrid-NP mit verbesserten Eigenschaften für biologische Studien. Insbesondere soll eine Unterdrückung der Proteinadsorption erlangt werden sowie stark fluoreszierende NP in Gegenwart serumreicher Medien erhalten werden. Zu Beginn wird der Syntheseweg zur Darstellung hoch fluoreszierender Silica-Nanopartikel präsentiert, durch kovalente Anbindung des Alexa Farbstoffs und nachfolgender Ummantelung durch eine zusätzliche Silicahülle. Diese Nanopartikel wurden mittels dynamischen Lichtstreuung (DLS), Transmissionselektronenmikroskopie (TEM) und Fluoreszenzspektroskopie untersucht. Letztgenannte methode beinhaltet die Bestimmung der absoluten Quantenausbeute solcher streuenden Suspensionen mit einer integrierenden Kugelkonfiguration sowie die Zuordnung von Helligkeitswerten. Bei geringer Ausdehnung der Hülle zeigen Silica NP mit Kern-Schale Architektur eine glatte Oberfläche und hohe Quantenausbeuten, in Größenordnung der freien Farbstoffe. Eine Erhöhung der Menge an Hüllen-Precusor führt zu einer himbeerartigen Morphologie der Oberfläche und einer Verminderung der Quantenausbeute. Es folgt die Darstellung zweier unterschiedlicher Typen neuartiger Silica-Polyethylenglykolhybride NP (H-SiO2-PEG und G-SiO2@PEG) unter Verwendung desselben polymer precursors oder desselben polymer precursors: Der Einfluß der Konzentration des polymer preursors Poly(ethylen glykol) methylether-3-(triethoxysilyl) propyl urethan (mPEG-IPTES) auf die Partikeleigenschaften wurde ausführlich untersucht. Bei polymergepfropften NP bestimmt die Konzentration des polymer precursors die Dichte des angekoppelten PEGs und folglich die Hydrophobie der NP Oberfläche. Dagegen beeinflusst bei kondensierten NP der precursor die Partikelgröße, aber nicht die Dichte der Polymerketten auf der Oberfläche. Abschließend wird der Einfluss der Polymerlänge auf die Verminderung der BSA Adsorption beschrieben. SNPs@PEG mit verschiedenen Molekulargewichten des mPEG (Mw = 350, 2000 und 5000 g/mol) wurden an die NP Oberfläche durch nucleophile Substitution von tosyliertem mPEG an aminierte Silica NP kovalent angebunden (hemisches Pfropfen). Die resultierenden Hybrid-NP wurden einheitlich mittels DLS, TEM, Fourier-Transformations-Infrarotspektroskopie (FTIR), thermogravimetrischer Analyse (TGA) und Photoelektronenspektroskopie (PES) charakterisiert. Bovine Serum Albumin (BSA) wurde in verschiedenen Konzentrationen als Modellprotein verwendet, um die Ausbildung der protein corona durch Adsorption an ursprünglichen sowie an modifizierten NP oder modifizierten NPs (SNPs@PEG) zu untersuchen. Das Zeta-Potenzial der ursprünglichen Silica NP sowie SNPs@PEG (Mw = 350 g/mol) zeigen eine dynamische Entwicklung der Nanopartikel-protein corona in Abhängigkeit von der Inkubationsdauer (0, 24, 48 h). Im Gegensatz hierzu konnte bei SNPs@PEG mit Mw 2000 g/mol eine signifikante Minderung der Ausbildung der protein corona sowie der zeitlichen Entwicklung beobachtet werden. Insgesamt wird die protein corona stark von den adsorptionshindernden Eigenschaften des PEGs beeinflusst.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-01-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3594</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38228</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38228</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3594/natte_kishore.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
