<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:46:18Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:467">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:467</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:660</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Application of combined non-thermal treatments for the processing of liquid whole egg</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die Entwicklung und die Optimierung eines nicht-thermischen Verfahrens von flüssigem Vollei durch die Anwendung hoher hydrostatischer Drücke, Nisin, Leistungsultraschall oder deren Kombinationen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lee, Dong-Un</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:660</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Ziel der Forschung war die Entwicklung und die Optimierung eines nicht-thermischen Verfahrens von flüssigem Vollei durch die Anwendung hoher hydrostatischer Drücke, Nisin, Leistungsultraschall oder deren Kombinationen. Als erster Schritt wurden die Koagulationsgrenzen des flüssigen Volleis während der Hochdruckbehandlung festgestellt. Die Parameter Druck (100-400 MPa), Temperatur (5, 25 und 45 °C) und Behandlungszeit (0-3600 s) wurden variiert und deren Einflüsse auf die Koagulation der Eiproteine durch ein rheologisches Meßverfahren evaluiert. Die ausgewerteten Prozeßkriterien zeigten, daß Druckbehandlungen bei niedrigen Temperaturen (5 und 25 °C) deutlich bessere Ergebnisse bei der Hochdruckbehandlung ohne Koagulation der Eiproteine. Kinetische Untersuchungen zur Abtötung der Mikroorganismen innerhalb dieser Prozeßkriterien zeigten, daß die Inaktivierung der Mikroorganismen nicht nur Behandlungsdruck und Temperatur sondern auch vom Phasenzustand des flüssigen Volleis abhängig war. Die optimierten Hochdruck Behandlungsbedingungen (250 MPa für 886 s oder 300 MPa für 200 s um 5 °C) wurden so festgelegt, daß sowohl die Erhaltung der rheologischen Eigenschaften als auch die maximale Abtötung der Mikroorganismen erreicht werden konnte. Die Kombinationsprozesse von Hochdruck mit anderen nicht-thermischen Verfahren, wie Nisin oder Leistungsultraschall, wurden erforscht um eine verbesserte Inaktivierung der Mikroorganismen zu erreichen. Der Kombinationsprozeß von Hochdruck mit Nisin zeigte ausgeprägte Synergismen gegen Gram-positive Listerien. Schließlich wurden die Wirkungen von Hochdruck und von Kombinationsprozessen auf die funktionellen Eigenschaften von flüssigen Volleier mit denen von frischer Volleier vergleichen. Die Ergebnisse zeigten, daß durch die Anwendung der ausgewählten nicht-thermischenVerfahren flüssiges Vollei mit bessere Qualität produziert werden konnen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The objective of this research was to investigate the applicability of non-thermal treatments for the processing of liquid whole egg (LWE). High hydrostatic pressure (HHP) was focused as the main unit operation among the non-thermal technologies, and the utilization of nisin or high-intensity ultrasound was also considered within the study. As a first step of process optimization, LWEs were subjected to a wide range of pressure (100-400 MPa), temperature (5, 25 and 45 °C), and time (0-3600 s) combinations, and the pressure-induced coagulation of LWE was determined by a rheological method. The HHP processing criteria were evaluated from the coagulation kinetics of LWE, and it was indicated that pressure treatments at lower temperatures (5 and 25 °C) had clearly better opportunities to conduct HHP treatments avoiding egg protein coagulation. The kinetic studies on the HHP inactivation of microorganisms were performed at 5 and 25 °C. The optimized HHP conditions were selected by incorporating the HHP processing criteria into the microbial inactivation kinetics, and they were 250 MPa for 886 s or 300 MPa for 200 s at the treatment temperature of 5 °C. These processing conditions ensured the minimum changes in the rheological properties of LWE, and effectively reduced the microbial loads of LWE. The combination processes of HHP with other non-thermal treatments were explored to achieve further microbial inactivation. The addition of nisin prior to pressure treatments significantly increased the lethal effects of HHP against Listeria seeligeri, but not against E. coli. The combination of ultrasound and HHP had only a marginal effect both on Listeria and E. coli within the experimental conditions. Finally, the effects of HHP and combined non-thermal processes on the functional properties of LWE were compared to those of fresh LWE. Little changes in foaming and emulsifying properties were observed by the application of HHP at optimized processing condition. The presence of nisin during HHP treatment also did not affect the foaming and emulsifying property. Therefore, LWE with superior quality could be produced by the application of appropriate (combined) non-thermal treatments.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2002-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/467</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-4621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-4621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/467/lee_dongun.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
