<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:07Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2555">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2555</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Expression und Funktion Apoptose modulierender Gene von Orthopockenviren</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Expression and function of apoptosis modulating genes of Orthopoxviruses</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Witkowski, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Dipl.-Ing. Peter Witkowski Abstract zur Dissertation „Expression und Funktion Apoptose regulierender Gene von Orthopockenviren“ Nach der Eradikation des humanpathogenen Variolavirus durch das WHO-Impfprogramm im 20. Jahrhundert treten andere Orthopockenviren (OPV) gehäuft als Erreger humaner Infektionen in Erscheinung. Weniger gefährlich als die humanen Pocken, können Kuhpocken- oder Vacciniaviren dennoch Menschen infizieren und zu schweren Komplikationen führen. OPV besitzen Erbinformationen für eine Vielzahl sogenannter Wirtsbereichsfaktoren, die bis zu 50% des gesamten Pockengenoms ausmachen können. Das Arsenal dieser Gene ist abhängig von der Virusspezies und hat großen Einfluss auf deren Pathogenese. Um den Einfluss pockenviraler Wirtsbereichsfaktoren auf die Infektion zu untersuchen, wurden Proteine ausgesucht, die inhibitorisch in apoptotische Kaskaden der Wirtszellen eingreifen. Zu den Zielen der Arbeit gehörte die Etablierung von Nachweismethoden für apoptotische Prozesse, die Charakterisierung der Apoptose modulierenden Wirkung pockenviraler Proteine, sowie eine Untersuchung der Funktion der Modulatoren als tatsächliche Virulenzfaktoren in vitro. Im Fokus des Projektes standen die Proteine CrmA als Kaspase-Inhibitor, F1L als Inhibitor der intrinsisch vermittelten Apoptose und schließlich P28 als RING-Finger-Protein mit unbekanntem Wirkmechanismus. Homologe dieser Proteine aus verschiedenen Vaccinia-, Kamel- und Kuhpockenviren wurden untersucht. Mittels real-time PCR wurde die Expression der untersuchten Genprodukte nach OPV Infektion quantifiziert. Die Ergebnisse haben gezeigt, dass spezifische mRNA bereits wenige Minuten nach der Infektion vorhanden ist und warfen Fragen bezüglich spezifischer Transkripte in Pockenvirionen auf, deren Existenz im Laufe dieser Arbeit gezeigt werden konnte. Um die Expression viraler Proteine untersuchen zu können, wurden spezifische IgY Antikörper generiert. Dies geschah basierend auf zirkulären DNA Vakzinen, die mit der Gene Gun in Hühner appliziert wurden. Ein neu entwickelter Antikörper-Neutralisationstest zur Charakterisierung der generierten IgY wurde in einem real-time Cell Electronic Sensing System angewendet. Im Laufe des Projektes konnten Apoptose Nachweismethoden auf der Basis von markierten Kaspase-Inhibitoren etabliert werden. Hierbei wurde gezeigt, dass OPV nach der Infektion zum Teil Apoptose induzieren, die Zellen jedoch gegenüber äußeren apoptotischen Stimuli schützen. Eine heterologe Expression der viralen Proteine in nicht-infizierten Zellen führte ebenfalls zur Apoptose Inhibition. Weiterhin gelang es mithilfe von shRNA, die Expression der drei Proteine in infizierten Zellen zu unterdrücken. Versuche in Zelllinien, als auch in primären Hühnerzellen haben jedoch gezeigt, dass der Knock down der Apoptose Inhibitoren keinen Einfluss auf die Virusvermehrung hatte.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Dipl.-Ing. Peter Witkowski Abstract for Dissertation „Expression and funktion Apoptose regulating genes of Orthopoxviruses“ The WHO vaccination programme against Variola virus in the end of the 1970s eradicated the human poxvirus worldwide. Since then other Orthopoxviruses (OPV) like Cowpox viruses or Vaccinia viruses from animal hosts are found increasingly to cause human infections. As the immune status of human populations decreases, OPV infections can lead to complications especially in high risk and immunocompromised patients. Up to 50% of the OPV genome, with a size of maximally 230,000 bp, code for so-called host-range proteins which are of high importance for viral permissiveness. The arsenal of these proteins mainly depends on virus species and controls mechanisms of pathogenesis. In order to determine the impact of host-range factors, proteins were chosen which interfere with the highly complex apoptotic cascades and work as apoptotic inhibitors. The first aims of this work were to establish detection methods for apoptotic processes in different cell lines, to characterise the anti-apoptotic impact of OPV proteins detached from the poxviral proteome and to examine the importance of these proteins as virulence factors. The project focused on CrmA as an extrinsically working inhibitor of caspases, on F1L as a mitochondrially located inhibitor of intrinsic apoptosis and on P28 as RING-finger protein with unknown mode of action. Homologues of these proteins from Vaccinia, Camelpox and Cowpox viruses were investigated. The expression of the listed proteins was shown and quantified by real-time PCR. The results showed that specific mRNA can be measured a few minutes after infection. This fact led to the suggestion that mRNA is possibly present, coding for immune modulators within OPV particles. Further experiments confirmed this hypothesis and explained how it was possible for OPV to engage the expression so quickly. In order to make more conclusions about protein expression, IgY antibodies specific for OPV immune modulators were generated by DNA vaccination of chickens via Gene Gun and antibodies with titres as high as 1:160,000 could be isolated. A new neutralisation test could be developed based on impedance measurement by real-time Cell Electronic Sensing system in order to characterise the IgY. In the course of the project, methods for apoptosis detection could be established on the basis of caspase inhibition. It could be shown that OPV induce apoptosis on very low levels after infection; however, infected cells are effectively protected from external apoptotic stimuli. Comparable testing after a transient OPV protein expression in non-infected cell cultures showed protection against external induction of apoptotic death. After probing the single OPV proteins, their expression in infected cells could be successfully suppressed by the design and deployment of shRNA. However, trials in cell lines and primary cells showed that the efficient knock-down had no significant impact on virus propagation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-06-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2555</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26607</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26607</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2555/witkowski_peter.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
