<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:46:47Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:589">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:589</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Enzymologie der bakteriellen Konjugation : Hydrolysieren Vertreter der VirB4 Proteinfamilie während der Pilusbiogenese Nukleosid-Triphosphate?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Enzymology of bacterial conjugation : do members of the VirB4 protein family hydrolize nucleoside-triphosphates during pilus biogenesis?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rabel, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Proteine der VirB4 Familie werden von mating pair formation (Mpf-) Systemen konjugativer Plasmide und von Typ IV Sekretionssystemen kodiert. Mpf- und Typ IV Sekretionssysteme haben sich vermutlich aus einem gemeinsamen Vorläufer entwickelt. Eine Aufgabe von Mpf-Systemen ist die Biogenese von Pili. Diese extrazellulären Filamente sind für konjugativen DNA-Transfer essentiell. Typ IV Sekretionssysteme stehen meist im Zusammenhang mit der Pathogenität Gram-negativer Bakterien, eine Eigenschaft scheint die Sekretion von Virulenzfaktoren zu sein. VirB4-ähnliche Proteine sind essentiell für diese Sekretionssysteme und sind deren größte Bestandteile; ihr wesentliches Merkmal ist eine Nukleotidbindungsstelle (Walker A box, NBS). VirB4 Proteine sind daher potentielle NTPasen oder Nukleotidbindungsproteine. In einem Multisequenzvergleich mit 19 Vertretern der VirB4 Proteinfamilie wurden hohe Sequenzähnlichkeiten gefunden. Neben der NBS und der Walker B box wurden zwei weitere konservierte Motive gefunden und in dieser Arbeit erstmals beschrieben. Das konjugative Modellsystem von RP4 (IncPalpha) wurde verwendet, um das VirB4 homologe Protein TrbE genetisch zu charakterisieren. Dazu wurden die Phänotypen Pilusproduktion, Vermehrung IncP-spezifischer Phagen und DNA-Transfer in Escherichia coli untersucht. Die Motive Walker A und B sind essentiell für die Aktivität von RP4 TrbE, das Protein dürfte daher in vivo Nukleotide binden oder hydrolysieren. Die zwei weiteren konservierten Motive sind ebenfalls essentiell bzw. wichtig für die Proteinaktivität. Nahezu das gesamte Polypeptid von 852 Aminosäuren ist für die Aktivität erforderlich. Die vorhergesagte transmembranale Helix am N-Terminus ist jedoch für die Aktivität des Proteins in E. coli entbehrlich. Zwei Vertreter der VirB4 Proteinfamilie wurden biochemisch untersucht. Das in vivo uneingeschränkt aktive Deletionsderivat RP4 TrbEHNdelta2 und das Wildtyp Protein TrwK des konjugativen Plasmids R388 (IncW) wurden gereinigt. Obwohl beide VirB4 Homologe fluoreszierende Nukleotidanaloga binden, wurden weder ATP noch GTP hydrolysiert. RP4 TrbEHNdelta2 und R388 TrwK verhielten sich in Lösung wie Monomere. Die Proteine bildeten mit Einzelstrang/Doppelstrang DNA keine stabilen Komplexe, scheinen also nicht direkt am DNA-Transport beteiligt zu sein. Die Ergebnisse deuten an, daß RP4 TrbEHNdelta2 und R388 TrwK ihre Aktivitäten nur im Verband mit weiteren Komponenten aus den Sekretionssystemen entfalten.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Proteins of the VirB4 family are encoded by mating pair formation (Mpf) systems of conjugative plasmids and by type IV secretion systems. These systems most probably evolved from a common ancestor. The task of Mpf systems is the production of pili, a prerequisite for conjugative DNA transfer. Type IV secretion systems are involved in the pathogenicity of Gram-negative bacteria, most likely secreting virulence factors. VirB4-like proteins, the largest proteins of these secretion systems, are essential components of the above-mentioned systems. As a common feature, VirB4 proteins contain a nucleotide binding site (Walker A box, NBS type A). Hence, members of the VirB4 family are potential NTPases or nucleotide binding proteins. A multiple sequence alignment of 19 VirB4-like proteins revealed striking sequence similarities. In addition to the NBS type A and B, two conserved motifs were detected and defined for the first time. The conjugative plasmid RP4 (IncPalpha) was used for a genetic characterization of the VirB4-like protein RP4 TrbE. Therefore, production of pili, propagation of IncP-specific phages, and DNA transfer ability were studied in Escherichia coli. Walker motifs A and B were found to be essential for the function of RP4 TrbE. Hence, the protein seems to bind or hydrolyze nucleotides in vivo. Furthermore, the two additional motifs were found to be essential or important for protein function. Nearly the complete polypetide of the 852 amino acid TrbE is required for protein function. However, the predicted transmembrane helix at the N-terminus is dispensable in E. coli. Two proteins of the VirB4 family were studied biochemically. The in vivo fully active deletion derivative RP4 TrbEHNdelta2 and the full-length R388 (IncW) TrwK were purified. Although both proteins bound tri-nitro-phenyl labeled nucleotides, no ATPase or GTPase activity was detected. Both polypetides behaved as monomers in solution. In the presence of single-stranded and double-stranded DNA, no stable protein-DNA complexes were formed. Apparently, these Mpf-components are not directly involved in DNA transfer. The results presented may indicate, that further components of the respective Mpf systems are required for the activities of RP4 TrbEHNdelta2 and R388 TrwK .</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2003-05-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/589</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-5839</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-5839</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/589/rabel_christian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
