<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:35Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2655">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2655</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:610</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Zelluläre und molekulare Determinanten der Therapieresistenz bei Kindern mit akuter lymphoblastischer Leukämie</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Cellular and Molecular Determinants of Therapy Resistance in Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rhein, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:610</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Bei der kindlichen akuten lymphoblastischen Leukämie (ALL) ist die Persistenz der leukämischen Zellen unter der Therapie (minimale Resterkrankung, MRD) von entscheidender prognostischer Bedeutung. Um Determinanten der Therapieresistenz bei der ALL zu identifizieren, wurden MRD-Zellen mittels genomweiter Genexpressionsanalyse eingehend charakterisiert. Die bioinformatische Auswertung der Genexpressionsdaten deutete daraufhin, dass sich die persistierenden Blasten in Richtung ruhender reifer B-Zellen entwickelt haben. Die Differenzierung der MRD-Zellen und ihre verringerte proliferative Aktivität konnte durch den Vergleich mit normalen B-Zellen auf zellulärer Ebene und Proteinebene bestätigt werden. Der ruhende, reifere Zustand der MRD-Zellen könnte die Therapieresistenz erklären und Auswirkungen auf den weiteren Verlauf der Chemotherapie haben, die in erster Linie auf proliferierende Zellen abzielt. Die Wirksamkeit der antileukämischen Chemotherapie wird durch die Aktivierbarkeit des Signalweges des Tumorsuppressors p53 bestimmt. Im Rahmen der Dissertation wurde der Einfluss mitochondrialer Faktoren auf den p53-Signalweg untersucht. Die Ergebnisse wiesen daraufhin, dass die p53-Aktivierbarkeit an den mitochondrialen Aktivitätszustand und die Bildung von reaktiven Sauerstoffspezies gekoppelt ist, wodurch die erhöhte Chemoresistenz von Zellen in einem ruhenden Zustand erklärt werden kann. Darüber hinaus konnten bei der Evaluierung der experimentellen Ergebnisse an unabhängigen Patientenkohorten neue potentielle Resistenzfaktoren identifiziert werden. Diesbezüglich zeigte sich die Expression des Adhäsionsmoleküls CD11b (ITGAM) von prognostischer Bedeutung und war mit einem ungünstigen Therapieansprechen assoziiert. Die präsentierten Ergebnisse tragen zum grundlegenden Verständnis der molekularen und zellbiologischen Eigenschaften therapieresistenter Leukämiezellen bei und könnten einen Ausgangspunkt für individualisierte Therapiestrategien bei der pädiatrischen ALL darstellen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL), persistence of leukemic cells during therapy (minimal residual disease, MRD) is of crucial prognostic significance. From a biological point of view MRD cells are the tumor cells, which survived anti-leukemic therapy. Therefore, the cell biologic characterization of these rare cells may considerably contribute to the identification of cellular and molecular determinants of therapy resistance in ALL. In order to approach this issue experimentally, a procedure has been established, which enabled a gene expression profiling of MRD cells persisting after one week of induction glucocorticoid therapy. The expression changes indicated a shift towards mature B cells, inhibition of cell cycling, and an increase of expression of adhesion (CD11b/ITGAM) and cytokine (CD119/IFNGR1) receptors. The differentiation shift and low proliferative activity in MRD cells has been confirmed by direct comparison with normal B cells at cellular and protein levels. Given that normal B cells are largely therapy resistant, the differentiation shift and low proliferative activity may account for the persistence of blasts during therapy and affect their sensitivity to further therapeutic treatment. Evaluation of the gene expression data in a clinical context indicated a prognostic significance of the CD11b-receptor. The expression of CD11b was inversely correlated with cytoreduction rates measured at clinically important timepoints of induction therapy. Moreover, due to the consistently increased expression levels in leukemic cells under therapy and to the cell surface allocation, CD11b has a promising potential as an MRD-specific marker to improve sensitivity and specificity of flow cytometric MRD detection. With regard to chemotherapy-specific mechanisms of action, activation of the tumor suppressor p53-signaling pathway has been reported in response to a large variety of drugs. The p53 system is highly stress-sensitive and integrates diverse intracellular signals in a complex and poorly defined manner. In this work, the role of mitochondrial activity has been investigated as one of the critical intracellular determinants involved in the regulation of energy metabolism, cellular redox state and apoptosis. Using cellular systems with endogenously expressed wild-type p53, including ALL blasts and normal lymphocytes, a linkage between mitochondrial activity and cellular stress responsiveness upstream of p53 activation could be identified. Through this linkage, resting cells with a downregulated mitochondrial activity have been found to acquire stress- and chemoresistance at p53 level. The presented data offer new insights into the mechanisms of therapy resistance and sensitivity of leukemic blasts. The identified parameters may be useful in predicting MRD status and clinical outcome after induction therapy and potentially provide a part for a future basis for more individually designed treatment strategies in upcoming clinical trials.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-10-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2655</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2655/rhein_peter.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
