<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:22Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2156">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2156</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:390</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Urban Ethnicity in Santiago de Chile. Mapuche Migration and Urban Space</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Urbane Ethnizit√§t in Santiago de Chile. Mapuche Migration und urbaner Raum</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Imilan Ojeda, Walter Alejandro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:390</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The urban phenomenon is changing. The social and political transformations of recent decades have created new forms and models of inhabiting in the city. In Latin America, phenomena of globalization and the implementation of liberal policies have, on the one hand, expanded flows of information and communication and, on the other hand, affected forms of social cohesion which were developed from the modern urbanization process of the mid-20th Century. This new context has transformed the ways in which the people build identity and a sense of belonging inside the urban society. Since the 1990s ethnicity has become an important source of identity construction for a growing percentage of city dwellers in Latin America. The ethnic roots of its inhabitants are turned into resources for social cohesion and recognition as social actors. The purpose of this study is to explore the process of formation of an urban ethnicity in Santiago de Chile. The Mapuches are the largest ethnic group in Chile and about half of their total population resides in the city of Santiago. However, despite being the largest ethnic group in Santiago, the Mapuche do not have a visible presence in the city. The emergence over the last decade of the political and social category of urban Mapuche and Mapuche-warriache describes the growing importance of ethnicity as a source of identity in Santiago. Ethnicity is related to the notion of collective identities. In this sense, it is a process whereby a group of people are collectively different from ‚Äúothers,‚Ä? ethnicity is a broad concept which describes a process of differentiation. The objective of this research is to investigate the strategies through which Mapuche society in Santiago establishes differences, both in relation to the remaining urban society, and to "traditional" Mapuche society. Accordingly, this work aims to identify processes through which an urban ethnic identity is constructed. The working hypothesis is that the Mapuche currently in the city - first and second generation migrants - build hybrid forms with the remaining urban society more than they reproduce or reterritorialize their society of origin. The Mapuches in the city are not trapped between their societies of origin and the host urban society, but are, in turn, building strategies in which ethnic identity is part of a system of identities in which they participate. The work has two parts. The first part presents two critical reviews: a chapter on the method of ethnographic research and its application to urban space, and another chapter which focuses on the history of modern Mapuche society. The second part is experimental and composed of three case studies. Each experimental case is presented and analyzed through ethnographic methodology. This work explores the urban ethnicity as a contemporary form of building identity and sense of belonging. Currently, in Latin America an essentialist perspective prevails to deal the indigenous identities. This paper argues that the Mapuches in the city are not trapped between their societies of origin and the host urban society, but are, in turn, building strategies in which ethnic identity is part of a system of identities in which they participate. These strategies are a very dynamic form of communication and differentiation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das urbane Ph√§nomen ist im Wandel. In den vergangenen Jahren tauchten neue Modelle und Formen von Urbanit√§t auf. Die Einf√ºhrung neoliberaler Politik als auch eine etablierte Globalisierung in Lateinamerika wirken sich nicht nur auf die Ausdehnung des Kommunikations- und Informationsflusses, sondern auch, auf Formen sozialer Koh√§sion aus, die seit Mitte des XX. Jahrhunderts entstanden sind. Dieser neue Kontext ver√§ndert bedeutsam die Art und Weise, in der die Menschen ihre Identit√§ten und Zugeh√∂rigkeitsgef√ºhle in der urbanen Gesellschaft entwickeln. Seit den 1990er Jahren ist Ethnizit√§t eine wichtige Ressource geworden, um dem zunehmendem Anteil der urbanen lateinamerikanischen Bev√∂lkerung Identit√§tsquellen zu liefern. Aus der Perspektive der St√§dter dienen ethnische Wurzeln als Ressourcen f√ºr soziale Koh√§sion und zur Anerkennung als soziale Akteure. Die Absicht der vorliegenden Arbeit ist die Erkundung des Bildungsprozesses einer urbanen Ethnizit√§t in Santiago de Chile. Mapuche bilden die zahlenm√§√üig st√§rkste ethnische Gruppe in Chile, ca. die H√§lfte von ihnen wohnt in Santiago. Obwohl Mapuche die gr√∂√üte indigene Gruppe in Santiago sind, wenn man den urbanen Raum betrachtet, sind Mapuche relativ unsichtbar. Die Entstehung der Kategorien von ‚Äöurbanem Mapuche‚Äô und ‚ÄöMapuche-Warriache‚Äô in den letzten Jahrzehnten weisen allerdings auf die zunehmende Relevanz der Ethnizit√§t, als Identit√§tsquelle in Santiago de Chile, hin. Ethnizit√§t bezieht sich hierbei auf kollektive Identit√§ten. In dieser Hinsicht ist Ethnizit√§t die Art und Weise mit der sich ein Kollektiv vom Anderen unterscheidet. Ethnizit√§t ist ein breites Konzept, das einen Differenzierungsprozess beschreibt. Das Hauptziel der vorliegenden Dissertation ist die Erforschung der Strategien, mit denen die Mapuche Gesellschaft in Santiago Differenzen - bezogen auf den Rest der sowohl urbanen Gesellschaft als auch der traditionellen Mapuche Gesellschaft ‚Äì aufbaut, als auch ethnische Identit√§tsbildungs-Prozesse zu erkennen. Die Arbeit baut auf der Hypothese, dass die heutigen urbanen Mapuche-Migranten und ihre zweite Generation hybride Identit√§ten bilden. Statt einer Art von Re-Territorialisierung oder Reproduktion ihrer originellen auf dem Lande liegenden Gesellschaft sollte sich Identit√§tsbildung vielmehr auf den Rest der urbanen Gesellschaft orientieren. Der lateinamerikanische Diskurs √ºber ethnische Identit√§ten wird derzeit von einer essentialistischen Perspektive beherrscht. Die Arbeit argumentiert, dass die Mapuche weder im sozialen Raum der traditionellen Gemeinschaft noch im kulturellen Raum der Gastgesellschaft eingesperrt sind und Strategien entwickeln k√∂nnten, in denen ethnische Identit√§ten ein Teil eines Systems von Identit√§ten sind. Dementsprechend sind solche Strategien sehr dynamische Formen von Kommunikation und Differenzierung. Der erste Teil der Dissertation setzt sich im ersten Kapitel in kritischer Weise mit der ethnographischen Methode und ihrer Anwendung im urbanen Raum auseinander. Das zweite Kapital fokussiert auf die Geschichte der modernen Mapuche Gesellschaft. Die durch ethnographische Methodik erarbeiteten experimentellen Studienf√§lle werden im zweiten Teil er√∂rtert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-06-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/vnd.oasis.opendocument.text</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2156</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22696</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22696</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2156/original_imilan_walter1.odt</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2156/original_imilan_walter2.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2156/original_imilan_walter3.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2156/original_imilan_walter4.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2156/imilan_walter.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
