<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:23Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3041">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3041</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:650</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Employee Entrepreneurship: When Do Inventors Found a Spin Off? Why Have Most Spin-Off Founders Worked Previously for Small Companies?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Mitarbeiter Entrepreneure: Wann gründen Erfinder ein Spin-off? Warum haben die meisten Spin-off Gründer vorher in kleinen Unternehmen gearbeitet?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lindenmann, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:650</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This thesis analyzes the decision of employees to found a spin-off (leaving an employed position in order to create an own new venture within the same industry). On the one hand, newly created ventures have a positive influence on the job market, the economy in general and are crucial to economic development and, on the other hand, spin-offs represent a highly successful and significant share of newly created ventures. The thesis consists of three independent papers and supplementary discussions. While the first paper details, based on the existing literature, when spin-off specifics need to be taken into account, the second and third papers empirically analyze the stylized fact that founders of new ventures have disproportionally often previously worked in companies with fewer employees. The first paper is based on the observation that studies currently often classify new ventures (de-novo) as one group without consideration of subgroup specifics. This is identified as problematic, as spin-offs make up a significant share (approx. 30% in Germany) of de-novo companies and show consistently different behavior along important dimensions. To back this finding, the first paper summarizes and categorizes the factors affecting founding and identifies variations between spin-off and other de-novo firm creation based on theory and empirical results. Thus, the key finding is that there is a risk of misleading results if studies have not controlled for spin-offs in the past, and that future studies on venture creation should differentiate for spin-offs to avoid this hazard. The rest of the thesis empirically details the above mentioned stylized fact, as the literature so far only speculates on the reason while acknowledging that understanding is important in order to further develop the current theories on spin-off founding. Based on a mail survey administered to patent applicants in Germany, eight factors derived from promising spin-off theories, the Employee Learning Theory (ELT) and the Voluntary Turnover Theory (VTT), are tested for their capability of explaining the stylized fact. Despite significant explanatory power for the probability of founding a spin-off by ELT measures such as experience working in a young company, network size, and quality of experience and VTT measures such as job security and job satisfaction, neither was able to explain the stylized fact. Thus, the key finding is that explanations for the stylized fact most often speculated in the literature are incorrect so far, signifying that ELT and VTT require further development. Based on theoretic reasoning and empirical results, knowledge of entrepreneurial business opportunity is recognized as one explanation for the stylized fact, presenting a direction for further expansion of the common spin-off theories.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Dissertation untersucht die Entscheidung von Mitarbeitern zur Gründung eines Spin-offs (Aufgabe des Angestelltenverhältnisses, um ein eigenes Unternehmen in der gleichen Industrie zu gründen). Das Thema ist wichtig, weil auf der einen Seite neue Unternehmen einen positiven Einfluss auf den Arbeitsmarkt, die Wirtschaft im Allgemeinen sowie deren Entwicklung haben und auf der anderen Seite Spin-offs eine bedeutende, sehr erfolgreiche Untergruppe der Neugründungen repräsentieren. Die vorliegende Arbeit umfasst drei unabhängige Artikel sowie ergänzende Beiträge. Während der erste Artikel basierend auf der vorhandenen Literatur prüft, wann Spin-off Besonderheiten bei Gründungsanalysen berücksichtig werden müssen, untersuchen die anderen beiden Artikel empirisch, warum überproportional viele Gründer vorher für kleine Unternehmen gearbeitet haben – ein „Stylized Fact“, der bei empirischen Studien immer wieder gefunden wird. Ausgangspunkt des ersten Artikels ist die Beobachtung, dass viele empirische Studien alle neuen Unternehmen als eine Gruppe (de novo) untersuchen, ohne die Besonderheiten von Untergruppen zu beachten. Dies ist problematisch, da Spin-offs einen signifikanten Anteil der de novo-Firmen ausmachen (~30% in Deutschland) und gleichzeitig ein durchgehend anderes Verhalten entlang wichtiger Dimensionen zeigen. Ermittelt wird dies durch Zusammenfassen und Gruppieren der wichtigsten Einflussfaktoren bezüglich Gründung und Analyse, inwieweit es Unterschiede zwischen Spin-offs und anderen de novo-Firmen gibt. Kernresultat ist, dass ein Risiko für Fehlschlüsse bei allen Analysen besteht, die nicht für Spin-off-Unterschiede kontrollieren. Dies ist sowohl bei bestehenden als auch zukünftigen Arbeiten zu bedenken. Die restliche Arbeit prüft empirisch den oben erwähnten „Stylized Fact“, bezüglich dessen bis jetzt in der Literatur nur spekuliert wird, obwohl die Bedeutung zur Weiterentwicklung der Spin-off Theorien bekannt ist. Aufbauend auf der Employee Learning Theory (ELT) und der Voluntary Turnover Theory (VTT) werden acht Erklärungen für den „Stylized Fact“ empirisch getestet. Grundlage dafür ist eine postalische Umfrage bei Patentanmeldern in Deutschland. Trotz signifikanter Erklärungskraft der ELT- und VTT- Faktoren bezüglich der Wahrscheinlichkeit, ein Spin-off zu gründen, kann der „Stylized Fact“ damit nicht empirisch erklärt werden. Demzufolge ist das Schlüsselergebnis, dass die üblicherweise in der Literatur geäußerten Begründungen nicht zutreffen und daher ELT und VTT weiterentwickelt werden müssen. Basierend auf theoretischen Überlegungen und empirischen Ergebnissen wird das Kennen von „Entrepreneurial Business Opportunities“ dafür als erfolgsversprechende Richtung identifiziert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-09-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3041</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32125</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32125</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3041/lindenmann_simon.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
