<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:18Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1968">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1968</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Pore space reconstruction of porous media - Coupling of microstructure, rock mechanics and flow properties depending on effective pressure</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Porenraumrekonstruktion por√∂ser Medien - Kopplung von Gesteinsstruktur, Gesteinsmechanik und Str√∂mungsverhalten in Abh√§ngigkeit vom Effektivdruck</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bl√∂cher, Mando Guido</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Zur Untersuchung von hydraulischen Parametern, welche an die Porenraumstruktur und an mechanische Prozesse gekoppelt sind, wurden folgende Laboruntersuchungen an verschiedenen Sandsteinen (Bentheimer, Fontainebleau, Flechtinger) durchgef√ºhrt: a) Porenraumstrukturanalyse mittels Quecksilberintrusion und 2D Bildanalyse; b) Skempton Koeffizient B (definiert als √Ñnderung des Porendruckes dPp gegen√ºber der √Ñnderung des Umschlie√üungsdruckes dPc (B = dPp/dPc)) in Abh√§ngigkeit des Effektivdrucks Peff; c) Permeabilit√§t k in Abh√§ngigkeit des Effektivdrucks Peff an verschiedenen Apparaturen (MTS und Hochdruck-Temperatur-Permeameter HTP). Mittels der Quecksilberintrusion und 2D Bildanalyse wurde neben der Gesamtporosit√§t vor allem auch die Porenform charakterisiert. Dabei wurde im Speziellen auf das Verh√§ltnis zwischen Porenhals- und Porenbauchradius, auf die Zirkularit√§t und auf die Konnektivit√§t der der Poren geachtet. Schon beim Vergleich von zwei Sandsteinen (Bentheimer und Flechtinger) werden signifikante Unterschiede in Porosit√§t und Porenform sichtbar. Der Bentheimer Sandstein mit einer Gesamtporosit√§t von ca. 23% weist gegen√ºber dem Flechtinger Sandstein (Gesamtporosit√§t von ca. 10%) eine bis zu 5-fach geringere Zirkularit√§t der Poren auf. Auch die Porengr√∂√üenverteilung des Bentheimer Sandsteins unterscheidet sich stark von der des Flechtinger Sandsteins. Im Flechtinger Sandstein zeigt sich eine Gleichverteilung der Porengr√∂√üe von 6.5 bis 200 Œºm, wohingegen die Porengr√∂√üe des Bentheimer Sandsteins vor allem im Intervall zwischen 40 und 110 Œºm liegt. Auch das Verh√§ltnis zwischen dem Porenbauchradius und Porenhalsradius ist f√ºr den Flechtinger Sandstein gr√∂√üer. Im Bentheimer Sandstein liegt dieses Verh√§ltnis nahe eins. Bei den mechanisch-hydraulischen Experimenten hat sich gezeigt, dass sowohl der Skempton Koeffizient als auch die Permeabilit√§t eine funktionelle Abh√§ngigkeit zum Effektivdruck haben. F√ºr den Flechtinger Sandstein f√§llt der Skempton Koeffizient von 0.85 auf 0.65 im Testintervall von 3 bis 26 MPa Effektivdruck. In einem √§hnlichen Testintervall (3 bis 30 MPa Effektivdruck) f√§llt die Permeabilit√§t von 0.56 mD auf 0.42 mD. Beim Bentheimer Sandstein reagiert der Skempton Koeffizient wesentlich sensibler auf eine Effektivdruck√§nderung und f√§llt von 0.7 auf 0.4 im Testintervall von 3 bis 29 MPa Effektivdruck. Die Permeabilit√§t bleibt hingegen konstant bei ca. 950 mD √ºber den gesamten getesteten Effektivdruckbereich. Die durch die Experimente gewonnenen Ergebnisse lassen sich nicht vollst√§ndig durch eine Strukturverfestigung erkl√§ren, sondern sie m√ºssen auch unter dem Aspekt einer heterogenen Porenraumver√§nderung betrachtet werden. Mittels numerischer Simulation und analytischer Rechnung hat sich gezeigt, dass jede Einzelpore in Abh√§ngigkeit von ihrer Form unterschiedlich auf √§u√üere Druck√§nderungen regiert. Grundlegend ist zu sagen, je irregul√§rer die Porenform ist, desto sensibler reagiert die Pore auf Druckschwankungen, d.h. bei gleicher Umgebungsdruck√§nderung werden h√∂here Porendr√ºcke induziert. Dar√ºber hinaus hat eine Zunahme der Heterogenit√§t des Porenraumes (Vernetzung von Poren unterschiedlicher Form) auch eine Zunahme der Druckempfindlichkeit zur Folge. Neben diesen poroelastischen Eigenschaften jeder Einzelpore f√ºhrt auch eine √Ñnderung des Porentypes (von durchstr√∂mbarer Pore √ºber Sackgassenpore bis hin zur separierten Pore) in Abh√§ngigkeit vom Effektivdruck zu einer √Ñnderung des Skempton Koeffizienten und der Permeabilit√§t. Mit Hilfe dieses Ansatzes, der Numerik und den analytischen Rechnungen lassen sich die Laborergebnisse qualitativ beschreiben. Eine Effektivdruckerh√∂hung im Bentheimer Sandstein hat zur Folge, dass sich die Porenform stabilisiert, ohne dass dabei signifikante Flie√üwege abgetrennt werden. Eine hohe Irregularit√§t (geringe Zirkularit√§t) der Poren f√ºhrt vor allem bei geringem Effektivdruck zur starken √Ñnderung der Porengeometrie, ausgedr√ºckt durch die starke √Ñnderung des Skempton Koeffizienten. Im Flechtinger Sandstein f√ºhrt eine Effektivdruckerh√∂hung daher zu einem Verschluss von Porenh√§lsen und somit zu einer Ver√§nderung des Porentypes. Diese Typ√§nderung hat zur Folge, dass sich Skempton Koeffizient und Permeabilit√§t gleicherma√üen ver√§ndern. Mittels numerischer Simulation konnte eine heterogene Porenraumver√§nderung in 2D nachgewiesen werden. Um die Auswirkungen einer heterogenen Porenraumver√§nderung auf den hydromechanischen Parameter Skempton Koeffizient und den hydraulischen Parameter Permeabilit√§t ausreichend zu untersuchen, m√ºssen neben den Laborexperimenten, der 2D Modellierung und der Analytik auch noch eine diskrete 3D Modellierung durchgef√ºhrt werden. Mittels dieser 3D Modellierung sollen hydraulisch-mechanisch-thermische Wechselwirkungen in por√∂sen Medien, basierend auf ihrer internen Struktur, nachgebildet werden. Teil dieser Arbeit war daher auch die Generierung einer diskreten Porenraumstruktur. Dazu wurde das Sedimentierungstool ‚Ä?Settle3D‚Ä? entwickelt, mit dessen Hilfe verschiedene por√∂se Medien nachgebildet werden k√∂nnen. Das Sedimentierungstool modelliert dabei den Sedimentierungsprozess auf Einzelkornebene unter Verwendung von einfachen physikalischen Gesetzm√§√üigkeiten wie gradliniger Bewegung und Rotationsbewegung. Mit Hilfe des Sedimentierungstool konnten in dieser Arbeit grundlegende Zusammenh√§nge f√ºr Sedimentgesteine nachgebildet werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">To investigate the hydraulic parameters depending on pore space geometry and mechanical processes, we performed the following laboratory experiments on different sandstones (Bentheimer, Fontainenbleau, Flechtinger): a) pore space geometry analysis by means of mercury injection and 2D image analysis; b) Skempton coefficient B (defined as ratio between pore pressure change and confining pressure change (B = dPp/dPc)) depending on effective pressure Peff change under undrained conditions; c) permeability k depending on effective pressure change at different apparatuses (Mechanical Test System MTS and High-Pressure-Temperature-Permeameter HTP). By means of mercury injection and 2D image analysis total porosity and pore shape geometry were characterized. Pore space geometry was classified by the ratio between pore throat and pore cavity, the circularity and connectivity of the pores. Comparison of two sandstones (Bentheimer and Flechtinger) shows significant differences in porosity and pore space geometry. Total porosity of Bentheimer sandstone is 19.2 (2D image analysis) to 26.4% (mercury injection) which is two times of Flechtinger sandstone (9.5 (mercury injection) to 10.7% (2D image analysis)). With 150 Œºm pore radius the perimeter length of a pore in Bentheimer sandstone is five times longer than in Flechtinger sandstone. This can be derived from a circularity contrast of 0.1 for Flechtinger and 0.02 for Bentheimer sandstone. Furthermore, the pore size in Flechtinger sandstone is uniformly distributed over the total resolvable range of pore radii (6.5 to 200 Œºm) but the Bentheimer sandstone shows an accumulation of pore size in a range from 40 to 110 Œºm. Therefore, the Flechtinger sandstone is more heterogeneous in pore size than the Bentheimer sandstone. Also, the ratio between pore cavity and pore throat in the Flechtinger sandstone is higher than in the Bentheimer sandstone. During the mechanic-hydraulic experiments we determined a functional dependency of the Skempton coefficient and permeability due to effective pressure. For the Flechtinger sandstone the Skempton coefficient started with 0.85 at 3 MPa effective pressure and decreased with increasing effective pressure to a minimum of 0.65 at 26 MPa. At a similar range of effective pressure (3 to 30 MPa) the permeability decreases from 0.56 mD to 0.42 mD. For the Bentheimer sandstone the Skempton coefficient was 0.7 at 3 MPa and decreased with an increasing effective pressure to a minimum value of 0.4 at 29 MPa. Permeability of the Bentheimer sandstone keeps nearly constant over the total range of effective pressure. The results of the laboratory experiment are not only explainable by a stiffening of the grain structure, but also a heterogeneous deformation of the pore space must be considered. By means of numerical simulations and analytical calculations it was shown, that each single pore reacts differently to an exterior pressure change. This diverse behaviour depends on the different pore shape. Basically, we can conclude the more irregular the pore geometry, the more sensitive the pore reacts on a confining pressure change, i.e. at the same confining pressure level the induced pore pressure increases with the irregularity of the pore geometry. Furthermore, an increase in pore space heterogeneity (caused by a connection of pores of different shape) will increase the pressure sensitivity, too. Besides this poroelastic behaviour of each single pore, also a change of the pore type (from catenary over cul-de-sac to closed) depending on an effective pressure change leads to a change in the Skempton coefficient and permeability. By means of this approach, the numerical simulation and the analytical calculation, the laboratory experiments can be explained qualitatively. An increase of effective pressure in the Bentheimer sandstone results in stiffening of the pore space geometry, but a change of pore type and/or a closing of pore throats can be neglected. The high irregularity (small circularity) of the pores leads to maximum change of the pore geometry at small effective pressure levels. Therefore, the maximum change of Skempton coefficient can be observed at small effective pressure rates. In contrast, an increase of effective pressure in the Flechtinger sandstone results in a closing of pore throats and micro cracks and therefore in a change of the pore type ratio. This results in a similar change of Skempton coefficient and permeability. By means of the numerical simulation, a heterogeneous deformation of the pore space geometry in 2D could be demonstrated. In order to show the influence of a heterogeneous pore space deformation on the hydraulic-mechanical parameter Skempton coefficient and hydraulic parameter permeability we have to perform (besides laboratory experiments, 2D modelling and analytical solutions) a discrete 3D modelling as well. Using this discrete 3D model, a coupling of hydraulic, mechanical and thermal properties in porous media depending on the internal pore space structure is possible. Therefore, a principle part of this work was to generate a discrete pore space structure. For this purpose the sedimentary tool ‚Ä?Settle3D‚Ä? was developed, which can generate different porous media. By means of the sedimentary tool and simplest physical laws such as translation and rotation we can rebuild the sedimentary process on single grain level. At the current state we can proof basic dependencies for sedimentary rocks.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-11-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>text/x-tex</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1968</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17972</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17972</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1968/original_Summary_short.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1968/original_diss.tex</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1968/bloecher_guido.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
