<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3716">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3716</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Climate variability of Svalbard in the first decade of the 21st century and its impact on Vestfonna ice cap, Nordaustlandet : An analysis based on field observations, remote sensing and numerical modeling</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Klimavariabilit√§t in Svalbard innerhalb der ersten Dekade des 21. Jahrhunderts und ihr Einfluss auf die Vestfonna-Eiskappe, Nordaustlandet : eine Analyse basierend auf Feldbeobachtungen, Fernerkundung und numerischer Modellierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Finkelnburg, Roman</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The Arctic is an important element in the global climate. Circulations of the atmosphere and the ocean transport energy from the equator to high-latitudes. In the northern hemisphere this is mainly done by transient disturbances of the atmospheric circulation (cyclones and anticyclones, low- and high-pressure regions) at mid-latitudes and the North Atlantic Current. Svalbard, an archipelago in the North Atlantic and Arctic Ocean, is strongly influenced by the activity of the North Atlantic cyclone track transporting moisture and moist static energy into the region. Furthermore, strong climate gradients with interannual and intra annual variability are generated by the interaction of the West Spitsbergen Current transporting warm Atlantic water northward and the fluctuating sea ice margin. The climate of Svalbard is characterized by close couplings between atmosphere, ocean and land. Two of the largest ice masses of the European Arctic (Vest- and Austfonna) and several smaller ice bodies (e.g. De Geerfonna) are located in the north-east of Svalbard, on Nordaustlandet. Little is known about the current state and variability of the surface energy balance (SEB) and surface mass balance (SMB) of these ice masses and their sensitivity to large-scale atmospheric forcing. The central goal of this work is to improve the understanding of atmosphere-cryosphere interactions on Arctic glaciers and in particular to investigate seasonality and variability of the climate in Svalbard and its impact on Vestfonna ice cap. A methodology combining field observations, remote sensing and numerical modeling is employed to provide detailed information about the state and sensitivity of SEB and SMB on Vestfonna, what meso-scale processes generate the changes and how these processes link the synoptic to the local process space during the first decade of the 21st century. This thesis also demonstrates how difficult it is to obtain field observational data and to reliably assess the current state and future development in the Arctic region. The SEB and SMB on Vestfonna show the highest sensitivity of surface ablation rates to changes in radiation conditions. Surface albedo is identified as a key factor for ablation rate estimations on Vestfonna. The SMB on Vestfonna also shows high dependency on snowdrift, causing considerable mass loss in accumulation rates. An annual SMB rate on Vestfonna of +0.02 ¬± 0.22 m w.e. yr‚àí1 is calculated from a regional reanalysis, i.e. the European Arctic Reanalysis (EAR), and an annual SMB rate of ‚àí0.02 ¬± 0.20 m w.e. yr‚àí1 is calculated by an empirical approach for the mass balance years 2001 to 2009. The estimate derived from the EAR is assumed to be too high since snow drift is not considered in the accumulation rates, and a constant high surface albedo could have caused underestimations in ablation rates. On the other hand the empirical approach shows uncertainty in estimating the air-temperature fields and refreezing rates. Thus, combining results derived from both approaches, the ‚Äúpessimistic‚Ä? annual SMB rate on Vestfonna of about ‚àí0.09 ¬± 0.19 m w.e. yr‚àí1 for the mass balance years 2001 to 2009 is estimated by using the higher ablation rates derived from EAR calculations and the lower accumulations rates derived from the empirical study. The activity of the North Atlantic cyclone track shows strong influence on accumulation and ablation rates on Vestfonna. Since the North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) is one of the most important indices of variability in the northern hemisphere atmospheric circulation, it also shows strong correlations with accumulation and ablation rates on Vestfonna. During winter, the NAO index significantly correlates with the frequency of cyclones from the North Atlantic sector through precipitation, air-temperature and wind speed. The moisture transported by the cyclones into the region during the winter season mainly determines the annual accumulation rates on Vestfonna. During summer, the NAO index significantly anti-correlates with local cyclogenesis and summer precipitation, generating variability in ablation rates on Vestfonna by complex feedback mechanisms between surface albedo, surface absorption of solar radiation and air-temperature. All results indicate that the annual SMB rate was almost balanced on Vestfonna during the first decade of the 21st century. However, especially changes in the rain-snow ratio due to changes in air-temperature are assumed to have great potential to generate strong changes in the SMB rates on Vestfonna in the future.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Arktis ist ein wichtiges Element des globalen Klimasystems. Zirkulationen der Atmosph√§re und des Ozeans transportieren Energie vom √Ñquator in die hohen Breiten. In der Nordhemisph√§re geschieht dies haupts√§chlich durch St√∂rungen der atmosph√§rischen Zirkulation (Zyklone und Antizyklone) in den mittleren Breiten und durch den Nordatlantikstrom. Die Inselgruppe Svalbard ist durch ihre Lage stark durch Sturmtiefs beeinflusst, die Feuchte und feuchtstatische Energie aus dem Nordatlantik in den Arktischen Ozean transportieren. Dar√ºber hinaus erzeugen der Westspitzbergenstrom, der warmes Atlantikwasser nordw√§rts transportiert, und die fluktuierenden Eiskante des Nordpolarmeeres starke Klimagradienten mit inter- und intraannueller Variabilit√§t, wobei die enge Kopplung von Atmosph√§re, Ozean und Land ma√ügeblich das Klima Svalbards pr√§gt. Zwei der gr√∂√üten Eismassen der europ√§ischen Arktis (Vest- und Austfonna) und etliche kleinere Eismasse (z.B. De Geerfonna) befinden sich im Nordosten Svalbards auf der Insel Nordaustlandet. Wenig ist √ºber den momentanen Zustand, die Variabilit√§t und die Sensitivit√§t der Oberfl√§chenenergiebilanz (SEB) und Oberfl√§chenmassenbilanz (SMB) dieser Eismassen und den gro√ür√§umigen Antrieb bekannt. Die zentrale Zielsetzung dieser Arbeit ist, das Verst√§ndnis der Wechselbeziehungen zwischen der Atmosph√§re und der Kryosph√§re bezogen auf Arktische Gletschersysteme zu verbessern. Im Speziellen sollen die Saisonalit√§t und Variabilit√§t des Klimas Svalbards und der damit verbundene Einfluss auf die Vestfonna-Eiskappe untersucht werden. Die angewandte Methodik kombiniert Felduntersuchungen, Fernerkundung und numerische Modellierung, um den Zustand und die Sensitivit√§t der SEB und der SMB des Vestfonna, die steuernden mesoskaligen Prozesse und die Art und Weise, wie diese Prozesse den synoptischen und lokalen Prozessraum verbinden, f√ºr die erste Dekade des 21. Jahrhunderts zu untersuchen. Diese Arbeit zeigt auch, wie schwierig es ist, Felddaten in der Arktis zu erheben und zuverl√§ssig den momentanen und zuk√ºnftigen Zustand in der Arktis abzusch√§tzen. Die Oberfl√§chenablationsraten des Vestfonna sind stark durch die Strahlung gesteuert, wodurch die Oberfl√§chenalbedo als ein entscheidendes Schl√ºsselelement zur Absch√§tzung der Ablationraten identifiziert wurde. Dar√ºber hinaus beeinflusst der Masseverlust durch windgesteuerte Schneeverfrachtung erheblich die Akkumulationsraten und stellt damit ein weiteres wichtiges Element der SMB des Vestfonna dar. Aus einer regionalen Reanalyse, der European Arctic Reanalysis (EAR), wurde eine j√§hrliche SMB von +0.02 ¬± 0.22 m w.e. yr‚àí1 und aus einem empirischen Ansatz eine j√§hrliche SMB von ‚àí0.02 ¬± 0.20 m w.e. yr‚àí1 f√ºr den Vestfonna als Mittelwert der Massenbilanzjahre 2001 bis 2009 berechnet. Da das f√ºr die EAR verwendete Modell keinen Masseverlust durch Schneeverwehungen berechnet und zus√§tzlich zu hohe Oberfl√§chenalbeden annimmt, sind die Akkumulationraten bei diesem Ansatz wahrscheinlich √ºber- und die Ablationsraten untersch√§tzt worden. Der empirische Ansatz zeigt hingegen starke Unsicherheiten in der Absch√§tzung des Temperaturfeldes und der Wiedergefrierraten. Eine Kombination der h√∂heren Ablationsraten der EAR und der niedrigeren Akkumulationsraten des empirischen Ansatzes ergeben eine j√§hrliche SMB des Vestfonna von ‚àí0.09 ¬± 0.19 m w.e. yr‚àí1 als Mittelwert der Massenbilanzjahre 2001 bis 2009. Sturmtiefs aus dem Nordatlantik zeigten starken Einfluss auf die Akkumulations- und Ablationsraten des Vestfonna. Da die Nordatlantische Oszillation (NAO) einer der wichtigsten Indizes f√ºr den Modus der atmosph√§rischen Zirkulation der Nordhemisph√§re ist, zeigte dieser Index auch Korrelationen mit den Ablations- und Akkumulationsraten des Vestfonna. Im Winter korrelierte der NAO-Index signifikant mit der H√§ufigkeit der eintreffenden Sturmtiefs aus dem Nordatlantik, welche stark auf Niederschlag, Lufttemperatur und Windgeschwindigkeit wirkten. Dabei wurde die j√§hrliche Akkumulationsrate des Vestfonna haupts√§chlich durch den mit den Sturmtiefs verbundene Feuchtetransport im Winter gepr√§gt. Im Sommer anti-korrelierte der NAO-Index signifikant mit der lokalen Zyklogenese und den damit verbundenen Niederschl√§gen. Die Analysen induzieren, dass die Ablationsraten des Vestfonna hierbei durch komplexe R√ºckkopplungen zwischen Niederschlag, Oberfl√§chenalbedo, Absorption solarer Strahlung und Lufttemperatur gesteuert wurden. Alle Ergebnisse zeigen eine fast ausgeglichene SMB des Vestfonna f√ºr die erste Dekade des 21. Jahrhunderts. Dennoch birgt die enge Kopplung der Ablationsraten an das Regen-Schnee-Verh√§ltnisses √ºber die Lufttemperatur ein gro√ües Potential f√ºr zuk√ºnftige √Ñnderungen der SMB des Vestfonna.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-05-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3716</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-39807</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-39807</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3716/finkelnburg_roman.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
