<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:45:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:296">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:296</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Experimental determination of the incorporation of Th into orthophosphates and the resetting of geochronological systems of monazite</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Experimentelle Bestimmung zum Einbau von Th in Orthophosphaten und zum Resetting der geochronologischen Systeme in Monazit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Seydoux-Guillaume, Anne-Magali</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorgelegte Dissertation beschäftigt sich mit (1) der Th Verteilung zwischen Monazit und Xenotim, (2) der Veränderung der Monazit Struktur beim Aufheizen, und (3) dem Resetting des U-Pb Systems in Monaziten. (1) Die Th Verteilung zwischen Monazit und Xenotim wurde, als Resultat der Th + Si = REE + P Substitution, experimentell (600-1100°C/2 kbar) untersucht. Dazu wurden Gele mit den gleichen Gehalten an CePO4 und YPO4 plus 10, 20 und 50 Mol % ThSiO4 als Anfangsmaterial benutzt. Nach den Experimenten wurden die Produkte mit AEM und XRD analysiert. Für alle Temperaturen und für Ausgangszusammensetzungen von 10 und 20 Mol % ThSiO4 wird ThSiO4 fast vollständig in Monazit eingebaut. Für 50 Mol % ThSiO4, kristallisiert zwischen 600° und 900°C Thorit. Das belegt, daß bei diesen Bedingungen Monazit an ThSiO4 gesättigt ist. Bei 1000°C kristallisierten Monazit, wenig Xenotim und kein Thorit. (2) Die Ausheilung von Strahlungsdefekten in einem natürlichen, homogenen, bei 474 ± 1 Ma konkordanten Monazit, wurde unter Verwendung von XRD, TEM, Raman und Kathodoluminescenz experimentell untersucht (500-1200°C/~7Tage). Der unbehandelte Monazit besteht aus einem Mosaik zweier Domänentypen (A) und (B), die zwei Monaziten mit unterschiedlichen Gitterkonstanten entsprechen. Die Domänen (A) entsprechen gut kristallisierten Bereichen, in denen He Atome, die eine Gitterexpansion induzieren, eingeschlossen sind. Die Domänen (B) entsprechen einem beschädigten Gitter (ohne He), dessen Defekte durch Alpha-Rückstoß Nuclei verursacht wurden. Während der Ausheilung, diffundiert das He aus dem Monazit-Gitter und induziert eine Gitterrelaxation. Gleichzeitig werden die defektreichen Domänen (B) ausgeheilt. Die komplette Heilung ist bei 900 nach 7 Tagen erreicht. (3) Um den Einfluß verschiedener Flüssigkeitszusammensetzungen und Temperaturen auf den Prozess des Resettings in Monazit zu untersuchen, wurden im Luftstrom gerundete Partikel (200-400 µm) des in (2) verwendeten Monazit experimentell (800-1000°C/14-39 Tage) in verschiedenen Lösungen (H2O bis 1200°C/5 Tage, NaCl, SrCl2, CaCl2, und Pb-spike) behandelt. Die Produkte wurden mit REM, EMP, SIMS und ID-TIMS analysiert. Für alle Experimente wurden mit EMP keine Pb Diffusionsprofile nachgewiesen. Signifikantes Aufwachsen von Monazit wurde nur bei 1000°C, in CaCl2 oder Pb-spike haltigen Experimenten beobachtet. In CaCl2-Lösungen erfolgte das Aufwachsen von neuem Monazit auf alten Monazitkörnern entsprechend einem Auflösungs/Ausfällungs Mechanismus. Signifikante Diskordanz wurde nur für den bei 1000°C in SrCl2 (16%) und CaCl2 (68%)-Lösungen ausgesetzten Monazit beobachtet. Monazite, die mit Pb-spike Lösungen koexistierten, zeigen nach den Experimenten höhere 207Pb/206Pb Alter.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This PhD thesis is divided into three parts: (1) the experimental incorporation of Th in monazite and xenotime, (2) the behaviour of the monazite structure under temperature-induced healing, and (3) the experimental resetting of the U-Pb geochronological system in monazite. (1) The Th distribution between monazite and xenotime as a result of the Th + Si = REE + P substitution mechanism was experimentally determined in the T-P-range of 600 to 1100°C and 2Kbar. Starting mixtures consisted of gels and were composed of equal amounts of CePO4 and YPO4 with addition of 10, 20 and 50 mole % of ThSiO4. Run products were analysed using AEM and XRD. At all temperatures, the ThSiO4 component is partitioned almost exclusively into monazite for a ThSiO4 component of 10 and 20 mole %. Xenotime is apparently ThSiO4-free. In the T-range 600°C-900°C and for ThSiO4 = 50 mole %, thorite is additionally formed indicating ThSiO4 saturation within monazite at these conditions. At 1000°C, only monazite and a small amount of xenotime crystallised. No thorite was observed. (2) The healing of radiation damage in a natural and chemically homogeneous concordant (474±1 Ma) monazite has been experimentally investigated (500-1200°C/~7days). XRD, TEM, Raman microprobe and Cathodoluminescence analysis were performed. The unheated monazite has a mosaic structure consisting of two domains corresponding to two monazite crystals with different lattice parameters. (A) domains correspond to well-crystallised areas where He atoms are trapped, thus inducing their lattice expansion. (B) domains are interpreted to exhibit a He-free distorted monazite crystal lattice which can be referred to old alpha-recoil tracks. With increasing temperature, He diffuses out of the monazite lattice, thus inducing its relaxation. Additionally, the nm-sized defect domains (B) are getting healed. The complete healing is achieved at 900°C after 7 days. (3) In order to investigate the influence of fluid composition and temperature on resetting, abraded fragments (200-400 µm) from monazite used in (2) were experimentally treated (800-1000°C/14-39 days) within solutions of different compositions (H2O up to 1200°C/5 days, NaCl, SrCl2 CaCl2-fluids and a Pb-spike-fluid). Products were analysed using SEM, EMP, SIMS and ID-TIMS. For all runs, EMP traverses revealed no Pb-diffusion profiles. Significant overgrowths of newly formed monazite occurred only in the 1000°C experiments when either CaCl2 or Pb-bearing fluids were present. For CaCl2, inherited core and newly formed Ca-rich and Pb-free monazite rim were produced by dissolution/precipitation. Significant discordancy was only observed when grains were treated with SrCl2 (16%) and CaCl2 (68%) solutions at 1000°C. Finally, experiments performed in the presence of Pb-standard produced sub-concordant monazite with a 207Pb/206Pb apparent age older than prior to the experiment indicating Pb-contamination by the fluid.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2002-01-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/296</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-2914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-2914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/296/seydoux_anne.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
