<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:44:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:63">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:63</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Strukturelle, kristallchemische und phasenpetrologische Untersuchungen an synthetischen und natürlichen Zoisit- und Klinozoisit-Mischkristallen</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Structural, crystallochemical and phasepetrological studies on synthetic and natural zoisite- and clinozoisite-solid solutions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brunsmann, Axel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Syntheseexperimente bei 2,0 GPa/750°C im System CaO-Fe2O3-Al2O3-SiO2-H2O (CFASH) ergaben homogen zusammengesetzte Zoisitkristalle mit Eisengehalten zwischen 0 und 14 Mol% Al2Fe. Diese wurden röntgenographisch untersucht. Rietveld-Strukturverfeinerungen zeigen, daß innerhalb der orthorhombischen Mischkristallreihe zwei Modifikationen Zoisit I und Zoisit II existieren. Sowohl in Zoisit I als auch in Zoisit II sind die Eisengehalte strukturell begrenzt. IR-Spektren dieser Proben zeigen, daß das Proton in Zoisit zwei Wasserstoffbrücken ausbildet, von denen eine gegabelt ist. Eine Bande bei ~ 2170 cm-1 wird als erster Oberton der "in-plane" Biegeschwingung dieser Wasserstoffbrücke interpretiert. Bandenlagen und integrale Intensitätsverhältnisse erlauben eine Bestimmung der Eisengehalte in Zoisit aus IR-Spektren. Mit Hilfe von Syntheseexperimenten im CFASH-System bei 0,5 GPa/500-650°C und 2,0 GPa/600-800°C wurden die Phasenbeziehungen zwischen Zoisit und Klinozoisit sowie innerhalb der monoklinen Mischkristallreihe konstruiert. Zoisit ist die Hochtemperatur/Hochdruckmodifikation. Die eisenfreie Endgliedreaktion Klinozoisit = Zoisit hat eine negative Steigung von - 8 MPa/°C. Mit steigenden Temperaturen werden koexistierender Zoisit und Klinozoisit eisenreicher. Das Zoisit-Klinozoisit 2-Phasenfeld ist sehr schmal. Es konnten zwei monokline Modifikationen Klinozoisit I und Klinozoisit II nachgewiesen werden, zwischen denen ein weiteres 2-Phasenfeld existiert. Natürliche, bei Hochdruckbedingungen gebildete Zoisitsegregationen zeigen, daß Zoisit signifikante Mengen an Sr, Pb und SEE einbauen kann und eine wichtige Rolle bei hochdruckfaziellen Fluid-Gesteinswechselwirkungen spielt. Berechnete Verteilungskoeffizienten für die LSEE zwischen Zoisit und Fluid belegen, daß die LSEE mit abnehmendem Ionenradius bevorzugt in Zoisit eingebaut werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Synthesis experiments at 2.0 GPa/750°C in the system CaO-Fe2O3-Al2O3-SiO2-H2O (CFASH) yielded homogeneous zoisite crystals with iron contents between 0 and 14 mol% Al2Fe. Run products were examined by X-ray diffractometry. Rietveld structural refinements show, that there exist two modifications zoisite I and zoisite II in the orthorhombic solid solution series. Iron contents in zoisite I as well as in zoisite II are structurally limited. IR-spectra of run products show that in zoisite the proton forms two hydrogen bridges, one of which is bifurcated. One band at ~ 2170 cm-1 is interpreted as the first overtone of the "in-plane" bending vibration of the bifurcated hydrogen bridge. The positions and the relative integral intensities of the IR-bands allow an estimation of the iron content in zoisite based on IR-spectra. Based on synthesis experiments in the system CFASH at 0.5 GPa/500 - 650C and 2.0 GPa/600 - 800°C the phase relations between zoisite and clinozoisite as well as within the monoclinic solid solution series has been constructed. Zoisite is the high-temperature and high-pressure modification. The iron-free endmember reaction clinozoisite = zoisite has a negative slope of - 8 MPa/°C. With increasing temperature iron contents in coexisting zoisite and clinozoisite increase. The zoisite-clinozoisite two-phase field is relatively narrow. Within the monoclinic solid solution series two monoclinic modifications clinozoisite I and clinozoisite II has been found. Between them there is a second two-phase field. Natural high-pressure zoisite segregations show, that zoisite is able to incorporate significant amounts of Sr, Pb and REE and plays an important role during high-pressure fluid-rock interactions. Calculated distribution coefficients for the LREE between zoisite and fluid show that the LREE are increasingly compatible in zoisite with decreasing ionic radius.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2001-04-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/63</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-580</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-580</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/63/brunsmann_axel.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
