<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:50Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1616">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1616</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Biogeochemistry of the deep microbial ecosystem in the Mallik 5L-38 Gas Hydrate Production Research Well</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Biogeochemie des tiefen mikrobiellen √ñkosystems der Mallik 5L-38 Gas Hydrate Forschungsbohrung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Haberer, Raingard Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">During the winter 2001/2002 the Mallik 5L-38 Gas Hydrate Production Research Well was conducted in the Mackenzie Delta (Northwest Territories, Canada) to investigate the gas hy-drates, which are occurring in the permafrost there, with regard to their geological, geophysical and geochemical properties. In the scope of the Mallik 5L-38 Gas Hydrate Production Research Well thirty core samples were collected for the current thesis from different lithologies (claystones, sandstones, siltstones, and lignites; late Oligocene) from above, within and below the gas hydrate bearing zone (810-1100m depth). The aim of this study is the characterisation of the organic matter, the reconstruction of the paleoenvironmental conditions, as well as the examination of the microbial communities with respect to their occurrence, their nature, and their habitat in deep subsurface sediments in a terrestrial setting near a gas hydrate zone by biogeochemical methods. The investigations of the organic matter composition (bitumen and kerogen) indicate a terrestrial and immature character of the organic. First evidence for the origin of the buried organic matter is given by the hydrogen (HI) and oxygen (OI) index values obtained by Rock-Eval-pyrolyses indicating a type III kerogen. Maturity indicators such as the Tmax values and the production index (PI), point to a thermally immature character of the organic material. These first results are supported by the maceral evaluation. On a molecular basis this is confirmed by the strong odd-over-even carbon number predominance of n-alkanes with a maximum in the range of n-C29 to n-C31 typical for immature land plant material. Additionally a second n alkane maximum at n-C23 in the lignite samples indicates the presence of the moss plant Sphagnum, which suggests the formation of the organic carbon rich lignites in a swampy mi-lieu, while the clay and sand layers are the result of a meandering river system. The occur-rence of specific higher land plant markers like the di- and triterpenoids supports the terrestrial character of the sample material and provide a more detailed insight into the plant communities. Therefore, it was recognized that the clay samples reveal the highest amounts of angiosperm markers. In contrast, lignite and sand samples contain significant amounts of gymnosperm biomarkers. Considering the documented variations of the paleovegetation, the changes of the climatic conditions can be estimate during the sedimentation within the Mackenzie Delta as well as in the upper course of the river. For the investigation of microbial biomass specific biomarkers like hopanoids, glycerol ethern and phospholipids were used. Hopanoids were found in significant amounts in almost all sediment samples investigated indicating a widely disseminated microbial biomass. The predominant occurrence of hopenes and hopanes in their biogenic 17Ô?¢ÔÄ®Ô?àÔÄ©ÔÄ¨21Ô?¢ÔÄ®Ô?àÔÄ©ÔÄ†configuration indicates the presence of immature microbial organic matter in deep subsurface Mallik sediments. However, because it can not absolutely be excluded that the hopanoids are part of the buried organic material preserved over time, phospholipids (PLs) were used as target molecules for the detection of viable microbial communities in the deep subsurface strata. Their potential as ‚Äúlife marker‚Ä? is their rapid degradation after cell death. The indigenous PL ester signals are in general low and often near the detection limit. However, structural elucidation using the MS/MS technique shows the presence of phosphatidyl-glycerols and phosphatidylethanolamines with mainly C16 and C18 fatty. Additionally, a series of specific compounds is detectable in significant amounts in almost all samples investigated. Their MS/MS fragmentation patterns suggest that these compounds are lyso-phosphatidylglycerols ethers. Such biomarkers would be of specific interest, because glycerol ethers are known to occur in archaeal biomass, thus the finding of lyso-phosphatidylglycerols supported by the detection of glycerol etherlipids may point to a microbial community of ar-chaea (e.g. methanogens or methanotrophs) in the gas hydrate bearing sediments of the Mallik site.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Im Winter 2001/2002 wurde im Mackenzie Delta (Northwest Territories, Kanada) die Mallik 5L-38 Gas Hydrate Production Research Well Bohrkampagne durchgef√ºhrt, deren Ziel es war, die im dortigen Permafrost vorkommenden Gashydrate hinsichtlich ihrer geologischen, geophysikalischen und geochemischen Eigenschaften zu untersuchen. Im Rahmen der Mallik 5L-38 Gas Hydrate Production Research Well Bohrung wurden f√ºr die vorliegende Arbeit drei√üig Bohrkernproben unterschiedlicher Lithologien (Tone, Sand- und Siltsteine, sowie Lignite) des oberen Oligoz√§ns √ºber, aus und unterhalb der Gashydrat-Zone (810-1100m Teufe) genommen. Das Ziel dieser Studie ist die Charakterisierung des organi-schen Materials, die Rekonstruktion der Pal√§oumweltbedingungen, sowie die Untersuchung mikrobieller Gemeinschaften hinsichtlich ihres Vorkommens, ihrer Besonderheiten und der Beschaffenheit ihres Lebenraumes in tiefen, terrestrischen Sedimentsschichten nahe einer Gashydrat-Zone mit Hilfe von biogeochemischer Analysenmethoden. Die Untersuchungen der Zusammensetzung des organischen Materials (Bitumen und Kero-gen) zeigen seinen terrigenen und unreifen Charakter an. Erste Hinweise auf die Herkunft des organischen Materials ergeben sich aus den Werten f√ºr die Wasserstoff- und Sauerstoffindizes (HI, OI), die bei der Rock-Eval-Pyrolyse bestimmt wurden und darauf hinweisen, da√ü das Kerogen dem terrigenen Typ III zugeordnet werden kann. Reifeparameter (Tmax, Produktions-index) indizieren die thermische Unreife des organischen Materials. Diese ersten Resultate wurden durch die Ergebnisse der Maceralanalyse zus√§tzlich untermauert. Auf molekularer Ebene wird die Unreife ebenfalls durch eine klare Dominanz der ungeradzahligen n Alkane mit einem f√ºr unreifes Landpflanzenmaterial typischen Maximum im Bereich von n C29 bis n C31 best√§tigt. Ein zweites Maximum (n-C23) in der n Alkanverteilung der Lignite deutet zus√§tzlich auf das Vorkommen der Mosspflanze Sphagnum und damit auf ihre Ablagerung in einem sumpfigen Milieu hin, w√§hrend die Ton- und Sandlagen ein Ergebnis des m√§andrieren-den Flu√üsystems sind und zumindest teilweise ein allochthones Signal wiederspiegeln. Die Pr√§senz spezifischer h√∂herer Landpflanzenmarker (Di- und Triterpenoide) unterstreichen den terrestrischen Charakter und erlauben einen detaillierteren Einblick in die Pflanzenvergesell-schaftung zur Zeit der Ablagerung. So ist in den Tonen ein h√∂herer Anteil an Angiospermbi-omarker feststellbar, w√§hrend das organische Material der Lignite und Sandsteine mehr Gym-nospermbiomarker enthalten. Anhand der feststellbaren Variation der Pal√§ovegetation l√§√üt sich auch die Entwicklung der klimatischen Bedingungen w√§hrend der Sedimentation sowohl im Mackenzie Delta als auch im oberen Flu√ülauf absch√§tzen. F√ºr die Untersuchungen der mikrobielle Biomasse werden spezifische Biomarker, wie Hopa-noide, Glycerolether und Phospholipide herangezogen. Hopanoide, insbesondere Hopene und Hopane mit biogener 17Ô?¢ÔÄ®Ô?àÔÄ©ÔÄ¨21Ô?¢ÔÄ®Ô?àÔÄ©ÔÄ≠Konfiguration, wurden in fast allen untersuchten Pro-ben gefunden, was auf eine ausgedehnte mikrobielle Biomasse in den tiefen Sedimenten in Mallik hindeutet. Da allerdings nicht ausgeschlossen werden kann, da√ü sie Teil des fossilen Materials sind und √ºber die Zeit konserviert wurden, werden Phospholipide (PLs) als soge-nannte ‚ÄúLife Marker‚Ä? f√ºr die Detektierung lebender mikrobieller Gemeinschaften genutzt. Durch ihren schnellen Abbau nach dem Zelltod sind sie daf√ºr besonders pr√§destiniert, so da√ü der Nachweis intakter PLs in Sedimenten des tiefen Untergrundes die Pr√§zens von lebenden Mikroorganismen best√§tigen. In den untersuchten Proben sind die Signale von indigenen PL estern jedoch generell gering und oft nahe am Detektionslimit. Dennoch k√∂nnen Phosphatidylglycerole und Phosphatidylethanolamine, haupts√§chlich mit C16 und C18 Fetts√§uren, nachgewiesen werden. Zus√§tzlich wurden weitere spezifischer Komponenten in nahezu allen untersuchten Proben festgestellt, deren MS/MS-Fragmentierungsmuster daraufhin deuten, da√ü es sich um Lyso-Phosphatidylglycerolether handelt. Das Auffinden dieser Biomarker ist von besonderem Inte-resse, da Glycerolether als Bestandteil von Archeen bekannt sind. Somit deutet der Nachweis von Lyso-Phosphatidylglycerolen zusammen mit dem Nachweis von Glyceroletherlipiden auf eine Archeenvergesellschaftung (methanogen oder methanotroph) in den Sedimentschichten der Gashydrat-Zone in der Mallikbohrung hin.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-11-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1616</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16819</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16819</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1616/haberer_raingard.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
