<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:43Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2688">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2688</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Modern Geophysical Techniques for Constructing a 3D Geological Model on the Nile Delta, Egypt</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Moderne geophysikalische Methoden zur Erstellung eines geologischen 3-D Modells für das Nil-Delta in Ägypten.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Barakat, Moataz Khairy Ahmad</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">The Nile Delta can be considered the earliest known delta in the world. It was described by Herodotus in the 5th Century AC. The Nile Delta (Ta-Mehet) in Hieroglyphic language means the land of the estuary water. It is one of the oldest intensely cultivated areas on the earth. The Nile Delta is illustrated to be an arcuate delta (arcshaped), as it resembles a triangle or lotus flower when seen from above. The name has been derived from the letter Thelta of the Greek alphabet. In comparison to the Mississippi, the Rhone, the Niger and the Ganges Deltas very little work has been published on the geological evolution of the Nile Delta. The present Nile Delta covers an onshore area of about 30,000 km2 and about an equal size offshore to the 200 m isobath. The southern apex of the delta is located approximately 30 km north of Cairo where the Nile River splits into the western Rosetta branch and the eastern Damietta branch. The delta reaches some 240 km along the Mediterranean coastline and extends to a maximum of 160 km from north to south. Without the Nile Valley and Delta, Egypt is mainly a desert country. It is difficult to investigate the ancient rocks of the Nile Delta, since no outcrops could be found as these are mainly covered by recent mud and alluvial deposits. On many maps the Nile Delta area is mostly represented a blank space described as Quaternary. The Nile Delta basin contains thick sedimentary sequences deposited mainly between Oligocene and Pliocene/Pleistocene extending to recent times. The Nile Delta plays a major role in the plate tectonic development of the eastern Mediterranean and north eastern Africa in a central position between the Red Sea rift and the subduction zone of the north-eastern Africa plate adjacent to the Cretan and Cyprus arcs. Structural styles and depositional environments varied during the Oligocene and Pliocene/ Pleistocene. Facies architecture and sequence stratigraphy of the Nile Delta are resolved using seismic stratigraphy based on 2D seismic lines including synthetic seismograms and tying in well log data. Synthetic seismograms were constructed using sonic and density logs. The combination of structural interpretation and sequence stratigraphy of the development of the basin was resolved. Seven chrono-stratigraphic boundaries have been identified and correlated on seismic and well log data. Several unconformities identified on seismic lines vary from angular unconformity to disconformity type. The Delta has experienced a rigorous and successful exploration campaign during the last few years. Nowadays, the Nile Delta is an emerging giant gas province in the Middle East with proven gas reserves which have more than doubled in size in the last years. This could be attributed to the fact that such province started to disclose part of its hidden hydrocarbon reserves as a direct result of using state of the art exploration techniques, in addition to the expanding use of different types of geological and geophysical modeling. Moreover, time structure maps, velocity maps, depth structure maps and isopach maps were constructed using seismic lines and log data. Several structural features include: normal faults, growth faults, listric faults, secondary antithetic faults and large rotated fault blocks mainly of Miocene age. In the Middle Miocene hiatus lasted about 10 my in the south-west delta, while the Late Miocene (Messinian) hiatus lasted only about 5 my in the same area. Also, sedimentary features such as paleo-channels were distinctively recognized. Typical sequence stratigraphic features such as incised valley, clinoforms, topsets, offlaps and onlaps are identified and traced on the seismic lines allowing insight into the sequence stratigraphic history of the Nile Delta most especially in the Miocene to Pliocene clastic sedimentary succession.The Nile Delta region is distinguished into three geological provinces for hydrocarbon exploration: a) the South Delta Block, b) the North Delta Basin and c) the deep offshore. With the advent of powerful computer workstations, the ability to perform interactive 3D modelling has become commonplace. The advantage of 3D modelling lies in its capability to allow viewing and evaluating a structure model by displaying cross section along any direction and through any well location of the model’s data base.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Das Nil-Delta gilt als das älteste noch aktive Delta der Welt. Geomorphologisch gehört es zum Typ der „komplexen bogenförmigen Deltas“. Die Breite des Deltas beträgt etwa 240 km entlang der Küste; die Nord-Süd Erstreckung erreicht maximal 160 km. Die Gesamtfläche wird mit ca. 60.000 km2 angegeben, je etwa zur Hälfte auf dem Festland sowie auf dem Schelf. Das Delta beginnt ca. 30 km nördlich von Kairo, an der Verzweigung des Nils in den westlichen Rosetta-Arm und den östlichen Damietta-Arm. Das Becken des Nil-Deltas beinhaltet sehr mächtige Sedimentabfolgen vom Oligozän bis zur Gegenwart, die in sehr verschiedenen Milieus zur Ablagerung kamen. Die Untersuchung der älteren Gesteine des Nil-Deltas gestaltet sich schwierig, da an der Oberfläche fast ausschließlich quartäre Ablagerungen anstehen. Das Nil-Delta liegt etwa mittig zwischen dem Riftsystem des Roten Meeres und einer Subduktionszone, die die nordöstliche afrikanische Platte von den kretischen und zyprischen Inselbögen trennt. Es spielt daher eine zentrale Rolle in der plattentektonischen Entwicklung des östlichen mediterranen Raumes. Die Bestimmung der Faziesverteilung sowie die Erstellung der Sequenzstratigraphie erfolgte mittels 2-D Seismik, die auf seismischer Stratigraphie basierte (inkl. synthetischer Seismogramme), sowie mittels der Einbindung von Bohrungsdaten (Logs). Synthetische Seismogramme wurden durch die Verwendung von Schall- und Dichtelogs konstruiert. Eine Kombination der strukturellen Interpretation und der Sequenzstratigraphie ermöglichte die Rekonstruktion der Entwicklungsgeschichte des Beckens. Insgesamt sieben chronostratigraphische Grenzen konnten ermittelt und über seismische und Bohrungsdaten korreliert werden. Die auf den seismischen Linien beobachteten Diskordanzen resultieren aus Winkeldiskordanzen bis hin zu Sedimentationsunterbrechungen. Des Weiteren wurden Zeit/Struktur-Karten, Geschwindigkeits-Karten und Isopachen-Karten aus den vorliegenden seismischen Linien und Log-Daten erstellt. Verschiedene strukturelle und tektonische Elemente wurden identifiziert, die zumeist im Miozän zwischen dem Tortonium und dem Messinium entstanden und mit Hiaten verknüpft sind. Weiterhin wurden Paläochannels identifiziert. Typische sequenzstratigraphische Strukturen wie „incised valleys“, „clinoforms“, „topsets und „onlaps“, die eine Rekonstruktion der miozänen und pliozänen Entwicklung des Nildeltas erlauben, konnten ebenfalls identifiziert und in ihrer Verbreitung innerhalb der klastischen Sedimentabfolge verfolgt werden. Das Gebiet des Nil-Deltas wird in drei Hauptregionen für die Kohlenwasserstoffexploration unterteilt: a) der südliche Delta-Block, b) das nördliche Delta-Becken and c) der tiefe Offshore-Bereich.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-11-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2688</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2688/barakat_moataz.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
