<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:09Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1935">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1935</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Bedingungen, Prozesse und Stoffdynamik der Bildung tertiärer kaolinitischer Tonlagerstätten in Sachsen und Sachsen-Anhalt und deren Auswirkungen auf die anwendungstechnischen Eigenschaften der Rohstoffe</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Conditions, processes and substance dynamics of the formation of Tertiary kaolinitic clay deposits in the German federal states of Saxony and Saxony-Anhalt and their effects on the application-technological properties of the raw materials </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmitz, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der Lausitz in Sachsen und im Geiseltal bei Halle in Sachsen-Anhalt befinden sich zahlreiche Vorkommen kaolinitischer Tone. Sie sind das feinkörnige terrestrische Umlagerungsprodukt einer mächtigen oberkretazisch-tertiären kaolinitischen Verwitterungskruste, die sich über den Basementgesteinen der Region entwickelte. Im Hangenden der in-situ-Kaoline entstanden Bodenhorizonte, die ähnlich wie rezente Acrisole und Alisole ausgebildet waren. Subrosion bzw. epirogenetische Bewegungen führten zu einer weitgehenden Erosion der kaolinitischen Verwitterungskruste vom Eozän bis zum Miozän und zur Sedimentation der kaolinitischen Tone in tertiären Becken. Die Tone gelangten in Bereichen geringer Strömungsenergie in Flüssen und Seen zur Ablagerung. Ziel der Untersuchung war es, die Bedingungen, die Prozesse und die stoffliche Dynamik der Tonlagerstättenbildung zu ermitteln und deren Auswirkungen auf die anwendungstechnischen Eigenschaften der Rohstoffe abzuschätzen. In der Oberlausitz wurden die Granodiorit-Kaoline der Lagerstätten Caminau und Wiesa sowie die Tone der Lagerstätten Wiesa, Wetro und Guttau systematisch beprobt. In der Region Merseburg-Weißenfels erfolgte die Probenahme in der Buntsandstein-Kaolinlagerstätte Spergau und der Tonlagerstätte Roßbach. Insgesamt wurden 43 Kaolin- und 122 Tonproben entnommen. Die Proben wurden chemisch und mineralogisch analysiert und die Kristallinität und die Einlagerungsfehlordnung der Kaolinite der Fraktion &lt;2 µm bestimmt. Die Kaoline und Tone bestehen überwiegend aus Kaolinit und Quarz sowie unterschiedlichen Anteilen an Illit/Muskovit, Smektit und Mixed-Layer-Mineralen. Akzessorisch treten Zirkon, Anatas, Pyrit, Fe-Oxide und SEE-Phosphate auf. Auf Grundlage älterer Untersuchungen konnten durch den Vergleich der mineralogischen und chemischen Zusammensetzung die Tone Kaolinen spezifischer Ausgangsgesteine zugeordnet werden. Durch die Kenntnis des Ursprungs des klastischen Materials der Tone konnte die qualitative und quantitative An- und Abreicherung der Komponenten untersucht und unterschiedliche Prozesse der Tonlagerstättenbildung voneinander abgegrenzt werden. Die qualitative Zusammensetzung der Tone beruht auf Prozessen der Verwitterung und der Bodenbildung. Sie regulierten die Art, die Menge und die Ausbildung der umgelagerten anorganischen und organischen Komponenten. Die Erosion, der Transport und die Sedimentation bewirkten eine Differenzierung der Komponenten der kaolinitischen Verwitterungskruste nach Kornform und -größe, Agglomerationsverhalten und Dichte im sedimentären Umfeld und bestimmten die quantitative Zusammensetzung der Tone. Durch die Klassierung von Quarz, Zirkon und eines Teils der Schwerminerale erfolgte die Anreicherung der durch Kaolinit dominierten Tonminerale der Kaoline und von Pflanzenresten der Bodenhorizonte in den korrelaten Sedimenten. Eine qualitative Änderung der Zusammensetzung kann nur durch Mischung mit Material einer weiteren Quelle erfolgen. Mit zunehmender sedimentärer Überdeckung durch Torfmoore wurden die Tone im Zuge der frühen Diagenese kompaktiert und die organische Substanz zu Weichbraunkohle umgewandelt. An Oxide gebundene Metalle wurden unter reduzierenden diagenetischen Bedingungen freigesetzt und sulfidisch im Tonsediment wieder fixiert. Die Kristallinität der Kaolinite der Fraktion &lt;2 µm der Kaoline und Tone ist nahezu identisch, die Einlagerungsfehlordnung ist hingegen sehr unterschiedlich. Es ist zu vermuten, dass sich in den Tonen Anteile sehr feinkörniger einlagerungsfehlgeordneter Kaolinite der Bodenhorizonte befinden. Die Bezeichnung von kaolinitischen Tonen als „umgelagerte oder sekundäre Kaoline“ im Sinne eines kurzstreckigen Massentransports ist aufgrund ihrer Genese nicht zutreffend. Die anwendungstechnischen Eigenschaften (Formgebungs-, Trocknungs- und Brenneigenschaften) der Tone können nicht auf das Ausgangsgestein der Kaolinisierung zurückgeführt werden, sondern sie sind im Wesentlichen von der Intensität der Verwitterung des Ausgangsgesteins und der Effektivität des hydraulischen Klassierungsprozesses abhängig. Aus Kaolinen unterschiedlicher Ausgangsgesteine können gleichartig mineralogisch zusammengesetzte kaolinitische Tone entstehen. Die Ergebnisse zeigen, dass die feuerfesten Tone beispielsweise zahlreiche feinkörnige einlagerungsfehlgeordnete Kaolinite der Bodenhorizonte enthalten. Qualitativ und quantitativ wirkende Bildungsprozesse sind für diese Tone von etwa gleichrangiger Bedeutung. Die Zusammensetzung keramischer Tone ist überwiegend auf qualitativ wirkende Bildungsprozesse zurückzuführen. Zu beachten sind sekundäre Prozesse in Bezug auf die Zu- und Abfuhr beispielsweise färbender Komponenten. Kaolinitische Tone sind das Produkt einer komplexen Prozesskette. Die Kenntnis der an der Tongenese beteiligten Prozesse kann zu einer optimierten Prospektion und Exploration, einem verbesserten Qualitätsmanagement und einer gezielteren Verwendung der Tone beitragen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In Lusatia in Saxony and in the Geiseltal close to Halle in Saxony-Anhalt there are numerous deposits of kaolinitic clays. They are the fine-grained terrestrial relocated product of a very thick kaolinitic weathering crust which developed above the basement rocks of the region from the Lower-Cretaceous up to the Tertiary. In the hanging wall of the in-situ kaolin soils developed, which were composed similar to recent acrisoles and alisoles. Subrosion or epirogenetic movements led to a widespread erosion of the kaolinitic weathering crust from Eocene to Miocene and to the sedimentation of kaolins in Tertiary basins. The deposition of the components of the kaolins took place in zones of low kinetic energy in lakes and rivers. It was the aim of the research to analyse the conditions, the processes and the substance dynamics of the formation of clay deposits and to evaluate their effects on the application-technological properties of the raw materials. In the region of the Oberlausitz the granodiorite-kaolins of the deposits of Caminau and Wiesa were systematically sampled as well as the clays of the deposits of Wiesa, Wetro and Guttau. In the region Merseburg-Weißenfels sampling was carried out in the Bunter-Sandstone-kaolin deposit Spergau and the clay deposit Roßbach. Altogether, there were taken 43 samples of kaolins and 122 samples of clay. The samples were analysed chemically and mineralogically and the crystallinity and the intercalation-disorder of the kaolinites of the fraction &lt;2 µm were determined. The kaolins and clays are mineralogically mainly composed of kaolinite and quartz as well as different concentrations of illite/muskovite, smectite and mixed-layer-minerals. The samples contain small amounts of zircon, anatase, pyrite, Fe-oxides and REE-phosphates. On the basis of former analyses it was possible by means of a comparison of the mineralogical and chemical composition to assign the kaolinitic clays to kaolins of specific parent rocks. It is due to the knowledge of the origin of the clastic clay material that it was possible to analyse the qualitative and quantitative enrichment and depletion of components, and different processes of the formation of clay deposits could be differentiated. The qualitative composition of the clays is based on processes of weathering and soil formation. These processes regulated type, quantity and composition of the relocated anorganic and organic components. The erosion, the transport and the sedimentation resulted in a differentiation of the components of the kaolinitic weathering crust according to the form and the size of the grains, the agglomeration behaviour and density in the sedimentary environment and they determined the quantitative composition of the clays. Because of the grading of quartz, zircon and some of the heavy minerals the kaolinite dominated clay minerals and relicts of plants of the soils were enriched in the sediment. A qualitative change of the composition of the clays could only result from a supply of components of another origin. The clays were covered by swamps and increasingly compacted. During early diagenesis the organic substance of the clays was transformed into lignite. Metals bound to oxides were released under reduced diagenetic conditions and they were fixed in the form of sulfides in the clay sediment. The crystallinity of the kaolinites of the fraction &lt;2 µm of the kaolins and clays is almost identical, in contrast with this, the values of the intercalation-disorder are differing very much. It can be assumed that the clays contain different proportions of fine-grained intercalation-disordered kaolinites of the palaeosols. The denomination of kaolinitic clays as „secondary kaolins“ in the sense of a short-distance mass transport is not appropiate due to their genesis. The application-technological properties of the clays are not attributable to the original parent rocks, but they are mainly dependent on the intensity of the alteration of the parent rocks and on the effectiveness of the hydraulic grading process. On the basis of kaolins of different parent rocks there may generate mineralogically identical kaolinitic clays. The results show that refractory clays contain numerous fine-grained intercalation disordered kaolinites of the palaeosols. Formation processes having qualitative and quantitative effects are of equivalent importance for these clays. The composition of ceramic clays is preponderantly attributable to the formation processes having qualitative effects. Secondary processes related to the enrichment or depletion of chemical components, for example of dyeing components, has to be taken into account. Kaolinitic clays are a product of a complex process chain. The knowledge of the processes being a part of the clay genesis can contribute to an optimised prospection and exploration, an improved quality management and a targeted application of the clays.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-10-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1935</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20355</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20355</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1935/original_schmitz_martin.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1935/schmitz_martin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
