<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:12Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2803">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2803</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Generation of a 3D city model of Baalbek/Lebanon based on historical photos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Generierung von 3D Stadtmodell von Baalbek/Lebanon mit der Auswertung von historischen Bildern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alamouri, Ahmed</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Within this research the combined evaluation of different types of historical photos for the documentation of cultural heritage sites is discussed. For this purpose the historical photos of Baalbek in Lebanon have been used which can be classified into three types: vertical, oblique and terrestrial photos. Due to the poor properties of these photos (such as: different cameras used and no primary data of cameras’ parameters, different image scales, different altitudes of the flight, the contrast of the gray values and the image noise are relative high, in addition the images had been taken in different dates, etc.), it is not a priori clear by which combination of the image orientation process the best results (namely, the accurate determination of camera parameters) could be achieved. Therefore, an approach for the relative orientation process will be discussed. Since the relative orientation is the position recovery and orientation of one image system relative to another, the potential of the mentioned approach is to reveal (from a mathematical point of view) the direct and indirect impact between the historical images of Baalbek to each other. It can be considered as a new contribution for the image orientation process based on the combination of different image types. This approach consists of three steps; the first one is the orientation of each image type in a separated block with its special properties (e.g. for each type a special camera was assumed). Second, the orientation process only for the vertical and oblique photos together has been achieved. Finally, all types of historic Baalbek’s photos have been assembled into the same block and then oriented. The abovementioned orientation steps were carried out using the bundle block adjustment method. This way has been selected because it enables to model the direct relation between the photo’s reference system and object space optimally. The mentioned relation between both systems describes the relationship between the input data which are called observations L ̃_i (e.g. the coordinates of image points, control points, etc.) and unknown parameters X ̃_i (e.g. the parameters of interior and exterior orientation). The requested relationship can be mathematically presented through a model (called a functional model) which will be the main form applied in the adjustment problem. In general, the functional model is highly non-linear; therefore a special emphasis has to be respected when solving this problem. Due to the assumption that the adjustment method is generally achieved with linear functions, a linearization process should be enforced. Based on the oriented model of the historical photos, the combination between the different historical images of Baalbek - in order to achieve a best possible 3D object reconstruction will be evaluated by independent controls. Moreover, Baalbek’s 3D data extracted from oriented historical photos will be considered the main input data used for a 3D CityGML modelling (City Geography Markup Language). CityGML modelling supports different Levels of Detail (LODs); by them different data collections can be represented and modelled. In this context, it will be investigated: in which LOD Baalbek data acquired can be modelled! In other words: based on the quality check of Baalbek data we want to know in which LOD Baalbek data available could be modelled. In addition, the semantic modelling of this city should be taken into account, because the geometric model does not support all information needed (e.g. classification of objects, building function, building class, names, etc.). Thus, the objects’ geometry isn’t the only quality concern. This will guarantee the creation of a geometric and semantic 3D city model of Baalbek which on the one hand provides an important document for this city and on the other hand allows to understand and to enable the analysis of the historical developments of Baalbek’s building remains from the prehistoric date until 20th century. Work results are: the internal geometric configuration of the different cameras used and the lens systems were determined; so that the measurement of the applicable 3D object points is possible. Moreover, the quality of Baalbek’s data extracted based on the oriented model of the photos has been checked. Depending on the quality assessment of Baalbek’s data a 3D city model of this historic city was created in two different LODs. The results will be also considered a data base for other applications and projects in Baalbek’s space (for e.g. the Geoinformation System GIS, archaeology, architecture, etc.).</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit befasst sich mit der Auswertung von historischen Bildern unterschiedlichster Art zur Dokumentation von Objekten des Weltkulturerbes. Beispielhaft wurde verfügbares Bildmaterial (vertikale, terrestrische und Schrägaufnahmen) der Stadt Baalbek in Lebanon verwendet und photogrammetrisch ausgewertet. Bei der Verarbeitung des historischen Bildmaterials tritt eine Vielzahl von Problemen auf, deren Ursache in der Aufnahmesituation (wie zum Beispiel: unterschiedliche Aufnahmezeitpunkte, unterschiedliche Bildmaßstäbe, verschiedene Flughöhen und verschiedene Kameras) bzw. in der Beschaffenheit der Bilder zu sehen ist (unterschiedlicher Kontrast der Grauwerte in den Bildern, Bildrauschen). In der Regel sind keine Daten über die verwendeten Kameras bekannt, was eine Auswertung wesentlich erschwert. In dieser Arbeit wird eine Strategie entwickelt, die einen Beitrag zur kombinierten Auswertung von historischen Bildern liefert. Der Lösungsansatz sieht drei Stufen vor: Unter diesen Bedingungen von den verwendeten Bildern wird in dieser Arbeit eine entsprechende Strategie basiert auf verschiedenen Klassen von historischen Bildern zur Kamerakalibrierung und Bildorientierung entwickelt. Diese Strategie liefert einen effektiven Beitrag für den relativen Orientierungsprozess, da diese kombinierte Auswertung von den historischen Bildern bisher nur unzureichend untersucht wurde. Sie bildet daher einen Schwerpunkt dieser Arbeit. Zunächst müssen die verfügbaren Bilder im Koordinatensystem Baalbeks gemeinsam orientiert werden, um die unbekannten Parameter der inneren sowie der äußeren Orientierung zu bestimmen. Diese Parameter werden durch einen speziellen Algorithmus auf Basis der Bündelblockausgleichung berechnet und somit die Verzerrungsparameter (radial und dezentral) ermittelt. In der Arbeit wird untersucht, wie die Näherungswerte der Unbekannten optimal geschätzt werden und wie weit sie die erforderliche Genauigkeit und Zuverlässigkeit beeinflussen. Zur relativen Orientierung der historischen Bilder von Baalbek wurde ebenfalls die Methode der Bündelblockausgleichung angewendet, da sie den Zusammenhang zwischen den Bildkoordinaten (als Beobachtungen) und den Objektkoordinaten direkt, d.h. ohne Umweg über Modellkoordinaten, herstellen kann. Dieser Zusammenhang lässt sich durch die mathematische Beziehung zwischen den Beobachtungen L ̃_i (z. B. Bildkoordinaten, Passpunkten, usw.) und den Unbekannten X ̃_i (wie z. B. die Parameter der inneren und äußeren Orientierung) präsentieren. Diese Beziehung kann mathematisch als funktionales Modell dargestellt werden, welches als die im Ausgleichungsprozess angewendete Hauptform gilt. Generell ist der funktionale Ansatz nichtlinear, deshalb wird im Rahmen der Arbeit der Lösung dieses Problems spezielle Aufmerksamkeit gewidmet. Unter der Annahme, dass die Ausgleichung generell mit linearen Funktionen gelöst werden kann, wird ein Linearisierungsprozess eingeführt. In den jetzt orientierten Bildern können räumliche Objektkoordinaten gemessen werden, um 3D-Objekte zu rekonstruieren. In dieser Arbeit wird untersucht, in wie weit durch die Kombination der verschiedenen historischen Bilder eine beste 3D-Objektrekonstruktion möglich ist. Die 3D-Daten Baalbeks liefern den Input zu einer 3D-Modellierung basierend auf CityGML (City Geography Markup Language). Daher beleuchtet die Arbeit, welcher Detaillierungsgrad (Level of Detail-LOD) bei der Modellierung erreicht werden kann. Darüber hinaus werden, soweit möglich, CityGML-Objekte (CityGML-Entitäten) der Stadt Baalbek durch semantische Informationen angereichert (z. B. Kategorie, Name und Adresse des Objekts), da sie einen wesentlichen Mehrwert für die Analyse der historischen Entwicklung der Stadt liefern. Mit der vorliegenden Arbeit wurde erreicht, dass die interne geometrische Konfiguration der unterschiedlichen verwendeten Kameras unter Berücksichtigung der Linsenverzerrung bestimmt werden konnte, und somit eine integrierte dreidimensionale Vermessung auf der Basis historischer Bilder möglich ist. Als weiteres anwendungsbezogenes Ergebnis wurde ein 3D-Stadtmodell von der historischen Stadt auf der Basis von CityGML in zwei verschiedenen LODs generiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-02-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2803</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29663</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29663</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2803/alamouri_ahmed.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
