<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:47:22Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:705">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:705</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:550</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Erschließung sedimentärer Speichergesteine für eine geothermische Stromerzeugung</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Development of sedimentary reservoir rocks for a geothermal power generation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Legarth, Björn Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:550</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Geothermische Stromerzeugung stellt Mindestanforderungen an Fluidförderraten und -temperaturen und damit an die Produktivität der zu erschließenden Reservoire. Im Falle der untersuchten klastisch sedimen-tären Speichergesteine des Norddeutschen Beckens ist die Ausgangsproduktivität zu gering für eine effi-ziente Förderung. Maßnahmen zur künstlichen Produktivitätssteigerung sind unerlässlich. Die potenziellen Nutzhorizonte sind fluidgesättigt und befinden sich in großen Versenkungsteufen abseits geothermischer Anomalien. Es handelt sich so um geothermale Fluidlagerstätten auf einem geringen Enthalphieniveau. Mit Hilfe binärer Konversionsanlagen ist eine Stromerzeugung bei ausreichendem Mas-senstrom jedoch realsierbar. Auf Grund ihrer weiten Verbreitung bergen sie demnach ein großes theoreti-sches Energiepotenzial. Da es sich um nicht-artesische Speicher handelt, sind Förderhilfsmittel einzusetzen. Die Überwindung der Diskrepanz zwischen dem einerseits geringen technisch-wirtschaftlichen und dem andererseits hohen theoretischen Nutzenpotenzial durch eine geeignete Erschließungstechnologie war die Hauptmotivation für die vorliegenden Untersuchungen. Die Untersuchungen befassten sich daher im Schwerpunkt mit hydraulischen Stimulationsmaßnahmen zur sekundären Produktivitätserhöhung. Neben allgemeinen Fragestellungen - Transfermöglichkeiten von Erkenntnissen und Technologien aus der Kohlenwasserstoffindustrie - wurde deren Machbarkeit und Wirkungsweise anhand eines konkreten Fallbeipiels überprüft. Hierfür erfolgte die Auswertung von Feld-experimenten, die in einer aufgewältigten Rotliegend-Erdgasbohrung im östlichen Bereich des Norddeut-schen Beckens durchgeführt wurden. Die Zielhorizonte waren Sandsteinformationen an der Basis der Rotliegend-Stratigraphie. Die Stimulationsmaßnahmen wurden als hydraulische Frac-Operationen unter Verwendung hochviskoser Fluide und dem Zusatz von Stützmitteln (Hydraulic Proppant Fracturing) ausgelegt. Das Ziel bestand darin, Risse in der porös-permeablen Matrix und damit neue hochkonduktive Fließwege zu erzeugen, um bohrlochnahe, produktive Reservoirzonen hydraulisch effektiv an die Bohrung anzuschließen. Die Stützmittel dienten dem langfristigen Offenhalten der Risse während der Förderphase. Für einen gesteigerten Stimulationserfolg sah das Konzept die sukzessive Behandlung zweier Intervalle im unverrohrten Abschnitt der Bohrung vor. Dadurch konnte eine maximale hydraulische Zuflussfläche erreicht werden. Das erforderte die Anwendung einer neuen Frac-Technologie. Es handelte sich um den Einsatz eines rückholbaren open hole Packers sowie einer Kiesschüttung, um die hydraulische Isolation des jeweiligen Behandlungsintervalls zu gewährleisten. Obwohl die eingesetzten Einzelkomponenten und verfahren aus der Kohlenwasserstoffindustrie bekannt sind, lag für das technologische Gesamtkonzept unter den am Standort gegebenen in situ Bedingungen keine Referenz vor. Trotz der erfolgreichen Erzeugung von hydraulischen Rissen in beiden Intervallen unter Verwendung von mehr als 104 kg Stützmittel und 200 m³ hochviskoser Fluide, konnte das Stimulationsziel nicht in vollem Umfang erreicht werden. Hierfür war unter anderem eine technisch bedingte Unterdimensionierung der Behandlung verantwortlich, die keinen effektiven hydraulischen Anschluss des Speichers ermöglichte. Ferner wurden chemisch-mechanische Effekte identifiziert und modelltechnisch nachgebildet, die während der Einschluss- und Förderphase zu einer Reduzierung der Risskonduktivität geführt haben könnten. Schlussfolgernd kann festgehalten werden, dass das Stimulationspotenzial der Zielhorizonte somit einerseits noch nicht ausgeschöpft, andererseits generell reservoirspezifisch begrenzt ist. Dies gilt unter alleiniger Berücksichtigung technisch und wirtschaftlich realisierbarer Stimulationspotenziale. Nicht zuletzt wurde eine Vielzahl neuer übertragbarer Erkenntnisse im Zusammenhang mit dem hydraulisch-mechanischen Gebirgsverhalten, der Rissmodellierung und der angewandten Frac-Technologie gewonnen, die als Grundlage für angepasste Stimulationsmaßnahmen dienen können.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">For an economic geothermal power generation certain fluid production rates and temperatures are required implying a corresponding reservoir productivity. In the case of the investigated clastic sedimentary reservoir rocks (Rotliegend sandstones) of the North German Basin the initial productivity is too low for an efficient fluid production. Therefore, measures for a secondary productivity enhancement become mandatory. The potential pay zones in this area are deep-seated aquifer structures aloof from positive geothermal anomalies. They can be classified as low-enthalpy fluid dominated geothermal reservoirs. However, using binary power plants a power generation becomes feasible for high flow rates. Nevertheless, because of the large distribution throughout the basin the reservoirs bear a high theoretic energy potential. As the reservoirs are non artesic, artificial lift systems have to be applied and included in the overall energy balance. Overcoming the discrepancy between a low technical feasibility on the one hand and a high theoretic availability by applying a fit-to-purpose development technology was the key motivation for the investigations carried out. The primary stress was put on evaluating the effectiveness of hydraulic stimulation technology in the given environment. Besides general aspects - including knowledge transferability from hydrocarbon industry - their feasibility and impact have been researched and verified by analysing large scale field experiments conducted in a designated research well in the North German Basin. The target horizons were sandstone formations at the base of the Rotliegend stratigraphy. The stimulation treatments were performed as hydraulic fracturing operations using high viscosity frac fluids and proppants (hydraulic proppant fracturing). The goal was to create highly conductive new flow paths in the porous-permeable matrix in order to effectively connect near-wellbore productive reservoir zones. Proppants were used to assure a long term fracture aperture during drawdown conditions. For an increased stimulation success two intervals were successively fracture treated in the open hole section (3,9 to 4,3 km depth below surface) of the well. By treating an open hole section the hydraulic connection of a maximum effective inflow area should be realized. An innovative fracturing technology concept was applied using an open hole retrievable packer and a sand plug to realize the zonal isolation of each interval respectively. Although the basic components and procedures are known in hydrocarbon industry, there was no technical reference available for the applied concept referring to the given in situ conditions (temperature, pressure, depth and fluid chemistry). Nevertheless, fractures could be created in both intervals placing more than 104 kg proppants and 200 m³ high viscosity fluids into the formations. Yet the initial stimulation goal could not be reached because the productive reservoir zones could not be effective enough connected to the wellbore. This was mainly due to a sub-dimensioning of the treatments in order to reduce the risk of a technical failure (e.g. by-pass of the packer). Moreover chemical-mechanical effects could be identified and analysed that led to a reduction of the fracture conductivity during shut in and production phases. Consequently the stimulation and productivity potential of the pay zones have not yet been fully reached. On the other hand the investigations showed that this potential is strongly reservoir specific and also limited. This is valid assuming a technical and economical feasibility. Nevertheless, a variety of transferable new insights in the field of the hydraulic-mechanical rock properties and behaviour of the target zones, fracture modelling and the applied technology concept could be gained from the experiments. They can be directly used for further stimulation treatments at this and geologically comparable sites. The investigations also covered energetic and cost issues related to the geothermal energy exploitation concept. In this context the energy demands for drilling and completing the wells and lifting the fluids from the reservoir to the surface were determined including a sensitivity study. The energetic efficiency of the overall concepts is dominated by the production effort that in return is directly depending on the reservoir productivity. The cost efficiency on the other hand is clearly dominated by the investment costs for the wells. On both sides key parameters, saving potentials and benchmarks could be determined. The research has shown that the target horizons have the potential to serve as potential pay zones only if they bear a moderate initial productivity and can be developed in an energy and cost efficient manner. Secondary stimulation treatments with the goal of enhancing the inflow performance by creating highly conductive flow paths are mandatory in this context. Guaranteeing their permanent effectiveness by proper treatment design, execution and production set up requires further research and development. To increase the overall productivity and to lower the site dependency future research should additionally focus on connecting further productive pay zones in the vicinity of the developed clastic sedimentary reservoir rocks.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2003-08-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/705</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-6998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-6998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/705/legarth_bjoern.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
