<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:55Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3170">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3170</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Simulation and Stability of Milling Processes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Simulation und Stabilität von Fräsprozessen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rott, Oliver</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The main optimisation goal for milling operations in mass production is to increase the material removal rate while maintaining an optimal product quality. In addition to the spindle power available, the loss of process stability imposes an upper boundary to the increase of the material removal rate. The challenges in research are therefore to formulate optimal design directives for new machines on the one hand and on the other to improve the reliability and the efficiency of stability prediction methods for given machines and processes. In order to address these issues, a new coupled model for milling processes is presented in this work together with a tailored numerical simulation algorithm. The model incorporates the machine dynamics and thermo--mechanical work piece effects. While the detailed representation of the machine structure provided by means of a multi body system gives useful information to discover structure optimisation potentials, the work piece representation as a 3D thermo--elastic solid guarantees high flexibility as a large range of possible geometries fits into this framework. The regenerative effect is incorporated by a new Dexel based material removal model that allows a realistic simulation of the generated work piece surface even for \mbox{(thermo--)elastic} work piece models. A newly developed algorithm based on a finite element discretisation of the work piece equations and a fast method for the assembly of the equations of motion for the multi body system guarantees a robust and effective numerical solution of the coupled system due to a fully implicit time integration scheme. Another novelty is related to the need for an efficient and reliable stability analysis method for large systems of periodic delay differential equations (PDDEs). Such systems arise either from the afore mentioned complex milling system involving a machine model and the discrete elasticity equations in 3D describing the work piece dynamics or even from complex dynamical systems representing the modal analysis data of a real milling machine in time domain. The key concepts to achieve this goal are, on the one hand, a new stability analysis approach based on the solution of non linear eigenvalue problems and, on the other hand, the consequent use of recently developed model reduction techniques. The work is organised as follows: The introduction is followed by a chapter dealing with the stability analysis for PDDEs, its applications with focus on coupled systems and the exploitation of model reduction techniques. Chapter~3 covers the development of a coupled milling system including a detailed description of the coupling terms involved. Chapter~4 is devoted to the discussion of discretisation schemes and the presentation of the time integration algorithm. The simulation results are presented in Chapter~5 while Chapter~6 covers the experimental verification. The last section is devoted to some closing remarks.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Bei der Optimierung von Fräsprozessen, die in der Massenproduktion genutzt werden, ist die Hauptaufgabe, das Zeitspanvolumen zu steigern und gleichzeitig die Produktqualität sicherzustellen. Die Erhöhung des Zeitspanvolumens ist jedoch durch die verfügbare Spindel-leistung und durch den Verlust der Prozessstabilität begrenzt. Die Entwicklung von optimierten Designvorgaben für neue Werkzeugmaschinen ist daher eine der Hauptaufgaben der Forschung. Für bestehende Werkzeugmaschinen und Prozesse müssen die Effizienz und die Zuverlässigkeit der Stabilitätsanalyseverfahren weiter gesteigert werden. Um diesen Anforderungen gerecht zu werden, wird in der vorliegenden Arbeit ein neues Fräsmodell zusammen mit einem speziell dafür entwickelten, numerischen Lösungsverfahren vorgestellt. Neben der Maschinendynamik wird das Werkstück-verhalten in dem neuen Modell berücksichtigt. Ein komplexes Mehrkörpersystem, das zur detaillierten Maschinenbeschreibung verwendet wird, ermöglicht es, Optimierungspotentiale in der Maschinenstruktur aufzudecken. Die Modellierung des Werkstücks als dreidimensionaler, thermoelastischer Festkörper erlaubt eine Untersuchung der Werkstückeinflussfaktoren und die Analyse verschiedener Geometrien. Mit Hilfe eines Dexel-basierten Materialabtrennungsmodells kann darüber hinaus, auch für (thermo--)elastische Werkstückmodelle, die erzeugte Werkstück-oberfläche und damit der Regenerativeffekt simuliert werden. Das numerische Lösungsverfahren basiert auf einer schnellen Methode zum Aufbau der Gleichungen des Mehrkörpersystems und einer Ortsdiskretisierung der Werkstückgleichungen mit Hilfe der Finiten Elemente Methode. Die effiziente Lösung des gekoppelten Systems im Zeitbereich wird durch ein implizites Zeitintegrationsverfahren gewährleistet. Ein weiterer Bestandteil der Arbeit ist ein neu entwickeltes, effizientes Verfahren zur Stabilitätsanalyse von periodischen Delaydifferentialgleichungen. Solche Systeme beschreiben das Stabilitätsverhalten komplexer Fräsmodelle oder repräsentieren dynamische Systeme, die von Modalanalysedaten realer Maschinen abgeleitet wurden. Das neue Verfahren basiert auf der Lösung von nichtlinearen Eigenwertproblemen und der konsquenten Ausnutzung von Modellreduktionstechniken. Die Arbeit ist wie folgt strukturiert: Im Anschluss an die Einleitung folgt ein Kapitel in dem das neue Verfahren zur Stabilitätsanalyse, einige Anwendungs-beispiele und die Modellreduktion erläutert werden. Kapitel~3 deckt die Entwicklung des komplexen Fräsmodells sowie eine detaillierte Beschreibung der Kopplungsterme ab. Kapitel~4 beschäftigt sich mit den Diskretisierungsansätzen und dem Zeitintegrationsverfahren. Die Präsentation der Simulationsergebnisse erfolgt in Kapitel~5 und Kapitel~6 behandelt die experimentelle Verifizierung. Der letzte Abschnitt enthält einige abschließende Bemerkungen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-12-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3170</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3170/rott_oliver.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
