<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:45:37Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:326">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:326</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Untersuchungen zur nachhaltigen Wirkung der Uferfiltration im Wasserkreislauf Berlins</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Investigations on the sustainability of bank filtration in Berlin's water cycle</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ziegler, Doerte H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Ca. 75 % des Berliner Trinkwassers besteht aus lokal gefördertem Uferfiltrat bzw. künstlich angerei-chertem Grundwasser (Schulze 1997). Gleichzeitig leiten Berlins teilweise stromaufwärts von Uferfiltratstrecken eingeleitet. Szenarien prognostizieren zudem einen lokalen Anstieg der Abwasseranteile (Schumacher &amp; Skripalle 1999, Heinzmann 1997). Da Kläranlageneinleitungen zu Stoffeinträgen führen, die trotz Bodenpassage und Wasseraufbereitung bis ins Trinkwasser gelangen können, wurden sowohl die Reinigungsleistung der Berliner Uferfiltration für organische Stoffe (DOC) sowie der Einfluss erhöhter Abwasseranteile untersucht. Das Hauptaugenmerk der Untersu-chungen lag auf der Selbstreinigungskraft sowie dem Regenerationsvermögen der Ressource Wasser, deren Erhalt im Sinne einer Nachhaltigen Wasserwirtschaft gefordert wird (Lehn et al. 1999). Über zwei Jahre wurden die gelösten organischen Stoffe an Uferfiltrationsstrecken an Tegeler See und Müggelsee in Berlin untersucht. Im Mittel werden ca. 20-45 % des DOC bei der Bodenpassage entfernt. Mit Bodensäulen gelingt eine Elimination von 30 % des DOC nach drei Metern. Vor allem höhermolekulare Anteile des DOC werden bei der Uferfiltration eliminiert, insbesondere eine den Polysacchariden zugeordnete Fraktion (®LC-OCD). Das Adsorptionsverhalten der gelösten organi-schen Stoffe (®Adsorptionsanalyse) ist sowohl vor als auch nach der Bodenpassage als schlecht ein-zuordnen. Die Reinigungsleistung der Uferfiltration für den DOC ist in Berlin-Tegel seit Jahrzehnten stabil und hängt vor allem von der Oberflächenwasserqualität ab. Kläranlageneinleitungen erhöhen den refraktären Teil organischer Verbindungen (RDOC) in den Berliner Gewässern. Sie tragen aber nicht zu einer wesentlichen Veränderung des Charakters des DOC bei in Bezug auf Molekulargewichtsverteilung, Adsorptionsverhalten oder Verteilung der funk-tionellen Gruppen (®13C-NMR). In Tegel trägt eine Phosphateliminierungsanlage (Fe-Flockung) zur Reduktion von ca. 25-30 % der zum Teil kläranlagenbürtigen organischen Stoffe bei. Entfernt wird vor allem der hochmolekulare huminstoffähnliche Anteil. Am Beispiel Berlin Tegels, wo für Berlin die höchsten Abwasseranteile im Trinkwasser von ca. 14-28 % vorliegen, wurden die Grenzen der indirekten Abwasserwiederverwendung untersucht. Zunächst wurden für RDOC, Chlorid und Sulfat die irreversiblen Stoffeinträge durch Wasserverbraucher sowie Kläranlagen bilanziert, indem die Stofffrachten des Berliner Trinkwassers denen der Kläranlagen-abläufe gegenübergestellt wurden. Die resultierenden Stoffeinträge (75-90 mg/l Chlorid, 35-45 mg/l Sulfat, 4-5 mg/l RDOC) werden in einem Modell (TegelSIM) zur Prognose der Trinkwasserkonzentra-tionen bei erhöhten Abwasseranteilen verwendet. TegelSIM zeigt, dass bei Rückführung von 60 % Trinkwasser zu der Kläranlage, deren Abwässer wieder zur Trinkwassergewinnung beitragen, bis zu Abwasseranteilen von 90 % im Trinkwasser keine problematischen Sulfat-, Chlorid- oder RDOC-Konzentrationen erreicht werden (Worst-Case: 248 mg/l SO4, 207 mg/l Cl, 7,7 mg/l RDOC). Für persistente Stoffe läßt sich die relative Trinkwasserkonzentration bezogen auf den Stoffeintrag je nach Abwasseranteil im Trinkwasser berechnen. Derzeit betrügen die Konzentrationen im Tegeler Trinkwasser infolge Verdünnung ca. 1/3 des Stoffeintrags eines persistenten bzw. refraktären Stoffes. Die Uferfiltration und künstliche Grundwasseranreicherung in Berlin tragen aufgrund ihrer langfristig fortbestehenden Reinigungsleistung und ihres geringen Energie- und Wartungsbedarfs zu einer nachhaltigen Wasserwirtschaft bei. Das Berliner System, in dem es teilweise zur indirekten Abwasser-wiederverwendung kommt, stößt allerdings mit Bezug auf die Selbstreinigungskraft insbesondere bei persistenten organischen Einzelstoffen an seine Grenzen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">About 75 % of Berlin´s drinking water is bank filtrate or artificially recharged groundwater. At the same time, Berlin´s treated wastewater is being discharged partially upstream of bank filtration sites. The surface water flow into Berlin is with about 53 m³/s relatively low. Due to lower groundwater abstraction for lignite coal mining upstream of Berlin, the first two decades of the 21st century will see a further reduction of this surface water flow to about 30 m³/s (Finke 2000). As a consequence, the portions of treated wastewater might increase in Berlin´s surface waters used for bank filtration and groundwater recharge. To ensure a high quality of the city´s drinking water, more information on the purification potential of Berlin´s bank filtration systems is required as well as increased knowledge about the consequences of increased wastewater portions in drinking water sources. This thesis investigates the purification capacity of bank filtration and groundwater recharge for dissolved organic substances. The focus lies on two aspects of a sustainable water management: the aspect of a long-term (self-)purification capacity of water, and the potential of water to be regenerated or recycled (adapted from Lehn et al. 1999). To investigate the aspect of (self-)purification of water via bank filtration in Berlin, DOC and UV analysis was carried out for monthly sampled groundwater monitoring wells over a period of two years. The monitoring wells are located at the banks of the lakes Tegeler See and Müggelsee in Berlin. In addition, soil passage was simulated using soil columns. Molecular weight distribution of organic compounds in bank filtrate, surface waters, treated wastewater and drinking water as well as for the soil columns was determined using batch-ultrafiltration and size exclusion chromatography (LC-OCD). Adsorption analysis gave information about the adsorption behavior of DOC on activated carbon. DOC of effluent, lake water, and two bank filtrates was fractionated using XAD resins (8 and 4 in tandem), and functional groups of the isolated DOC were analyzed using 13C-NMR. Lake bank filtration in Berlin eliminates about 20-45 % of DOC. Using soil columns, 30 % of DOC are eliminated after 3 meters. Larger molecular weight compounds are preferably removed during bank filtration, especially a fraction of polysaccharides (identified using LC-OCD). Dissolved organic substances of both Berlin´s surface waters and bank filtrates have been found to adsorb very poorly onto activated carbon. Wastewater discharges increase both DOC and the refractory part of dissolved organic compounds (RDOC) in surface waters. However, the character of DOC in surface waters is not changed significantly, namely molecular weight distribution, adsorption behavior and functional group distribution. In Berlin, the increase in RDOC due to wastewater discharges is not reflected in bank filtrate quality, although wastewater is partly being discharged upstream of bank filtration sites. DOC concentrations of lake Tegeler See and Tegel drinking water, which contains 80 % bank filtrate and artificially recharged water, show that the purification capacity of lake bank filtration remains constant over decades, and that drinking water DOC is mainly dependent on surface water quality. In lake Tegeler See, phosphate elimination by iron flocculation and the subsequent decrease of eutrophication both led to a reduction in DOC concentrations of about 4-6 mg/l. This reduction is reflected in DOC concentrations of Tegel drinking water, which decreased by about 1,5 mg/l. In a second part of the thesis, the qualitative and quantitative limits of indirect wastewater reuse were investigated. In Berlin, lake Tegeler See is a special example of indirect waste-water reuse: About 80 % of the groundwater abstracted around this lake consists of lake water. One of the largest water treatment plants of Berlin (WTP Tegel) abstracts lake water via bank filtration and artificial groundwater recharge. The portions of treated wastewater in the lake were found to be about 17-35 % (mean values, 1993-1998). In Tegel drinking water, wastewater portions were calculated to be 14-28 %. Berlin´s other water treatment plants have much lower portions that might reach maximum values of 11 % in times of extreme water shortage. Water users and wastewater treatment plants cause irreversible inputs of certain substances, such as RDOC, chloride, and to some extent sulfate. RDOC, chloride and sulfate inputs were quantified for Berlin by comparing the mass fluxes of Berlin´s drinking water with those of Berlin´s treated wastewater. The difference is called water use input. In Berlin, a single use cycle of water increases chloride by about 75-90 mg/l, sulfate by about 35-45 mg/l, and RDOC by about 4-5 mg/l. The water use input can explain the total input of DOC into Berlin´s surface waters (comparison of surface water mass fluxes into and out of Berlin). However, both chloride and sulfate fluxes increase to an extent that neither the water use input nor other material fluxes, i.e. from drainage water, can explain this increase satisfyingly. To quantify the limits of indirect wastewater reuse in partly closed water cycles with regard to drinking water concentrations of salts, RDOC, and single refractory compounds, a model was created (TegelSIM). The model was used to calculate scenarios for the Tegel water cycle. It was shown that when 60% of wastewater at WWTP Schönerlinde originate from WTP Tegel, 90% of this drinking water would have to consist of wastewater for salt concentrations to exceed drinking water standards. For this unlikely case, sulfate concentration in drinking water would be 248 mg/l, chloride concentration 207 mg/l, and DOC 7,7 mg/l. Using TegelSIM, the accumulation of a persistent compound added by water users in a partly closed water cycle can be simulated. It is assumed that the compound is neither eliminated in the WWTP nor during flocculation and soil passage. To reach or surpass the concentration of the water use input in drinking water, at least 62 % of drinking water would have to consist of treated wastewater (while assuming that 60% of wastewater consists of this same drinking water). Although added constantly, the concentration in drinking water would reach a maximum under stable conditions. Lake bank filtration and artificial groundwater recharge in Berlin play an important role in sustainable water management in the city due to their stable purification capacity and low energy and maintenance requirements. Berlin´s water system with its cases of unplanned, indirect wastewater reuse is limited in its (self-)purification capacity, especially when looking at persistent, polar organic compounds. A planned water reuse for Berlin would require an assessment and evaluation of concentrations of those persistent compounds in drinking water.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2001-05-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/326</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/326/ziegler_doerte.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
