<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:57Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2751">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2751</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Evaluation of environmental life cycle approaches</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Evaluierung ökologischer Lebenszyklusansätze</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Reimann, Kathy</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Environmental policies focussing on a life cycle approach of products are integrated on a political level and adopted by societal stakeholders. These policies aim to promote the idea of Life Cycle Thinking – taking into account the environmental performance of systems throughout their life cycle. In order to provide sound information on the life cycle performance of a system, reliable methods need to be applied if the strategies are meant to be realised practically. The objective of this thesis is to evaluate the suitability of different life cycle methods for applications of micro and macro level decision making in order to provide a sound basis for the principle of life cycle thinking. The methods are selected as being representative and widely used for both decision-making levels taken into account and are assessed with regard to general, methodological and technical issues of importance in their application. For this purpose a comprehensive evaluation scheme is developed consisting of ten criteria and descriptive sub-criteria and aspects. Compliance of the methods for each sub-criterion is evaluated by assessing their fulfilment with these aspects. Case studies are conducted in order to check the theoretical evaluation and provide additional insight into practical considerations. An unambiguous result can be shown for micro level applications as process-based LCA shows a generally higher compliance with the considered criteria than any other method. On the macro level the result is revealed to be more diverse, none of the methods shows clear advantages in an overall evaluation but rather different strength and foci. The case studies confirm the evaluation on both levels for the most part, adding insight on which criteria might be most case specific and how they might be affected by practical conditions. This leads to the conclusion that specific conditions of an application need to be taken into account before deciding for one of the methods; especially for macro level applications. The information given by this evaluation can provide valuable decision support for the method selection, either with regard to the methods evaluated in this thesis or as the basis for further method evaluations.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Umweltorientierte Strategien, die einen Lebenszyklusansatz von Produkten verfolgen, werden auf politischer Ebene integriert und von gesellschaftlichen Gruppen angewandt. Solche Strategien zielen auf die Förderung des Lebenszyklusgedankens ab, d.h. sie betrachten die Umweltleistung von Produkten über den gesamten Lebensweg. Um diese Strategien praktisch umzusetzen bedarf es zuverlässiger Methoden, die fundierte Informationen über die Lebenszyklusleistung von Systemen liefern können. Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, verschiedene Lebenszyklusmethoden hinsichtlich ihrer Eignung für die Bereitstellung einer gesicherten Grundlage bezüglich des Lebenszyklusprinzips für die Anwendung in Entscheidungsprozessen auf Mikro- und Makroebene zu bewerten. Die ausgewählten Methoden sind repräsentativ für die Anwendung auf den betrachteten Entscheidungsebenen und werden in Bezug auf allgemein, methodisch und technisch bedeutende Fragen ihrer Anwendung bewertet. Zu diesem Zweck wird ein umfangreiches Bewertungsschema, bestehend aus zehn Kriterien und diese beschreibenden Unterkriterien sowie Aspekten, entwickelt. Die durchgeführten Fallstudien dienen der Überprüfung der theoretischen Erkenntnisse und stellen weitergehende Informationen zu praktischen Belangen bereit. Für die Anwendung der Methoden auf der Mikroebene liefert die Bewertung ein eindeutiges Ergebnis, da die prozessbasierte Ökobilanz hier generell besser abschneidet als die anderen betrachteten Methoden. Auf der Makroebene ergibt sich ein breiter gefächertes Ergebnis, da keine der Methoden generell Vorteile in allen untersuchten Bereichen gegenüber den anderen Methoden aufweist. Die Methoden haben vielmehr unterschiedliche Stärken und Schwerpunkte. Die Fallstudien bestätigen diese Ergebnisse größtenteils und zeigen auf, welche der Kriterien besonders fall- und praxisabhängig sind. Daraus ergibt sich die Notwendigkeit, die spezifische Situation einer möglichen Anwendung in Betracht zu ziehen, bevor eine Entscheidung für eine der Methoden getroffen wird. Dies gilt insbesondere bei Anwendungen auf der Makroebene. Die Erkenntnisse aus dieser Arbeit können eine nützliche Entscheidungshilfe bei der Auswahl von Lebenszyklusmethoden sein, sowohl in Bezug auf die hier untersuchten Methoden als auch als Basis für die Bewertung weiterer Methoden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-01-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2751/reimann_kathy.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
