<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3773">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3773</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-05</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Signature of Photon Emission and Laser Stimulation for Failure Analysis of Semiconductor Devices with respect to Thin-Film Solar Cells</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die Signaturen von der Photonemission und Laser-Stimulation für die Fehleranalyse von Halbleiterbauelementen mit Bezug auf die Dünnschicht-Solarzellen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Boostandoost, Mahyar</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The objective of this study is to explore how some well-developed microelectron-ics (µE) optical characterization techniques can be transferred in photovoltaic (PV). The techniques of interest are the OBIC (Optical Beam Induced Current) and PEM (Photon Emission Microscopy). The purpose is to gain more insight into performance of PV devices based on silicon thin-film technology. In the first technique of interest - the OBIC - mostly NIR (Near Infrared) lasers are employed for performing measurement, because devices must be investigated from the backside where no metal layers is preventing the laser from reaching active components. For successful establishment of this technique, so called IR-LBIC (Infrared Light Beam Induced Current) in PV, we study important parameters relevant to characterization of the silicon based thin-film solar cells: laser wavelength, effect of local illumination and laser power. The experimental data are evaluated with the help of two-dimensional modelling and device simulation. Then, we investigate different types of thin-film solar cells by employing various specifications of the OBIC measurement, e.g. the low absorption of the applied laser at wavelength of 1064 nm in silicon materials. Following this approach, we demonstrate the ability of the IR-LBIC technique to obtain information about the sub-bandgap response of the device for detecting light scattering/trapping effects, and to study the grain boundary characteristics. The second technique, PEM, is based on the electroluminescence (EL) mechanism. This technique is established in PV as EL preferably in the forward bias in order to detect the local distribution of series resistance, to evaluate material properties like minority carrier diffusion length in the absorber layer, to deduce process induced defects and to gain insights into the quality of production processes. Whereas in electronic circuits the p-n junctions usually operate in the reverse bias to localize leakage currents or switching of logical states. However, the PV-equivalent ReBEL (Reverse Bias EL) is not well established yet. High resolution ReBEL map are also used to analyse the pre-breakdown behaviour and the defects distribution in the device. Additionally, the spectral EL and ReBEL analyses and some complementary measurements such as dark current-voltage (I-V), temperature dependence I-V characteristic, sample cross sectioning using FIB (Focused Ion Beam)/SEM (Scanning Electron Microscopy) system, as well as surface to-pography measurements using AFM (Atomic Force Microscopy) are done on the investigated solar cells. For further discussion on the NIR specific characteristics of the investigated devices, the EL and ReBEL measurements are also performed using a detector with the wavelength sensitivity extended in the NIR region (In-GaAs detector) giving particular advantages over capacity of Si-CCD camera. This perspective, based on the study objective and presented results, enables us to develop some new PV applications by applying the optical characterization tech-niques from the world of µE devices to silicon based thin-film solar cells. We ef-fectively employ the higher accuracy of these techniques to get more quantitative evaluations. Therefore, use of microelectronic failure analysis tools in PV tech-nology has been investigated and gives prominent outcome in practical adapting relevant techniques. Additionally, a better understanding of the challenges associ-ated with transferring these techniques into PV helps us to extend our expertise in microelectronic failure analysis.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit befasst sich mit der Übertragung hoch entwickelter optischer Charakterisierungsverfahren aus der Fehleranalyse von mikroelektronischen Bauelementen in die Photovoltaik (PV). Speziell werden hier die Methoden des optisch induzierten Stromes (OBIC) sowie die Photonemissionsmikroskopie (PEM) angewendet. Ziel ist ein höheres Verständnis in der Leistungsanalyse von Bauelementen der PV mit dem Fokus auf siliziumbasierten Dünnschichttechnologien. Gegenwärtig wird OBIC, die erste genannte Technik, im Bereich der mikroelekt-ronischen Bauelemente fast ausschließlich im nahen Infrarot (NIR) betrieben, dadurch kann bei der notwendigen Rückseitenanalyse das Siliziumsubstrat mög-lichst verlustfrei durchstrahlt werden. Für die erfolgreiche Übertragung dieser auch IR-LBIC (Infrared Light Beam Induced Current) genannten Technik in die PV-Analyse siliziumbasierter Dünnschicht-Solarzellen, wird in dieser Arbeit aus-führlich der Einfluss der relevanten Messparameter wie z.B. der Laserwellenlänge, der lokalen Beleuchtung und der Laserleistung untersucht. Die experimentel-len Ergebnisse werden unter Einbeziehung von unterstützenden optoelektronischen Modellrechnungen diskutiert. Es wird gezeigt, dass sich gerade die spezifischen Eigenheiten des OBIC Messverfahrens, wie z.B. die geringe Absorption des NIR-Lichtes im Si-Material, für die Charakterisierung der Dünnschicht-Solarzellen vorteilhaft nutzen lassen, um Einsichten in sub-bandgap Eigenschaften des Absorbermaterials, die Charakteristik von Korngrenzenregionen und lokalen Lichteinfangeffekten zu erhalten. Das zweite zentrale Verfahren, das in dieser Arbeit betrachtet wird, ist die PEM. Dieses Verfahren wird bereits in der PV-Analyse als Elektrolumineszenz (EL) vorwiegend im Durchlassbereich eines pn-Überganges angewendet, um die lokalen Serienwiderstände oder die Diffusionslänge der Minoritätsladungsträger in der Absorberschicht zu erfassen, sowie zur Identifizierung von beim Herstellungsprozess der Solarzellen induzierten Defekten. Während PEM im Bereich der elektro-nischen Schaltungen eher im Sperrbereich angewendet wird, um Leckströme oder logische Schaltvorgänge zu identifizieren, ist das PV-Äquivalent ReBEL (Reverse Bias EL) noch nicht etabliert. In dieser Arbeit werden die hochaufgelösten ReBEL Bilder verwendet, um die Defektverteilung und das Vordurchbruch-Verhalten in den PV-Bauelementen zu untersuchen. In diese Analyse einbezogen werden auch die Ergebnisse spektral aufgelöster PEM-Messungen sowie ergänzender Verfahren wie die Strom-Spannung (I-V)- Messung (auch temperaturabhängig), die Mikrostrukturuntersuchungen unter Verwendung eines Rasterelektronenmikroskopie (SEM)/Focused Ion Beam (FIB)-Gerätes und die Untersuchungen zur Oberflächentopographie mittels Rasterkraftmikroskopie (AFM). Für eine verbesserte Empfindlichkeit der spektral aufgelösten EL-Messungen im NIR-Bereich wird zusätzlich ein InGaAs-Detektor eingesetzt, dessen Vorteile im Vergleich zur üblichen Si-CCD Kamera diskutiert werden. Insgesamt ergeben sich aus den präsentierten Ergebnissen eine Reihe neuer An-wendungen von optischen Charakterisierungsmethoden aus der Mikroelektronik-Welt für siliziumbasierte Dünnschicht-PV. Die höhere Messgenauigkeit ermöglicht präzisere quantitative Auswertungen. Darüber hinaus hat die grundlegende Analyse dieser Methoden bei der Übertragung nicht nur zu einem besseren Verständnis in der PV beigetragen, sondern umgekehrt auch das Know-How in der Fehleranalyse der mikroelektronischen Bauelemente gestärkt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-06-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3773</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40463</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40463</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3773/boostandoost_mahyar.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
