<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:55Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3600">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3600</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Form  Finding for Cable-Stayed and Extradosed Bridges</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Formfindung für Schrägseilbrücken und Extradosed Brücken</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>El Shenawy, El Araby</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The form finding for cable supported structures (roof structures or bridge structures) means simply the definition of the cable forces under dead load. The form finding method for conventional cable-stayed bridges with concrete-only or steel-only deck cross sections is well established. In this research work the common methods used for the determination of the stay cable forces under dead load will be discussed. It will be shown that these methods will not lead to the desired stay cable forces or the desired bridge alignment in case of cable-stayed bridges with composite decks. A new method will be presented for the form finding of cable-stayed bridges with composite (steel/concrete) or (concrete/concrete) deck cross sections if the composite section is planned to be constructed in two stages. For the establishment of the new method for the form finding of cable-stayed bridges with composite decks, the following effects will be investigated: - The ratio between the moment of inertia of the first part of the composite section and the total moment of inertia of the composite section and the vertical shift between the center of gravity of the first part of the composite section and the center of gravity of the total composite section. - The time dependent forces due to creep and shrinkage. Further, the study carried out for the form finding of conventional cable-stayed bridges will be extended to additionally present a new method for the form finding of extradosed bridges. The extradosed bridges emerged in the last two decades as a promising structural system to effectively and economically bridge spans ranging between 100 and 200 m. For such spans the prestressed box girder bridges require deep and heavy deck cross section. Further, conventional cable-stayed bridges with spans less than 200m appear to be not economical. The researches and the survey of the extradosed bridges built so far, indicate that there is still a need to establish a consistent method for the definition of the stay cable forces under dead load. The method established in this research work for this purpose, includes also solutions to determine and handle the required internal and/or external prestressing within the deck cross section. The proposed method for the form finding of the extradosed bridges is suitable for use for bridges with concrete, steel or composite sections. For extradosed bridges with a concrete deck, a combination of the stay cable forces and the prestressing forces inside the deck section may be targeted to eliminate the bending moment along the entire length of the deck under dead load.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Formfindung für Seilkonstruktionen (Dachkonstruktionen oder Brückenbauwerke) bedeutet im vereinfachten Sinne die Definition der Seilkräfte für das Tragwerk unter Eigengewicht. Die gängigen Formfindungsverfahren für konventionelle Schrägseilbrücken mit Fahrbahnüberbauten aus Beton oder Stahl haben sich bereits etabliert. Die üblichen Methoden, die zur Ermittlung der Seilkräfte unter Eigengewicht verwendet werden, werden in dieser Forschungsarbeit diskutiert. Es wird gezeigt, dass für Brücken aus Verbundquerschnitten, diese Methoden weder zu den gewünschten Seilkräften noch zu der gewünschten Brückengeometrie führen. Für Schrägseilbrücken aus Verbundquerschnitten, die in zwei Bauabschnitten (BA) hergestellt werden, wird in dieser Forschungsarbeit ein neues Verfahren für die Berechnung der Seilkräfte unter Eigengewicht vorgestellt. Für diese neue Methode werden die folgenden Faktoren untersucht: - Das Verhältnis zwischen dem Trägheitsmoment des Teilquerschnitts (erster BA) und dem Trägheitsmoment des Gesamtquerschnitts (zweiter BA) und der vertikale Abstand zwischen dem Schwerpunkt des Teilquerschnitts (erster BA) und dem Schwerpunkt des Gesamtquerschnitts (zweiter BA). - Die Zeitabhängigen Kräfte infolge Kriechen und Schwinden. In dieser Arbeit wird auch eine neue Methode zur Formfindung von Extradosed Brücken vorgestellt. Die Extradosed Brücken entstanden in den letzten zwei Jahrzehnten als ein effektives und wirtschaftliches Brückentragwerk für Spannweiten zwischen 100 und 200 m. Für solche Spannweiten erfordern die vorgespannten Hohlkastenbrücken sehr große Überbauhöhen. Darüber hinaus scheinen die konventionellen Schrägseilbrücken mit Spannweiten weniger als 200 m unwirtschaftlich zu sein. Die Forschungen und die Untersuchungen der bisher gebauten Extradosed Brücken zeigen, dass eine konsistente Methode zur Definition der Seilkräfte unter Eigengewicht noch nicht vorhanden ist. Die zu diesem Zweck in dieser Arbeit vorgestellte Methode eignet sich für Überbauten aus Beton-, Stahl- und Verbundquerschnitten. Außerdem werden Methoden zur Bestimmung der erforderlichen internen und externen Vorspannung empfohlen. Für Extradosed Brücken mit Fahrbahnüberbauten aus Beton können die Biegemomente unter Eigengewicht entlang der gesamten Brückenlänge, durch das aufeinander abstimmen der Seilkräfte und der Vorspannkräfte im Überbau eliminiert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-01-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3600</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38324</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38324</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3600/elshenawy_elaraby.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
