<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2293">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2293</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Material science examination on pineapple fruit puree and raw material</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Material wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen vom Ananas Puree und Rohmaterialen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Uan-On, Tanat</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Pineapple (Ananas comosus (L.) Merr.) is the one of importance commercial topical fruit. It grows on several countries, such as Thailand, Philippines and South America. The pineapple puree is one of primary product in many industries, such as bakery industry, which uses it as fruit filling. Normally pineapple puree is preserved as pineapple puree can or pineapple puree frozen. However, pineapple puree has a problem during storage or after blending. Pineapple puree is not stable structure and will be separated into serum and fiber during storage. The aim of this work was to increase the stability of pineapple puree structure by using selected gums as stabilize. The gums used in this study such as pectin, locust bean gum, guar gum, xanthan gum. Results have shown that the quality of pineapple fruit was depending on the level of maturity. Pineapple was softer and color of pulp was darker when level of maturity increased. The properties of gums solution were investigated before added to pineapple puree by using the rheological methods, such as shear rate examination and oscillation test. In the case of pectin, the effect of pectin type (citrus and apple pectin), pectin concentration, DE, concentration of added Ca-ion on rheological properties were investigated. Results showed that citrus pectin performed higher stability and viscosity than apple pectin. High-DE exhibited good stability, but the viscosity was not high. Ca-ion adding had the great impact on low-DE pectin. In addition, LBG, guar and xanthan gum, were studies to determine the effect of concentration and temperature on rheological properties of gums solution. Results showed that stability and viscosity of LBG and guar gum was increased with increasing the gum concentration. The temperature effect on rheological properties of LBG and guar gum was at higher gum concentration distinctive. Xanthan gum also showed the increased stability and viscosity with concentration. However, temperature didn’t have impact on xanthan gum compared to LBG and guar gum. Mixture of LBG and xanthan gum indicated Synergistic effect on stability of gum solution. The effect of adding gums in pineapple pure on rheological properties such as stability and viscosity was carried out using different gums and at different gum and sugar concentration. Application of amidated pectin resulted better stability and viscosity than normal pectin. In addition, the stability and viscosity of puree was increased with increasing of pectin concentration. Adding sugar in puree resulted decreasing the stability, but increased the viscosity of puree. The stability of pineapple puree containing LBG was decreased rapidly after adding 0.2 to 0.8 % gum concentration. After adding gum more than 1 % the stability of pineapple puree remains unchanged. Temperature effect on stability of pineapple puree containing LBG was particularly at higher gum concentration distinctive. The stability of pineapple puree containing guar gum resulted decreasing with increasing of gum concentration, but viscosity increased. The temperature has at higher concentration of gum more effect on stability of pineapple than at low gum concentration. The stability and viscosity of pineapple puree containing xanthan gum was increased with increasing of xanthan concentration. In contrast, temperature don’t show any distinct effect on stability of pineapple puree containing xanthan Thus, temperature resistance of pineapple puree supplemented with xanthan gum was better than other gum. Synergistic of xanthan and guar gum on the stability and viscosity was better than xanthan and LBG. In conclusion, xanthan gum performed was suitable stabilizer for pineapple puree, but viscosity was insufficient. Thus, the mixture of xanthan gum and guar gum was the best choice in term of high stability and very good viscosity of pineapple puree.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Dem Ananas (Ananas comosus (L.) Merr) kommt unter den kommerziellen, tropischen Früchten eine große Bedeutung zu. Normalerweise wird Ananaspüree als Sterilkonserve in Dosen oder durch als Gefrierkonserviert. Ein Frischeprodukt in Pureeform ist nicht bekannt. Allerdings treten Probleme während der Lagerung oder dem Mischen auf. Die mangelnde Stabilität führt zu einer Trennung in Fasern und Serum. Das Ziel dieser Arbeit war es, die Stabilität des Ananaspürees durch Verwendung verschiedener Hydrokolloide wie Pektin, Johannesbrotkernmehl, Guarkernmehl und Xanthan zu verbessern. Die Ergebnisse haben gezeigt, dass die Qualität des Ananasproduktes vom Reifegrad abhängig ist. Mit zunehmendem Reifegrad wurde die Farbe des Zellstoffes dunkler und die Ananas war weicher. Im Fall des Pektin einsatzes zur Pureeherstellung wurden die Parameter Pektintyp (Zitrus und Apfel), Pektinkonzentration, Veresterungsgrad und Konzentration an zugesetzten Calciumionen betrachtet. Die Ergebnisse haben gezeigt, dass Zitruspektin eine höhere Stabilität und Viskosität aufweist als Apfelpektin. Ein hoher Veresterungsgrad resultierte in einer guten Stabilität allerdings war die resultierende Viskosität nicht sehr hoch. Die Zugabe von Calciumionen hatte den größten Effekt auf Pektin mit niedrigem Veresterungsgrad. Zusätzlich wurde für Johannesbrotkernmehl, Guarkernmehl und Xanthan der Effekt der Konzentration und der Temperatur auf die rheologischen Eigenschaften der Hydrokolloidlösungen untersucht. Die Stabilität und Viskosität des Johannesbrotkernmehls und des Guarkernmehls stieg mit steigender Konzentration. Der Temperatureffekt auf die rheologischen Eigenschaften war signifikant für höhere Hydrokolloidkonzentrationen im Fall des Johannesbrotkernmehls und Guarkernmehl. Xanthan zeigte das gleiche Verhalten bezüglich der Viskosität und Stabilität mit steigender Konzentration. Allerdings hatte die Temperatur keinen signifikanten Effekt auf die rheologischen Eigenschaften. Eine Mischung aus Johannesbrotkernmehl und Xanthan induziert einen synergistischen Effekt bezüglich der Stabilität der Hydrokolloidlösung. Der Effekt der zugesetzten Hydrokollide auf die rheologischen Eigenschaften wie Viskosität und Stabilität des Ananaspürees wurde unter Verwendung verschiedener Hydrokolloide, sowie Hydrokolloid- und Zuckerkonzentration untersucht. Die Verwendung von amidiertem Pektin führte zu einer besseren Stabilität und Viskosität als Pektin. Zusätzlich erhöhten sich die Stabilität und Viskosität von Ananaspüree mit steigender Pektinkonzentration. Der Zusatz von Zucker zum Püree führte zu einer reduzierten Stabilität aber zu einer erhöhten Viskosität. Die Stabilität des Pürees unter Zusatz von 0,2 - 0,8 % Johannesbrotkernmehl nahm rapide ab, bis sich ein konstanter Stabilitätslevel ab einer Konzentration von 1 % einstellte. Der Temperatureffekt auf die Stabilität war signifikant für höhere Konzentrationen von Johannesbrotkernmehl. Die Stabilität von Ananaspüree nahm ab mit steigender Konzentration von Guarkernmehl. Wohingegen die Viskosität anstieg. Die Temperatur hatte einen größeren Einfluss auf die Stabilität des Pürees je höher die Konzentration des Guarkernmehls war. Die Stabilität und die Viskosität von Ananaspüree unter Zusatz von Xanthan nahmen mit steigender Konzentration zu. Die Temperatur hatte keinen signifikanten Einfluss auf Stabilität und Viskosität. Als Schlussfolgerung kann die Temperaturbeständigkeit/stabilität des Ananaspürees unter Zusatz von Xanthan als vorteilhaft gegenüber dem Zusatz anderer Hydrokolloide bewertet werden. Ein synergistischer Effekt von Xanthan und Guarkernmehl bezüglich einer besseren Stabilität und Viskosität war besser als bei der Mischung von Xanthan und Johannesbrotkernmehl. Zusammenfassend kann Xanthan als geeigneter Stabilisator für Ananaspüree bewertet werden. Nachteilig muss allerdings der nicht ausreichende Viskositätslevel angemerkt werden. Daher muss in Bezug auf eine hohe Stabilität und Viskositätslevel dies Mischung aus Xanthan und Guarkernmehl im Verhältnis 25:75 einer 1 prozentigen Lösung favorisiert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-11-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2293</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-24074</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-24074</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2293/original_uan_on_tanat.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2293/uan_on_tanat.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
