<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:23Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2616">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2616</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Environmentally orientated research on solid household waste management in Khanty-Mansiysk Autonomous Okrug ‚Äì Ugra</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Umweltorientierte Untersuchungen des Abfallwirtschaftssystems in Khanty-Mansiysk Autonome Region - Ugra</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kaazke, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">A continuous rise in waste volume produced has been recorded in the Russian Federation for several years. Therefore, the conventional methods of waste disposal have reached their limits. Additionally, there are gaps in the Russian legislation that complicate the development of integrated waste management concepts. Based on agreements between the European Union and the Russian Federation regarding environmental protection measures in the Russian Federation, the question has arisen whether decision support tools developed within the European framework programme are transferable to Russia. Decision support tools with an international approach have been developed in the European framework program based on co-operation between different states. This international approach was a precondition in the research proposal of the dissertation. It was assumed that such tools are more likely transferable to Siberian conditions. Consequently, several tools useable for the development of integrated waste management concepts were researched. Subsequently, their transferability to the Khanty-Mansiysk Autonomous Region ‚Äì Ugra (research area) was tested. The point of departure was research which demonstrated that the following work steps and tools play an essential role for the development of an integrated waste management concept: Guideline for the development of integrated waste management concepts: - ‚ÄúPreparing a waste management plan. A methodological guidance note‚Ä? by the European Topic Centre on Waste and Material Flows and commissioned by the European Commission DG Environment (EC, 2003) Work steps for the development of integrated waste management concepts: - Waste analysis: ‚ÄúMethodology for the Analysis of Solid Waste (SWA-Tool)‚Ä? by the European Commission (EC, 2004) - Public participation: ‚ÄúToolkit. Social Assessment and Public Participation in Municipal Solid Waste Management‚Ä? by The World Bank (2004). (This is an exception as the research demonstrated that there is no developed tool for a public participation within the European framework program.) - Waste prognosis as well as life cycle assessment: ‚ÄúThe use of life cycle assessment tool for the development of integrated waste management strategies for cities and region with rapid growing economies (LCA-IWM)‚Ä? in the 5th EU framework (Project Coordinator TU Darmstadt, 2005) A strength-weakness analysis of all tools in the research area in Siberia expressed that almost all tools are transferable with modifications. The LCA is not transferable. Recommendations for essential modifications are given in order to guarantee an optimal use at the local level in Siberia. The research also emphasises that these tools are used separately at the moment and hardly any correlations are recognisable. However, only interlinking these tools will lead to an integrated waste management concept. Therefore, the aim is to make be a better correlation among these tools in order to optimally develop an integrated waste management concept and to use synergy effects.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der Russischen F√∂rderation ist seit einigen Jahren ein kontinuierlicher Anstieg der Abfallmengen zu verzeichnen. Die herk√∂mmlichen Methoden der Abfallentsorgung sto√üen daher an ihre Grenzen. Dar√ºber hinaus existieren gesetzliche Unsicherheiten und erschweren die Entwicklung eines integrierten Abfallwirtschaftskonzeptes. Basierend auf Abkommen zwischen der Europ√§ischen Union und der Russischen F√∂rderation wurde hinsichtlich des Umweltschutzes, vor allem in der Russischen F√∂rderation, die Frage aufgeworfen, ob Instrumente, die im Europ√§ischen Rahmenforschungsprogramm entwickelt worden sind, auf die Russische F√∂rderation √ºbertragbar seien. Innerhalb des Rahmenforschungsprogramms der Europ√§ischen Union werden, durch die Zusammenarbeit von Staaten in unterschiedlichen Projekten, Instrumente mit internationalem Ansatz entwickelt. Dieser internationale Ansatz war Grundbedingung im Forschungsansatz der Doktorarbeit, da angenommen wurde, dass solche Instrumente am ehesten auf die Konditionen in Sibirien anwendbar seien. Deshalb wurden einige Instrumente, die bei der Entwicklung von Abfallwirtschaftskonzepten Anwendung finden, ausgesucht und anschlie√üend auf ihre √úbertragbarkeit in die Region Khanty-Mansiysk Autonome Region ‚Äì Ugra, Westsibirien (Untersuchungsgebiet) √ºberpr√ºft. Ausgangspunkt der Untersuchungen war eine Recherche und es zeigte sich, dass folgende Arbeitsschritte und Instrumente eine essentielle Rolle in der Entwicklung eines Abfallwirtschaftskonzeptes spielen und daher ber√ºcksichtigt wurden: Richtlinie zur Entwicklung eines Abfallwirtschaftskonzeptes: - ‚ÄúPreparing a waste management plan. A methodological guidance note‚Ä? by the European Topic Centre on Waste and Material Flows and commissioned by the European Commission DG Environment (EC, 2003) Arbeitsschritte und Instrumente f√ºr die Entwicklung eines Abfallwirtschaftskonzeptes: - Abfallanalyse: ‚ÄúMethodology for the Analysis of Solid Waste (SWA-Tool)‚Ä? by the European Commission (EC, 2004) - Partizipation der lokalen Bev√∂lkerung: ‚ÄúToolkit. Social Assessment and Public Participation in Municipal Solid Waste Management ‚Ä? by The World Bank (2004) (Das ist eine Ausnahme, da die Recherche aufzeigte, dass innerhalb des Rahmenforschungsprogramms kein Instrument zur Partizipation der lokalen Bev√∂lkerung bisher erarbeitet wurde.) - Prognose von Abfallmengen und -zusammensetzung sowie √ñkobilanzierung: ‚ÄúThe use of life cycle assessment tool for the development of integrated waste management strategies for cities and region with rapid growing economies (LCA-IWM)‚Ä? in the 5th EU framework (Project Coordinator TU Darmstadt, 2005) Eine St√§rken-Schw√§chen-Analyse der Instrumente am Fallbeispiel der genannten sibirischen Region zeigte auf, dass mit Ausnahme der √ñkobilanzierung- alle Instrumente mit Modifikationen √ºbertragbar sind. Empfehlungen f√ºr notwendige Ver√§nderungen wurden ausgesprochen, um einen optimalen Einsatz auf lokaler Ebene, spezielle im sibirischen Raum, zu erm√∂glichen. Deutlich wurde auch, dass diese Instrumente derzeit unabh√§ngig voneinander angewandt werden und kaum Bezugspunkte zwischen ihnen zu finden sind, obwohl nur ein Zusammenwirken zu einem integrierten Abfallwirtschaftskonzept f√ºhren. Ziel muss es sein, diese Instrumente zuk√ºnftig besser aufeinander abzustimmen, um auf bestm√∂glicher Art und Weise ein integriertes Abfallwirtschaftskonzept zu entwickeln sowie Synergieeffekte zu nutzen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-09-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2616</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27399</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27399</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>---</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2616/Appendix-Chapter-3-Maps_Appendix-Chapter-4.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2616/kaazke_julia.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
