<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:03Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2775">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2775</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Experimental Investigation on Gas Separation Using Porous Membranes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Experimentelle Untersuchungen von poroesen Membranen auf Eignung zur Gastrennung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zhang, Weiqi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Membranes have been long utilized in industry for separation of gas mixtures\cite{Andrzej2008}. Thanks to their chemical, physical, and thermodynamic stability, as well as for their high durability at elevated temperatures and high permeation flux, ceramic membranes have become especially popular in the field. Cement is looked at as a valid alternative for the future, as in addition to being stable, it would bring the advantage of lower costs and longer lifespan. Research is still necessary to access the performance and reliability of cement membranes and the present thesis wants to contribute to this topic. More specifically, purpose of this work was to investigate the influence of gas molecules properties on material transport, and to explore the influence of operating conditions and membrane composition on separation efficiency. To this aim, a series of experiments were performed. In more detail, an experimental setup was manufactured and tested. Fifty types of membranes were produced. Several membrane cells were designed into a module with counter current flow pattern, where gases on two sides of the membrane flow in contrary directions. Pure H2, CO2, CO, CH4, two-component gas (49.8% H2 and 50.2% CO2), and five-component gas (13% H2, 16% CO, 13% CO2, 53% N2, and 5% CH4) were used as feed gases, while N$_2$ and CO were used as sweeping gases. A new method was introduced to calibrate the automatic injection of sample gases into gas chromatography. Experiments were conducted from high to low temperatures. Chromatograms obtained by GC could then be used to determine the amount of each component in both permeate and retentate gas. New calibration formulas, which offer more accurate quantification methods, are also presented in this work. On this base, permeation rate and efficiency of gas separation could be calculated and the influence of operating condition and membrane shape and composition could be studied. Main results of this work cement are: the influence of all the above parameters is collected, the best conditions and membrane type are found, cementitious material has the ability to separate gas mixtures, and new designs considering purification of the product gases are provided.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In den letzten Jahrzehnten hat die Anwendung der membranbasierten Gastrennung im Bereich der „clean technology“ viel Aufmerksamkeit auf sich gezogen. Einige anorganische Membranen, insbesondere keramische Membranen sind dank ihrer chemischen, physikalischen, thermodynamischen und thermischen Stabilität sowie ihrer hohen Durchflussrate bekannt geworden. Zement ist ein anorganisches Material, das die Festigkeiten besitzt und zudem die Vorteile niedriger Kosten und langer Lebensdauer bietet. Daher hat es als Membranmaterial große Zukunft. Das Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, den Einfluss der Gaseigenschaften auf den Transport in porösen Feststoffen sowie die Auswirkung der Betriebsparameter und Membraneigenschaften auf die Trennwirkung zu untersuchen. Fünfzig unterschiedliche Membranen wurden hergestellt, mehrere Membranreaktoren entworfen und als einstufige Module im Gegenstromverfahren betrieben. Ein Versuchsstand wurde aufgebaut, getestet und fortlaufend verbessert. Als Feedgase kamen H2, CO2, CO, CH4 sowie ein Zweikomponentengemisch ( 49.8 % H2 and 50.2 % CO2) und ein Fünfkomponentengemisch (13 % H2, 16 % CO, 13 % CO2, 53 % N2, and 5 % CH4) zum Einsatz. Als Spülgase wurden N2 und CO genutzt. Die Trennwirkung der Membranen wurde bei unterschiedlichen Temperaturen untersucht, wobei für jede Temperatur vier Messwerte zur Berechnung des Mittelwerts aufgenommen wurden. Die Volumenanteile der einzelnen Komponenten in Retentat und Permeat wurden mit Hilfe eines Gaschromatographen ermittelt und in Molanteile umgerechnet, wobei Kalibriergase zur Ermittlung der Referenzwerte verwendet wurden. Permeationsraten und Trennfaktoren wurden berechnet und einander gegenübergestellt. Die neuen in dieser Arbeit präsentierten Kalibrierformeln ermöglichen eine genaue Quantifizierung, da die Einflüsse der unterschiedlichen Betriebsparameter darin zusammengefasst werden. Die Trennfaktoren bei Raumtemperatur wurden für alle scheibenförmigen Membranen berechnet. Für ausgewählte Membranen wurden weitere Kennwerte berechnet, um die Leistungsfähigkeit zu charakterisieren. Konzepte zur Reinigung der Produktgase wurden ebenfalls näher ausgeführt. Neben der Bereitstellung von Messdaten in diesem Forschungsfeld konnte die Permeabilität der Zementmembranen mit dieser Arbeit experimentell bestätigt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2775</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29200</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29200</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-938720-74-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2775/zhang_weiqi.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
