<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2133">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2133</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">DiaTrans – A Multi-Component Model for Density-Driven Flow, Transport and Biogeochemical Reaction Processes in the Subsurface</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">DiaTrans – Ein Mehrkomponenten-Modell für dichtegetriebene Strömungs-, Transport- und biogeochemische Reaktionsprozesse im Untergrund</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schankat, Mirko</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The investigation of the transition zone between subsurface sediments and the water column, in addition to an enhanced understanding of the underlying processes, becomes more and more important when dealing with ecological questions not only in coastal areas. Therefore, DiaTrans (diagenetic transport), a one-phase/multi-component model to simulate multi-dimensional fully coupled density-driven flow, transport and biogeochemical reaction processes in the subsurface underlying a seawater column, including bioturbation and bioirrigation, is presented. The components include water and an arbitrary number of dissolved constituents such as chloride, methane, sulphate or oxygen. The governing equations are discretized using a Finite-Volume-Method (FVM) on two-dimensional rectangular structured grids in an object-oriented framework. A fully-upwinding technique is employed for the advective fluxes. The sparse and non-symmetric system of highly non-linear equations is solved, utilizing the Newton-Raphson method with an inner linear preconditioned BiCGSTAB solver. This implicit fully-coupled formulation of physical and biogeochemical processes, which has certain advantages, is a new approach not only in near-shore sediments, as generally decoupled methods are employed. The model accounts for different domain sizes and grid resolutions, unsteady conditions to simulate tidal cycles and variable physical parameters such as permeabilities and porosities which are important to cope with lateral heterogeneities. Typical benchmark tests have been carried out to verify DiaTrans' capability to model flow, transport and reaction processes in the subsurface. These include the Henry problem and the salt dome problem for density-driven flow and transport as well as an example for standard diagenetic biogeochemical reaction processes. As natural test cases for the numerical modeling different application examples are presented. First, the physical processes at sand boils, which account for submarine groundwater discharges at a site in the Wadden Sea of Cuxhaven, North Sea, Germany are investigated and the simulation results are compared to field measurements which have been carried out by the Alfred Wegener Institute for Polar and Marine Research (AWI), Bremerhaven, Germany. Second, reaction influenced methane concentration profiles at so-called vent and partial vent sites in Eckernförde Bay, Baltic Sea, Germany are simulated with a special focus on the effects of bioturbation and bioirrigation. For both applications, rather good matches are observed between model results and field data. The last application example deals with qualitative statements about the interaction processes at the sediment-water interface where the influence of surface water velocities on the fate of methane in the water column is investigated, considering biogeochemical reaction processes such as methane re-oxidation by oxygen and sulfate. Because of its object-oriented nature, the model can easily be extended to additional physical processes, more complex biogeochemical reaction processes or enhanced numerics in the future. DiaTrans is considered as a sophisticated model for multi-dimensional density-driven flow, transport and biogeochemical reaction processes in porous media for both small and larger scale problems.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der Schwerpunkt der Arbeit liegt in der Verbesserung des Prozessverständnisses für den Interaktionsbereich Untergrund und freier Wassersäule und darauf aufbauend in einer verbesserten Quantifizierung von Stoffflüssen, welche beispielsweise für ökologische Fragestellungen in Küstengebieten erforderlich ist. Dazu wurde DiaTrans (diagenetic transport), ein mehrdimensionales, voll gekoppeltes Ein-Phasen/Mehr-Komponenten-Modell zur Simulation von dichtegetriebenen Strömungs-, Transport- und biogeochemischen Reaktionsprozessen im Untergrund, entwickelt. Auch typische küstennahe Prozesse wie Bioturbation und Bioirrigation werden darin explizit berücksichtigt. Neben der Hauptkomponente Wasser kann eine beliebige Anzahl gelöster Substanzen, wie z. B. Chlorid, Sulfat, Methan oder Sauerstoff, betrachtet werden. Mit Hilfe eines objektorientierten Ansatzes werden die Bilanzgleichungen mit einer Finiten-Volumen Methode (FVM) auf zweidimensionalen strukturierten Rechteckgittern diskretisiert, wobei eine Fully-Upwind-Methode für die advektiven Flussterme verwendet wird. Das daraus resultierende unsymmetrische System aus stark nichtlinearen Gleichungen wird mit einem Newton-Raphson Verfahren mit innerem linearen BiCGSTAB-Gleichungslöser berechnet. Diese implizite und vollständige Kopplung von Strömungs-, Transport- und Reaktionsprozessen stellt einen neuen Ansatz auf diesem Gebiet der Forschung dar. Das Modell berücksichtigt neben verschiedenen Gebietsgrößen und Netzauflösungen auch instationäre Bedingungen zur Simulation von Tidezyklen. Physikalische Parameter wie Durchlässigkeiten und Porositäten sind frei wählbar, um auch lokale Heterogenitäten berücksichtigen zu können. Um die Leistungsfähigkeit von DiaTrans auf dem Gebiet der dichtegetriebenen Strömungs-, Transport- und Reaktionssimulation zu gewährleisten, wurde das Modell mit typischen Benchmark-Tests verifiziert. Die vielfältigen Anwendungsmöglichkeiten des Modells werden anhand von praxisrelevanten Fragestellungen aufgezeigt. Zum einen werden die physikalischen Prozesse an submarinen Grundwasseraustrittsstellen im Sahlenburger Watt, Nordsee, untersucht und die Simulationsergebnisse mit Feldmessungen des Alfred-Wegener-Instituts für Polar und Meeresforschung (AWI) verglichen. Zum anderen wird der Einfluss der Reaktionskinetik auf Methankonzentrationsprofile an submarinen Grundwasseraustrittsstellen in der Ostsee simuliert, wobei ein Hauptaugenmerk auf dem Einfluss der Bioturbation und Bioirrigation liegt. Für beide Anwendungsbeispiele konnten gute Übereinstimmungen zwischen Simulation und Naturmessungen erzielt werden. Darüber hinaus können mit DiaTrans qualitative Aussagen über die Vermischungsprozesse von gelösten Substanzen im Interaktionsbereich von Untergrund und freier Wassersäule getroffen werden. Dieser Ansatz wird anhand von Methan, mit expliziter Berücksichtigung der Oxidationsprozesse durch Sauerstoff und Sulfat, erläutert. Durch seine objektorientierte Struktur kann DiaTrans in der Zukunft um weitere physikalische Prozesse, komplexere Reaktionsprozesse oder um numerische Verfahren in einfacher Weise erweitert werden. DiaTrans genügt hohen Ansprüchen auf dem Gebiet der Simulation von dichtegetriebenen Strömungs-, Transport und Reaktionsprozessen in Sedimenten und porösen Medien sowohl auf kleinen als auch auf größeren räumlichen Skalen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-05-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2133</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22399</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22399</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2133/original_schankat_mirko_quellen.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2133/schankat_mirko.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
