<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:12Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1708">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1708</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">On the acoustics of small partially open enclosures densely packed with active and passive installations</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Über die Akustik in kleinen, teilweise geöffneten Räumen, dicht gefüllt mit aktiven und passiven Einbauten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Prager, Jens</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In the study presented different aspects are investigated of air borne sound propagation inside a partially open enclosure densely packed with active and passive installations. Primarily the work is aimed at predicting the sound field at the interfaces of the enclosure to the adjacent fluid space. The prediction procedure is subdivided into the description of the sound sources inside the enclosure and the prediction of the transfer impedance linking the sound sources to the sound field at the interface to the adjacent fluid. Depending on the relation between wavelength and the geometrical dimension of the system the sound field structure inside the enclosure is found to vary markedly with frequency. Common analysis tools are adapted for their applicability in the given context. The Statistical Energy Analysis (SEA), which is assumed to be applicable in the high frequency region, is supplemented by an approach including the influence of source and receiver positions close to boundaries or field discontinuities. Therefore a correction is integrated into the SEA considering the first order reflections by including the corresponding image sources. From testing the applicability of common analysis tools it is shown a lack of appropriate analysis tools for the intermediate frequency range, which also provide information about the reliability of the analysis results. Two novel approaches are presented to predict the sound field in a frequency region of low modal density. The approaches are based on probabilistic descriptions of the system geometry, which appear promising with regard to the engineering practice. It is shown that the acoustical behaviour can be extracted by either modelling the remaining free fluid space or the installations inside the enclosure. Although the validity limitations of the approaches presented are different, both approaches produce similar results in the considered frequency region. The validity and applicability of the probabilistic approaches is demonstrated by comparing the results with those from a numerical calculation. Strategies are presented for integrating the sound sources into the modelling. For the coupling between source characterisation and sound propagation it is suggested to use a decomposition of complex shaped sound sources into multipoles of different order. The decomposition in terms of spherical Nearfield Holography (NAH), however, is found to be limited to simple source geometries. For complex shaped sound sources, not fulfilling the validity conditions of the Rayleigh hypothesis a method using a truncated series of Gegenbauer polynomials is proposed to overcome the problems arising from singularities in the sound field. The validity of the proposed approaches, methods and simplifications is verified by comparing the results with those of dedicated experiments.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Arbeit beschreibt die Untersuchungen verschiedener Aspekte der Luftschallausbreitung in kleinen, teilweise offenen Hohlräumen, die mit aktiven und passiven Einbauten gefüllt sind. Die Untersuchungen werden unterteilt in die Beschreibung der Schallquellen im Hohlraum einerseits und die Vorhersage der Transferimpedanz als Bindeglied zwischen den Quellen und den Feldgrößen an den Schnittstellen zur Umgebung andererseits. Es ist zu berücksichtigen, dass die Struktur des Schallfeldes im Hohlraum stark abhängig ist vom Verhältnis zwischen der Wellenlänge des Luftschalls und den Abmessungen des betrachteten Systems. Drei ausgeprägte Frequenzbereiche werden unterschieden, für die die bekannten Vorhersagemethoden angepasst bzw. neuartige Modellierungsansätze entwickelt werden. Die statistische Energieanalyse (SEA), die im Bereich hoher Frequenzen geeignete Methoden liefert, wird durch einen Korrekturterm ergänzt, der Quell- und Empfängerpositionen in der Nähe der Raumbegrenzungen berücksichtigt. Dieser Korrekturterm berücksichtigt die ersten Reflexionen an den Begrenzungswänden mit Hilfe von Spiegelschallquellen. Für den Bereich mittlerer Frequenzen werden zwei neuartige Ansätze zur Vorhersage des Schallfeldes vorgeschlagen. Die präsentierten Ansätze basieren auf wahrscheinlichkeitstheoretischen Beschreibungen der Systemgeometrie und ermöglichen so auch Aussagen über die Zuverlässigkeit der Berechnungsergebnisse. Die vorgeschlagenen Methoden basieren zum Einen auf der Modellierung des freien Fluidvolumens im Hohlraum und zum Anderen auf der Modellierung der Einbauten als einfach geformte Streukörper. Wenngleich die Gültigkeitsbereiche der vorgeschlagenen Verfahren unterschiedlichen Beschränkungen unterliegen, liefern beide Methoden vergleichbare Ergebnisse im interessierenden Frequenzbereich. Die Gültigkeit und Anwendbarkeit der vorgeschlagenen Verfahren wird durch den Vergleich mit den numerischen Berechnungen überprüft. Verschiedene Ansätze werden vorgestellt, um die Schallquellen in das Modell zu integrieren. Als Bindeglied zwischen Quellbeschreibung und Schallausbreitung wird die Zerlegung der komplex geformten Quellen in Multipole verschiedener Ordnung vorgeschlagen. Bei der Zerlegung komplex geformter Quellen unter Anwendung der sphärischen Nahfeldholographie (NAH) sind häufig die Gültigkeitsbedingungen der Rayleigh-Hypothese nicht erfüllt. Für diesen Fall wird ein Näherungsverfahren vorgestellt, dass eine Reihenentwicklung in eine begrenzte Anzahl von Gegenbauer-Polynomen verwendet, um die Probleme durch Schallfeldsingularitäten zu beseitigen. Die Gültigkeit und Anwendbarkeit der vorgestellten Verfahren, Methoden und Ergebnisse, werden durch den Vergleich mit experimentell gewonnenen Ergebnissen validiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-03-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1708</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17707</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17707</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1708/original_Gesamt_13.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1708/prager_jens.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
