<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1535">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1535</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-21</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Condensation in an inclined tube with small diameter. Modeling, analysis and numerical simulation of a moving boundary problem with phase change and surface tension</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Kondensation in geneigten Strömungskanälen mit geringem Durchmesser. Modellierung, Analyse und Numerische Simulation eines 'Moving Boundary' Problems mit Phasenübergang und Oberflächenspannung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dziubek, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this thesis we investigated condensation in a tube with small diameter where surface tension is important. Such hydrodynamical channels are found in compact heat exchangers. The goal was to establish a better understanding of the physical process and to enhance the heat transfer. First, the plan was to simulate the problem numerically using a CFD-program. But it turned out that the equations were not implemented correctly, so that we decided to analyze the equations of continuum mechanics of such moving boundary problems and to derive a suitable model. For this we worked out the complete model equations for moving boundary problems with phase change and surface tension. Surface tension is both a characteristic of geometry, and physics of the interface between vapor and liquid. This increase the complexity of the interface model equations significantly. To the best of our knowledge such a complete derivation can not be found in literature. Then we analyzed these equations using generalized dimensional analysis and derived a simplified model for the vertical tube. By this we reintroduced and reformulated generalized dimensional analysis, a very algorithmically method which fell occasionally into oblivion. Generalized dimensional analysis is an extension of classical dimensional analysis, where additionally the model equations are evaluated to find the dimensionless numbers of the process. It allows an analysis based on the two length sales of the process (film thickness and tube length). The results are compared with experimental results and explain the better heat transfer in an inclined tube in the case of low surface tension. The derived interface model equations (jump conditions) are equivalent to boundary layer equations in the sense that they are based on the same conditions. Next we derived an ordinary differential equation for condensation in a vertical tube and by this we extended Nu{\ss}elt's theory to condensation in a tube under rotational symmetry where surface tension is taken into account. The heat transfer decrease for very small tube diameters independent of surface tension (thicker condensate film) and increase for extreme high surface tension. The derived model is compared to parametrical models from literature. It is better then Nu{\ss}elt's model. With Chen's model higher heat transfer rates are predicted. Chen's model is based on available experimental information for co-current condensation inside vertical tubes and takes shear stress exerted by co-current vapor flow into account (which result in a thinner condensate film). After spatial discretization the model equations form a system of ordinary differential equations and algebraic equations (DAE). We analyzed the complexity (the index) of this DAE system and showed that the index of moving boundary problems is determined by the Navier-Stokes equations and not by the (transient) moving boundary problem. We compared different index reduction methods. Based on this thesis we discussed some aspects of numerical methods for moving boundary problems. Decisive for a moving boundary problem is not the index but the nonlinearity introduced by the film thickness as a new unknown. The transformation of an equation with dimension into a dimensionless equation is a symmetry transformation. We extended the idea of symmetry analysis to Lie group analysis and determined the symmetry groups of the model equations, and we showed how to construct analytical solutions for differential equations using the symmetries of an equation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wird der Einfluss der Oberflächenspannung auf die Kondensation in Strömungskanälen mit geringem Durchmesser untersucht. Solche Strömungskanäle kommen in der Prozessindustrie in kompakten Wärmetauschern vor. Um die Physik des Prozesses besser zu verstehen und damit den Wärmeübergang zu verbessern war zunächst geplant, das Problem mit kommerzieller CFD-Software zu simulieren. Es stellte sich jedoch heraus, dass die Modellgleichungen für das Problem in den verwendeten Programmen nicht richtig implementiert waren. Stattdessen werden die vollständigen kontinuumsmechanischen Modellgleichungen für solche Moving Boundary Probleme mit Phasenübergang und Oberflächenspannung hergeleitet und analysiert. Die Oberflächenspannung ist eine physikalische Eigenschaft der Phasengrenzfläche und erfordert daher eine eigene Bilanzgleichung. Außerdem ist sie eine Funktion der mittleren Krümmung, und damit der Geometrie der Phasengrenzfläche. Diese beiden Tatsachen erhöhen die Komplexität der Modellgleichungen wesentlich. Die Modellgleichungen werden mit verallgemeinerter Dimensionsanalyse für ein vertikales Rohr vereinfacht und die wesentlichen Phänomene des Problems bestimmt. Das Ergebnis wird mit einer experimentellen Untersuchung verglichen, es erklärt den besseren Wärmeübergang bei Fluiden hoher Oberflächenspannung in geneigten Rohren. Verallgemeinerte Dimensionsanalyse ist eine (in Vergessenheit geratene) Weiterentwicklung der klassischen Dimensionsanalyse, bei der zusätzlich auch die Modellgleichungen ausgenutzt werden, um die dimensionslosen Kennzahlen des Problems zu erhalten. Damit ist es möglich die Modellgleichungen auf Basis der beiden unterschiedlichen Längen (Filmdicke und Rohrlänge) zu analysieren. Es werden Phasengrenzflächenbedingungen (Jump conditions) hergeleitet, die auf den gleichen Annahmen beruhen wie die Prandtlschen Grenzschichtgleichungen. Anschließend wird auf Basis der vereinfachten Modellgleichungen ein Ein-Gleichungs-Modell hergeleitet und numerisch berechnet. Das entwickelte Modell ist eine Erweiterung der Nu{\ss}elt Theorie. Der Wärmeübergang wird im vertikalen Rohr für sehr kleine Rohrdurchmesser unabhängig von der Oberflächenspannung schlechter (der Film wird dicker) und für extrem hohe Oberflächenspannung besser (der Film wird dünner). Das entwickelte Modell wird mit parametrischen Modellen verglichen, es ist besser als Nu{\ss}elts Modell und etwas schlechter als Chens Modell. Die diskretisierten Modellgleichungen bilden ein System von differentiellen und algebraischen Gleichungen (DAE). Der Differentiationsindex des Systems wird untersucht. Es wird gezeigt, das der Index durch die Navier-Stokes Gleichungen bestimmt ist und nicht durch das (instationäre) Moving Boundary Problem verändert wird. Verschiedene Methoden der Indexreduktion werden verglichen. Das Hauptproblem von Moving Boundary Problemen ist die Nichtlinearität der Gleichungen. Auf Basis der Arbeit werden die Vor-und Nachteile von verschiedenen numerischen Methoden für Moving-Boundary Probleme diskutiert. Die Transformation von dimensionsbehafteten Gleichungen in dimensionslose Gleichungen ist eine Symmetrietransformation. Es wird ausgeführt wie man mit der Lie-Gruppen Theorie analytische Lösungen für Differentialgleichungen entwickelt. Die Lie Theorie wird mit der verallgemeinerten Dimensionsanalyse verglichen und die Symmetrien der Modellgleichungen werden bestimmt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-07-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1535</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-15511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-938720-19-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1535/dziubek_andrea.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
