<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:12Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1949">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1949</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Azeotropic Pressure Swing Distillation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Azeotropentrennung im Zweidruckverfahren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Klein, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The distillation process is the most used thermal unit operation in industry. Most of the mixtures have non-ideal behavior, so the separation will only be possible with a great complexity concerning plant, automation and equipment. The systematic feed back inside these systems makes the process control and automation very complex and the design of the system challenging. In the past the research has added a lot of alternatives to the distillation, like membrane processes, adsorption processes, but in the future distillation will also be one of the main unit operations in thermal separation especially for the separation of non-ideal liquid mixtures in big dimensions. The pressure swing distillation (PSD) uses the dependency of azeotropic composition on the system pressure to break the azeotrope. The main advantages of these processes compared to the other is, that no additional substances (entrainer) have to be used. The PSD process can be operated in continuous or in discontinuous mode and also in semi-continuous mode. This unit operation is not widely used in industry used but the PSD process has a high potential because of the possible energy savings (continuous process) and the simple process structure (discontinuous process). The objective of this work is the analysis, evaluation and comparison of the discontinuous and the continuous operation concerning design, process control concepts, energy demands and complexity and feasibility, to expand the experimental data basis and the theoretical knowledge of the PSD process and to get industrial relevant data and better process understanding. To close the gaps and solve the problems mentioned above, the present work will first reduce the lack of missing experimental data and than discuss the different PSD processes in detail to get more knowledge of this unit operation. The work starts with the state of the art with an overview of the publication and a description of the main process structures of the PSD process. After that a basic model and a rigorous dynamic model with start-up from cold and empty will be introduced and described in detail. These two approaches will first help finding the feasible batch structure for a given PSD case and second will give the possibility to design a good process control structure for the continuous process. It follows the experimental validation of the different models. That includes first experimental results for batch PSD processes as well as the validation of the startup processes of the continuous totally heat integrated columns system. Then the continuous process will be analysed concerning possible process control concepts and process design concepts, which will also be evaluated. Here it can be shown that a process control concept can handle feed concentration changes into the other distillation region in a very stable way. The chapter ends with a detailed analysis of the start-up concepts. The main challenge lies in the coupling of the columns during start-up. The discontinuous pressure swing distillation process is discussed next. As well as for the continuous process the process control concepts and the process designs will be discussed and analyzed. The main improvement in inverted batch design is the introduction of the advanced batch structure. Furthermore the start-up of the batch processes is discussed. The focus lies here in the automatic switching of the controllers. The different batch design concepts will be compared in a simulations study using an analytical as well as the rigorous dynamic model. The potential of the heat integration discussed for the pressure swing distillation leads to the idea to uses this concept with other unit operation as well. So a new way of using an energy integration concept for a Hybrid-process composed of a distillation and a pervaporation unit will be introduced, including a first feasibility study, also for the example of the homogenous azeotropic mixture acetonitrile / water as an alternative process concept to the pressure swing distillation process mainly discussed in this work. Finally a summary of all results and an outlook for further studies in the range of azeotropic separation is given. In conclusion the main contributions from this work are the new experimental data for the continuous and especially for the discontinuous pressure swing distillation processes, the development and verification of a stable process control structure for the heat- and mass-integrated continuous process with energy savings up to 45%, the heuristically analysis of the start-up process of the coupled system including PCS visualization for the operator, the analytical method for a first and fast comparison of the regular and inverted batch process, the verification of a reasonable use of the inverted batch column in case of pressure swing distillation and the transfer of the heat integration concept to other separation processes like hybrid processes.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit ist die Analyse, Bewertung und der Vergleich des kontinuierlichen und der diskontinuierlichen (Batch) Zweidruck-Destillations-Prozesse. Hierzu wurde ein rigoroses dynamisches Modell entwickelt, welches den Anfahrvorgang der Kolonnen aus kaltem und leerem Zustand für beide Prozesse berücksichtigt. Für den kontinuierlichen Prozess wurde die Wärmeintegration analysiert. Hier sind Energieeinsparungen von bis zu 45% möglich. Mit Hilfe des Modells wurden unterschiedliche Prozessdesigns und Prozessführungskonzepte entwickelt, verglichen und bewertet. Der Schwerpunkt der Arbeit liegt in der Analyse von praktikablen und industrierelevanten Prozesskonzepten unter realistischen Bedingungen. Daraus folgt der Vergleich der einzelnen Prozesse auf volumetrischer Basis und nicht wie sonst üblich auf molarer Basis. Die wesentlichen Ergebnisse werden im Folgenden vorgestellt. Vollständig stoff- und wärmeintegrierte Zweidruckkolonnensysteme können stabil und robust mit einem relative einfachen Prozessführungskonzept sowohl für kleine Feed-Konzentrationsstörungen als auch für große Feed-Konzentrationsstörungen in das andere Destillationsgebiet betrieben werden. Der limitierende Faktor ist allerdings die Größe der Destillateströme (Recycleströme) an den Köpfen der Kolonnen. Für den diskontinuierlichen Zweidruckprozess wird ein neu entwickelter analytischer Ansatzes vorgestellt, mit dem es in Abhängigkeit der Feedstartkonzentration, der Produktreinheit und der Destillationsregion (Hochdruck oder Niederdruck) leicht möglich ist, die geeignete Batchvariante zu ermitteln. Dieser dient allerdings nur für eine erste Abschätzung, so dass für den detaillierten Vergleich das dynamische rigorose Anfahrmodell genutzt wird. Der reguläre Batchprozess hat insbesondere für Feedstartkonzentration in der Nähe des azeotropen Punkts Vorteile, der inverse Batchprozess für Feedstartkonzentration in der Nähe der Reinstoffe. Der erweiterte inverse Batchprozess stellt ein neues Prozessdesign dar und ist grundsätzlich besser als der klassische inverse Batchprozess und kann sehr gut mit dem regulären Batchprozess konkurrieren. Er stellt eine echte Innovation gegenüber dem klassischen inversen Prozess dar. Eigene neue experimentelle Daten schließen die Lücke in der Literatur und dienen der Validierung der einzelnen Prozessmodelle. Insbesondere sind hier die erstmals vorgestellten experimentellen Ergebnisse für den inversen Batch Prozess hervorzuheben. Außerdem wurde der Anfahrvorgang auf heuristischer Basis analysiert. Hier ist hervorzuheben, dass beim Anfahren eines gekoppelten Zweidrucksystems zur Trennung azeotroper Stoffgemische das Überlappen der Kopfkonzentrationen und damit eine ausreichende Druckdifferenz zwischen den Kolonnen zwingend erforderlich ist, um den Betrieb des Systems zu gewährleisten bzw. überhaupt zu ermöglichen. Hierzu wurde ein mit dem Prozessleitsystem gekoppletes Visualisierungstool entwickelt. Abschließend wurden die Nutzung der Wärmeintegration in anderen Prozessen, insbesondere von hybriden Prozessen, vorgestellt und erste Ideen zu deren Umsetzung diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-10-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1949</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20500</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20500</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1949/original_klein_andreas_original.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1949/klein_andreas.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
