<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3491">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3491</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Active flow separation control of ground transportation vehicle configurations</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Aktive Beeinflussung der Strömungsablösung von Fahrzeug-Konfigurationen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eichinger, Sandor</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The aerodynamic drag of ground vehicles (like trucks, buses or passenger cars) consists of two main components: the friction drag and the pressure drag. As the vehicle moves relative to the surrounding air, a friction force is generated between the gas and the solid body surfaces due to the effect of viscosity. Because of the blunt shape of most vehicles the flow is not able to follow the body contour at the rear end due to the effect of momentum. Here the flow separates, resulting in a pressure difference between the front and the rear parts which makes up the pressure drag. The separated regions are dominated by complex three-dimensional and time-dependent vortices. The pressure distribution on the body surfaces are also dependent on these structures. The drag force due to pressure is significantly larger than the friction force, and its transient character can additionally cause stability and handling problems. Active ow control approaches were developed in order to reduce the aerodynamic drag of a generic square-backed vehicle. After the base flow simulations with Large-Eddy-Simulation (LES) and Reynolds Averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS) methods active flow control was applied in order to achieve drag reduction using steady blowing through small slits near the edges of the rear surface. The blowing velocity was equal to the inflow velocity (vblow=U0), and the blowing angle was changed from θ=0 degree to θ=60 degree. It is shown that these control techniques can achieve a maximum drag decrease for the θ=45 degree control version of around 11%. Additionally the effect of moving floor was studied and comparison was made for the baseline and for the θ=45 degree flow control variant. Further control setups with omitted slits around the corners and with pulsed blowing were investigated as well at θ=45 degree. It was found that the stagnation point on the rear surface moves upwards, and the vertical extension of the wake section reduces, so the evolving pressure level on the back surface increases. Subsequently a study of the blowing velocity was performed, and it was concluded that the sum of the required energy to realize the actuation and the energy saved due to the achieved drag reduction has an optimum around 11%, using the steady blowing of vblow=1.25 U0. Based on the previous studies a H∞ robust controller was implemented using LES approach as well. Drag reduction was also achieved in case of cross wind. In order to develop an efficient flow control approach and to reduce the number of experiments required for the parameter study the Design of Experiment method was employed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der aerodynamische Widerstand von Bodenfahrzeugen, wie z.B. Kraftfahrzeugen, setzt sich im Wesentlichen aus dem Reibungswiderstand und dem Druckwiderstand zusammen. Während der Reibungswiderstand aufgrund der Reibung zwischen dem umströmenden Fluid und der festen Fahrzeugoberfläche entsteht, resultiert der Druckwiderstand aus einer ungleichmäßigen Druckverteilung um das Fahrzeug. Diese wird durch Ablösegebiete verursacht, die auf der stromab gewandten Fahrzeugseite entstehen. Die Ablösegebiete zeigen sowohl räumlich als auch zeitlich einen sehr komplexen Aufbau, der von großskaligen Wirbelstrukturen geprägt ist. Der Druckwiderstand bildet den größten Anteil am aerodynamischen Gesamtwiderstand eines solchen Fahrzeugs. Außerdem verursacht die Wirbelablösung instationäre Kräfte auf das Fahrzeug, die die Fahrstabilität und -kontrolle negativ beeinflussen können. In dieser Arbeit wird aktive Strömungskontrolle auf ein generisches Fahrzeugmodell mit quadratischer Heckfläche angewendet, um den aerodynamischen Widerstand zu reduzieren. Zunächst wurde die Ausgangskonfiguration ohne Strömungskontrolle mithilfe einer Large-Eddy-Simulation (LES) und einer Reynolds Averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS) Methode simuliert. Mithilfe kleiner Schlitze in der Nähe der Hinterkanten des Hecks wurde anschließend kontinuierlich ausgeblasen, um den Widerstand der Ausgangskon guration zu reduzieren. Die Ausblasgeschwindigkeit ist dabei gleich der globalen Einströmgeschwindigkeit, und der Ausblaswinkel wurde zwischen 0 und 60 Grad variiert. Diese Methode erreichte bei einem Ausblaswinkel von 45 Grad eine maximale Widerstandsreduktion von 11% im Vergleich zur unangeregten Ausgangsströmung. Auch der Effekt eines mit der Anströmung bewegten Bodens wurde für die unangeregte und angeregte Strömung untersucht und verglichen. Für den Fall mit 45 Grad Ausblaswinkel wurden außerdem weitere Variationen mit gepulstem Ausblasen und ohne Schlitze an den Ecken überprüft. Dabei hat sich gezeigt, dass sich der Staupunkt auf der Heckfläche nach oben verlagert, und dass die vertikale Ausdehnung des Nachlaufbereichs abnimmt. Folglich steigt der Druck auf der Heckfläche an, und der Widerstand wird reduziert. Eine Studie mit variierender Ausblasgeschwindigkeit konnte zeigen, dass es unter Berücksichtigung der aufgewendeten Energie ein Effizienzoptimum bei dem 1.25-fachen der globalen Einströmgeschwindigkeit gibt. Die Energieersparnis betrug in diesem Fall 11%. Im Laufe der Arbeiten wurden auÿerdem weitere Verfahren wie ein auf LES basierender, robuster H∞ -Regler eingesetzt. Ergänzend wurde der Einfluss der Anregung bei Seitenwind untersucht und eine Parameterstudie per Design of Experiment erfolgreich angewendet.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-10-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37078</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37078</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3491/eichinger_sandor.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
