<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:00Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3193">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3193</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The influence of femoral component malalignment on the biomechanics of the knee after total knee arthroplasty</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Zum Einfluss von Fehlorientierungen der femoralen Komponente auf die Biomechanik des Knies nach totalem Kniegelenkersatz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>König, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Total knee arthroplasty (TKA) is an established and successful procedure with increasing numbers performed each year. In the US alone, an increase from 611000 operations annually to as many as 3.5 million is estimated for the year 2030. However, the patients’ high expectations of the functional and clinical outcome are not always met. Considering the current 10-year failure rates of as much as 12% and the projected number of cases in the future, a significant increase in revision TKA must be expected. One of the possible causes that lead to failure of the TKA is a sub-optimal placement of the femoral component, which can occur in six degrees of freedom (DOF) and is also referred to as a femoral component malalignment (FCM). While specific malalignment in a single DOF, such as frontal plane malalignment (varus-valgus malalignment), has been clinically associated with post-operative complications, knowledge of the effects of complex FCMs on the knee’s biomechanics is limited. However, such knowledge is essential to identify and to avoid FCMs, which can cause unfavourable biomechanical conditions, possibly contributing to a negative post-operative result. Therefore, the aim of this study was to analyse the biomechanical consequences of femoral component malalignment on the joint’s biomechanics during the activities of daily living. After basic investigations of the biomechanical conditions in the healthy knee, validated musculoskeletal models were adapted to simulate a post-TKA condition. A cranial-caudal malalignment of the femoral component, which has been associated with clinical complications, was then simulated, and its effect on the tibio- and patellofemoral contact forces and on the function of the collateral ligaments was characterized. While an elevated joint line was shown to lead to increased patellofemoral contact forces and thus, can contribute to failure-related complications such as pain and wear, a direct effect of joint line elevation on the function of the ligamentous stabilizers, specifically in mid-flexion, was not seen. Surprisingly, the data was indicative of increased loading in the ligaments, which has been previously associated with the development of arthrofibrosis, which can lead to a limited capacity in joint motion. More complex FCM in all six DOFs was then simulated to represent situations more likely to occur in a clinical scenario. Calculating the contact forces for more than 160000 malalignment conditions revealed that the influence of a specific FCM is dependent on the joint analysed and the activity performed. The most influential parameters were found to be the internal-external rotation of the femoral component, the location of the joint line and the varus-valgus alignment. The analyses showed that, in 28% of the simulated malalignment conditions, FCM led to a 10% or greater increase in joint contact forces, relative to the optimally reconstructed joint. More incidences were found in the patello- than in the tibiofemoral joint. Such contact force increases can be caused by every type of malalignment. Even if an individual DOF was kept in its reference condition, malalignment in the remaining DOFs could lead to contact force increases of 10% or more, indicating that monitoring of a single DOF is not sufficient to detect a possible contact force increase. In some DOFs, individual levels of malalignment were involved in more than 50% of all observed cases of increased contact forces, reaching a share of up to 92% (e.g. internal rotation &gt;5°, patellofemoral joint, stair climbing). In the clinic, this would give only few options to avoid a load increase by the targeted manipulation of the remaining DOFs. More significant load increases of 50% and more were found primarily when varus malalignment was combined with an internal rotation (each 5° or above). In the clinic this FCM should therefore be avoided. The intra-operative identification of FCMs causing smaller load increases is almost impossible for the surgeon without assistance, especially since there is also a dependency on the activity and the analysed joint. Enhancing orthopaedic navigation systems with a database similar to the one presented in this study, which contains a matrix of malalignment in all DOFs and the resulting contact forces, would allow for the intra-operative detection of increased load conditions. This study emphasises that it is not sufficient to analyse only individual DOFs of femoral component malalignment to draw a conclusion on its biomechanical effects, as the presence of malalignment in the remaining DOFs can have a significant impact on the joint’s biomechanics. The approach presented in this study to biomechanically assess malalignment in all six DOFs is an essential step towards an intra-operative and patient-specific analysis of the femoral component placement. Ideally this can help to minimize the risk of creating overloading conditions, possibly also reducing the incidences of implant failure after TKA.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der totale Ersatz des Kniegelenks ist ein etabliertes und erfolgreich angewandtes operatives Verfahren mit zunehmenden Fallzahlen. Allein in den USA wird ein Anstieg von derzeit jährlich etwa 611.000 auf 3,5 Millionen Operationen im Jahr 2030 prognostiziert. Schon jetzt können die hohen Erwartungen der Patienten an das postoperative klinische und funktionelle Ergebnis nicht immer erfüllt werden. Ausgehend von den aktuellen 10-Jahres Revisionsraten von bis zu 12% und den prognostizierten Fallzahlen ist ein erheblicher Anstieg von Revisionseingriffen zu erwarten. Eine der in klinischen Studien identifizierten möglichen Ursachen, die zum Versagen einer Knieendoprothese führen können, ist eine suboptimale Ausrichtung der femoralen Prothesenkomponente. Bisher wurde jedoch noch keine umfassende Studie durchgeführt, welche die Auswirkung der Fehlorientierungen der femoralen Komponente auf die Biomechanik des Kniegelenks untersucht und die beobachteten klinischen Probleme möglicherweise erklärt. Die Ergebnisse einer solchen Studie sind weiterhin eine wichtige Voraussetzung, um perioperativ unvorteilhafte biomechanische Bedingungen zu identifizieren und gegebenenfalls zu vermeiden. Ziel dieser Arbeit war es daher, die Auswirkungen einer Fehlorientierung der femoralen Komponente auf die Biomechanik des Kniegelenks während der Ausübung von Aktivitäten des täglichen Lebens zu analysieren. Nach der Durchführung von grundlegenden Untersuchungen zur Biomechanik des gesunden Kniegelenks wurden validierte muskuloskeletale Modelle modifiziert und eine klinisch oft mit Komplikationen assoziierte cranial-caudal Fehlpositionierung der femoralen Komponente simuliert. Die Auswirkung dieser Fehlpositionierung auf die Kontaktkräfte im patello- und tibiofemoralen Gelenk sowie auf die Funktion der Seitenbänder wurde anschließend untersucht. Die Ergebnisse zeigten, dass eine erhöhte Gelenklinie zu erhöhten Kontaktkräften führt und somit versagensrelevanten Komplikationen wie Schmerz und verstärkter Abrasion zuträglich sein kann. Ein vermuteter Zusammenhang zwischen einer erhöhten Gelenklinie und Instabilität in mittleren Kniebeugewinkeln konnte hingegen nicht bestätigt werden. Zur Untersuchung eines kliniknaheren Szenarios wurde angenommen, dass von den sechs möglichen Arten einer Fehlorientierung der femoralen Komponente mehrere gleichzeitig in einer klinisch repräsentativen Variationsbreite auftreten können. Die Berechnung der Gelenkkontaktkräfte für mehr als 160.000 simulierte Fehlorientierungen zeigte, dass der Einfluss eines Orientierungsparameters von der durchgeführten Aktivität und dem betrachteten Gelenk abhängig ist. Die einflussreichsten Parameter waren die interne-externe Rotation der femoralen Komponente, die Lage der Gelenklinie und eine varus-valgus Fehlorientierung. In 28% aller untersuchten Fälle wurde eine Kontaktkrafterhöhung von 10% und mehr registriert, wobei die Häufigkeit im Patellofemoralgelenk höher war als die im Tibiofemoralgelenk. Diese Fälle erhöhter Kontaktkräfte traten bei allen Varianten von Fehlorientierung auf. Selbst bei optimaler Orientierung eines Parameters kann es zur Kontaktkrafterhöhung kommen. Es ist daher nicht ausreichend nur einen Parameter zu überwachen um Kontaktkrafterhöhung zu identifizieren. Fehlorientierungen in bestimmten Ausprägungen können in bis zu 92% aller Fälle mit Kontaktkrafterhöhung vorherrschend sein (z.B. interne Rotation &gt;5°, Patellofemoralgelenk, Treppesteigen). Dies limitiert die Möglichkeiten, die Kontaktkräfte durch eine gezielte Manipulation der anderen Orientierungsparameter zu verringern. Erhebliche Belastungsanstiege von 50% und mehr wurden bei der Kombination von varus Fehlstellungen mit einer internen Rotation gefunden (bei beiden 5° und mehr). Diese Fehlstellung sollten daher in der Klinik vermieden werden. Die intraoperative Identifizierung der häufiger auftretenden Fälle mit geringeren Kontaktkraftanstiegen ist für den Operateur kaum möglich, da ein komplexer Zusammenhang zwischen den einzelnen Orientierungsparametern, dem analysierten Gelenk und der Aktivität besteht, der ohne die Zuhilfenahme von computergestützten Assistenzsystemen schwer zu erfassen ist. Die Ergebnisse dieser Arbeit unterstreichen, dass es nicht ausreicht, nur einzelne Orientierungsparameter zu betrachten, da zusätzlich auftretende Fehlorientierungen die Kontaktkräfte im Gelenk stark beeinflussen können. Der beschriebene Ansatz ermöglicht es patientenbezogen die postoperative Biomechanik abzuschätzen und die Implantation der femoralen Komponente hinsichtlich der Kontaktkräfte zu optimieren. Somit kann das Risiko von auftretenden Überlastungsbedingungen minimiert und postoperative Komplikationen möglicherweise verringert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-01-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33623</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33623</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3193/koenig_christian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
