<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:20Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2603">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2603</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Major Organic Foulants in Ultrafiltration of Treated Domestic Wastewater and their Removal by Bio-filtration as Pre-treatment</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Hauptverursacher des Foulings bei der Ultrafiltration von Kläranlagenablauf und dessen Entfernung durch Biofiltration als Vorbehandlungsprozess</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zheng, Xing</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Ultrafiltration (UF) membranes can be used after conventional wastewater treatment to pro-duce particle free and hygienically safe water for reuse. However, membrane fouling affects UF performance to a large extent. Without suitable pre-treatment and optimized operational conditions, the membrane can loose its permeability quickly. Althogh hydraulic backwashing is periodically used to remove the foulants, the accumulation of hydraulically irremovable fouling reduces the efficiency of the membrane permanently. Thus, qualitative and quantita-tive identification of the major foulants is necessary to understand and control fouling. This research investigated the variation of fouling potential of domestic wastewater applying bio-filtration as a pre-treatment process. The aim is to identify and quantify the major foulants and understand fouling control effects using bio-filtration. Pilot-scale bio-filtration processes were used to treat secondary effluent prior to UF. The fouling potential of various water sam-ples was assessed by lab-scale stirred cell experiments. An UF pilot plant was used to verify the correlation between the feedwater characteristics and membrane fouling. The lab-scale stirred cell experiments demonstrated that the dissolved substances larger than or comparable to the UF pore size are major foulants, in either secondary effluent or in bio-filtrate. These substances were detected as biopolymers using liquid chromatography with online organic carbon detection, UV absorption and organic nitrogen detection (LC-OCD-UV-OND) which were characterized as macromolecular protein-like and polysaccharide-like substances. The content of biopolymers influenced the filterability of water samples in UF proportionally. It affected the reversibility of formed fouling crucially. The correlation be-tween the biopolymer content in feedwater and the performance of UF was verified to be re-producible by pilot-scale UF experiments. Bio-filtration was demonstrated to be able to improve the performance of the downstream connected UF due to the removal of particles, colloids and especially biopolymers from the secondary effluent. The elimination of biopolymers was observed mainly within the upper active filter layer and was revealed to be relevant to biological processes. The operational conditions of bio-filtration, e.g. temperature, biopolymer concentration in feedwater and fil-tration rate, influenced biopolymer removal efficiency. After bio-filtraton, although the fouling potential of secondary effluent could be significantly reduced, operational conditions of UF plant affected fouling development to a large extent. Backwash interval and filtration flux were identified as the most important operational pa-rameters affecting the severity of fouling. Severe fouling can appear due to the extension of filtration time and/or the increase of filtration flux. To control fouling development under these critical conditions, different chemicals were used to perform chemically enhanced backwash. The results showed that NaClO and H2O2 were effective reagents in controlling irreversible fouling. Chemical cleaning was carried out to restore the permeability of a fouled UF membrane. In the present study, the combination of NaOH and NaClO as cleaning reagent was identified as an effective choice.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der weitergehenden Aufbereitung von Kläranlagenablauf bietet der Einsatz von Ultrafiltra-tionsmembranen eine Energie schonende Aufbereitungsmöglichkeit bezüglich pathogener Keime und Partikeln. Bei der Membranfiltration führen jedoch Ablagerungen auf der Memb-ran sowie in den Membranporen (Fouling) sukzessive zu einer Reduzierung der Filtrations-leistung. Für einen stabilen Betrieb der Ultrafiltration sind daher eine geeignete Vorbehand-lung des Rohwassers und die optimale Betriebsführung der Filtration erforderlich, um den Permeabilitätsverlust zu reduzieren. Eine qualitative und quanitative Analyse der für das Fouling primär verantwortlichen Substanzen ist notwendig, um die dominierenden Fouling-mechanismen zu verstehen und das Fouling kontrollieren zu können. Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit wurde die Biofiltration zur Vorbehandlung von Kläranlagenablauf und deren Auswirkung auf das Ultrafiltrationsverhalten untersucht. Dafür wurde eine Pilotan-lage betrieben, die Biofiltration mit anschließender Ultrafiltration für die Aufbereitung von Kläranlagenablauf kombinierte. Mit Hilfe von Laborfiltrationsversuchen wurde das Fouling-potential des biologisch behandelten Abwassers vor sowie nach Durchlaufen der Biofiltration betrachtet. Parallel konnte über das Filtrationsverhalten der UF-Pilotanlage der Zusammen-hang zwischen den Rohwassereigenschaften und dem Membranfouling verifiziert werden. Die Ergebnisse der Laborfiltrationsversuche zeigten, dass sowohl im Kläranlagenablauf als auch im Biofiltrat gelöste Substanzen größer oder im Größenbereich einer Membranpore das Fouling hauptsächlich beeinflussen. Bei der Analyse mittels Größenausschlusschroma-tographie und anschließender Detektion des organischen Kohlenstoffs, der UV-Absorption sowie des organischen Stickstoffs (LC-OCD-UV-OND) eluierten diese Stoffe als Biopolyme-re. Steigende Biopolymerkonzentrationen im Rohwasser führten zu einer proportional sinken-den Filtrationsleitung und wirkten sich ebenfalls auf die Reversibilität der Foulingschicht aus. Die Biofiltration zeigte sich aufgrund der Entfernung von Partikeln, Kolloiden und insbeson-dere Biopolymeren aus dem Ablauf der Kläranlage geeignet für die Verbesserung der Leis-tungsfähigkeit der nachgeschalteten UF. Die Reduzierung von Biopolymeren fand hierbei hauptsächlich in der oberen aktiven Filterschicht statt und ist damit auf biologische Prozesse zurückzuführen. Betriebsparameter wie beispielsweise die Temperatur, die Biopolymerkon-zentration im Rohwasser sowie die Filtrationsgeschwindigkeit beeinflussten die Effizienz der Biopolymerentfernung. Die Biofiltration reduzierte das Foulingpotential des Kläranlagenablaufs signifikant. Weiter wirkten sich optimale Betriebsbedingungen der UF positiv auf ihre Leistung aus. Der Filtrati-onsflux sowie das Rückspülintervall erwiesen sich als wichtigste Betriebsparameter für eine Reduzierung des Foulings. Um einen stabilen Betrieb auch unter diesen kritischen Bedingun-gen zu erreichen, wurden verschiedene Reinigungschemikalien für die Realisierung einer chemisch unterstützten Rückspülung untersucht. NaOCl und H2O2 erwiesen sich als am effek-tivsten, um dem irreversiblen Fouling entgegenzuwirken. Sobald die Filtrationsleistung der UF auf ein Minimum sank, wurden die Membranmodule chemische gereinigt, um die Aus-gangspermeabilität wiederherzustellen. Die effektivste Reinigungsleistung erreichte die Kom-bination der Chemikalien NaOH und NaOCl.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-08-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27477</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27477</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-89720-557-4 </dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2603/zheng_xing.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
