<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:51Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3584">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3584</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Challenges of Offshore LNG Transfer</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Hydrodynamische Herausforderungen bei der Offshore Flüssiggasverladung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sprenger, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Developing maritime gas fields in deep water by Floating Liquefied Natural Gas (FLNG) concepts poses demanding technical challenges. So far, no systems are in operation but projects in the design or construction phase are characterized by a floating terminal barge that produces, liquefies and stores natural gas at the offshore location. Frequently operating shuttle tankers are moored either alongside (side-by-side) or at the stern of the terminal (tandem) to receive the cryogenic liquefied cargo. During the offloading procedure, which takes 18 to 24 hours in changing environmental conditions, the transfer system has to tolerate the occurring relative motions between the terminal and the tanker. Gradually changing filling levels and free surface effects inside the tanks significantly influence the seakeeping behavior of the LNG carrier. Methods and research results published so far encompass experimental and numerical analyses of individual aspects of the complex hydrodynamic problem related to offshore LNG transfer. Well known work includes the determination of pressure peaks on tank walls caused by violent sloshing or exemplary reproductions of coupling effects between resonant internal fluid motions and wave-induced vessel motions. However, available results are mostly based on idealized conditions (two-dimensional setups, model testing with fresh water instead of LNG) where relevant hydrodynamic effects are observed to some extend but their consequences on the extrapolation of data to full scale operations is not fully comprehended. Due to these restrictions, most of the results obtained by current standard approaches are defective or at least incomplete. In this thesis, the first validated holistic numerical method, which captures all hydrodynamic aspects that are relevant during offloading operations is presented. By in-depth studies on the basis of this approach, the background of the occurring phenomena can be fully comprehended, which allows accurate extrapolation of results from model scale to full scale. Combining the introduced method and the gained background knowledge is a critical prerequisite for the conduction of trustworthy feasibility studies and the determination of operational ranges for FLNG projects. The selected linear potential theory based procedure is capable to excellently reproduce seakeeping characteristics as well as internal fluid motions. The entire calculation process is exemplarily demonstrated for the MPLS20 system in the Haltenbanken region. By detailed numerical investigations, it is revealed for the first time that the differences between natural tank modes and sloshing-related maximum values in the respective motion response amplitude operators (RAO) are attributed to the ratio of rigid body mass to added mass. Here, hydrodynamic coupling of different degrees of freedom are a crucial factor. The most important consequence from this finding is that – in contrast to the well-established practice – results obtained from model tests with fresh water filling inside the tanks cannot be extrapolated to full scale operations with LNG. Comprehensive three-dimensional analyses reveal for the first time that for LNG carriers, significant fluid sloshing and body motions occur perpendicular to the direction of excitation. This phenomenon is caused by asymmetries of the submerged hull geometry as well as asymmetric mass distribution. This observation leads to the conclusion that commonly published idealized two-dimensional approaches are inadequate for the prediction of the motion behavior of vessels with partially filled tanks.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Zur Erschließung maritimer Gaslagerstätten in großen Wassertiefen werden sogenannte Floating Liquefied Natural Gas (FLNG) Konzepte entwickelt. Eine schwimmende Terminalbarge fördert und verflüssigt Erdgas, welches regelmäßig an Flüssiggastanker übergeben wird. Während dieser 18 bis 24 Stunden dauernden Verladeprozedur muss das Transfersystem den aus den vorherrschenden Umweltbedingungen resultierenden Relativbewegungen zwischen Terminal und Tanker standhalten. Insbesondere das Bewegungsverhalten des Tankers wird hierbei durch die sich kontinuierlich ändernden Füllstände und freien Flüssigkeitsoberflächen in den Ladetanks signifikant beeinflusst. Bisher veröffentlichte Ergebnisse und Methoden zur hydrodynamischen Analyse von Offshore-Verladeprozessen gehen von idealisierten Bedingungen aus (zweidimensionale Betrachtungen, Modellversuche mit Wasser anstelle von LNG). Relevante hydrodynamische Phänomene werden teilweise beobachtet, ohne jedoch deren Einfluss auf die Extrapolation von Ergebnissen auf die Großausführung vollständig zu verstehen. Dadurch sind viele der durch heutige Standardverfahren ermittelten Resultate unbrauchbar bzw. unvollständig. Mit dieser Arbeit liegt erstmals ein validiertes, ganzheitliches numerisches Verfahren vor, welches die relevanten hydrodynamischen Aspekte, die während des Verladevorgangs auftreten, vollständig berücksichtigt. Vertiefende Untersuchungen auf Basis dieses Verfahrens tragen zum grundlegenden Verständnis der auftretenden Effekte bei, wodurch eine fehlerfreie Ergebnisextrapolation vom Modell auf die Großausführung ermöglicht wird. Die vorgestellte Methode in Kombination mit dem erlangten Hintergrundwissen kann als vertrauenswürdige Ausgangsbasis für Machbarkeitsstudien und Einsatzgrenzenbestimmungen von FLNG-Projekten herangezogen werden. Es zeigt sich, dass das gewählte lineare, auf Potentialtheorie beruhende Verfahren sowohl im Hinblick auf die Bewegungscharakteristika unter Einfluss von freien Flüssigkeitsoberflächen als auch auf die Fluidauslenkungen in den Tanks hervorragende Ergebnisse liefert. Vertiefende numerische Untersuchungen zeigen erstmals, dass die Differenzen zwischen Tankresonanzfrequenzen und den durch internes Sloshing verursachten Maxima der entsprechenden Bewegungsübertragungsfunktionen vom Verhältnis der Festkörpermasse zur hydrodynamischen Masse des Schiffes abhängen. Die wichtigste Schlussfolgerung aus dieser Beobachtung ist, dass Ergebnisse aus Modellversuchen oder Simulationen mit Wasser in den Ladetanks entgegen des oftmals praktizierten Vorgehens nicht auf den realen Betrieb mit LNG extrapoliert werden können. Durch umfassende dreidimensionale Analysen kann außerdem erstmals gezeigt werden, dass bei Flüssiggastankern aufgrund von Asymmetrien resonantes Tanksloshing und dadurch induzierte Starrkörperbewegungen senkrecht zur Angriffsrichtung der erregenden Wellenkräfte auftreten. Diese Beobachtung lässt den Schluss zu, dass durch eine idealisierte, zweidimensionale Betrachtung der Problemstellung keine vollständigen Aussagen über das Bewegungsverhalten von Schiffen mit teilgefüllten Tanks zu treffen sind.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-12-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3584/sprenger_florian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
