<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:01Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2767">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2767</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Preloading Effects on Dynamic Sand Behavior by Resonant Column Tests</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Untersuchung der Einflüsse aus Vorbelastungen auf das dynamische Verhalten von Sand in Resonant Column Versuchen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bai, Lidong</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Dynamic behavior of Berlin sand and the preloading effects on shear modulus and damping properties of sand were investigated by resonant column tests in this study, in addition, a new reliable calibration method for the Stokoe resonant column apparatus is also presented. The influences of confining pressure, void ratio, water content, sampling method, stress history, confinement duration and others on dynamic properties of Berlin sand were examined by resonant column tests. An empirical equation was proposed to predict the small-strain shear modulus, and two empirical models were proposed to simulate the nonlinear modulus and damping properties of Berlin sand, a brief comparison of small-strain shear modulus by resonant column and bender element tests is addressed as well. In this study, the author initially introduced the preloading concept to investigate vibration history effects on dynamic sand behavior, which is quite different from the prestraining concept conventionally employed in previous investigations. For the preloading concept, the previous vibration applied to specimen is employed by the non-resonant vibration mode of stress-controlled shear by resonant column apparatus. With this concept the number of loading cycles can be enlarged to a range from one to any desired number. By contrast the prestraining concept cannot investigate low number of cycles due to the necessary several hundreds of cycles to determine the resonant frequency. In addition, the use of the preloading concept can also ensure constant preloading stress during the previbration is applied to the tested specimen at the same vibration frequency and input drive voltage. The prestraining concept may introduce less precision of the calculation of prestraining amplitude if the set vibration frequency and input drive voltage are not adjusted during previbration. That is due to variation of the resonant vibration frequency and other parameters, if the stiffness of tested specimen varies with number of cycles, and therefore the set vibration frequency is not the resonant frequency of the vibration system any more. The effects of many factors which may influence the preloading effects on the dynamic behavior of sand were fully explored in this study. One of the most important findings is that the shear modulus or stiffness of sand decreases with number of cycles if it does not exceed a threshold number and increases when the number of cycles exceeds this threshold. A theoretical interpretation of the reduction of stiffness of sand subjected to preloading was proposed herein.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Gegenstand der Arbeit ist die Untersuchung des Einflusses von zyklischen und dynamischen Vorbelastungen auf das dynamische Verhalten von Berliner Sand. Hierzu wurden der Schubmodul und die Dämpfung in Resonant Column Versuchen ermittelt. Darüber hinaus wird eine neue Methode zur Kalibrierung von Resonant Column Geräten des Stokoe Typs vorgestellt. In den Resonant Column Versuchen wurden die Einflüsse aus der Größe und Einwirkungsdauer der Konsolidierungsspannung, der Porenzahl, dem Wassergehalt, der Probenvorbereitungsmethode und der Spanungsgeschichte untersucht. Basierend auf den Versuchsdaten werden empirische Beziehungen für den Schubmodul bei sehr kleinen Schubverzerrungen sowie die Verläufe von Schubmodul und Dämpfung von Berliner Sand in Abhängigkeit von der Schubverzerrung vorgeschlagen. Die im Resonant Column Versuch ermittelten Schubmoduln bei sehr kleinen Schubverzerrungen werden den ebenfalls eigenen Ergebnissen von Bender Element Versuchen gegenübergestellt. In dieser Arbeit werden die Vorbelastungseinflüsse durch kraft- bzw. spannungsgesteuerte Resonant Column Versuche untersucht. Demgegenüber stehen die üblicherweise mittels weg- bzw. verzerrungsgesteuerten Versuchen erhaltenen Ergebnisse in der Literatur. Die Kraftsteuerung erfolgt dabei nicht im Resonanzzustand der Probe, wie es bei Wegsteuerung der Fall ist. Dadurch sind bei kraftgesteuerten Versuchen beliebige Zyklenzahlen bei konstanter Vorbelastungsamplitude und -frequenz erzielbar, während bei Wegsteuerung zunächst einige Hundert Belastungszyklen zur Ermittlung des Resonanzzustands der Probe erforderlich sind, bevor die Vorbelastungszyklen aufgebracht werden können. Die weggesteuerte Belastung erfordert bei Änderungen der Probensteifigkeit während der Belastung eine wiederholte Anpassung der Belastungsamplitude und –frequenz, infolge steifigkeitsbedingter Veränderungen des Resonanzzustands. Zu den wesentlichen Erkenntnissen der Arbeit zählt die experimentelle Feststellung einer Grenzzyklenzahl, bei der sich das Verhalten des Schubmoduls in Abhängigkeit von der Anzahl der Vorbelastungszyklen ändert, d.h. Verringerung bzw. Vergrößerung des Schubmoduls mit der Zyklenanzahl bei Unterschreiten bzw. Überschreiten der Grenzzyklenzahl. Es wird eine theoretische Interpretation dieses Effektes vorgestellt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-01-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2767</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2767/bai_lidong.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
