<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3503">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3503</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Fire retardancy of wood-plastic composites</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Entwicklung flammgeschützter Wood-Plastic Composites</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Seefeldt, Henrik</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Up to now only little knowledge has been recorded about the fire behavior and flame retardancy of wood-plastic composites (WPCs). The use of WPCs has increased continuously in recent years. Especially in their main field of application as a decking material, WPCs present a big share of the market. To date no flame-retarded solution has been introduced for WPC materials that fulfils the necessary requirements. But flame-retarded materials are indispensable, especially for indoor use and the protection of escape routes. In this study basic knowledge about the fire behavior of WPCs is investigated first. Second, the effectiveness and mode of action of different flame-retardant additives is investigated. Special attention is drawn to products made of WPC material. Therefore WPC was further investigated in its main field of application as decking boards. The fire behavior of materials and products was investigated by means of cone calorimeter measurements as well as radiant panel tests. Furthermore numerical simulations were carried out to study the effects of various thermal material properties on burning behavior. Thermal decomposition was studied using thermogravimetric methods and spectroscopic investigations. Against this background, models for thermal decomposition pathways were built for combinations of WPC material with different flame retardants. WPCs show burning behavior similar to that of pure wood samples with an increased heat release rate due to polymeric fractions. It is shown that all investigated flame retardants had a positive effect on the burning behavior of WPCs. The best results were achieved by the flame retardants ammonium polyphosphate, Paxymer and expandable graphite. Especially in combination with red phosphorus, expandable graphite was highly effective because red phosphorus stabilized formed residue. Apart from the influence of flame retardants, other influencing factors like geometry and moisture content also played an important role concerning the flame retardancy of WPC decking boards. Indeed, hollow decking boards offer a reduced amount of combustible material, but their flame spread is increased in comparison to solid samples.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Über das Brandverhalten von Wood-plastic Composites (WPCs) und deren Flammschutz ist bislang wenig bekannt. Die Verwendung von WPCs ist in den vergangenen Jahren stetig gestiegen. Vor allem in ihrem Hauptanwendungsgebiet als Bodenbeläge verzeichnen WPC Materialien einen großen Marktanteil. Bis jetzt existiert jedoch noch keine Flammschutzlösung, die alle nötigen Anforderungen im Bauwesen erfüllt. Flammgeschützte Materialien sind jedoch vor allem für Innenanwendungen und im Bereich von Fluchtwegen unabdingbar. In dieser Arbeit werden zum einen grundlegende Mechanismen über das Brandverhalten von WPCs aufgeklärt. Zum anderen werden die Wirksamkeit und die Wirkungsweise verschiedener Flammschutzmitteln in WPC Materialien untersucht. Ein spezielles Augenmerk wird dabei auch auf Endprodukte aus WPC Materialien gelegt. WPC wurde dabei in seiner Hauptanwendung als Fußbodenbelag untersucht. Das Brandverhalten wurde für Materialien und Produkte mit Hilfe von Cone Calorimeter Untersuchungen und Radiant Panel Tests bestimmt. Zudem wurden numerische Simulationen genutzt, um den Einfluss verschiedener thermischer Materialparameter auf das Brandverhalten zu erforschen. Des weiteren wurde das thermische Zersetzungsverhalten mittels thermogravimetrischer Methoden und spektroskopischen Untersuchungen ermittelt. Auf dessen Grundlage konnten Abbaumechanismen für WPC Materialen in Verbindung mit verschiedenen Flammschutzmitteln erstellt werden. WPCs zeigen das gleiche Brandverhalten wie Holz, auf Grund des polymeren Anteils ist jedoch die Wärmefreisetzungsrate während der Verbrennung stark erhöht. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass alle untersuchten Flammschutzmittel einen positiven Effekt auf das Brandverhalten von WPCs hatten. Beste Ergebnisse wurden durch Ammonium Polyphosphat, Paxymer und expandierbaren Graphit erzielt. Expandierbarer Graphit war besonders in Verbindung mit rotem Phosphor sehr wirksam, da der Phosphor den gebildeten Rückstand stabilisierte. Neben dem Einfluss von Flammschutzmitteln konnte gezeigt werden, dass für WPC Fußbodendielen auch andere Einflussfaktoren, wie die Geometrie und der Feuchtigkeitsgehalt eine wichtige Rolle spielen. So weisen Hohlkammerprofildielen im Vergleich zu Vollprofilproben zwar eine verminderte Menge an brennbarem Material auf, die Flammenausbreitung ist jedoch stark erhöht.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-10-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3503</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3503/seefeldt_henrik.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
