<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:23Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2396">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2396</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The Martian Moon Phobos - A Geodetic Analysis of its Motion, Orientation, Shape, and Physical Parameters</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Der Marsmond Phobos - Eine geodätische Analyse seiner Bewegung, Orientierung, Form und physikalischer Parameter</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Willner, Konrad</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Mars is accompanied by two small natural satellites. Deimos, the smaller of the two, is orbiting at a greater distance from Mars while Phobos revolves around the planet at a mean altitude of approximately 6,000km with respect to the Martian surface, deep in the gravity field of the planet. An in-depth study of the irregular shaped moon Phobos was commenced due to remaining questions on its orbital motion, shape, and physical parameters based on new high resolution images of the Super Resolution Channel (SRC) and the High Resolution Stereo Camera (HRSC) which are part of the European Mars Express Mission (MEX). Parameters of ephemerides models were questioned after the finding of large discrepancies of Phobos' position to astrometric observations. During the course of this study astrometric measurements were made in fly-by images of Phobos and through observations of Phobos' shadow on the Martian surface. While results of the latter analysis led to largely scattered differences compared to orbit prediction models with high uncertainties, the fly-by observations were in agreement with the ephemerides models within the error bands. Offsets were rather consistent and systematic indicating that Phobos is ahead of its predicted position by approximately 2 km. To be able to model the irregular shape of Phobos by means of different techniques - namely a digital terrain model and a model based on spherical harmonic functions - a new global control point network was established. The 665 object point coordinates with respect to the Phobos body-fixed coordinate frame were determined through observations in 53 SRC and 16 Viking Orbiter images. Coordinates of the object points were computed by means of a least-squares bundle block adjustment. The overall accuracy was estimated to be in the order of +/-17 m. The control network proved to be a valuable tool to observe the forced libration amplitude - a superimposed oscillation on the rotation of Phobos due to interactions between the irregularly shaped Phobos and the gravity field of Mars. A global digital terrain model (DTM), which is based on stereo images of the HRSC and Viking Orbiter images, was computed and was used to ortho-rectify SRC and Viking images. Based on the ortho-rectified images an accurate map of Phobos was prepared. Since the DTM representation of Phobos' shape is rather inefficient to obtain physical parameters, the coeffcients of the surface spherical harmonic function to degree and order 17 were determined through the control point coordinates. The analytical expression for Phobos was used to re-estimate the volume, bulk density of Phobos and the moment of inertia tensor. A volume of 5689km³ and a corresponding bulk density of 1.85 g/cm³ were determined. The results were in good agreement, but signiffcantly improved accuracy compared to previous estimates of these values. The moments of inertia were primarily computed assuming a homogeneous mass distribution within Phobos. The principle moments of inertia can be put in relation to the forced libration amplitude. The modeled forced libration amplitude agrees well with the observed value within its error bounds. Applying simple two layer mass distribution models, exact agreement between observation and model of the forced libration amplitude could only be achieved assuming extreme model parameters. This suggests a more complex mass distribution within Phobos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Mars wird von zwei Monden umkreist, Deimos und Phobos. Der größere, Phobos, umrundet Mars mit einem durchschnittlichen Abstand von ca. 6000km über der Marsoberfläche, tief in dem Gravitationsfeld des Planeten. Auf der Grundlage der neuen hochauflösenden Bilder des Super Resolution Channels (SRC) und der High Resolution Stereo Camera (HRSC), welche Teil der Europäschen Raummission Mars Express (MEX) sind, wurde eine eingehende Studie des unregelmäßig geformten Mondes Phobos durchgeführt, um offene Fragen seiner orbitalen Bewegung, seiner Form sowie physikalischer Kenngrößen zu klären. Parameter von Bahnmodellen für Phobos wurden in Frage gestellt nachdem große Diskrepanzen zu astrometrischen Beobachtungen von Phobos festgestellt wurden. Aus Vorbeiflug-Bildern von Phobos und aus Beobachtungen von Phobos' Schatten auf der Marsoberfläche wurden in dieser Studie astrometrische Beobachtungen abgeleitet und ausgewertet. Ergebnisse der Schattenbeobachtungen zeigen eine weite Streuung mit großen Unsicherheiten im Vergleich zu den Bahnmodellen, während die Vorbeifluugbeobachtungen mit den Bahnmodellen innerhalb der Fehlergrenzen übereinstimmten. Die Kontinuität und Systematik der Differenzen zwischen Beobachtungen und Vorhersagen lassen darauf schließen, dass Phobos seiner vorhergesagten Position etwa 2km voraus ist. Basierend auf einem Kontrollpunktnetz wurde die Figur von Phobos mittels verschiedener Techniken - durch ein digitales Oberflächenmodel (DOM) und durch Kugelflächenfunktionen - modelliert. Die 665 Kontrollpunktkoordinaten im Phobos-festen Koordinatensystem wurden aus Beobachtungen in 53 SRC und 16 Viking Orbiter Bildern berechnet. Die Berechnung der Objektpunktkoordinaten erfolgte über einen Bündelblockausgleich mit einer durchschnittlichen Genauigkeit von +/-17 m. Das Kontrollnetz stellte sich als wichtiges Werkzeug zur Beobachtung der Amplitude der erzwungenen Libration - einer der Rotation von Phobos überlagerten Schwingung, die aufgrund von Interaktionen mit dem Gravitationsfeld des Mars und der unregelmäßigen Form entsteht - heraus. Auf der Grundlage von Stereobildern der HRSC und von Viking Orbiter Bildern wurde ein globales DOM berechnet. SRC und Viking Bilder wurden genutzt, um eine genaue Karte von Phobos zu erstellen. Zur Berechnung von physikalischen Kenngrößen wurden die Koeffzienten einer Kugelflächenfunktion anhand der Kontrollpunkte bis Grad und Ordnung 17 berechnet. Mittels des analytischen Ausdrucks wurden das Volumen, die mittlere Dichte und die Trägheitsmomente neu bestimmt. Ein Volumen von 5689km³ und eine dazu korrespondierende mittlere Dichte von 1,85 g/cm³ wurden berechnet, welche in guter Übereinstimmung mit bisherigen Abschätzungen sind. Die Trägheitsmomente wurden anfänglich unter der Annahme einer homogenen Massenverteilung berechnet. Die Hauptträgheitsmomente können in Relation zu der Amplitude der erzwungenen Libration gesetzt werden, welche mit dem beobachteten Wert innerhalb der Fehlergrenzen überein stimmt. Durch einfache Zwei-Schicht-Modelle konnte die modellierte Amplitude nur unter Annahme extremer Modellparameter mit der Beobachtung in Übereistimmung gebracht werden. Dieses deutet auf eine komplexere Massenverteilung im Inneren von Phobos hin.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-01-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2396</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25117</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25117</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2396/willner_konrad.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
