<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:55Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3382">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3382</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">On Turbulent Swirling Jets:Vortex Breakdown, Coherent Structures,and their Control</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Analyse und Kontrolle des Wirbelaufplatzens und der kohärenten Strukturen in turbulenten Drallstrahlen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oberleithner, Kilian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This thesis provides an experimental and theoretical investigation of turbulent swirling jets with the emphasis on the formation of large-scale coherent flow structures. The involved mechanisms are highly three-dimensional due to the coexistence of an axial and an azimuthal shear layer. Moreover, swirling jets are prone to a unique flow phenomenon that causes an abrupt change of the entire flow. The so-called vortex breakdown is manifested in the appearance of an internal recirculation bubble, which creates an inner and an outer shear layer. The complexity of this flow configuration poses a great challenge to fundamental research and deals as a benchmark for recent theoretical concepts. Furthermore, the present work is of great importance for the gas turbine industry, where swirling flows are frequently applied to improve combustion processes. The work consists of four major investigations. First, the dominant flow dynamics are characterized at different swirl intensities via time-resolved stereo particle image velocitmetry. This experimental work provides an overview of the main flow features with particular focus on the formation of vortex breakdown and the onset of global instability. A self-excited single-helical mode is found to arise from the axisymmetric breakdown state when the recirculation bubble reaches a sufficient streamwise extent. The preceding onset of breakdown is explained by the criticality of the rotating base flow. The second investigation consists of a detailed examination of the coherent flow structures that amplify in the swirled shear layer. The impact of swirl on the driving instabilities is addressed theoretically by means of spatial stability analysis based on the mean turbulent flow. The most dominant instability is of Kelvin--Helmholtz type, similar to the non-swirling jet. However, swirl effects the phase velocity of the helical instability waves and renders the shear layer as strongly dispersive. Moreover, the azimuthal shear destabilizes steady modes that gain significant amplitudes, which may lead to a breaking of the mean flow symmetry. The theoretical predictions are confirmed by hot-wire measurements of the pulsed and the single-mode actuated swirling jet. The third investigation focuses on the coherent structures associated with the swirling jet's global mode that arises from the axisymmetric vortex breakdown state. A method based on the proper orthogonal decomposition is developed that allows to reconstruct the phase-averaged velocity field of the dominant coherent structures from uncorrelated flow snapshots. The obtained coherent structures are compared to the global eigenmode derived theoretically from a local spatial stability analysis. The global mode is characterized by a precessing vortex core located upstream of the breakdown bubble. It is interpreted as the global wavemaker that imposes its frequency onto the highly receptive outer shear layer, causing large-scale helical flow structures to evolve in the periphery of the jet. The last investigation focuses on the control of the swirling jet undergoing vortex breakdown. By combining the findings of the preceding studies, it is possible to derive a control scheme that enables to dampen the natural global mode at low amplitude forcing. The natural flow is shown to be globally unstable to a single-helical mode resulting in the precession of the vortex core. Convectively unstable modes forced at the nozzle lip lead to an enhanced growth of the outer shear layer. The resulting change of the mean flow leads to a global stabilization of the single-helical mode and to the suppression of the internal feedback that causes the precession of the vortex core.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit umfasst die experimentelle und theoretische Untersuchung der Entstehung großskaliger kohärenter Strukturen in turbulenten Drallstrahlen. Die untersuchte Strö-mungskonfiguration zeichnet sich durch eine hohe Komplexität aufgrund gleichzeitig auftretender axialer und azimutaler Scherschichten aus. Darüber hinaus tritt ab einer gewissen Drallintensität ein Phänomen auf, was zu einer abrupten Änderung der gesamten Strömung führt. Durch das sogenannte Aufplatzen des Wirbelkerns (vortex breakdown) entsteht eine Rückströmblase auf der Strahlachse wodurch sich eine innere und eine äußere Scherschicht manifestiert. Die Analyse und Kontrolle dieser komplexen Strömungskonfiguration stellt allgemein eine große Herausforderung für die Grundlagenforschung dar und ist darüber hinaus von großem Nutzen für die Optimierung drallstabilisierter Verbrennung in Gasturbinen. Die Arbeit ist im Wesentlichen in vier Untersuchungen unterteilt. Im ersten Teil werden die verschiedenen Strömungszustände bei ansteigender Drall charakterisiert. Dieser rein experimentelle Teil gibt einen Überblick über die wesentlichen Strömungsphänomene, mit dem Augenmerk auf das Aufplatzen des Wirbels und das damit verbundene Einsetzen einer globalen Instabilität. Die Experimente zeigen, dass eine globale Oszillation dann einsetzt, wenn die Rückstromblase eine kritische Größe erreicht hat. Das diesem Vorgang vorangehende Einsetzen des Wirbelaufplatzens wird anhand stehender Wellen im Wirbelkern erklärt. Die zweite Untersuchung geht detailliert auf die Charakteristik räumlich anwachsender kohärenter Strukturen im global stabilen Drallstrahl ein. Die hydrodynamischen Instabilitäten, welche die Entstehung dieser Strukturen antreiben, werden mittels räumlicher Stabilitätsanalyse systematisch untersucht. Es wird gezeigt, dass trotz des Einsetzens einer Zentrifugalinstabilität mit ansteigendem Drall, die Kelvin--Helmholtz-Instabilität dominiert. Jedoch beeinflusst der Drall die Phasengeschwindigkeit der helikalen Instabilitätsmoden und erhöht dabei die Dispersivität der Scherschicht. Außerdem sorgt zunehmender Drall für eine Destabilisierung stehender Moden, was dazu führen kann, dass die mittlere Strömung ihre Axialsymmetrie verliert. Diese Ergebnisse werden durch Experimente des harmonisch und des gepulst angeregten Strahls bestätigt. Im dritten Teil dieser Arbeit werden die kohärenten Strukturen der globalen Mode untersucht. Basierend auf der proper orthogonal decomposition, wird die phasengemittelte Geschwindigkeit bezüglich der globalen Oszillationsfrequenz aus zeitlich unkorrelierten Daten extrahiert. Die resultierenden kohärenten Strukturen werden mit der globalen Eigenmode verglichen, die mittels räumlicher Stabilitätsanalyse berechnet werden kann. Die globale Mode zeichnet sich durch einen präzedierenden Wirbelkern (precessing vortex core) stromauf der Rückstromblase aus, der als der Taktgeber ('wavemaker') interpretiert wird. Von dort wird die Oszillation auf die gesamte Strömung aufgeprägt, was zu einem synchronen Anwachsen helikaler Strukturen in der äußeren Scherschicht führt. Die vierte Untersuchung geht auf die Kontrolle der globalen Stabilitätsmode mittels sinusförmiger Anregung ein. Aus den Ergebnissen der ersten drei Untersuchungen lässt sich eine Kontrolltechnik ableiten, die bei geringer Anregungsamplitude größtmögliche Wirkung erzielt. Die Anregung konvektiv instabiler Moden am Düsenaustritt führt dabei zu einer Änderung des mittleren Strömungsfeldes und zu einer Unterdrückung der Rückkopplung in Strahlinneren, was zu einer Dämpfung des präzedierenden Wirbelkerns führt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-07-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35933</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35933</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3382/oberleithner_kilian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
