<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:08Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2096">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2096</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Electronic Drive for Low Wattage Metal Halide Lamps Focused on Acoustic Resonance in HID Lamps</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Elektronischer Betrieb von Halogenmetalldampflampen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ghasemi Afshar, Farhang</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this work the concept of acoustic resonance (AR) in High Intensity Discharge (HID) lamps theoretically and experimentally is studied. A fundamental investigation is carried out in order to get a better understanding of physical backgrounds which are responsible in excitation of acoustic resonances and acoustic instabilities in such lamps. The existing theories, which have introduced during the last four decades is explored. Based on the theory of acoustic streaming, a new hypothesis about the possible physical reasons for the excitation of acoustic instabilities and the temporal response of the discharge is given. To support the discussed hypothesis a real case of acoustic instability is investigated. A numerical method to solve the wave equations inside the lamp's arc tube which accounts for the temperature distribution of the filling gas is then introduced. In contrast to the classic method, which solves the wave equation in a cylindrical arc tube considering a homogenous sound velocity, the method mentioned in this work, considers the exact geometry of the arc tube and the sound velocity distribution as well. Some different practical methods in order to detect, to avoid or to establish acoustic resonances are then discussed. There are some phenomena in High Intensity Discharge (HID) lamps which have the potential to make the discharge unstable. Discharge instability, can lead to some transients in light intensity, or in its periodic form, to annoying light flickering. Instabilities appear in a very vast range. Depending on the strength of the source of instability, it varies from a very slight deflection of sodium sheath to extreme deviations of conducting channel from its normal position which can extinguish the lamp as well. In order to detect the existence of such phenomena and predict their potential power, their effects and consequenes on the light intensity can be analyzed. This has been carried out by using a tuned model of the human eye-brain system, to predict the perceptibility of the transient changes of light. The concept of light flicker factor based on eye-brain model as a measure of discharge instabilities will be introduced. The implementing method of the model and a proper measuring system for light flicker factor is being discussed. Some laboratory experiments to support this method of measurement are presented. In order to avoid the acoustic instabilities in metal halide (MH) lamps a proper method is to supply the lamp with a low frequency square wave (LFSW) current. Due to the topology of electronic ballasts for such an application, there is a high frequency ripple in the current or voltage waveform. It is known that such ripples with sufficient energy at the proper frequency are able to excite acoustic resonance in MH lamps. The threshold value for high frequency ripples in order to excite an acoustic mode and destabilize the lamp is under debate. This threshold is lamp dependent and should be measured experimentally for each lamp type. This work addresses an automated experimental method to determine the threshold value of the power ripple in a frequency range of 10-400 kHz. The experimental results show that less than 1% of power ripple at the resonance frequency is sufficient to excite a detectable (perceptible to the human eye) acoustic instability. The experimental results of this work, in the process of a standardization of low frequency square wave electronic ballasts in the range of 20 to 150W, are already used.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wird das Konzept der akustischen Resonanz in Hochdruckentladungslampen (HID) theoretisch und experimentell erforscht. Eine phänomenologische Untersuchung wurde durchgeführt, um bestehende Theorien zum physikalischen Hintergrund der Anregung von akustischen Instabilitäten zu erhärten oder Unzulänglichkeiten aufzuzeigen. Eine Theorie der akustischen Instabilitäten, die auf der Ausbildung von akustischen Strömungen (acoustic streaming) in HID Lampen basiert, wurde erläutert. Das Problem der akustischen Resonanz, hinsichtlich einer gegebenen Temperaturverteilung innerhalb des Bogen-Gefäßes, wurde numerisch gelöst. Die klassische Methode für die Berechnung der akustischen Resonanzfrequenzen ist nur für zylinderförmige Geometrien des Brenners anwendbar, da sie nicht die Gastemperaturverteilung einbezieht. Eine verbesserte Methode zur Berechnung der Resonanzfrequenzen wurde in dieser Arbeit vorgestellt. Die Methode erzielt präzisere Ergebnisse durch die Verwendung der realen Geometrie des Brenners und der Temperaturverteilung innerhalb des Brenners. Eine numerische Berechnung der Wellengleichung innerhalb des Brenners ermöglicht die Bestimmung der Position von Knoten und Gegenknoten der stehenden Druckwellen und der linearen akustischen Geschwindigkeit. Nach der Theorie des "acoustic streaming" können die Richtung und die Position der Füllungsströme festgestellt werden. Dieses Verfahren hilft, den Einfluss der Anregung der akustischen Resonanzen auf die Entladung für die verschiedenen akustischen Moden zu verstehen und vorauszusagen. In einem realen Fall wird die Hypothese des "Effect of acoustic streaming on the discharge" verwendet, um das Verhalten der Entladung, infolge der Anregung der akustischen Resonanz, zu erklären. Es wird gezeigt, dass die vorgeschlagene Hypothese in der Lage ist, einige Beobachtungen in Bezug auf die akustische Instabilität der Entladung zu erklären. Der praktische Aspekt dieser Arbeit besteht in der Ermittlung der erforderlichen Güte der Leistungseinspeisung (Oberwellengehalt), die einen stabilen Betrieb, ohne Anregung störender akustischer Resonanzen ermöglicht. Alle wahrnehmbaren Änderungen des ausgestrahlten Lichtes der Lampe, die durch Anregung der akustischen Resonanzen verursacht werden, müssen vermieden werden. Basierend auf diesem Kriterium, wurde eine Methode mit Messaufbau entwickelt, um Schwankungen des Lichtstromes in Bezug auf das menschliche Auge quantitativ zu bewerten. Dieser Messaufbau kann auch für weitere Anwendungen eingesetzt werden, indem die zeitliche Änderung des Lichtes in Bezug auf die Wahrnehmung durch den Menschen untersucht wird. Es wurde ein automatisiertes Messsystem, einschließlich des Flickermeters, entwickelt, um die Empfindlichkeit der Anregung von akustischen Resonanzen in HID Lampen infolge von Hochfrequenzbestandteilen der Leistung experimentell zu untersuchen. Basierend auf Labormessungen, wurde die Toleranzgrenze für den Wert der Welligkeit der Lampenleistung für die Halogen-Metalldampflampen (Nennleistung bis zu 250 W) ermittelt. Es konnte bestätigt werden, dass die Toleranzgrenze extrem von der Frequenz der Welligkeit und von der Brennposition der Lampe abhängt. Allgemein gesprochen kann eine Leistungswelligkeit mit einem Umfang von weniger als einem Prozent, wenn sie exakt bei der Resonanzfrequenz eingekoppelt wird, eine wahrnehmbare Bogeninstabilität anregen. Die Ergebnisse dieser Arbeit sind bereits in ein Normungsverfahren zur Schnittstelle zwischen Halogen-Metalldampflampen der Leistung im Bereich von 20 bis 150 W und elektronischen Vorschaltgeräten mit Rechteck-Betrieb eingeflossen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2096</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21432</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21432</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2096/original_ghasemi%20afshar_farhang_original.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2096/ghasemi_afshar_farhang.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
