<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:51Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3816">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3816</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-05-28</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:workingpaper</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">CO2-Balance for Buildings and Transportation in Hashtgerd New Town and Tehran Region </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arndt, Wulf-Holger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Huber, J√∂rg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>K√§mpfer, Rene</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nasrollahi, Farshad</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Due to the very high energy consumption in the Tehran region, CO2 emissions are also very high, with the residential and commercial buildings making up the largest share of 41% by 2008 and for transportation up to 25%. This publication tries to estimate the results of different planning fields in New Town Hashtgerd and Teheran-Karaj region in Iran regarding the development of CO2 emissions. Concerning this goal the expressiveness of the paper is limited to emissions caused by mixed-use-buildings, office-buildings and transportation. In order to evaluate the project‚Äôs impact in terms of CO2 reduction, the emission savings through the implementation of Young Cities‚Äô project findings and recommendations are estimated. The CO2 emissions of buildings and transportation are calculated based on their energy consumption, based on energy simulation, and the CO2 emission factors for different energy carriers. First the specific CO2 emissions are balanced for the project area of Hashtgerd New Town and then they are extrapolated for the whole former Tehran province. The CO2 emissions per capita and year are estimated and compared using two forecast scenarios for the year 2027 based on the preliminary results of the residential and office building as well as transport planning within the Young Cities project. The first scenario ‚Äúbusiness as usual 2027‚Ä? visualizes the CO2 emissions in 2027, with the development following the current trends in Iran. The second scenario ‚Äúplanning scenario 2027‚Ä? forecasts the CO2 emissions for 2027 assuming that two per cent of all new buildings are built according to the results of the Young Cities project and the suggested transportation system is implemented. The comparison of these two scenarios indicates the possible reduction of CO2 emissions for 2027 achieved through the implementation of the Young Cities‚Äô research findings. All areas monitored show significant potentials of possible emission savings which have been developed in the Young Cities project. It therefore appears that the implementation of the developed measures could lead to eminent energy and emission savings in comparison with conventional planning, construction and behaviour approaches. Anyway it needs to be born that the results provided in this paper is based on simulation algorithms trying to represent real conditions as far as possible. As long as those estimations are based on various assumptions meanderings can therefore not be excluded. To fulfil the requirements of an overall CO2 balance in Hashtgerd additional energy intensive fields like industry, agriculture and power plant need to consider as well. Nonetheless the results of this paper underline the effectiveness of the developed approaches and emphasise ways of future development in the Tehran-Karaj region.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Aufgrund des hohen Energieverbrauches in der Teheran-Region sind die CO2-Emissionen ebenfalls sehr hoch. Wohn- und B√ºrogeb√§ude machten 2008 einen Anteil an der CO2-Emission von 41% und Transport bis zu 25% aus. In dieser Ver√∂ffentlichung werden die Ergebnisse der verschiedenen Planungsfelder betreffend der Entwicklung von CO2-Emissionen in der New Town Hashtgerd und der Teheran-Karaj-Region im Iran dargestellt. Die Absch√§tzungen sind auf die Emissionen von Wohn-, Mischnutzung-, B√ºrogeb√§uden und Verkehr beschr√§nkt. Die Auswirkung der Planungsans√§tze im Projekt auf die CO2-Reduktion werde abgesch√§tzt und die Handlungsempfehlungen gegeben. Die CO2-Emissionen von Geb√§uden und von Verkehr werden basierend auf ihren Energieverbrauch mithilfe einer Energiesimulation und von CO2-Emission-Faktoren f√ºr verschiedene Energietr√§ger berechnet. Zuerst sind die spezifischen CO2-Emissionen f√ºr das Projekt der New Town Hashtgerd bestimmt worden. Dann wurden diese f√ºr die ganze ehemalige Teheran-Provinz extrapoliert. Die CO2-Emissionen pro Kopf und Jahr wurden in zwei Forecast-Szenarios f√ºr das Jahr 2027 gesch√§tzt und verglichen. Diese beruhen auf den Ergebnissen der Konzepte zu den Wohn- und B√ºrogeb√§uden sowie f√ºr die Verkehrsplanung in der New Town. Das erste Szenario ‚ÄûBAU 2027‚Äú zeigt die CO2-Emissionen im Jahre 2027, wenn die Entwicklung im Iran den aktuellen Trends folgt. Das zweite Szenario ‚ÄûPlanungsszenario 2027‚Äú prognostiziert die CO2-Emissionen f√ºr 2027, wenn zwei Prozent aller Neubauten entsprechend den Standards von New Towns errichtet werden und das vorgeschlagene Verkehrskonzept umgesetzt wird. Der Vergleich dieser beiden Szenarios zeigt die erreichbare Reduzierung von den CO2-Emissionen f√ºr 2027 bei Umsetzung der Young Cities-Forschungsergebnisse. Alle betrachteten Bereiche zeigen bedeutende Potenziale von m√∂glichen Emissionseinsparungen, welche im Young Cities-Projekt entwickelt worden sind. Die Umsetzung der entwickelten Ans√§tze f√ºhren im Vergleich zu herk√∂mmlichen Planungs-, Bau- und Verhaltensans√§tze zu deutlichen Energie- und Emissionseinsparungen. Hingewiesen werden muss, dass die dargestellten Ergebnisse auf Simulationsalgorithmen basieren, die wirkliche Zusammenh√§nge soweit wie m√∂glich modellieren. Die Sch√§tzungen basieren auf verschiedene Annahmen, sodass Abweichungen nicht ausgeschlossen werden k√∂nnen. F√ºr eine Gesamt-CO2-Bilanz m√ºssen noch andere energieintensive Bereiche betrachtet werden wie Industrie, Landwirtschaft und Energieerzeugung. Nichtsdestotrotz unterstreichen die Ergebnisse dieser Ver√∂ffentlichung die Wirksamkeit der entwickelten Ans√§tze und zeigen m√∂gliche nachhaltige Entwicklungspfade in der Teheran-Karaj-Region auf.</dc:description>
          <dc:contributor>Sponsored by German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF)</dc:contributor>
          <dc:date>2013-06-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>workingpaper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:workingpaper</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3816</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40640</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40640</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-7983-2584-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3816/No13_Co2%20Balance%20for%20Buildings%20and%20Transportation%20in%20Hashtge.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
