<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:23Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2613">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2613</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Simulation-based Investigation of Interface Delamination in Plastic IC Packages under Temperature and Moisture Loading</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Simulation-basierte Untersuchung der Interface Delamination in Plastic IC Packages unter Temperatur und Feuchte</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Shirangi, Mohammad Hossein</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Interface delamination between dissimilar materials is one of the major threats to the structural integrity and reliability of multi-layered structures. In many of these structures, such as micro-electronic assemblies, one or more of the materials are made of polymers. In this case, moisture poses a significant threat to the reliability of these products and can be regarded as one of the principal causes of many premature failures. Epoxy Molding Compounds (EMCs) are widely used as encapsulating materials in semiconductor packaging industry. The interface between EMC and the copper-based leadframe in plastic IC packages has been found to be one of the weakest joints. Most of cracks in plastic encapsulated microcircuits (PEMs) initiate and propagate in this interface. The crack propagation facilitates, when the EMC materials absorb moisture from the environment. This research provides a com-prehensive understanding of the primary mechanisms responsible for the interfacial delamination due to the presence of moisture. The experimental and numerical investigations of this research can be divided into four catego-ries: • The process-induced stresses due to cure shrinkage of the epoxy molding compound and thermal mismatch between the materials in plastic IC packages were investigated. A numerical solution was proposed and the method was benchmarked by comparing the warpage of a simple bimaterial beam with the results from Finite Element (FE) analysis. • Moisture diffusion (absorption, desorption and re-sorption) experiments were carried out on bulk EMC samples. Several sample geometry and aging conditions were used to understand the anomalous behavior of these materials in terms of moisture uptake. The results of these tests explain the complicated mechanism of moisture diffusion in epoxy molding compounds. Two highlights of these experiments are identifying the dual-stage moisture absorption during exposure to humid environments and residual moisture content upon baking the plastic parts. Additionally, the moisture diffusion in the plastic package was modeled by FE analysis. Since the standard FE tools can only solve the problem of conventional Fickian diffusion, novel si-mulation techniques were suggested and verified to account for the non-Fickian dual stage moisture diffusion during moisture absorption and residual moisture content upon baking of these products at elevated temperature. • The hygroscopic swelling of the polymers upon moisture absorption is also a major threat to the reliability of PEMs. The value of the coefficient of hygroscopic swelling was determined experimentally by warpage analysis of bimaterial beams and implemented in the FE code. • Fracture tests were carried out to measure the interfacial adhesion in terms of interfacial frac-ture toughness. Effects of temperature, aging in dry and humid conditions and mode angle were investigated. It was observed that the exposure of a Cu/EMC bimaterial beam to mois-ture prior to fracture tests results in a degradation of the adhesion. This degradation is the re-sult of the diffusion of water in the interface. For samples that were shortly exposed to humid environment the degradation was partially reversible by applying an appropriate heat treatment at mild annealing conditions. However, long-term aging in humid condition caused a permanent adhesion loss, which was attributed to the effect of hydrogen bonding between wa-ter molecules and polymer chains at the interface. The investigation of the delamination risk in a plastic IC package by FE analysis showed that the proposed method can be well used to evaluate the critical crack length in a package. Additional-ly, the method may be used in order to reduce the delamination risks by design optimization. Moreover the predictive model provides a useful tool for selecting proper material combinations. This enables rapid virtual qualification technique by experimental and numerical fracture me-chanics approach.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Grenzschicht-Delamination zwischen verschiedenen Materialien ist eine der größten Herausfor-derungen für die strukturmechanische Zuverlässigkeit von Mehrschichtsystemen. Viele Produkte, wie beispielsweise mikroelektronische Baugruppen, enthalten polymer-basierte Materialien. Da Polymere Feuchtigkeit aufnehmen, stellen die mit Feuchtigkeit verbundenen Phänomene erhebli-che Probleme für die Zuverlässigkeit dieser Produkte dar und können als eine Hauptursache für viele vorzeitige Ausfälle betrachtet werden. In der Halbleiterindustrie haben sich als Verkapselungsmaterialien Epoxid-Moldmassen, soge-nannte Epoxy Molding Compounds (EMCs) etabliert. Die Grenzfläche zwischen EMC und Kup-fer-basierten Leadframes in Plastic verkapselten IC-Packages ist als schwächste Grenzfläche identifiziert. Die meisten Risse in Plastic Encapsulated Microcircuits (PEMs) beginnen und ver-größern sich an dieser Grenzfläche. Diese Dissertation bietet eine umfassende Untersuchung der Mechanismen, die für die Grenzschicht-Delamination verantwortlich sind. Die experimentellen und numerischen Untersuchungen dieser Forschung lassen sich in vier Kate-gorien unterteilen: • Die prozessinduzierten Spannungen werden untersucht, darunter Spannungen infolge Schrumpfung der Epoxid-Moldmasse und Spannungen aus dem Unterschied zwischen den thermischen Ausdehnungskoeffizienten der Grenzschicht-Materialien. Eine numerische Lö-sungsmethode wird vorgeschlagen und durch den Vergleich der Verwölbung eines einfachen Bi-Material Streifens mit den Ergebnissen aus der Finite Elemente (FE) Analyse verifiziert. • Es werden Experimente zur Untersuchung der Feuchtediffusion (Absorption, Desorption und Re-Sorption) mit EMC Proben durchgeführt. Mehrere Probengeometrien und Alterungsbedin-gungen werden verwendet, um das ungewöhnliche Verhalten dieser Materialien in Bezug auf Feuchtigkeit zu verstehen. Zwei der wichtigsten Erkenntnisse sind die Ermittlung der zweistu-figen (dual stage) Feuchtigkeitsaufnahme während der Absorption und Restfeuchte nach dem Desorptions-Test. Zudem wird die Feuchtediffusion in den EMCs durch FE-Analyse nachges-tellt. Da die Standard FE-Tools nur das Problem der konventionellen FICK’schen Diffusion di-rekt lösen können, werden neuartige Simulationsverfahren vorgeschlagen und überprüft, um die Nicht-FICK’sche zweistufige Feuchtigkeitsdiffusion zu berücksichtigen. • Die hygroskopische Quellung der Polymere aufgrund der Feuchtigkeitsaufnahme verändert den Ausdehnungsunterschied zwischen den Materialien und kann so die Zuverlässigkeit von PEMs verringern. Der Koeffizient der hygroskopischen Schwellung kann experimentell durch Vorwölbungsmessung der Bimaterial-Streifen ermittelt und in den FE-Code umgesetzt wer-den. • Zur Bestimmung der Haftfestigkeit in Bezug auf Grenzflächenbruchzähigkeit sind bruchme-chanische Experimente durchgeführt worden. Dabei waren die Einflüsse von Temperatur, Al-terung in trockenen und feuchten Bedingungen und Mode-Winkel zu untersuchen. Die Lage-rung eines Cu/EMC Bi-Material Streifens in Feuchtigkeit führt zu einer Verschlechterung der Adhäsion zwischen EMC und Leadframe. Diese Adhäsionsverschlechterung kann auf den Bindungsabbau zwischen Polymermolekülen und Leadframe zurückgeführt werden und ist das Ergebnis der Diffusion von Wasser in die Grenzfläche. Bei Proben, die sich kurzfristig in einer feuchten Umgebung befanden, ist der Abbau teilweise durch die Anwendung einer geeigneten Hitzebehandlung reversibel. Dagegen verursacht eine langfristige Lagerung in feuchten Zustand eine ständige Abnahme der Haftfestigkeit, die auf die Wirkung von Wasserstoffbrücken zwischen Wassermolekülen und Polymerketten an der Grenzfläche zurückgeführt wurde. Die Untersuchung der Delamination in einem Plastic IC Package durch FE-Analyse zeigt, dass die vorgeschlagene Methode erfolgsreich eingesetzt werden kann, um die kritische Risslänge in einem Package zu bewerten. Darüber hinaus kann die Methode verwendet werden, um die Dela-mination durch optimiertes Design zu vermeiden. Das im Rahmen der Dissertation entwickelte Modell kann als Werkzeug eingesetzt werden, um geeignete Materialkombinationen auszuwählen. Es ermöglicht eine schnelle Bauteilbewertung durch Methoden der experimentellen und nu-merischen Bruchmechanik.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-09-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2613</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27687</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27687</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-86955-433-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2613/shirangi_mohammadhossein.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
