<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:22Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3255">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3255</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Local Structure of Al-based Amorphous Alloys after Microalloying by Element Substitution and after Ball Milling</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Lokale Struktur von Al-basierten Amorphen Legierungen nach Mikrolegierungen durch Elementsubstitution und nach Kugelmahlen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Liu, Yao</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Structural stability of glassy Al85Ni10La5 as-atomized powder was investigated after ball mill-ing using scanning electron microscopy (SEM), differential scanning calorimetry (DSC), X-ray diffractometry (XRD), transmission electron microscopy (TEM), and X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS). Fcc-Al nanocrystals were found after ball milling. The crystallization behaviour upon thermal treatment depends on the deformation level. Because the solute atoms Ni and La diffuse out of the Al crystal and create a solute rich area around the crystal, the composition of the residual amorphous phase changes towards higher contents of Ni and La. Furthermore, crystallization under ball milling depends on the ball milling temperature indi-cating a combined role of temperature and plastic deformation for the crystallization behavior of Al85Ni10La5 powder during ball milling. The coordination number N of Ni obtained by XAS measurements decreases exponentially as a function of ball milling time. The exponential decrease in N(Ni) during plastic deformation was described in the frame of a shear band model, in which N(Ni) is 6 outside the shear bands and 5 within the shear bands. The local structures around nickel and cobalt atoms in Al86Ni8Y6 and Al86Ni6Co2Y4.5La1.5 bulk amorphous alloys were measured by XAS. The same local structure around Ni and Co atoms was found which is ascribed to a site substitution of Ni by Co atoms in the amorphous structure. The configurational entropy is estimated to be the main thermodynamic driving force for the increase in glass forming ability when substituting Ni by Co and Y by La. The cluster-line model is not supported by our results. The local structure after minor substitution of Ni by Co, Ge, Pd, Ag and Zr in Al-Ni-Y and Al-Ni-La systems was also investigated by XAS. Three groups of elements which are ‚Äúsmall‚Ä?, ‚Äúmedium‚Ä? and ‚Äúlarge‚Ä? atoms were identified and discussed in terms of coordination number as a function of the interatomic distance. The most striking result is the bond-shortening be-tween the absorbing atoms and Al resulting in large changes of the effective radii compared to their metallic radii and a concomitant reduction of the number of nearest neighbours. This effect is most pronounced for the small atoms, especially for Ag atoms, allowing the Ag atoms to have the same local environment as Ni and Co.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die strukturelle Stabilit√§t von pulververd√ºstem Al85Ni10La5 Glas wurde nach Kugelmahlen mittels Rasterelektronenmikroskopie (SEM), differentieller W√§rmekalorimetrie (DSC), R√∂ntgendiffraktion (XRD), Transmissionselektronenmikroskopie (TEM) und R√∂ntgenabsorptionsspektroskopie (XAS) untersucht. Fcc-Al Nanokristalle wurden nach Kugelmahlen nachgewiesen. Das Kristallisationsverhalten bei thermischer Behandlung h√§ngt vom Grad der Verformung ab. Da Ni und La aus dem Al-Kristall herausdiffundieren und eine H√ºlle um den Kristall bilden, die angereichert ist an den gel√∂sten Atomen Ni und La, √§ndert sich die Zusammensetzung der amorphen Phase hin zu h√∂heren Konzentrationen von Ni und La. Weiterhin h√§ngt das Kristallisationsverhalten w√§hrend des Kugelmahlens von der Mahltemperatur ab, was auf eine kombinierte Rolle von Temperatur und plastischer Deformation bei der Kristallisation von Al85Ni10La5 w√§hrend des Kugelmahlens hinweist. Die aus R√∂ntgenabsorptionsspektroskopie-Experimenten abgeleitete Koordinationszahl N von Ni nimmt als Funktion der Zeit des Kugelmahlens exponentiell ab. Die exponentielle Abnahme von N(Ni) unter plastischer Deformation wurde im Rahmen eines Scherbandmodells, in dem N(Ni) ‚âà 6 au√üerhalb des Scherbandes und N(Ni) ‚âà 5 innerhalb des Scherbandes ist, beschrieben. Die lokalen Strukturen um die Nickel- und Kobalt-Atome in den bulk-amorphen Legierungen Al86Ni8Y6 und Al86Ni6Co2Y4.5La1.5 wurden mittels XAS untersucht. Um Ni und Co wurden die gleichen lokalen Strukturen gefunden, was der Platz-Substitution von Ni durch Co in der amorphen Struktur zugeschrieben wird. Die Konfigurationsentropie ist die wesentliche thermodynamische Kraft f√ºr die Zunahme der Glasbildungsf√§higkeit wenn Ni durch Co und Y durch La ersetzt wird. Das Clusterline Modell wird durch unsere Ergebnisse nicht gest√ºtzt. Die lokale Struktur nach geringf√ºgigem Ersetzen von Ni durch Co, Ge, Pd, Ag und Zr in Al-Ni-Y und Al-Ni-La Systemen wurde ebenfalls mittels XAS untersucht. Drei Gruppen von Elementen wurden identifiziert und in Bezug auf die Koordinationszahl als Funktion des interatomaren Abstandes diskutiert: ‚Äûkleine‚Äú, ‚Äûmittlere‚Äú und ‚Äûgro√üe‚Äú Atome. Das am meisten hervorstechende Ergebnis ist die verk√ºrzte Bindungsl√§nge zwischen dem absorbierenden Atom und Al, was gro√üe √Ñnderungen der effektiven Radien im Vergleich zu deren metallischen Radien und gleichzeitig eine Abnahme der Anzahl von n√§chsten Nachbarn zur Folge hat. Dieser Effekt ist am st√§rksten ausgepr√§gt f√ºr die kleinen Atome, insbesondere f√ºr Ag-Atome, so dass die Ag-Atome die gleiche lokale Umgebung besitzen wie die Ni- und Co-Atome.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-03-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3255</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34523</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34523</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3255/yao_liu.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
