<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:09Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2565">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2565</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Optimierungspotenziale im Wirtschaftsverkehr durch bestellerseitige Kooperation. Untersuchung des Ansatzes einer Beschaffungs-/Bestellerkooperation als ein Instrument für eine effiziente und stadtverträgliche Gestaltung des Wirtschaftsverkehrs</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Potential of optimization in commercial transport by cooperation of orderer. Analysis of procurement/orderer cooperation as an instrument for efficient and urban compatible commercial transport</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arndt, Wulf-Holger</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Optimierungspotenziale im Wirtschaftsverkehr durch bestellerseitige Kooperation Es wird ein neuer Ansatz zur Verkehrs- und Kostenreduzierung im Wirtschaftsverkehr (genauer Lieferverkehr) untersucht. Die virtuelle Zusammenfassung von Bestellungen z.B. über eine Internet-/Intranetplattform - eine Empfänger/Besteller¬kooperation kann möglicherweise zur Bündelung der Lieferverkehre führen. Aufgrund von neuen Produktionsmethoden und Managementstrategien zur Stärkung der Eigenverantwortlichkeit von Unternehmens¬bereichen und Abteilungen laufen Bestellprozesse oft separat und unkoordiniert ab. Eine Folge ist die Zersplitterung der Bestellungen und die geringe Auslastung von Lieferverkehren. Neben dieser Dezentralisierung führt „Outsourcen“ dazu, dass Bestellungen immer kleinteiliger und weniger zusammengefasst werden. Um trotzdem Kosten zu sparen versuchen Lieferanten Bündelungen durchzuführen. Dies geschieht bei Spedition am ehesten unternehmensintern aber auch in Netzwerken oder bei der City-Logistik auch überbetrieblich als Versenderkooperation. Dies ist aber nur die eine Seite des Beschaffungsprozesses. Außerdem ist der Versenderkooperation durch Konkurrenz¬situationen Grenzen gesetzt. Auf der anderen Seite ist eine Bündelung (der Bestellungen) ebenfalls denkbar, wenn sich daraus Vorteile für die Besteller ergeben, z.B. Preisreduktionen aufgrund größerer Bestellmengen. Das wäre eine Besteller- bzw. Empfängerkooperation. Die Besteller/Empfänger schließen sich zusammen und nehmen durch die Bestellungsbündelung den Versendern und Transporteuren quasi die Abstimmungs-Probleme einer Kooperation untereinander teilweise ab. Werden Lieferprozesse mit in die Kooperation integriert, handelt es sich um eine Beschaffungs-kooperation. Früher war eine solche Bündelung auf Bestellerseite durch große bestellende Einheiten (Werksgröße, Zentralisierung, hohe Produktionstiefe,...) per se gegeben. Diese Produktions-methoden sind nicht einfach wieder herstellbar. Eine virtuelle Bündelung z.B. mittels E Procurement (u.a. Internet-Bestellplattform) wäre heute zeitgemäß. Diese realisiert quasi eine virtuelle Zentralbestellung innerbetrieblich für dezentral organisierte Strukturen oder überbetrieblich zwischen unabhängigen Unternehmen. Die hauptsächlichen Vorteile einer solchen Kooperation sind neben Prozessvereinfachung, Transparenzerhöhung sowie Verbesserung der Steuerung und Kontrolle bei der Beschaffung, Kosteneinsparung durch Aufwandsminimierung und Nutzung von Preisrabatten durch Bündelung der Bestellmengen von mehreren Bestellern. Im Wirtschaftsverkehr sind Effizienzsteigerung und Verkehrsreduzierung durch Kooperationen noch wenig untersucht. Insbesondere Planungsinstrumente zur Förderung solcher Kooperationen müssen entwickelt werden. Innerhalb dieser Arbeit fanden umfangreiche Erhebungen statt. In Felduntersuchungen an der Technische Universität Berlin, verschiedenen Gewerbe¬gebieten, Handels¬einrichtungen (Shop-in-Shop-Systemen) und Bürohäusern wurden Beschaffungs¬prozesse, Organisationsprobleme und Kooperations¬neigungen analysiert. Auf Grundlage der Erkenntnisse aus diesen quantitativen Befragungen und zusätzlichen qualitativen Experten¬interviews zur Beschaffung sind verschiedene Varianten des Ansatzes entwickelt worden. In einer abschließenden deutschland¬weiten Online-Unternehmensbefragung mit 1.700 auswertbaren Antworten, einer Conjoint-Analyse und weiteren Experteninterviews wurden verkehrliche Wirkungen untersucht, Kooperations¬ansätze bewertet und weiter entwickelt. Wulf-Holger Arndt</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Potential of optimization in commercial transport by cooperation of orderer This Book introduce in an approach to reducing traffic and costs in commercial transport (delivery transport). The virtual summary of orders e.g. by an Internet/Intranet platform - a receiver/orderer cooperation- can possibly lead to the bundling of the delivery traffics. The demand of commercial transport (business and goods transport) has dramatically changed over the last years. Current trends in globalisation and the change of general conditions of trade, associated with changes in economic structures, play a central role. A few examples of effects important for commercial transport are the expansion and internationalisation of markets, a sharing of labour, which is both increasingly distance-intensive and geographically independent, higher requirements regarding the timing of goods provision and an increase of complexity in the logistics of providing supplies and services. Many of the accepted new logistics technologies lead to an increase in traffic. An increasing number of small-component products have to be transported more frequently over longer distances. Enterprises react on these changes and on increasing competition with reduction of costs in production and reproduction as well as with reducing of capital bond. These concepts of rationalisation include outsourcing, modular technologies, abolition of stores, or global sourcing for lowest purchasing prices. Logistic strategies such as ‘just in time delivery’ and ‘hub and spoke networks’ of freight forwarder may lead to an increase in trip frequency and to more commercial transport on roads. Mostly of the approaches to save cost in this situation are supplier and/or forwarding business cooperations, also known as city logistics. The past models of supplier cooperations have rather modest success. Competition and coordination problems are two of the reasons. By bundling of orders, however, the problematic coordination of deliver by of carrier agents could be avoided in the first place. E-procurement systems with internet/intranet platform may be use for order bundling leading. The whole approach would result in traffic and cost reduction. The research in the area of orderer/receiver or procurement cooperation is, however, still pending. For participating companies (or public institutions) a procurement cooperation has clear advantages: use of scale effects (price discounts) by higher order quantities, better order competence, more transparency (especially by use of e-procurement) and process cost savings in procurement. On the social level, the bundling of orders leads to higher vehicle load factor and traffic reduction. The research of orderer/receiver or procurement cooperation is, however, still pending. Especially planning instruments for promotion of cooperation have to be developed. The effects of procurement cooperation, impacts of concepts and planning instruments for promotion were analyzed in this book. For this investigation a combination of different surveys was developed: An Germany-wide online survey with 1.700 responders for basic company and procurement data as well as traffic impacts of the approach, a conjoint analysis to evaluate the preferences of types of procurement cooperation and expert interviews to analyse the procurement decisions and prerequisites for implementation of procurement cooperation. Wulf-Holger Arndt</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-07-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2565</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26982</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26982</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2565/arndt_wulfholger.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2565/arndt_wulfholger_anhang.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
