<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:52Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1861">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1861</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Online-Analyse von Teer aus der Biomassevergasung mit Lasermassenspektrometrie</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Online-Analysis of tar from biomass gasification with laser-mass-spectrometry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Neubauer, York</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Biomasse bietet ein großes Potenzial für eine Vielzahl von Wegen zur energetischen Nutzung in einem geschlossenen Kohlenstoffkreislauf. Im Gegensatz zur Gewinnung von Strom aus den erneuerbaren Quellen Sonne und Wind, kann Biomasse als Energieträger gespeichert werden und erlaubt dadurch eine kontinuierliche Nutzbarkeit. Sie kann entweder direkt energetisch genutzt werden oder auch in flüssige und gasförmige Energieträger gewandelt werden. Biomasse ist sie die einzige erneuerbare Quelle für Kohlenstoff und damit eine regenerative Quelle für Grundchemikalien und Kraftstoffe auf Kohlenwasserstoffbasis. Die Technologien zur energetischen Biomassewandlung sind so vielfältig wie ihre Erscheinungsformen. Physikalische, biologische und thermochemische Prozesse sind für die energetische Nutzung entwickelt und optimiert worden. Die vorliegende Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit dem thermochemischen Prozess der Vergasung und den damit verbundenen technologischen Herausforderungen. Ein Hauptgrund für den bislang mäßigen kommerziellen Erfolg dieser Technologie ist das Entstehen von kondensierbaren Substanzen (Teer) im Vergasungsprozess. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wird Teer im Allgemeinen betrachtet und es werden Methoden für eine schnelle, informationsreiche online-Teeranalyse diskutiert. Zu Beginn wird ein Überblick über die energetische Nutzung von Biomasse unter besonderer Berücksichtigung der Vergasung gegeben. Anschließend werden Definition und Klassifizierung von Teer behandelt. Ein historischer Rückblick thermochemischer Wandlungsprozesse zeigt, dass Teer ein wertvolles Produkt darstellte, das die Menschheit über Jahrhunderte gezielt genutzt hat. Mit dem Beginn der Industrialisierung und der Entwicklung der chemischen Wissenschaft wurde die Analyse von Teer und seiner Bestandteile intensiver betrieben. Neue Analysemethoden wurden entwickelt. Verfügbare Methoden für die Teeranalyse werden vorgestellt. Laser-Massenspektrometrie bietet ein großes Potenzial für die detaillierte Teeranalyse. Grundlagen der Massenspektrometrie und der Laser-Ionisation werden beschrieben. Es werden Beispiele für Messungen mit Laser-Massenspektrometern in verwandten Anwendungen diskutiert sowie die Vor- und Nachteile verschiedener Ansätze für eine schnelle und detaillierte Teeranalyse analysiert. In dieser Arbeit werden Gaschromatographie und Massenspektrometrie für die online-Teeranalyse im Produktgas eines Biomassevergasers angewendet. Ein kommerziell erhältliches Labor-GC/MS wurde modifiziert. Zusätzlich zur eingebauten Ionenquelle, basierend auf Elektronenionisation, wurde das System mit einem Laser-Ionisationssystem ausgestattet. Die Modifikationen des Messsystems werden beschrieben und Vergleichsmessungen werden vorgestellt. Für die Analysen im Realgas, für welche das System vorgesehen ist, wurde eine Wirbelschichtvergasungsanlage gebaut. Design und Aufbau dieser Anlage werden in einem separaten Kapitel beschrieben. Messergebnisse aus den Realgasmessungen werden präsentiert. Von besonderem Stellenwert die online-Teeranalysen im Rohgas vor und im Gasstrom nach einem Reaktor zur katalytischen Teerreformierung. Abschließend werden weitere Anforderungen und erforderliche Verbesserungen des Messsystems besprochen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Biomass offers a great potential for multiple ways of energetic use within a closed carbon cycle. In contrast to the generation of electricity by the renewable sources sunlight and wind, biomass can be stored and can therefore be utilized continuously. Furthermore it can be converted into liquid and gaseous energy carriers. Biomass is present in many different forms and is widely distributed what makes it more difficult for processing. Nevertheless it is the only renewable source of carbon, making it a renewable source for base chemicals and fuels. Conversion technologies are as manifold as there are forms of biomass. Physical, biochemical and thermochemical processes for biomass conversion are available. The following work deals with the thermochemical process of gasification and the technological challenges incorporated with its use. A main barrier for market penetration of gasification technology up to date is the evolution of condensible hydrocarbons (tar) in the gasification process. Much work has been carried out to overcome this problem and to allow for stable gasifier operating conditions at reasonable costs. Anyhow, tar still remains a larger problem for manufacturers entering the market turning their prototypes into continuously operating plants. For these reasons, tar is still considered to be the bottleneck of gasification technology. For solving tar related problems it is necessary to know about the amount of tar and about its composition. Measuring tar is as challenging as dealing with this mixture of substances in the process. Over the years many tar analysis methods were tested and applied and in recent years a standardized procedure has been developed. Nevertheless tar measurement is time consuming, requires specific knowledge and instrumentation and is therefore expensive. That is one reason why tar is not controlled on a routine basis and therefore remains problematic. In this thesis tar is discussed in general and methods for fast, information rich online tar analysis are examined. In the beginning an overview about technologies for energetic biomass use with special emphasis to gasification is given. Tar is defined and a review in history of thermochemical biomass conversion shows, that tar has been a valuable product used by mankind over many centuries. With the beginning of industrialization and the development of chemical science the analysis of tar components was studied more intense and new analysis methods evolved. Methods which can be used for the analysis of tar in general will be discussed. Mass spectrometry and especially laser mass spectrometry offer a great potential for detailed tar analyses. Fundamentals of mass spectrometry and of laser ionization are given. Examples of measurements with laser-MS in related fields of analysis are discussed. Benefits and drawbacks of different approaches for a fast and detailed online analysis are examined. For this work gaschromatography and mass spectrometry are applied for online tar analysis in the product gas of a biomass gasifier. A commercially available benchtop GC/MS was modified and in addition to the built in ion source based on electron ionisation the system was equipped with an optical access to make use of multiphoton laser ionization. The modifications of a the system are described and comparison measurements are presented. For real gas analyses that the system is intended for a laboratory scale gasificytion system was built. Design and setup of this plant are described in a separate chapter. Measurement results from real gas analysis are presented showing the diversity of tar concentrations between raw and treated gas. Further requirements and needed future improvements will be discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-08-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1861</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-19417</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-19417</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-938720-32-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1861/original_york_neubauer.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1861/neubauer_york.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
