<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:28Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2634">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2634</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Phosphate Adsorption onto Granular Ferric Hydroxide (GFH) for Wastewater Reuse</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Untersuchungen zur Phosphatadsorption an Granuliertes Eisenhydroxid (GEH) für die Abwasserwiederverwendung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sperlich, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Adsorption onto Granular Ferric Hydroxide (GFH), a commercially available, synthetic adsorbent is studied as treatment process for phosphorus removal from wastewater. The objective is to evaluate the suitability of this process alternative for advanced wastewater treatment and reuse. Within this scope, the present work focusses on quantification of competitive adsorption of phosphate and development of a regeneration process that allows multiple application of GFH. Furthermore, breakthrough prediction of GFH fixed-bed columns is assessed. Adsorption of phosphate in artificial model solutions, natural and waste waters onto GFH was studied in batch and fixed-bed column experiments. Equilibrium isotherms and adsorption edges show that phosphate adsorption is strongly pH dependent. High capacities of up to 24 mg/g P (at pH 6 and an equilibrium concentration of 2 mg/L P) can be reached. Presence of calcium is shown to improve adsorption of phosphate. This is supposed to be the reason for higher capacities in waste and drinking water as compared to DI water and membrane concentrates. The diffuse double layer model can in principle be used to describe phosphate adsorption onto GFH, but fails to describe simultaneous adsorption of phosphate and calcium. Whereas generally effective for phosphate removal from NF concentrates, GFH adsorption cannot be recommended for membrane concentrate treatment. Since membrane concentrates are often supersaturated with respect to calcium carbonate and/ or calcium phosphate compounds, this can lead to scaling and head loss in the fixed-bed column. Chemical precipitation can effectively remove phosphate and calcium ions and thus reduce the scaling potential of membrane concentrates. This may allow for higher recoveries in the NF/ RO process. Rapid small-scale column tests (RSSCTs) were shown to be a useful tool for simulation of fixed-bed columns. Isotherm results can be used to provide a rough estimation of operation time, i.e. the ideal breakthrough point of a fixed-bed column, but are of limited use due to the strong influence of mass transfer on the shape of the breakthrough curve. RSSCTs using different empty-bed contact times show that phosphate adsorption kinetics onto GFH are very slow and result in asymptotically shaped breakthrough curves. Analysis of breakthrough data proves that operation of two GFH beds in series can contribute to a more efficient use of the adsorbent. Breakthrough curves were modeled using the homogeneous surface diffusion model (HSDM) and two of its derivatives, the constant pattern homogeneous surface diffusion model (CPHSDM) and the linear driving force model (LDF). Input parameters, the Freundlich isotherm constants, and mass transfer coefficients for liquid- and solid-phase diffusion were determined and analysed for their influence on the shape of the breakthrough curve. HSDM simulation results predict the breakthrough of phosphate, and the also investigated adsorbates arsenate, salicylic acid, and DOC satisfactorily. Due to a very slow intraparticle diffusion and hence higher Biot numbers, LDF and CPHSDM could not describe arsenate breakthrough correctly. Based on this observation, limits of applicability were defined for LDF and CPHSDM. When designing fixed-bed adsorbers, model selection based on known or estimated Biot and Stanton numbers is possible. GFH is stable at high pH and can be efficiently regenerated using 1 M NaOH. Approximately 80 % of the initially bound phosphate can be eluated. However, the incomplete desorption leads to decreasing capacities with each additional use. Multiple uses are thus limited, but at least three operation cycles are feasible. GFH desorption is fast and most of the desorbable phosphate could be eluated using 4 - 6 bed volumes of regenerant. A reuse of the regenerant solution is possible. Despite high phosphate concentrations in the regenerate, 61 - 85 % of the bound phosphate could be desorbed. Phosphate can be recovered from the highly concentrated regenerant stream (up to 3.5 g/L P). Precipitation with lime water resulted in 90 % P removal and a plant available precipitate. Regeneration and multiple use of GFH can significantly increase operation times of fixed-bed adsorbers and be an economically favourable option compared to single use. Laboratory results were confirmed in pilot-scale experiments in Beijing, China which show that selective nutrient removal by adsorption onto GFH after a membrane bioreactor (MBR) can maintain a total phosphorus concentration of &lt; 0.03 mg/L P, thus preventing eutrophication of artificial lakes. In conclusion, GFH adsorption is an effective and promising treatment technique to remove phosphorus from waste and surface waters. Economic use is limited to special applications where near zero effluent concentrations are required. Regeneration and serial operation prolonge operation times of fixed-bed columns and decrease the specific adsorbent costs. Printed Version available: Verlag PAPIERFLIEGER, www.papierflieger-verlag.de</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Gegenüber den herkömmlichen Verfahren zur Phosphatentfernung kann es bei bestimmten Fragestellungen der Abwasserwiederverwendung sinnvoll sein, Phosphat bis auf ganz geringe Restkonzentrationen zu entfernen. Dies kann beispielsweise bei der Wiederverwendung von Abwasser in Landschaft gestaltenden künstlichen Gewässern der Fall sein. Dass Eisenhydroxide hohe Adsorptionskapazitäten für Phosphat zeigen, ist seit langem bekannt. Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit ist es, die Phosphatadsorption an kommerziell verfügbare Adsorbentien auf Eisenbasis hinsichtlich der Eignung für die weitestgehende Abwasserreinigung und Abwasserwiederverwendung zu bewerten. Im Mittelpunkt der Untersuchungen steht Granuliertes Eisenhydroxid (GEH), das vor allem in der Arsenentfernung eingesetzt wird. Zentrale Fragestellung ist die Quantifizierung der konkurrierenden Adsorption von Abwasserinhaltsstoffen und der damit einhergehenden Kapazitätsverluste und die Entwicklung eines Regenerationsverfahrens, das die Wiedernutzung des Adsorbens ermöglicht. Schließlich soll eine Methodik zur Vorhersage des Durchbruchs von Festbettadsorbern mittels mathematischer Modelle erarbeitet werden. Laborversuche mit Abwasser, natürlichen Wässern und Modelllösungen zeigen eine starke pH-Abhängigkeit der Adsorption von Phosphat an GEH. Hohe Beladungen von bis zu 24 mg/g P (bei pH 6 und einer Gleichgewichtskonzentration von 2 mg/L P) werden erreicht. In Abwasser und Trinkwasser werden höhere Beladungen beobachtet als in vollentsalztem Wasser. Als Grund wird die Anwesenheit von Calcium vermutet, die die Adsorption von Phosphat an GEH deutlich verbessert. Eine modellhafte Beschreibung der Adsorption mittels des Doppelschichtmodells ist prinzipiell möglich, eine Simulation der simultanen Adsorption von Phosphat und Calcium gelingt jedoch nicht. Mittels Isothermenversuchen kann der ideale Durchbruch von Festbettfiltern berechnet werden, dessen Aussagekraft jedoch aufgrund des großen Einflusses der Kinetik auf die Form der Durchbruchskurve begrenzt ist. Kleinfilterversuche (Rapid small-scale column tests - RSSCT) zeigen, dass die Kinetik der Adsorption von Phosphat an GEH sehr langsam ist und zu asymptotisch geformten Druchbruchskurven führt. Anhand von Durchbruchsdaten konnte zudem gezeigt werden, dass die Reihen-Wechsel-Schaltung von Festbettadsorbern eine bessere Ausnutzung des Adsorbens ermöglicht. Experimentell aufgenommene Durchbruchskurven lassen sich mit dem Oberflächendiffusionsmodell (HSDM) und zwei abgeleiteten Modellen, CPHSDM und LDF, darstellen. Der Einfluss der experimentell bestimmten Modelleingabeparameter wie der Freundlich-Isothermenkonstanten und der Stoffübergangskoeffizienten der Film- und Korndiffusion auf die Form der Durchbruchskurve wurde analysiert. Der Durchbruch von Phosphat und den ebenfalls untersuchten Adsorbaten Arsenat, Salicylsäure und DOC konnte mit dem HSDM zufriedenstellend wiedergegeben werden. Durch den sehr langsamen inneren Stofftransport treten höhere Biot-Zahlen auf, bei denen LDF und CPHSDM den Durchbruch nicht korrekt vorhersagen können, wie für Arsenat beobachtet wurde. Anhand dieser Ergebnisse wurden Anwendungsgrenzen für LDF und CPHSDM definiert und gezeigt, dass eine Modellauswahl mittels bekannter oder abgeschätzter Biot- und Stanton-Zahlen möglich ist. GEH ist auch bei hohen pH-Werten stabil und eine Regeneration mittels NaOH ist möglich. Etwa 80 % des anfangs adsorbierten Phosphats können eluiert werden. Die unvollständige Desorption führt zu Kapazitätsverlusten mit jeder Wiedernutzung, deren Anzahl dadurch begrenzt ist. Es sind mindestens drei Betriebszyklen ohne Wechsel des Materials möglich. Die Desorption von Phosphat ist schnell und der Hauptteil des gebundenen Phosphats kann innerhalb der ersten 4–6 Bettvolumen eluiert werden. Die gebrauchte Natronlauge kann wieder verwendet werden. Eine Phosphorrückgewinnung aus der konzentrierten Lauge (bis zu 3.5 g/L P) ist möglich. Die Regeneration und Mehrfachnutzung von GEH erhöht die Standzeiten der Adsorber deutlich und ermöglicht einen kostengünstigeren Einsatz des Verfahrens. Die Ergebnisse der Laborexperimente zur Adsorption und Regeneration wurden durch Pilotversuche auf einer Kläranlage in Peking (China) bestätigt. Durch selektive Nährstoffentfernung mittels Adsorption an GEH anschließend an einen Membranbioreaktor kann eine Ablaufkonzentration von &lt; 0.03 mg/L P Gesamtphosphor sicher eingehalten und die Eutrophierung künstlicher Seen verhindert werden. Zusammenfassend ist festzustellen, dass die Adsorption an GEH für die Phosphorentfernung aus Ab- und Oberflächenwasser geeignet ist. Ein ökonomisch sinnvoller Einsatz beschränkt sich auf Anwendungen, in denen sehr geringe Restkonzentrationen benötigt werden. Regeneration und Reihen-Wechsel-Schaltung verlängern die Standzeiten der Adsorber und verringern die spezifischen Materialkosten. Gedruckte Version im Verlag erschienen: PAPIERFLIEGER, www.papierflieger-verlag.de</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-09-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2634</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-89720-560-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2634/sperlich_alexander.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
