<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:41Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3782">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3782</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-06-30</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:book</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Green Office Buildings : Low Energy Demand through Architectural Energy Efficiency</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nasrollahi, Farshad</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The first step towards creating an environmental design and identifying the possibilities for climate responsive architecture is the analysis of the climatic data. In order to understand the climate conditions and create an energy-efficient design, tools, such as the psychrometric chart, wind wheels, sun charts and sun shading charts, are required. The first chapter of this publication shows how the climate data must be analysed and which conclusions can be drawn from these analyses for an environmental design. As the research findings presented in this book are elaborated for Hashtgerd New Town, the climatic conditions of this particular city are used as a basis. The studies have shown that passive solar heat gains (24.8% of the year) and internal heat gains (20.0% of the year) are very important for heating buildings, but that shading devices at windows (17.2% of the year) and natural ventilation (7.4% of the year) are also very important measures for cooling. Due to the fact that energy savings through cost and energy-intensive measures can only be achieved with a great consumption of resources and CO2 emissions for their production, it is first of all necessary to apply cost and resource-efficient measures to save energy in buildings. Architectural Energy Efficiency is a parametric method of energy saving which separately studies the effects of various energy-related architectural factors on the energy demands of buildings. Dynamic energy simulation methods are used to find the optimum value for each of the architectural factors, including orientation, building elongation, building form, opening ratio in different orientations, sun shading, natural ventilation etc. As the architectural design affects the heating and cooling as well as the lighting energy demands of buildings, the criteria for selecting the best variant is best based on the total heating, cooling and lighting energy demand, or the primary energy demand, the CO2 emissions, energy costs or life cycle costs for all three energy demands. In this publication, Architectural Energy Efficiency is implemented in office buildings in the climatic conditions of the Tehran region. The study has shown that the optimum orientation for a minimum total and primary energy demand is the south orientation. The primary energy demand of north-facing office buildings is also fairly low. According to the results regarding the window area, the cardinal direction can significantly affect the building’s energy demand. Buildings with the same window-to-wall ratio in all cardinal directions and without shading devices have their lowest total and primary energy demands at a window-to-wall ratio of 50% and 30% respectively. The proportion of window area for each orientation should differ; the optimum window-to-wall ratios for the south, east/west and north-facing facades are 60%, 10% and 30% respectively. The results regarding shading devices show that large overhangs and an increase of overhang depth raise the total energy demand of office buildings. Office buildings with external blinds require less energy than office buildings without any blinds; however, this is only the case if the blinds are controlled effectively. The third chapter presents the design process of the New Generation Office Building as an energy and cost-efficient office building. In comparison to an average office building, the energy-efficient design principles, which resulted from the application of Architectural Energy Efficiency in this pilot project, led to energy savings of 50%. Some further energy saving concepts have been applied in this green office building for additional energy savings. These include an optimal urban and building form, innovative fixed shading devices, a combination of natural ventilation and evaporative cooling, solar reflectors, a mechanical heat recovery system and extensive green roofs. The last part of the book explores the energy and cost efficiency of heating and cooling systems for energy-efficient office buildings in the climate conditions of Hashtgerd New Town. The research considers the suitability of solar heating and solar cooling systems in Iran from an economic point of view and determines the optimum area of the solar collector, the size of the buffer tank and the slope of the panels for the New Generation Office Building. The results show that solar energy systems, in place of conventional systems, are not always feasible, since the prices of fossil fuels are still relatively low in Iran, even after reducing the energy subsidies. From an economic point of view, it is therefore more suitable to install a gas heater for heating and an evaporative cooling system for cooling in Iran’s current economic conditions. The installation of a subsoil heat exchanger and/or an air-to-air heat exchanger is always worthwhile, as it decreases the heating and cooling energy demands as well as the size of the HVAC system.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der erste Schritt zu einem Nachhaltigen Entwurf führt über die Analyse der Klimadaten, um die Möglichkeiten des Klimas für einen klimatisch verantwortungsvollen Entwurf zu untersuchen. Das erste Kapitel dieser Publikation zeigt auf, wie Klimadaten zu analysieren sind und welche Folgerungen aus diesen Analysen für einen klimagerechten Entwurf gezogen werden können. Da die Studien, die in diesem Buch publiziert werden, für Hashtgerd New Town durchgeführt wurden, wurden die Klimadaten dieser Stadt analysiert. Diese haben gezeigt, dass passive solare Gewinne (24,8% p.A.) und interne Wärmegewinne (20,0% p.A.) wichtige Faktoren zum beheizen des Gebäudes sind, Fensterverschattung (17,2% p.A.) und die natürliche Belüftung (7,4% p.A.) wirken sich hingegen positiv auf die Kühlung des Gebäudes aus. Aufgrund der Tatsache, dass Energieeinsparungen in Gebäuden nur durch kosten- und energieintensive Messungen mit hohem Resssourcenverbrauch und CO2-Ausstoß möglich sind, ist es zuerst nötig, kosten- und ressourcenschonende Methoden zur Ermittlung von Einsparpotentialen anzuwenden. Die Methode der architektonischen Energieeinsparung ist eine parametrische Methode zur Energieeinsparung, in der für sich betrachtet einzelne energiebezogene architektonische Faktoren bezüglich ihres Energiebedarfes im Gebäude untersucht werden. Dabei kommen dynamische Energie-Simulationen zum einsatz, um die optimalen Werte jedes einzelnen architektonischen Faktors zu finden. Diese sind unter anderem die Ausrichtung, die Erstreckung des Baukörpers, die Gebäudekubatur, das Öffnungsverhältnis in den verschiedenen Himmelsrichtungen, die Verschattung und die natürliche Belüftung. Nachdem diese Entwurfsparameter den Heiz- und Kühlbedarf, sowie den Bedarf an künstlicher Beleuchtung beeinflusst, lassen sich die besten Varianten basierend auf eben diesen Faktoren durch den Endenergiebedarf, Primärenergiebedarf, den CO2-Ausstoß, Energiekosten oder die Lebenszeitenkosten für den Energiebedarf ermittelt werden. In dieser Publikation wird die Architektonische Energieeinsparung an einem Bürogebäude im Klima der Region um Tehran angewandt. Diese Studie hat gezeigt, dass die optimale Ausrichtung für einen minimalen absoluten und minimalen Primärenergiebedarf in Richtung Süden ist. Der Primärenergiebedarf von nord-ausgerichteten Bürogebäude ist ebenfalls niedrig. Gemäß den Ergebnissen, die die Fensterflächen des Gebäudes untersucht haben, trägt die Abmessung der Fensterfläche wesentlich zum Energiebedarf bei. Bei Gebäuden mit einem allseitig gleichen Fenster-zu-Wand-Verhätnis und ohne Verschattungselemente betrug die optimale Fensterrate für den geringsten Endenergiebedarf und Primärenergiebedarf 50% beziehungsweise 30%. Wenn man den unterschiedlichen Himmelsrichtungen mit verschiedenen Fassaden gerecht wird, ergibt sich für die Südseite ein Wert von 60%, im Norden 10% und im Osten, sowie Westen 30%. Die Ergebnisse bezüglich der Verschattungselemente zeigen, dass bei tiefen Überhängen ein erweitern der Tiefe auch den totalen Energieverbrauch des Bürogebäudes ansteigen lässt. Bürogebäude mit außenliegenden Verschattungselementen benötigen weniger Energie als Gebäude ohne. Dies trifft jedoch nur zu, wenn die Verschattungselemente effektiv gesteuert werden. Das dritte Kapitel des Buches zeigt den Entstehungsprozess des New Generation Office Buildings als energie- und kosteneffektives Bürogebäude. Die Entwurfsgrundsätze richten sich nach den Erfordernissen der Architektonischen Energieeinsparung. In diesem Gebäude ermöglichen diese Maßnahmen Energieeinsparungen von bis zu 50% im Vergleich zu bestehenden Bürogebäuden. Zusätzlich werden weitere Methoden für zusätzliche Einsparungen angewandt, wie unter anderem innovative feste Verschattungselemente, die Kombination von natürlicher Belüftung und Verdunstungskühlung, Sonnenlichtlenkung, mechanische Wärmerückgewinnungsanlagen, sowie ein begrüntes Dach. Der letzte Teil dieses Buches untersucht die Energie- und Kosteneffizienz von Heizungs- und Kühlsystemen für energieeffiziente Bürogebäude unter den klimatischen Bedingungen von Hashtgerd New Town. Eine Machbarkeitsstudie für solare Heizsysteme und Kühlsysteme wurde unter wirtschaftlichen Gesichtspunkten im Iran durchgeführt, ebenfalls wurde die optimale Fläche für Sonnenkollektoren, die bestmögliche Größe eines Speichertanks und die optimale Neigung der Sonnenkollektoren ermittelt. Die Ergebnisse zeigen, dass sich aufgrund der relativ niedrigen Preise für Erdöl im Iran sogar nach einer Reduktion der Energiesubventionen ein solares Energiesystem nicht immer lohnt. Aus wirtschaftlicher Sicht ist der Einbau einer Gasheizung und einem Verdunstungskühlsystem unter der derzeitigen wirtschaftlichen Situation im Iran besser geeignet für das Bürogebäude. Der Einbau eines Erdwärmetauschers und eines Luft-Luft-Wärmetauschers können den Energiebedarf des Gebäudes sowie die Größe der Klimageräte jedoch zusätzlich verringern.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-06-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>book</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:book</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3782</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-7983-2579-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3782/No08_GreenOfficeBuildings.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
