<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:38Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2211">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2211</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">PLURAL - Private And Public Spaces Of The Polykatoikia In Athens</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">PLURAL - private und √∂ffentliche R√§ume der Polykatoikia in Athen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Woditsch, Richard</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This PhD-thesis reflects the questions about the constituent components that allow the polykatoikia whether in the centre or in the periphery to absorb the city and its public spaces and to carry out its interior ‚Äòlandscape‚Äô to the outside. For such research to be effective, the physical, spatial and programmatic pluralism of this building type is visualized and evaluated based on current research status of the polykatoikia and by means of an empiric configurational analysis of cases in Athens. Spatial effects are caused by these physical decisions, based in legal preconditions. Concluding the results, the built forms of the polykatoikia are shaped, located and oriented by human agency, but in the light of laws which control their effects. This thesis is intended as a first step in the exploration of the shifting relationships of the society and city and provides an important basis for defining of a theoretical knowledge of the vernacular of the polykatoikia. By this the polykatoikia, a building type, which has proofed its sustainability and variability in space and time, offers an exemplary approach for future development of European cities.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Dissertation spiegelt die Frage nach den konstituierenden Komponenten wider, die der Polykatoikia sowohl im Zentrum als auch in der Peripherie zum einen die Absorbierung der Stadt und ihrer √∂ffentlichen R√§ume und zum anderen das Ausstrahlen seiner eigenen innerer ‚ÄúLandschaft‚Ä? nach Aussen erm√∂glicht. In dieser Forschungsarbeit sind die physikalischen, r√§umlichen und programmatischen Pluralismen dieser Geb√§udetypologie veranschaulicht und auf Grundlage des bisherigen Wissensstand √ºber die Polykatoikia und empirischer Konfigurationsanalysen von Referenzbeispielen ausgewertet. R√§umliche Effekte entspringen baulicher Entscheidungen, die sich wiederum auf die gesetzlichen Vorbedingungen beziehen. Zusammenfassend sei festgehalten, dass die gebaute Form der Polykatoikia durch den Menschen geformt, verortet und ausgerichtet wird, jedoch stets durch die Logik des Raums kontrolliert wird. Die Dissertation ist als ein erster Schritt in der Erkundung dieser sich ver√§ndernden Verh√§ltnissen zwischen Gesellschaft und Stadt zu sehen und bietet einen wichtigen Ausgangspunkt f√ºr die Definition eines theoretischen Wissens √ºber das Vernakular der Polykatoikia. Hierdurch bietet sich die Polykatoikia - eine Geb√§udetypologie, die ihre Nachhaltigkeit und Ver√§nderlichkeit in Raum und Zeit bewiesen hat ‚Äì als m√∂glichen Ansatz f√ºr zuk√ºnftige Entwicklungen der westlichen Stadt an.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-08-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2211</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22322</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22322</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2211/woditsch_richard.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
