<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:18Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2139">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2139</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Housing as Governance -Interfaces between Local Government and Civil Society Organisations in Cape Town, South Africa</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Housing as Governance -Interfaces between Local Government and Civil Society Organisations in Cape Town, South Africa</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ley, Astrid</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The dissertation explores the dynamic roles and linkages of public sector institutions and civil society actors in housing provision for the urban poor in South Africa. This focus is motivated by the fact that the state allows a degree of participation in the housing process whilst civil society organisations are restructuring their engagement with the state. This, according to the hypothesis, leads to innovative structures within the civil society as well as to new interfaces between the state and civil society. The empirical analysis applies actor-centred and network theories. Two cases of civil society alliances are to reveal how their active engagement in the housing process affects the organisational structures and networks. The results prove that institutionalised participation in housing processes remains limited. Civil society responds to this limitation with different strategies: Whereas some apply advocacy and lobbying to expand formal housing delivery to the poor, others aim at strategic partnerships with the state to test alternative practices. Both positions highly affect the basic formation of the alliances. A major finding of the research is that existing typologies of civil society organisations are insufficient. The classification along the attributes of organisations and networks does not comprehend case reality: the existing civil society structures comprise both network and organisational characteristics; they are hybrids. In their engagement with the state, actors within alliances at times emerge as organisation-like networks and at other times as network-like organisations. This fluidity indicates the most crucial finding: It is possible to sustain the hypothesis that organising structures are oscillating. Governance arrangements have emerged outside the institutional channels of the state. Relationships are established through inviting government representatives to the informal governance space which indicates a convergence towards the informalisation of horizontal governance. The emergence of oscillating structures and informal governance spaces represent new challenges for local decision-making processes. Co-operation and action-oriented approaches in housing seemingly need to be based on more detailed understanding of the complex interfaces which go far beyond the conventional ideal of partnerships and participation between sectors.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Thema dieser Arbeit ist die Interaktionsdynamik zwischen zivilgesellschaftlichen und staatlichen Akteuren in der Wohnungsversorgung für einkommensschwache Haushalte in Südafrika. Die Arbeit basiert auf der Annahme, dass durch die Hinwendung zum partizipativen Wohnungsbau neue Be-teiligungs¬räume entstehen und dass zivilgesellschaftliche Organisationen den Gemeinschaften vor Ort politischen Einfluss ermöglichen. Beides führt, so die Hypothese, sowohl zu innovativen Strukturen innerhalb von zivilgesellschaftlichen Allianzen als auch zu neuen Beziehungsgeflechten zwischen Staat und Zivilgesellschaft. Die empirische Untersuchung orientiert sich an Akteurs- und Netzwerktheorien, um anhand von Fallstudien zu zwei zivilgesellschaftlichen Allianzen in Kapstadt nachzuweisen, dass eine aktive Beteiligung in der Wohnraumversorgung sich in der Organisations- und Netzwerkstruktur niederschlägt. Die Ergebnisse belegen, dass institutionalisierte Beteiligungsmöglichkeiten in der Wohnraumversorgung eingeschränkt bleiben. Zivilgesellschaftliche Akteure versuchen als Reaktion darauf durch Lobbyarbeit größeren politischen Einfluss geltend zu machen oder strategische Partner auf staatlicher Seite zu gewinnen, um alternative Praktiken zu testen. Beide Handlungslogiken haben Auswirkungen auf ihren Organisationsaufbau. Ein grundlegendes Ergebnis der Arbeit ist die Feststellung, dass gängige Typologien zu zivilgesellschaftlichen Organisationen unzureichend sind. Die Ergebnisse belegen, dass eine eindeutige Zuordnung zu Organisationen und Netzwerken nicht möglich ist. Die vorgefundenen Strukturen haben sowohl Netzwerk- als auch Organisationsmerkmale inne; sie sind Hybride. Beide Allianzformen führen unterschiedlich vielschichtige und dynamische Beziehungsgeflechte zu Akteuren auf staatlicher Seite. Als Konsequenz entstehen oszillierende Strukturen, die zeitweise stärker Organisationscharakter und zeitweise stärker Netzwerkcharakter haben. Es entstehen informelle Governance-Räume auf Initiative der zivilgesellschaftlichen Strukturen. Die Inklusion von staatlichen Akteuren in diese Beteiligungsräume deutet einen Wandel an zur Informalisierung horizontaler Governance-Strukturen. Daraus ergeben sich neue Herausforderungen an lokale Entscheidungsfindungsprozesse. Partnerschaft und Partizipation in der Wohnungsversorgung, wie sie durch internationale Vereinbarungen eingefordert werden, benötigen somit ein Verständnis abseits des Denkens in gesellschaftlichen Sektoren. Die Einbeziehung der flexiblen Organisationsstruktur von zivilgesellschaftlichen Akteuren und insbesondere der Interaktionsdynamiken mit dem Staat kann neue Kooperations- und Handlungsansätze in der Wohnungsversorgung ermöglichen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-06-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2139</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22384</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22384</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2139/original_ley_astrid_original.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2139/ley_astrid.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2139/ley_astrid_annex.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
