<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:43Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3121">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3121</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Das formelle Bauordnungsrecht in Berlin.  Wirkungsanalyse zur Genehmigungsfreistellung und zum vereinfachten Baugenehmigungsverfahren</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The Formal Building Law in Berlin. Impact Analysis to the Permission Exemption and the Simplified Building Permission</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hannewahr, Vanessa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Mit der Novellierung der Berliner Bauordnung im Jahr 2005 wurde das formelle Bauordnungsrecht in der Bundeshauptstadt konstitutiv neu ausgerichtet. Damit folgt Berlin dem bundesweiten Trend der Deregulierung des Bauordnungsrechts in Deutschland. Die novellierte Bauordnung für Berlin reagiert insbesondere auf die anhaltende Kritik am Baugenehmigungsverfahren, das sowohl einen hohen Verwaltungsaufwand, als auch langwierige Abstimmungsprozesse mit sich brachte. Die Gesetzesnovelle zielte darauf ab, die Genehmigungspraxis in Berlin spürbar zu beschleunigen und zu vereinfachen. Einerseits sollte durch die Aufgabe der Schlusspunkttheorie die Anzahl an Genehmigungsverfahren deutlich reduziert und die Verwaltung entlastet werden. Andererseits sollte das bauaufsichtliche Verfahren aus Sicht der Antragsteller durch Entbürokratisierung und Rechtsvereinfachung bürgerfreundlicher gestaltet werden. Bislang bot die Baugenehmigung für den Bauherrn ein Höchstmaß an Rechtssicherheit. Die Bauaufsicht koordinierte nicht nur das gesamte Verfahren, sondern sorgte dafür, dass alle zusätzlich erforderlichen Genehmigungen eingeholt wurden. Die Baugenehmigung bestätigte dem Bauherrn schließlich die Einhaltung des gesamten öffentlichen Rechts. Die Loslösung von der Genehmigungspflicht führt zu einer veränderten Rollenverteilung der Genehmigungsbehörde und der Bauherrenschaft im bauaufsichtlichen Verfahren. Die präventive Einbindung der Bauaufsicht wurde im Genehmigungsverfahren jedoch deutlich zurückgedrängt, während zahlreiche planerische und organisatorische Aufgaben auf die Antragsteller übertragen wurden. Zwar gewinnt der Antragssteller damit mehr Gestaltungsfreiraum im bauaufsichtlichen Verfahren, zugleich wird er aber in seiner Eigenverantwortung mehr beansprucht. Berlins Erfahrungen vorangegangener Novellierungen im Bauordnungsrecht wurden bisher keiner wissenschaftlichen Analyse unterzogen bzw. es fehlt eine fundierte Überprüfung ihrer tatsächlichen Auswirkungen. Die vorliegende Arbeit erforscht erstmals die Effekte der letzten Gesetzesnovelle anhand ausführlicher Datenerhebungen in vier Berliner Bezirken. Das Gesetzgebungsverfahren im Vorfeld der Novellierung warf die wesentlichen, bislang unbeantworteten Fragen zur Genehmigungspraxis in Berlin auf, die im Rahmen der Arbeit beantwortet werden. Die Wirkungsanalyse betrachtet die Effektivität und Wirksamkeit der Novellierung der Berliner Bauordnung vorrangig aus Sicht der Verwaltung. Sie belegt in einem direkten Vergleich – bezogen auf den Zeitraum vor und nach der Novellierung der Berliner Bauordnung –, welche Faktoren die einzelnen gesetzgeberischen Maßnahmen fördern und inwieweit gesetzliche Regelungen die Beschleunigung und Vereinfachung des formellen Bauordnungsrechts konterkarieren. Darüber hinaus zeigt die Forschungsarbeit erste Lösungsansätze auf, die den Ablauf im Genehmigungsverfahren weiter optimieren können.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The revision of the Berliner Bauordnung (BauO Bln - Berlin building regulations) in 2005 lead to a constitutive realignment of the federal capital's formal building law. With this revision, Berlin is following the nationwide trend towards the deregulation of German building legislation. The revised Berlin building regulations address, in particular, the fact that the building permission procedure has been the target of ongoing criticism due to the high level of administrative effort and the time-consuming coordination process it required. The goal of the law amendment was to noticeably accelerate and simplify the permission procedures in the federal state of Berlin. On the one hand, by abandoning the long disputed so-called Schlusspunkttheorie (according to which the building authority has to fulfil its coordinative function by granting a building permission only after all other required permissions have been obtained and the conformity of the planned project with all public regulations and requirements is guaranteed), the number of permission procedures was to be reduced and pressure to be taken off the administrative bodies. On the other hand, the building control procedure was to be made more resident-friendly from the applicants' point of view through debureaucratisation and the simplification of law. Up to now, the building permission provided the builder with maximum legal security. The building supervisory authority not only co-ordinated the whole procedure but also made sure that all other required permissions were obtained. Finally, the builder was granted a building permission which confirmed the compliance of the project with all public legislation. The disentanglement from the authorisation requirement led to a change in role allocations between the approving authority and the builder within the framework of the building control procedure. Whereas the preemptive involvement of the building supervisory authority was significantly pushed back in the permission procedure, numerous tasks in terms of planning and organisation were transferred to the applicant. Hence, applicants gain more scope for action. At the same time, however, their own responsibilities have increased considerably. Experiences that were made in Berlin with previous amendments of the building legislation have never been the subject of a scientific analysis. In other words, there is a lack of thorough examination of the actual consequences of such amendments. The thesis at hand examines for the first time the effects of the latest amendment to the law on the basis of a detailed and comprehensive data assessment in four Berlin administrative districts. The essential, so far unanswered questions concerning the Berlin permission procedure, which are now answered within the framework of this thesis, were raised by the legislative procedure in the run-up to the amendment itself. The impact analysis looks at the effectiveness and efficiency of the amended Berlin building regulations primarily from the point of view of the public authorities involved and not only verifies - through direct comparison of the state of affairs prior to and after the amendment – the factors that encourage the individual legislative measures but also clarifies the extent to which legal regulations counteract the acceleration and simplification of the formal building law. Furthermore, the research work indicates initial solution approaches that can further optimise building permission procedures.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-11-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3121</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32424</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32424</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3121/hannewahr_vanessa.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
