<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:22Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1751">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1751</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Hochhausfassaden aus Membranen. Untersuchung transparenter Folien als vorgespanntes Membranentragwerk bei Hochhausfassaden.</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Membrane high-rise buildings facades. The examination of transparent foils as a pre-stressed membrane facade of high-rise buildings.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Adamczewski, Piotr</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit untersucht die Anwendung transparenter Membranen als äußere Gebäudehülle von Hochhäusern. Die Schwerpunkte dieser Untersuchung bilden die gestalterischen Möglichkeiten der Membranfassaden und deren Spannungs- und Verformungsanalyse. Die Arbeit ist als erster Schritt der noch ausstehenden Prüfung der technischen und anwendungsbedingten Einsatzmöglichkeiten von Membranen als Hochhausfassade zu sehen. Das erste Kapitel gibt einen Überblick über die Haupteigenschaften der Membrankonstruktionen. Außerdem werden die Membranmaterialien vorgestellt und unter dem Aspekt der Anwendung als Hochhausfassade beurteilt. Vorteile für den Einsatz transparenter Membranen als Gebäudehülle sind in der Anwendung als Außenschale einer Doppelfassade sowie als einschalige Membranfassade für Lichthöfe oder Wintergärten zu erwarten. Diese Einsatzbereiche bilden den Schwerpunkt der Untersuchung. Im zweiten Kapitel sind die möglichen Formen der Membranfassaden für die jeweiligen Einsatzbereiche systematisch dargestellt und an die üblichen Hochhauskonstruktionen und -formen angepasst. Die Auswahl möglicher Fassadenformen für weitere Untersuchung ergibt sich aus den konstruktiven und funktionalen Anforderungen einer Fassade. Das dritte Kapitel umfasst die Spannungs- und Verformungsanalyse der Membranfassaden aus transparenter ETFE-Folie unter Einwirkung der Normlasten. Hierfür ist die Folie durch ein Seilnetz modelliert und die Spannungen und Verformungen sind nach der Kraftdichtemethode berechnet. Diese Vorgehensweise dient der Einschätzung des Anwendungsbereichs der einzelnen Fassadenmodelle. Die Bewertung der Berechnungsergebnisse bildet die Grundlagen für eine konstruktive Ausbildung von Hochhausfassaden aus Membranen. Anschließend sind die Untersuchungsergebnisse untereinander verglichen und es sind Fassadentypen für bestimmte Anwendungsbereiche ausgewählt. Ein Ausblick zeigt das Entwicklungspotenzial von Membranfassaden für Hochhäuser sowie noch offene Untersuchungsfelder in diesem Gebiet auf.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work examines the application of transparent membranes as a facade of high-rise buildings. The emphasis is put on the formative possibilities of the membrane facades and their tension and deformation analysis. This work is to be seen as the first step in the verification of a technical and application-conditioned implementation of membranes as a high-rise building facade. The first chapter gives an overview of the main characteristics of the membrane constructions. Additionally, the membrane materials are presented and judged under the aspect of their application as a high-rise building facade. The advantages of transparent membranes as a building envelope are to be expected when membranes are used as an outer skin of a double facade as well as facades of patios or winter gardens. These areas of application form the main focus of the work. In the second chapter, the possible forms of the membrane facades for the respective areas of application are shown successively. The membrane forms are adapted to the usual high-rise forms and constructions. The selection of possible facade forms for further investigation results from the constructive and functional requirements of a facade. The third chapter contains the tension and deformation analysis of the membrane facades made of transparent ETFE foil under the effect of the norm loads. The foil is modelled by a cable net and the tensions and deformations are calculated according to the force density method. This approach serves an appraisal of the range of applications of the facade models. The evaluation of the calculation results forms the basis for constructional planning of high-rise building facades from membranes. Afterwards, the investigation results are compared and facade types for certain ranges of application are selected. An outlook indicates the developing potential of membrane facades for high-rises as well as still open fields of investigation in this area.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-04-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/octet-stream</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17941</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17941</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1751/original_Fassaden_aus_Membranen.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1751/original_Fassaden_aus_Membranen_Anhang.indd</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1751/adamczewski_piotr.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1751/adamczewski_piotr_Anhang.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
