<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2185">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2185</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Sustainable developing strategies of settlements and residential buildings in China’s small towns and rural areas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Strategien zur nachhaltigen Entwicklung von Siedlungen und Wohngebäuden in Chinas kleinen Städten und im ländlichen Raum</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Qu, Jing</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">With the rapid progress of urbanization China is currently faced with unprecedented energy and resource deficiency as well as environmental crisis. Especially in non-urban areas due to the fast economic growth and great change of life style the problems of energy waste and environmental degradation are emerging. The dissertation explores the sustainable developing strategies of settlements and residential buildings in China’s small towns and rural areas. The study includes field survey in representative regions in China, including Guizhou province（Southwest China, zoning: Mild）, Zhejiang Province ( Southeast China, zoning: hot in summer and cold in winter) and Heilongjiang Province (Northeast China, zoning: extremely cold). The dissertation analyzes the data obtained from the survey and summarizes the existing problems and experiences that is worthy of being transferred. Then the dissertation discusses and explores the indigenously ecological design philosophy of traditional Chinese dwellings and concludes the aspects still valuable to be inherited nowadays. In the following chapter the guidance principles for development of sustainable settlement and green building technologies of Germany are introduced and analyzed for reference. Based on the study mentioned above, a system is formulated at the end of the dissertation for the principles applicable to the preparation, design and construction phases of settlements and residential buildings in small towns and rural areas in China. The system includes 19 items and certain subentries to each item. It also refers to the 4 parties involved in the phases (the central government, the local governments, the architects and the users). With detailed analysis of each subentry and the current relevant laws, norms and regulations, the system not only defines the principles from the outset to the final delivery of the projects but also makes clear the responsibilities of each party involved including relevant laws, norms, regulations and financial programmes that ought to be formulated and lauched by the central government, the obligations of the local governments, the responsibilities of the architects and the participation of the users. In this sense it is the first of such systems for development of settlements and residential buildings in China’s small towns and rural areas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Mit dem schnellen Fortschritt der Urbanisierung sieht sich China mit unvorhergesehenen Energie- und Ressourcendefiziten konfrontiert, genau so wie mit Umweltproblemen. Aufgrund des schnellen ökonomischen Wachstums und des grundlegenden Wandels des täglichen Lebens sind in den ländlichen Gebieten Probleme aus ineffizienter Energienutzung und Umweltbelastung von zunehmender Bedeutung. Diese Dissertation entwickelt Strategien für eine nachhaltige Entwicklung in den Bereichen Siedlungsplanung und Architektur in ländlichen Gegenden. Die Untersuchung beinhaltet eine Feldstudie in repräsentativen Gebieten Chinas, einschließlich der Provinz Guizhou (südwestliches China, mildes Klima), der Provinz Zhejiang (Südöstliches China, heißes Sommer- und kaltes Winterklima), der Provinz Heilongjiang (Nordöstliches China, extrem kaltes Klima). Im weiteren Verlauf der Arbeit werden die ermittelten Daten der Feldstudie analysiert und eine Zusammenfassung der aktuellen Probleme und Erfahrungen erstellt. Daraus folgend wird die einheimische Designphilosophy traditioneller, chinesischer Wohnhäuser diskutiert und nimmt dabei besondere Rücksicht auf die Aspekte, die sich auch heute noch anzuwenden lohnen. Im darauf folgenden Kapitel werden zur Vervollständigung die grundlegenden Prinzipien der Entwicklung nachhaltiger Siedlungen und grüner Gebäudetechnologie Deutschlands vorgestellt und analysiert. Auf der oben erwähnten Studie aufbauend, wird ein System anwendbarer Prinzipien in der Vorbereitungs- , der Entwurfs- und der Bauphase von Wohnungshäusern und -gebieten in kleinen Städten und ländlichen Gebieten Chinas aufgestellt. Das System beinhaltet 19 Bestandteile und einige Teilelemente pro Bestandteil. Außerdem berücksichtigt es die 4 Gruppen (Zentralregierung, lokale Regierung, Architekten und Benutzer), die in der Entstehungsphase involviert sind. Mit detaillierter Analyse jedes Unterpunktes und den aktuell relevanten Gesetzen und Normen, definiert das System nicht nur die Prinzipien von Projektbeginn bis Fertigstellung eines Projektes, sondern auch die Verantwortlichkeiten jeder involvierten Gruppe, sowie finanzielle Programme die von der zentralen Regierung zu formulieren und umzusetzen sind, Auflagen der lokalen Regierungen, Verantwortung des Architekten und die Beteiligung der späteren Nutzer. In diesem Sinne beschreitet diese Dissertation Neuland in der Entwicklung von Chinas kleinen Städten und ländlichen Gebieten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-07-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2185</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22795</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-22795</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2185/qu_jing.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2185/qu_jing.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
