<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:49Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2255">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2255</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:520</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Characterization of the stellar variability in CoRoT fields with BEST telescopes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Charakterisierung stellarer Variabilität in CoRoT-Feldern mit BEST und BEST II</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kabath, Petr</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:520</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The first extrasolar planet 51 Peg b around the G-type star has been reported in 1995. The planet with few Jupiter masses orbiting its star very closely was detected by measurement of the oscillation in the radial velocity of the host star. In 1999 the first transit, when the planet is eclipsing the host star, of the extrasolar planet HD209458 b was observed with a small ground based photometric telescope. Ever since, new planets in distant systems are continuously being detected with new high precision instruments from the ground and from space. The department of Extrasolar Planets and Atmospheres at Deutsches Zentrum für Luft- und Raumfahrt, Berlin (DLR) is involved in the detection and characterization of extrasolar planets, through participation in the CoRoT space mission. Furthermore, two ground based photometric telescope systems are operated as a ground based support for the space mission CoRoT, dedicated to asteroseismology and to extrasolar planet search with the help of the transit method. The BEST project consists of two small aperture wide field-of-view photometric telescopes devoted to the search for transiting Jupiter-sized extrasolar planets and to the characterization of variable stars in CoRoT target fields. The BEST telescope is located at Observatoire de Haute Provence, France and the BEST II telescope is located in the Atacama desert, Chile. The aim of the thesis is to present the results obtained from BEST project with a particular focus on the BEST II system. Part of the project presented in this thesis concentrated on the setup, laboratory tests and preparation for the operations of the BEST II system in its initial phase in Chile. In particular, technical aspects of the BEST II system, implementation of the robotic mode and the operations were the topic of the second phase of the thesis work presented here. In the final phase, the robotic observational campaign on LRa02 CoRoT target field was successfully carried out and results will be summarized in the second half of this thesis. Essential part describing the results on LRa02 campaign includes the results of work on the data reduction process with determination of the quality of photometric calibration and the estimation of photometric precision of the system. In addition, the comparison of the duty cycles of BEST and BEST II is made. Finally, general implications for the transit search from BEST project are also presented. The thesis summarizes the scientific results obtained and based on the observations of CoRoT long and intial run fields in the period 2005 to 2009. The data were collected in order to support the CoRoT's follow-up team in the confirmation process of planetary candidates. BEST telescopes can in some cases reject the false positive identification of the planetary candidate which can be due to a background object mimicking the transit event. Additionally, since BEST telescopes observed the CoRoT fields approximately one year ahead the CoRoT the archive data can extend the ephemerids of objects detected with CoRoT. As a result of observations data on the CoRoT IRa01, LRa01, LRc01, LRc02, LRa02 target fields were collected with both telescopes. Typical campaign length was about three months. The data contain observations from 128 nights (672 hrs.). The whole light curve archive contains information on more than 250000 stars from which about 22423 are marked as potentially variable objects which were further investigated in order to detect new periodic variable stars and planetary transits. Also a direct contribution to the CoRoT follow-up team which includes an investigation of BEST light curves corresponding to 160 CoRoT candidates will be presented in this thesis. Furthermore, presented work contains an identification of transit events of confirmed planets CoRoT 1b and CoRoT 2b in the BEST data sets after being reported by CoRoT team. The results on new periodic variable stars contain more than 900 new detections and about 31 reconfirmations of previously detected variable stars which were already listed in catalogs. The result of the transit survey is an identification of two high quality candidates for extrasolar planets in LRa02 data set.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Der erste extrasolare Planet um einen sonnenähnlichen Stern, 51 Peg b, wurde im Jahr 1995 entdeckt. Er ist um ein Vielfaches größer als Jupiter, umkreist seinen Stern in einem sehr nahen Orbit und wurde durch Oszillationen in der Radialgeschwindigkeit des Zentralsterns nachgewiesen. Im Jahr 1999 konnte mit einem kleinen bodengebundenen photometrischen Teleskop zum ersten Mal ein Transit eines extrasolaren Planeten (HD209458 b) beobachtet werden. Seitdem werden fortlaufend neue Planeten in weit entfernten Systemen sowohl vom Boden als auch vom Weltraum aus detektiert. Die Abteilung "Extrasolare Planeten und Atmosphären" am Deutschen Zentrum für Luft- und Raumfahrt (DLR) in Berlin ist durch die Weltraummission "COnvection, ROtation and planetary Transits" (CoRoT) an der Entdeckung und Charakterisierung extrasolarer Planeten beteiligt. CoRoT ist der asteroseismologischen Untersuchung entfernter Sterne sowie der Suche nach extrasolaren Planeten mithilfe der Transitmethode gewidmet. Darüberhinaus werden vom DLR mit dem BEST-Projekt ("Berlin Exoplanet Search Telescope") bodengebundene Unterstützungsbeobachtungen für die CoRoT-Mission durchgeführt. Das BEST-Projekt besteht aus zwei Teleskopen mit kleiner Öffnung und großem Gesichtsfeld, die jeweils der Suche nach extrasolaren, jupiterähnlichen Transitplaneten sowie der Charakterisierung von variablen Sternen in CoRoT-Feldern gewidmet sind. BEST befindet sich am Observatoire de Haute Provence in Frankreich, BEST II in der chilenischen Atacamawüste. Das Ziel dieser Doktorarbeit ist die Präsentation des BEST-Projekts, wobei der Schwerpunkt auf BEST II liegt. Dabei sind Aufbau, Test und Inbetriebnahme des BEST II Teleskops in Chile Teil der Arbeit. Besondere technische Aspekte des BEST II-Systems, wie z.B. die Implementierung und Funktion des robotischen Beobachtungsmodus, werden vorgestellt. In der letzten Phase der Arbeit wurde die robotische Beobachtungskampagne des CoRoT-Feldes LRa02 erfolgreich durchgeführt; die Ergebnisse werden im zweiten Teil präsentiert. Dies beinhaltet die Datenauswertung und Ergebnisse der Beobachtungen, Bestimmung der Qualität der photometrischen Kalibrierung, Abschätzung der resultierenden photometrischen Genaugkeit des Systems und einen Vergleich von Beobachtungszeiten von BEST und BEST II bzw. die Folgerungen daraus für die Transitsuche. Beobachtungsdaten der CoRoT-Felder IRa01, LRa01, LRc01, LRc02 und LRa02 wurden mit beiden Teleskopen gesammelt. Die typische Kampagnenlänge betrug drei Monate. Die Datensätze beinhalten Beobachtungen von insgesamt 128 Nächten (672 Beobachtungsstunden). Das gesamte Lichtkurvenarchiv beinhaltet mehr als 250.000 Sternen, von denen 22.423 als potentiell variabel markiert und weiter auf Periodizität untersucht wurden. Dabei konnten mehr als 900 Sterne als neue Variable identifiziert und einem Katalog präsentiert werden, sowie 31 bekannte variable Sterne bestätigt werden. Desweiteren wird in dieser Arbeit ein direkter Beitrag zu den Nachfolgebeobachtungen von 160 CoRoT-Planetenkandidaten vorgestellt und die Entdeckung der Transitplaneten CoRoT 1b and CoRoT 2b in BEST-Lichtkurven diskutiert. Nicht zuletzt konnten im LRa02-Datensatz zwei Transitkandidaten identifiziert werden, die ebenfalls vorgestellt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-10-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2255</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-23540</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-23540</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2255/kabath_petr.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
