<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:12Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2349">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2349</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Analysis of AU-rich Elements in the Yeast Pichia pastoris</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Analyse von AU-reichen Elementen in der Hefe Pichia pastoris</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lautz, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The tight regulation of mRNA stability and translation by specific cis-acting sequences and trans-acting factors is an essential means for the control of gene expression. These processes allow cells to rapidly adjust the expression pattern of regulatory factors and response transiently to internal and external signals including cell proliferation, signal transduction, inflammatory stimuli and radiation. A well known important cis-acting sequence element that controls mRNA stability is the AU-rich element (ARE) found in the 3‚Äô untranslated region (3‚ÄôUTR) of many, but not all, unstable mRNAs of various growth factors, cytokines, proto-oncogenes and transcription factors. A heterologous system for the analysis of AREs in the yeast Pichia pastoris was established. The AREs from the human proto-oncogene c-fos and the cytokine TNFÔ?° were separately cloned into the 3‚Äô UTR of P. pastoris expression vectors. It was demonstrated that both AREs are functional in this yeast and that they are regulated in different ways. This finding further stresses that the ARE-regulated system is conserved among eukaryotes and it underlines the importance of the system in the cellular context. A set of reporter constructs and mutational analysis were used to, analyse the importance of two special hairpins, which we hypothesize to have significant influence on transcript stability and translation. Thus, evidence is provided for the involvement of ARE-flanking sequences in ARE-mediated mRNA turnover and most likely in the selectivity of RNA-binding proteins. Finally, a model is proposed that explains the observed effects on protein and mRNA level in a RNA-structure-dependent manner. In order to find further support for the findings and to identify ARE-BPs gel retardation assays were performed. As a result an approximately 14 kDa protein could be identified as a binding partner of the core c-fos and TNFÔ?° AREs in Pichia.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die strenge Regulation von mRNA Stabilit√§t und Translation durch spezifische ‚Äúcis-acting‚Äú-Sequenzen und ‚Äûtrans-acting‚Äú-Faktoren ist f√ºr die Kontrolle der Genexpression ein essentielles Mittel. Diese Prozesse erlauben es der Zelle, das Expressionsmuster von regulatorischen Faktoren als transiente Antwort auf interne oder externe Signale wie Zellproliferation, Signaltransduktion, inflammatorische Stimuli oder (UV)-Strahlung einzustellen. Eine heute gut untersuchte ‚Äûcis-acting‚Äú-Sequenz, die die mRNA-Stabilit√§t kontrolliert, ist das ‚ÄûAU reiche Element‚Äú oder ‚ÄûAU rich element‚Äú (ARE), das in der 3‚Äô untranslatierten Region (3‚Äô UTR) von vielen, aber nicht allen, instabilen mRNAs von verschiedenen Wachstumsfaktoren, Cytokinen, Protooncogenen und Transkriptionsfakotren zu finden ist. Es wurde ein heterologes System f√ºr die Analyse von AREs in der Hefe P. pastoris etabiliert. Die zwei AREs des humanen Protoonkogen c-fos und des Cytokins TNFÔ?° wurden in die 3‚Äô UTR von P. pastoris Expressionsvektoren kloniert. Es wurde gezeigt, dass beide AREs in dieser Hefe Funktionalit√§t besitzen und verschiedenartig reguliert werden. Dieses Ergebnis betont zus√§tzlich die Konservierung des ARE-regulierten Systems unter Eukaryonten und unterstreicht seine Wichtigkeit im zellul√§ren Zusammenhang. Eine Auswahl von verschiedenen Reporterkonstrukten sowie Mutationsanalysen zeigten die Wichtigkeit zweier spezieller mRNA Hairpins, die einen signifikanten Einfluss auf Transkriptstabilit√§t und Translation haben k√∂nnen. Damit konnte die Involvierung von ARE-flankierenden Sequenzen und Strukturen bei dem ARE-regulierten mRNA-Umsatz und sehr wahrscheinlich bei der Selektion von ARE-Bindungsproteinen (ARE-BP). Schlie√ülich konnte ein Modell aufgestellt werden, das die beobachteten Effekte abh√§ngig von der mRNA Sekund√§rstruktur erkl√§rt. Um weitere f√ºr dieses Modell unterst√ºtzende Daten zu sammeln und um endogene ARE-BPs zu identifizieren, wurden Gelretardationsassays durchgef√ºhrt. Es konnte ein ca. 14 kDa gro√ües Protein als Bindungspartner f√ºr die c-fos als auch TNFÔ?° ARE Sequenzen identifizert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-11-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17340</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17340</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2349/original_PhDThomasLautz2007_v.1.7_final_Bibliotheksversion.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2349/lautz_thomas.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
