<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:48Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2478">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2478</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">[NiFe] hydrogenases from Desulfovibrio vulgaris Miyazaki F and Aquifex aeolicus studied by FTIR, EPR and electrochemical techniques: Redox intermediates, O2/CO sensitivity and light-induced effects</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">[NiFe] Hydrogenasen aus Desulfovibrio vulgaris Miyazaki F and Aquifex aeolicus untersucht mit FTIR, EPR und elektrochemischen Methoden: Redox Intermediaten, O2/CO Sensitivität and Licht-induzierte Effecte</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pandelia, Maria-Eirini</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">[NiFe] hydrogenases are important metalloenzymes that carry out the reversible oxidation of dihydrogen. Understanding their mechanism is crucial for the synthesis of biomimetic catalytic systems and future ‘green’ biotechnology. The present work is focused on the study of two distinct types of enzymes; a [NiFe] hydrogenase from the strictly anaerobic sulphate reducing bacterium Desulfovibrio vulgaris Miyazaki F and a [NiFe] hydrogenase from the micro-aerophilic hyperthermophilic bacterium Aquifex aeolicus. The first part is centred on the study of the [NiFe] enzyme from D. vulgaris, for which the intermediates of the reaction cycle were studied in detail by infrared techniques. Using SEIRA spectroscopy the catalytic activity of this enzyme adsorbed on an electrode was monitored, yielding essentially the same results as FTIR spectroelectrochemistry in solution. The EPR silent inactive state (Ni-SIr)I was shown to be light sensitive and a new state Ni-SL could be detected. Wavelength dependence and time resolved kinetics showed that the light sensitivity corresponds to the dislocation of the hydroxyl ligand present in the active site of (Ni-SIr)I. For the transition from the light-induced Ni-L state to Ni-C a large (H/D) kinetic isotope effect was obtained, showing that the rate limiting step is the binding of a hydron at the active site. Using FTIR spectroelectrochemistry and EPR, the inhibition of the enzyme by carbon monoxide was studied and formation of two CO-adducts demonstrated. Time resolved FTIR studies at low temperatures used the reversible photolysis of the external CO ligand to estimate the activation barrier for its rebinding at the active site. The second part of this study comprises an in-depth investigation of the Hydrogenase I from Aquifex aeolicus. Chronoamperometric electrochemical measurements provided evidence for the oxygen tolerance of this hydrogenase. FTIR electrochemistry in solution detected only four redox intermediate states with significantly more positive midpoint potentials than those measured for standard hydrogenases. Carbon monoxide was shown to bind to the active site of Hydrogenase I much weaker than to that of D. vulgaris. By an EPR redox titration the types and midpoint potentials of all iron-sulphur centres were determined. Based on these results a model for the oxygen tolerance of Hydrogenase I is proposed The study is concluded by examining the interaction of the active site with the substrate in the catalytically active Ni-C state, in which a weakly bound hydride was found.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">[NiFe]-Hydrogenasen sind Enzyme, die die reversible Oxidation von molekularem Wasserstoff katalysieren. Das Verständnis ihres Mechanismus ist notwendig für die Synthese biomimetischer katalytischer Systeme und für ein zukünftige “grüne“ Biotechnologie. In dieser Arbeit wurden [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen aus zwei unterschiedlichen Organismen untersucht, eine aus dem streng anaeroben Bakterium Desulfovibrio vulgaris Miyazaki F und eine aus dem mikro-aerophilen hyperthermophilen Bakterium Aquifex aeolicus. Der erste Teil der Arbeit konzentriert sich auf die Untersuchung der [NiFe] Hydrogenase aus D. vulgaris; hier wurden die Intermediate des Reaktionszyklus durch verschiedene Infrarot-Techniken im Detail untersucht. Durch Einsatz der SEIRA-Spektroskopie, bei der das Enzym an die Oberfläche einer Elektrode gebunden ist, konnte dieselbe katalytische Aktivität wie auch durch FTIR-Spektroelektrochemie in Lösung erhalten werden. Ferner wurde gezeigt, dass der EPR-inaktive Zustand (Ni-SIr)I lichtempfindlich ist und in einen neuen Zustand, Ni-SL, übergeht. Wellenlängenabhängige und kinetische Messungen zeigten, dass die Lichtempfindlichkeit des (Ni-SIr)I Zustands auf eine Verschiebung des an das aktive Zentrum gebundenen Hydroxyl-Liganden zurückzuführen ist. Für den Übergang von dem lichtinduzierten Ni-L in den Ni-C Zustand wurde ein (H/D) kinetischer Isotopeneffekt beobachtet. Dies zeigt, dass der geschwindigkeitsbestimmende Schritt dieses Übergangs die Bindung eines Protons an das aktive Zentrum beinhaltet. Mittels FTIR-Spektroelektrochemie und EPR wurde die Inhibierung des Enzyms durch Kohlenmonoxid untersucht und die Bildung von zwei CO-inhibierten Zuständen gezeigt. Zusätzlich wurde die Aktivierungsenergie für die Bindung des CO an das aktive Zentrum mittels zeitaufgelöster FTIR Studien bestimmt. Der zweite Teil dieser Arbeit befasst sich mit der Untersuchung der Hydrogenase I aus Aquifex aeolicus. Chronoamperometrische elektrochemische Messungen belegten die Sauerstofftoleranz dieser Hydrogenase. Durch FTIR-Spektroelektrochemie in Lösung konnten vier Redox-Intermediate detektiert werden, die ein signifikant höheres Redoxpotential aufweisen als die [NiFe]-Hydrogenasen aus anderen Organismen. Die Bindung von Kohlenmonoxid an das aktive Zentrum der Hydrogenase I aus A. aeolicus ist deutlich schwächer als diejenige an die Hydrogenase aus D. vulgaris. Durch EPR-detektierte Redox-Titrationen konnten verschiedene Typen von Eisen-Schwefel Zentren und alle dazu gehörigen Redoxpotentiale bestimmt werden. Basierend auf diesen Ergebnissen wurde ein Modell für die Sauerstofftoleranz der Hydrogenase I vorgeschlagen. Abschließend wurde die Wechselwirkung des aktiven Zentrums des katalytisch aktiven Ni-C Zustands mit Wasserstoff in A. aeolicus mittels moderner EPR-Techniken untersucht, wobei ein schwach gebundenes Hydrid detektiert werden konnte.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2478</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25887</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25887</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2478/pandelia_maria.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
