<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:06Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2790">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2790</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Toll-like receptor 9 mediated tolerance in murine systemic lupus erythematosus</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Der TLR9 abhängige Toleranzmechanismus in murinem Systemischen Lupus Erythematodes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schön, Carolin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The autoimmune disease Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) is associated with high titers of inflammatory serum IgG autoantibodies, which accumulate in the kidney, where they recruit inflammatory immune cells such as macrophages, inducing nephritis. Autoreactive B cells have been shown to be activated by B cell receptor (BCR) and innate Toll-like receptor co-signaling. Thus, Toll-like receptor 9 (TLR9), which specifically binds DNA, is associated with the generation of pathogenic DNA-reactive IgG antibodies. However, the role of TLR9 in the development of SLE remains controversial. In various lupus mouse models loss of TLR9 abolishes the generation of anti-nucleosome serum IgG autoantibodies but at the same time exacerbates lupus disease. Hence, besides the induction of autoimmunity, TLR9 also regulates tolerance to self-antigens. In this study we used mice deficient for the IgG inhibitory receptor FcgRIIB (FcgRIIB-/-) to investigate the role of TLR9 in murine lupus. We show that loss of TLR9 in FcgRIIB-/- mice is associated with low levels of IgG antibodies specific to nucleosomes, but at the same time with exaggerated IgG antibody responses specific to other self-antigens, such as DNA, RNA associated ribonucleoproteins (RNP) and self-IgG. TLR9 deficiency in FcgRIIB-/- mice furthermore results in the activation and accumulation of pro-inflammatory T helper cells, most notably Th1 and Th17 cells and highly increased mortality rates. Inconsistent with raised IgG serum autoantibody responses, levels of self-reactive IgM serum antibodies are significantly reduced in the absence of TLR9. Contrary to high affinity IgG serum autoantibodies, self-reactive IgM serum antibodies are associated with protection and not inflammation in several autoimmune disorders. Indeed, reconstitution of IgM levels in FcgRIIB-/- mice lacking TLR9 (FcgRIIB-/-TLR9-/-) with recombinant monoclonal self-reactive IgM antibodies was sufficient to reduce the frequency of pro-inflammatory Th17 cells and to ameliorate lupus disease. We could ascribe low levels of protective self-reactive IgM serum antibodies in FcgRIIB-/-TLR9-/- mice to low peritoneal B-1b cell frequencies. This work clearly demonstrates that TLR9 stimulation in vitro and in vivo leads to the activation and proliferation of innate-like FcgRIIB deficient B-1b cells, promoting the production of protective self-reactive IgM antibodies. Similarily to the application of monoclonal self-reactive IgM antibodies, the transfer of TLR9-expressing peritoneal B-1b cells from FcgRIIB-deficient mice prevents the accumulation of pro-inflammatory Th17 cells and lupus disease in FcgRIIB-/-TLR9-/- mice. Taken together, these data provide evidence for the function of self-reactive IgM antibodies produced by peritoneal B-1b cells as mediators of TLR9-dependent tolerance and thus, may be implicated in TLR9 ligand-dependent therapies and B cell depletion protocols as a treatment of SLE. In particular, these results should encourage the generation of human monoclonal self-reactive IgM antibodies that may be beneficial for the treatment of SLE and other autoimmune disorders.  </dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Autoimmunerkrankung Sytemischer Lupus Erythematodes (SLE) ist mit der Entstehung selbstreaktiver Antikörper verbunden, die sich in Form von Immunkomplexen in der Niere ablagern. Autoreaktive B Zellen werden während des Krankheitsverlaufes durch die Kostimulierung des B Zellrezeptors und verschiedener Toll- like Rezeptoren (TLR) aktiviert. Dabei bindet TLR9 spezifisch an bakterielle DNA und wurde deshalb lange Zeit mit der Bildung von pathogenen anti-DNA IgG Autoantikörpern in Verbindung gebracht. Allerdings ist die Funktion von TLR9 in der Entstehung von SLE immer noch sehr umstritten. In verschiedenen Lupus Mausmodellen verhindert die Deletion von TLR9 die Generierung von IgG anti-Nukleosomen Antikörpern, gleichzeitig aber verschlimmert der Verlust von TLR9 das Krankheitsbild. Dies unterstreicht die wichtige Funktion von TLR9 in der Toleranzregulation gegenüber Selbstantigenen. In dieser Arbeit wurden FcgRIIB defiziente (FcgRIIB-/-) Mäuse verwendet, um die Rolle von TLR9 in murinem SLE zu untersuchen. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass der Verlust von TLR9 in FcgRIIB-/- Mäusen einerseits die Entstehung von anti-Nukleosomen IgG Antikörpern verhindert, andererseits aber die IgG Autoantikörperantwort spezifisch für zahlreiche andere Selbstantigene wie DNA, RNA assoziierte Ribonukleoproteine (RNP) und Selbst-IgG stark erhöht. Das Fehlen von TLR9 führt ausserdem zur Aktivierung und Akkumulation proinflammatorischer T Helfer Zellen, vorallem Th1 und Th17 Zellen, und zu einer stark verminderten Überlebensrate. Es konnte weiterhin gezeigt werden, dass anders als bei IgG Autoantikörpern, die Abwesenheit von TLR9 zu einer drastischen Verringerung der selbstreaktiven IgM Antikörper führt. Im Gegensatz zu hochaffinen IgG Autoantikörpern, werden selbstreaktive IgM Antikörper nicht mit Entzündungsreaktionen sondern mit dem Schutz vor Autoimmunität assoziiert. Durch die Rekonstitution der Serum IgM Titer in TLR9 defizienten FcgRIIB-/- (FcgRIIB-/-TLR9-/-) Mäusen mit monoklonalen selbstreaktiven IgM Antikörpern konnte die Bildung proinflammatorischer Th17 Zellen unterdrückt und der Ausbruch von SLE verhindert werden. Niedrige Titer selbstreaktiver IgM Antikörper in FcgRIIB-/-TLR9-/- Mäusen konnten eindeutig auf stark verringerte peritoneale B-1b Zellzahlen zurückgeführt werden. Diese Arbeit zeigt, dass TLR9 Stimulierung in vitro und in vivo unweigerlich zur Aktivierung und Proliferation von FcgRIIB-/- B-1b Zellen führt und dabei die Produktion von protektivem selbstreaktivem IgM induziert. Ähnlich wie der direkte Transfer von monoklonalen selbstreaktiven IgM Antikörpern, führt auch der Transfer von FcgRIIB-/-TLR9+/+ B-1b Zellen in FcgRIIB-/-TLR9-/- Mäuse zur Reduktion von Th17 Zellen und verminderten Sterberaten. Zusammengefasst zeigen die in dieser Arbeit generierten Daten, dass TLR9 Stimulierung in B-1b Zellen zur Produktion von selbstreaktiven IgM Antikörpern führt, welche die Toleranz gegenüber Selbstantigenen aufrecht erhalten. Humane monoklonale selbstreaktive IgM Antikörper können daher eine neue Möglichkeit der Therapie von SLE und anderen Autoimmunerkrankungen darstellen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-02-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2790</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29338</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29338</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2790/schoen_carolin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
