<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:50Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3361">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3361</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Nanomaterials for Ammonia Decomposition</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Nanomaterialien für Ammoniakzersetzung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zheng, Weiqing</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">With the aim of developing a high efficient catalyst for COx-free hydrogen production from ammonia, a series of well define nanostructured materials were synthesized, characterized and evaluated for the catalytic decomposition of ammonia. The ruthenium nanoparticles were deposited on carbon nanotubes (CNTs) and graphite with different local geometry and functionalities in order to vary the metal-support interaction. The work starts with surface modification of carbon by chemical functionalization, exfoliation and thermal annealing. The characterization results reveal that the pretreatments can efficiently remove the pyrolytic carbon and vary the oxygen functional groups on the surface of carbon. Post characterization of Ru/carbon catalysts supports the notion that high reactivity of Ru particles benefits from the high graphitization of carbon support leading to a weaker metal-carbon interaction and hence to form larger particles. According to the high-resolution TEM images, the local disorder of the support induces the local disorder to the Ru particle immobilized on it, and further influence the desorption of nitrogen from catalyst surface, which is the most difficult step for ammonia decomposition. The direct observation of reaction intermediate (adsorbed dinitrogen) from in situ XPS measurement operating at 400 °C and relative high pressure of ammonia, efficiently supports the conclusions from the post characterization of the Ru particles on carbon materials. Considering the sintering and nitridation of Fe at working conditions, Fe catalyst was modified by alloying Co or Ni and supported on CNTs. The homogeneous distributions of Fe and Co in the isolated nanoparticles were evidenced by the bulk and surface structural and compositional characterization. The stability of iron was significantly improved by alloying with cobalt or nickel, and by encapsulated inside the tubular channel of CNTs. About 30 mmol/(gcat•min) constant H2 production rate could be achieved over a high surface area molybdenum carbide catalyst in 100 hours. Observed deactivation (in the first 15 hours) of the molybdenum carbide during reaction was ascribed to considerable reduction of specific surface area due to the nitridation of carbide under reaction condition. The relatively high rate of reaction is ascribed to the highly energetic sites (twin-boundaries, stacking faults, steps and defects) which are observed in both the molybdenum carbide and nitride samples. The prevalence of such sites in the as-synthesised material results in a much higher H2 production rate in comparison with previously reported Mo-based catalysts. Homogeneous molybdenum nitride nanoparticles dispersed in carbon were prepared by using hydrothermal carbonization and ammolysis with proper Mo:C mole ratio. With the help of carbon, the individual MoN particles could survive throughout the long-term catalytic reaction and offer a constant H2 formation rate (23 mmol/(gcat•min)). We herein show that the transition metal carbide and nitride materials have great potential to replace Ru as the catalyst for ammonia decomposition. The last part of this work is the reaction kinetic study over the three catalytic systems by varying the partial pressures of NH3, N2 and H2 at different temperatures. The kinetic results from applying the power-law model show that the reaction behaviors were controlled by the domain crystalline size of molybdenum nitride. Lower activation energy and strong inhibitive effect of hydrogen were observed on nanostructured molybdenum nitride, close to those for supported ruthenium nanoparticles indicates the similar properties between nitride and noble metal for the reaction of ammonia decomposition.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Mit dem Ziel der Entwicklung hocheffizienter Katalysatoren zur COx-freien Wasserstoff-Synthese aus Ammoniak wurden eine Reihe wohldefinierter, nanostrukturierter Materialien auf Basis von Ruthenium, Eisen und Molybdän dargestellt, charakterisiert und hinsichtlich ihrer Eigenschaften für die katalytische Zersetzung von Ammoniak untersucht. Ru-Nanopartikel wurden auf Kohlenstoffnanoröhren („CNTs“) und Graphit abgeschieden, wobei durch die Verwendung unterschiedlicher Geometrien und Funktionalisierungen am Träger eine breite Variation der Metall-Träger-Wechselwirkung erreicht wurde. Ex situ Untersuchungen an diesen Katalysatoren deuten darauf hin, dass hohe Aktivitäten des Metalls durch größere Partikel erreicht werden, welche bei hoher Graphitisierung des Kohlenstoffs und damit schwächeren Metall-Träger-Wechselwirkungen entstehen. Hochauflösende TEM-Aufnahmen zeigen, dass lokale Fehlordnungen am Träger die Ausbildung lokale Defekte am Metallpartikel bewirken. Diese beeinflussen maßgeblich die Desorption von Stickstoff von der Oberfläche als geschwindigkeitsbestimmenden Schritt. Die direkte Beobachtung von adsorbiertem Distickstoff an der Metalloberfläche gelang mit Hilfe von in situ XPS-Experimenten, welche die Schlussfolgerungen der vorrangegangenen ex situ Untersuchungen weiter bekräftigen. Fe/CNT-Katalysatoren konnten hinsichtlich ihrer Stabilität gegenüber Sintern und Nitridierung unter Reaktionsbedingungen durch Legieren mit Co und Ni wesentlich verbessert werden, wobei die hierbei notwendige Homogenität der Legierungspartikel durch verschiedene bulk- und oberflächensensitive Methoden sichergestellt wurde. Die Stabilität wird zusätzlich durch die gezielte Immobilisierung der Partikel im Innenraum der Kohlenstoffnanoröhren erhöht. Mittels eines Molybdäncarbids mit hoher Oberfläche konnten konstante H2-Bildungsraten von ca. 30 mmol/(gKat•min) nach 100 Stunden erzielt werden. Eine dabei beobachtete 15 Stunden andauernde Deaktivierungsphase zu Beginn der Reaktion wird mit der Umsetzung des Metallcarbids zum Metallnitrid und einhergehender deutlicher Verringerung der spezifischen Oberfläche begründet. Die dennoch, verglichen mit literaturbekannten Mo-Katalysatoren, hohe Reaktionsrate lässt sich auf das präparationsbedingte vermehrte Auftreten hochenergetischer Zentren in Form von Zwillingsgrenzen, Stufen und Stapelfehlern zurückführen. Desweiteren wurden in Kohlenstoff dispergierte Molybdännitrid-Partikel durch Hydrothermalsynthese dargestellt. Durch die Anwesenheit des Kohlenstoffs unterliegen die Molybdännitrid-Partikel keinen Sintervorgängen unter Reaktionsbedingungen und zeigen eine stabile H2-Bildungsgeschwindigkeit von 23 mmol/(gKat•min). Diese Ergebnisse verdeutlichen das hohe Potential von Metallcarbiden und –nitriden als Katalysatoren für die Zersetzung von Ammoniak. Schließlich wurden kinetische Untersuchungen an den beschriebenen Katalysatorsystemen durch Änderung der Partialdrücke von NH3, N2 und H2 bei verschiedenen Temperaturen vorgenommen. Durch Anwendung des „Power-Law“-Modells lässt sich zeigen, dass die katalytischen Eigenschaften des Molybdännitrides durch dessen Kristallitgröße bestimmt werden. Die niedrigen Aktivierungsenergien und Inhibierungseffekte des H2 des nanostrukturierten Molybdännitrides sind vergleichbar mit denen der geträgerten Ru-Nanopartikel und zeugen von den sehr ähnlichen Eigenschaften eines Edelmetalls und eines Nitrids als Katalysatoren für die Zersetzung von Ammoniak.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-06-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3361</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3361/zheng_weiqing.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
