<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:04Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1672">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1672</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">X-ray imaging by partially coherent synchrotron light: Application to metallic alloys, tooth dentin and natural rock</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Roentgenbildgebung mit teilkohaerentem Synchrotronlicht: Anwendung auf Metalllegierungen, Zahnbein und Naturstein</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zabler, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The hard spectrum which is available on the BAMline at Berlin’s synchrotron BESSY offers the rare opportunity to perform high-resolution X-ray imaging experiments with a partially coherent beam. This thesis work reports on the development of a new tomography system, including Fresnel-propagated imaging, and its application to three specific materials science problems from the fields of engineering materials, biology and earth science. The microstructure of metallic alloys exhibits a large variety of geometrical forms (globular, lamellar, dendritic, etc.). The interface between the different phases which characterizes this geometry, changes its shape under certain experimental conditions, in particular when the material is processed in the semisolid state. In this state the alloy is characterized by a solid-liquid mixture which is obtained by partial melting. Both static particle coarsening and external shearing forces are known to alter the microstructure of the alloy. In this work, static and dynamic 2D and 3D images were recorded from a variety of aluminum-based alloys. Unlike surface imaging methods, X-ray radiography and particularly tomography provide direct access to the 3D particle chararacteristics, e.g. size, shape, orientation, connectivity and contiguity. Coarsening of particle agglomerates (at high solid volume fraction) in liquid solution, as well as rheological properties of semi-solid alloys are thus characterized. Dentin is the bulk material of teeth, and is covered with a cap of dense enamel. Dentin is characterized by a quasi-parallel arrangement of micrometer-sized tubules which are believed to incarnate a natural mechanical design. Despite numerous measurements on 2D sections and structural models, the structure function relationship between tubules and tooth performance is still far from being fully understood which is why 3D maps of dentin microstructure were recorded. Fresnel-propagated tomography is shown to be the ideal technique to measure the arrangement of the tubules. This work shows how high-resolution 3D images of water-immersed tooth dentin are recorded, and detailed simulations of the optical wave propagation reveal that Fresnel-images contain additional information about the dense cuff of peritubular dentin surrounding the tubules. The cuff thickness can be extrapolated from the interference fringes that form the propagated images of tubules. Thus, 3D images are shown to contain far more information than the mere position and orientation of the individual tubules. Understanding rock fracture is one of the fundamental problems in earth science. Although rocks are an extremely inhomogeneous material, cracking does not occur randomly but it follows a well known en-echelon (staggered) propagation that results from mechanical interaction between tensile and shear-cracks. Absorption and Fresnel-propagated X-ray tomography are applied to measure samples of different rocks before and after mechanical compression nondestructively. In a first approach, limestone and greywacke are investigated, representing two sedimentary rocks of different grain size. Basalt and granite are tested in a second approach to compare different rock types. Development of cracks is observed in all materials, leading to fracture when increasing mechanical load is applied. In this work, relatively small mm-sized samples are used in order to test a classical fracture model wherein micro-flaws initiate the formation of larger cracks. For the first time, Fresnel-propagated imaging is applied to rock samples, highlighting micrometer-sized intergranular porosity as well as different material phases. The latter is shown to indicate a preferred crack orientation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das harte Spektrum der BAMline am Berliner Synchrotron BESSY bietet die seltene Möglichkeit, Experimente mit hochauflösender Röntgenbildgebung und teil-kohärenter Strahlung zu machen. Diese Promotionsarbeit umfasst die Entwicklung eines neuen Tomographieaufbaus und dessen Anwendung auf drei spezifische Probleme der Materialwissenschaften aus den Gebieten der Werkstoffkunde, Biologie und Geologie. Die Mikrostruktur von Metalllegierungen nimmt eine Vielzahl geometrischer Formen an (runde Körper, Lamellen, Dendriten, etc.). Die Grenzschicht zwischen den einzelnen Phasen beschreibt diese Geometrie und sie verändert sich unter bestimmten Einflüssen, z. B. wenn eine Legierung in halbfestem Zustand verarbeitet wird. Dieser Zustand wird mit einem fest-flüssig Gemisch beschrieben welches bei teilweisem Schmelzen der Legierung entsteht. Sowohl statische Partikelreifung als auch äußere Scherkräfte führen zu einer Veränderung des Gefüges. Statische Röntgenbilder und Filmsequenzen wurden in 2D und 3D von einer Reihe von Aluminiumlegierungen gemacht. Anders als Oberflächenmessungen erlaubt Radiographie und besonders Tomographie eine statistische Analyse der 3D Gefügeparameter, z.B. Partikel-Größe, -Form, -Lage, -Koordinationszahl und Kontiguität. Reifungsgesetze für Agglomerate (bei hohem Festphasenanteil) und rheologische Eigenschaften wurden somit erforscht. Zahnbein ist das Grundmaterial unserer Zähne. Es liegt unter einer harten Schutzkappe aus Zahnschmelz. Zahnbein wird von Mikrometer-großen quasi-parallelen Kanälen durchzogen, denen im Allgemeinen eine mechanische Funktion zuschrieben wird. Trotz zahlreichen 2D Messungen und darauf aufbauenden Strukturmodellen, ist diese Funktionalität so unklar wie denn je. 3D Messungen sollen helfen diese Lücke zu schließen. Tomographie mit Hilfe von Fresnel-Beugung ist hervorragend geeignet, um die räumliche Anordnung der Kanäle zu verstehen. Mit dieser Arbeit wurde eine spezielle Technik entwickelt, mit der hochauflösende 3D Bilder von nassem Zahnbein aufgenommen werden können. Richtung, Verlauf und Biegung von einzelnen Kanälen können somit bestimmt werden. Simulationen der optischen Beugung an einem einzelnen Kanal zeigen ferner, dass die Beugungsbilder zusätzliche Informationen über die Dicke jener dichten Mineralschicht liefert, die die hohlen Kanäle umschließt (die Dicke kann aus dem Kontrast der Interferenzstreifen extrapoliert werden). Das Bruchverhalten von Steinen zu verstehen ist eine der grundlegendsten Aufgaben der Geologie. Trotz der sehr inhomogenen Mirkostruktur von Steinen entstehen Brüche nicht in willkürlichen Mustern sonder folgen einer bekannten „treppenförmigen“ Ausbreitung, welches ihren Ursprung in den Wechselwirkungen zwischen Zug- und Scherrissen hat. Mit Hilfe von Absorption- und Fresnel-Beugungs-Tomographie wurden Bilder von verschiedenen Gesteinen, vor und nach mechanischer Belastung erstellt. Zuerst wurden Grauwacke und Kalkstein als Vertreter von Sedimentgestein unterschiedlicher Korngrößen untersucht. Dann wurden Basalt und Granit verwendet, um unterschiedliche Gesteinstypen zu testen. In allen Steinen konnte Rissausbreitung beobachtet werden, die bei gesteigerter Belastung zum Bruch führte. Die Daten wurden mit einem bekannten mechanischen Modell verglichen, wobei Mikrosprünge das Entstehen von größeren Spalten begünstigen. Fresnel-Beugung erlaubte es zusätzlich, die Porosität und evtl. Erzminerale an den Korngrenzen besser zu erkennen. In Grauwacke wurde so eine Vorzugsrichtung für neu entstehende Risse gefunden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-01-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1672</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1672/zabler_simon.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
