<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:20Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1974">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1974</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Investigations of the interfacial electron transfer of cytochrome c6 and cytochrome c by surface-enhanced resonance Raman spectroscopy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Untersuchungen des Elektronentransfers von Cytochrome c6 and Cytochrome c an Grenzfl√§chen mit Hilfe von oberfl√§chenverst√§rkter Resonanzramanspektroskopie </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kranich, Anja</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Elucidating the mechanism and dynamics of electron transfer (ET) processes between redox proteins is one of the fundamental challenges in molecular biophysics. Surface enhanced resonance Raman (SERR) spectroelectrochemistry is a especially suitable technique for studying heterogeneous ET reactions as it selectively probes the redox sites solely of the adsorbed protein. SERR spectroscopy combines the advantages of the surface and resonance enhancement by exciting a heme protein immobilised on rough silver electrodes in the Soret (or Q band) absorption band region. Upon coating Ag electrodes with self-assembled-monolayers (SAMs) of amphiphiles, it is possible to mimic biological interfaces where most of the electron transfer processes of redox proteins take place. This approach has the specific advantage of facilitating the determination of ET rate constants as a function of distance by simply varying the chain length of the thiols. By changing the functional head groups, the electrode potential, pH and ionic strength the electric field strength can be controlled as a prerequisite for studying its influence on the interfacial ET process. The investigations focussed on two low spin mono-heme proteins. First, cytochrome c6 (Cyt c6), which acts as electron carrier between the b6f-complex and photosystem I (PS1) in the photosynthetic redox chain of cyanobacteria and green algae, was studied, using the wild-type (WT) form and its mutant M58H from the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp. The mutant M58h exhibits a bis-histidine ligation due to the replacement of the axial ligand methionine by an histidine. Both proteins were successfully attached to the electrode and retained in their native properties. The interfacial ET was monitored by time-resolved SERR spectroelectrochemistry. The distance-, overpotential- and viscosity dependence of the heterogeneous ET rate constants indicate a gated ET mechanism similar to cytochrome c (Cyt c), in which a non-Faraday reaction step becomes rate-limiting. A kinetic model of gated ET mechanism was applied to all experimental data and provides a consistent qualitative picture. The second objective of this thesis was to identify the nature of the gating step of the interfacial ET of Cyt c, that carries electrons in the respiratory chain of aerobic organism. Its nonadiabatic ET at biomimetic interfaces is characterised by unusual distance dependences of the ET rates, whose origin has been elusive and discussed controversially. Using a novel two colour time-resolved SE(R)R spectroelectrochemical approach it was possible to monitor simultaneously and in real time the structure, ET kinetics and configurational fluctuations of Cyt c electrostatically adsorbed to SAM-coated electrodes. It is shown that the overall ET kinetics is determined by protein dynamics rather than by tunnelling probabilities. The protein reorientation is controlled by the interfacial electric field. Implications for the inter-protein electron transfer at biological membranes are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Elektronentransfermechanismen zwischen Redoxproteinen aufzukl√§ren, ist eine der wichtigsten Herausforderungen in der molekularen Biophysik. Oberfl√§chenverst√§rkte Resonanz-Raman (SERR) Spektroelektrochemie ist eine besonders geeignete Technik zur Untersuchung heterogener Elektronentransferreaktionen (ET), da sie selektiv die Redoxzentren nur der adsorbierten Proteine abfragt. Die SERR-Spektroskopie verbindet die Vorteile der Oberfl√§chen- mit der Resonanzverst√§rkung, in dem H√§mproteine auf einer angerauhten Ag-Elektrode adsorbiert werden und im Bereich der Soret (oder Q-)√úberg√§nge angeregt werden. Durch Beschichten der Ag-Elektroden mit selbstorganisierendenMonoschichten (SAMs) aus Amphiphilen ist es m√∂glich, biologische Membranen nachzuahmen, an denen die meisten ET von Redoxproteinen stattfinden. Dieser Ansatz hat den besonderen Vorteil, die Bestimmung von ET-Geschwindigkeitskonstanten als Funktion des Abstands durch Variation der Kettenl√§nge der Thiole zu erm√∂glichen. Durch Modifikation der Kopfgruppen, des Elektrodenpotentials, des pH und der Ionenst√§rke kann das elektrische Feld variiert werden. Das ist eine Grundvoraussetzung f√ºr die Untersuchung des Einflusses der elektrischen Feldst√§rke auf die ET an den Grenzfl√§chen. Im Zentrum der Untersuchungen befanden sich zwei low-spin mono-H√§mproteine. Zun√§chst wurde Cytochrome c6 (Cyt c6), ein Elektronentransporter zwischen dem b6f-Komplex und dem Photosystem 1 (PS1) in der Photosynthese von Cyanobakterien und Gr√ºnalgen untersucht, vertreten durch den Wildtyp (WT) und der Mutante M58H vom Cyanobakterium Anabaena sp. In der Mutante wurde der axiale Met-Ligand des H√§meisens durch His ersetzt, was zu einer bis-His-Konfiguration f√ºhrt. Beide Proteine konnten erfolgreich an die Elektrode gebunden werden unter Erhalt ihrer nativen Eigenschaften. Die ET an der Grenzfl√§che wurden mit zeitaufgel√∂ster SERR-Spektroskopie untersucht. Die Abstands-, √úberpotential- und Viskosit√§tsabh√§ngigkeit der heterogenen ET-Geschwindigkeitskonstanten weist auf einen ‚Äúgated‚Ä? Elektronentransfermechanismus √§hnlich dem von Cytochrome c (Cyt c) hin, bei dem ein nicht-Faraday‚Äôscher Reaktionsschritt geschwindigkeitsbestimmend wird. Ein kinetisches Model des ‚Äúgated‚Ä? ET wurde auf alle experimentellen Ergebnisse angewandt und ergab eine konsistente, qualitative Beschreibung. Das zweite Fragestellung dieser Arbeit war, genaueres √ºber die Art des ‚Äúgating‚Ä? Schrittes des ET von Cyt c, an Grenzfl√§chen herauszufinden. In seiner nat√ºrlichen Funktion transportiert Cyt c Elektronen in der Atmungskette aerober Organismen. Der nichtadiabatische ET von Cyt c an biomimetischen Grenzfl√§chen ist charakterisiert durch eine ungew√∂hnliche Abstandsabh√§ngigkeit der ET-Geschwindigkeiten, dessen Ursprung kontrovers diskutiert wurde. Durch einen neuartigen zwei-Farben zeitaufgel√∂sten SE(R)R spektroelektrochemischen Ansatz war es m√∂glich, simultan und in Echtzeit die Struktur, ET-Kinetiken und Konfigurationsfluktuationen von Cyt c, das elektrostatisch an einer SAM-beschichteten Elektrode adsorbiert war, zu beobachten. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass die gesamte ET Kinetik st√§rker durch die Proteindynamik als durch Tunnelwahrscheinlichkeiten bestimmt wird. Die Proteinorientierung wird kontrolliert durch das elektrische Feld in der Grenzfl√§che. Auswirkungen f√ºr den inter-Protein ET an biologischen Membranen werden diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-11-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/postscript</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20551</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20551</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1974/original_kranich_anja.ps</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1974/kranich_anja.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
