<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:04Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3628">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3628</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Pattern Formation in Multi-component Membranes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Musterbildung in Mehr-Komponenten-Membranen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rouhiparkouhi, Tahereh</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Biological membranes contain large number of different components, are selective barrier that separate cells interior side from the external world. Multi-component membranes consisting of a small number of lipids types provide simple model systems for biological membranes. Since the thickness of the lipid bilayer is much smaller than the overall membrane area, we treat the membrane as 2-dimensional systems that can have different thermodynamic phases. When the component composition in a multicomponent membrane change, it exhibits phase separation and pattern of intramembrane domains. Sufficiently large domains can be observed by fluorescence microscopy on giant vesicles, solid-supported membranes, hole-spanning (or black lipid) membranes, as well as pore-spanning membranes. In the presence of an adhesive substrate surface, the different molecular components of the membrane will, in general, exhibit different surface affinities as has been observed for supported bilayers. The generic interactions between the lipid molecules and the substrate surface arise from hydration, van der Waals, and electrostatic forces that depend on the molecular architecture of the lipids and decrease with increasing separation from the surface. This affinity contrast between substrate and components leads to the change of concentration in contact area and thus the formation of patterns in unbound and adhering membrane segments. This study develops the phase-behavior of multi-component membranes in contact with an adhesive substrate surface in the framework of thermodynamics and statistical mechanics. We used lattice binary mixtures as a simple and flexible model for multicomponent membranes in adhesion to a substrate surface. By combining the binodals of a free vesicle membrane and explicit calculation, we obtained the coexisting regions in the phase diagram of adhering membrane systems. Also we used exact solution of the Ising model and mean field approximation to proof the adhering membrane phase behavior. The surface affinity contrast was found to have a profound effect on the phase behavior and to induce two distinct phase transitions in large membrane segments. Our results, are applicable to the adhesion of vesicles, to pore-spanning membranes and to membranes supported by chemically patterned surfaces, all of which are accessible to experimental investigations.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Biologische Membranen bestehen aus einer Vielzahl von verschiedenen Komponenten und dienen als selektive Barrieren, die das Innere von Zellen vor Einflüssen aus der Umgebung schützen. Als einfache Modelle dieser sehr komplexen Biomembranen dienen Multi-Komponenten-Membranen aus einer kleinen Anzahl von Lipidsorten. Da die Dicke von Lipidmembranen sehr klein ist im Vergleich zu ihrer Fläche, können wir sie als zweidimensionale Systeme behandeln, die sich in verschiedene thermodynamischen Phasen befinden. Ändert sich die Zusammensetzung einer Multi-Komponenten-Membran, treten Phasenseparationen und intramembrane Domänen auf. Sind diese Domänen ausreichend groß, können sie im Fluoreszenzmikroskop auf sehr großen Lipidvesikeln supported lipid bilayers (Lipidmembranen auf ebenen Trägerstoffen), hole-spanning or black lipid membranes und pore-spanning membranes (über Löcher in einem Trägermaterial gespannte Lipidmembranen) beobachtet werden. In Gegenwart eines adhäsiven Substrats zeigen die verschiedenen Komponenten einer Membran im Allgemeinen unterschiedliche starke Oberflächenaffinitäten. Die generische Wechselwirkung zwischen den Lipidmolekülen und der Substratoberfläche wird bestimmt durch Hydrations-, van-der-Waals- und elektrostatische Kräfte, die von der molekularen Architektur der Lipide abhängen und mit der Entfernung zur Oberfläche abnehmen. Der Affinitätskontrast zwischen Substrat und Komponenten führt zu einer Änderung der Lipidzusammensetzung in der Kontaktfläche und somit zur Bildung von Mustern im ungebundenen und im haftenden Membransegment. In dieser Doktorarbeit wird das Phasenverhalten von Multi-Komponenten-Membranen in Kontakt mit adhäsiven Substratoberflächen mit Methoden der Thermodynamik und Statistischen Physik untersucht. Durch Kombination der Binodalen von freien Vesikelmembranen allgemeinen Relationen für die Partitionierung das Lipid moleküle und das chemische Gleichgewicht innerhalb der Membrane von adhärierenden vesikeln erhalten wir zwei Koexistenzregionen im Phasendiagramm des adhärierenden Membransystems. Ausserdem verwenden wir Ising modelle und binäre Gittermischungen als einfache Modellsysteme. Dabei nutzen wir Molekularfeldnäherungen und exakte Lösungen des Ising-Modelle um das Phasenverhalten der adhärierenden Vesikel zu zeigen. Es stellt sich heraus, dass der Oberflächenaffinitätskontrast einen großen Einfluss auf das Phasenverhalten und die Erzeugung von zwei verschiedenen Phasenübergängen in großen Membransegmenten hat. Unsere Ergebnisse lassen sich von der Adhäsion von Vesikeln auf pore-spanning membranes und auf Membranen auf chemisch gemusterten Oberflächen übertragen und in allen Fällen experimentell überprüfen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-02-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3628</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38553</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38553</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3628/rouhiparkouhi_tahereh.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
