<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:03Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3623">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3623</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy for planetary research: Analysis of salts and frozen salt solutions under Martian conditions</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Laser-induzierte Plasmaspektroskopie in der Planetenforschung: Analyse von Salzen und Salzeisloesungen unter Mars-aehnlichen Bedingungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schröder, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The research presented in this thesis addresses laser-induced breakdown spectroscopy (LIBS) and its potential for in-situ investigations of geological samples for planetary science. The focus of this work was on the ability of LIBS to detect and identify various salts and frozen salt solutions under Martian atmospheric conditions by utilizing different multivariate analysis (MVA) methods. LIBS is an emission spectroscopy technique and permits rapid multi-elementalanalysis both qualitatively and quantitatively. It relies on ablating and evaporating material from the target by focusing radiation from a pulsed laser onto the sample surface. The generated plasma is analyzed spectroscopically and information about the elemental composition is obtained from specific atomic or ionic transitions and the associated emanating photons, which result in characteristic spectral lines. For the geochemical investigation of extraterrestrial surfaces LIBS has been suggested as a powerful analytical tool and is part of the payload on NASA's rover MSL (Mars Science Laboratory), which will reach Mars in August 2012. This is the first time that LIBS will be used for planetary science. In this work, salts, which are considered relevant for Martian geochemistry were investigated, including sulfates, chlorides, and perchlorates. The salts were investigated in their pure form, mixed with Martian analogue soil and in frozen salt solutions under simulated Martian atmospheric conditions. In general, the emission lines of metals are detectable with LIBS with high signal-to-noise ratios, which facilitates a relatively straightforward identification of the type of the cation. However, due to weak excitation of the high-energy levels required for efficient radiative transitions of both sulfur and chlorine ions, their emission lines are typically weak and hardly detectable, in particular in the LIBS spectra of the ices. This considerably complicates differentiation between salts with the same type of cation. The focus in this study was on the capability of different MVA techniques applied to LIBS data to discriminate between salts with cations of the same kind in frozen salt solutions. The influence of different gating parameters for time-resolved detection of the plasma were studied for analyzing salts and frozen salt solutions and parameters best suited for the LIBS analysis of ices were determined. The applied MVA methods differed in suitability in terms of discriminating between the various salts. The most important emission lines for successful discrimination were identified for the LIBS spectra and spectral features such as line profiles, shifts, and the influence of background radiation were investigated. Partial least squares discriminant analysis (PLS-DA), which is a special form of PLS regression using a binary matrix that comprises information on the sample classes for compiling a prediction model, was found to be best suited for the purpose of identification of a test set in the case of the frozen salt solutions, but also for the other sample sets. LIBS spectra of salts with the same cation in frozen salt solution could be identified within the scope of the prediction model, although there were no chlorine and sulfur lines detectable. This was achieved on the basis of emission line intensities and line profiles of other lines available in the LIBS spectra. The results of this work demonstrate that LIBS is a suitable analytical technique for the investigation of salts and frozen salt solutions under Martian atmospheric conditions. With appropriate prediction models, salts in different matrices, such as in frozen salt solutions, can be identified. These results are not only important for the application of LIBS for the analysis of salts and frozen salt solutions on Mars, but also in view of possible future missions to the icy satellites of the gas giants in our Solar System like Europa and Enceladus.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Dissertation beschäftigt sich mit dem Einsatz der laserinduzierten Plasmaspektroskopie (LIBS, engl. Laser-induced Breakdown Spectroscopy) in der Planetenforschung zur in-situ Analyse von geologischen Proben. Der Schwerpunkt liegt hierbei auf der Detektion und Identifizierung von Salzen und gefrorenen Salzwasserlösungen unter marsähnlichen Umgebungsbedingungen und unter Anwendung verschiedener multivariater Analysemethoden. LIBS stellt eine Variante der optischen Atomemissionsspektroskopie dar und erlaubt die simultane und schnelle Analyse von vielen Elementen. Hierzu wird mit einem gepulsten Laser Probenmaterial abgelöst, atomisiert und ionisiert. Die elementspezifische Strahlung des entstandenen Plasmas wird zur qualitativen als auch quantitativen Bestimmung der Elemente in der Probe spektroskopisch analysiert. LIBS ist eine leistungsstarke Analysetechnik, welche für die geochemische Untersuchung planetarer Oberflächen mehrfach für verschiedene Missionen vorschlagen wurde. Das erste LIBS Instrument für den Einsatz in der Planetenforschung befindet sich derzeit auf dem Rover MSL (engl. Mars Science Laboratory) der NASA auf dem Weg zum Mars, wo er im August 2012 landen wird. In dieser Arbeit wurde eine experimentelle Studie an einer Auswahl von Salzen durchgeführt, die für die geochemischen Vorgänge auf der Marsoberfläche von besonderer Bedeutung sind. Unter simulierten marsähnlichen Bedingungen wurden Sulfate, Chloride und Perchlorate mit LIBS sowohl pur als auch gemischt mit marsanalogem Gestein sowie in gefrorenen Salzwasserlösungen untersucht. LIBS erlaubt eine einfache Identifizierung der Kationen der untersuchten Salze anhand ihrer intensiven Emissionslinien. Die Detektion von Chlor und Schwefel ist jedoch wegen der deutlich höheren Anregungsenergien im Vergleich zu den Metallen stark erschwert bzw. im Fall der Salzeise nicht möglich. Aus diesem Grund stand die Frage im Mittelpunkt, ob mit LIBS und multivariaten Analysemethoden zwischen Salzen unterschieden werden kann, die das gleiche Kation haben. Zu diesem Zweck wurden im Rahmen dieser Arbeit geeignete Messparameter für die optimierte zeitaufgelöste Detektion der LIBS Spektren der Salzeise ermittelt. Mit den verschiedenen auf die LIBS Daten angewandten multivariaten Analysemethoden konnten die Spektren unterschiedlich gut ausgewertet und unterschieden werden. Die für die Unterscheidung der Proben wichtigen Spektrallinien wurden identifiziert und die spektralen Eigenschaften wie Linienprofile, Linienverschiebungen und Untergrundstrahlung der verschiedenen Proben aufgezeigt. Die PLS-DA (engl. Partial Least Squares Discriminant Analysis) stellte sich als am besten für die Identifikation von Testspektren gefrorener Salzwasserlösungen als auch für die der anderen Probensets geeignet heraus. Die PLS-DA ist eine Art der PLS Regression, welche die in binärer Form vorliegende Information über die verschiedenen Salzgruppen bei der Erstellung des Vorhersagemodels miteinbezieht. LIBS Spektren von Salzen mit dem gleichen Kation im Wassereis können somit trotz nicht detektierbarer Chlor- und Schwefellinien auf Grund der Linienintensitäten und -profile anderer im Spektrum vorkommenden Emissionslinien unterschieden und damit identifiziert werden. Die Ergebnisse dieser Arbeit zeigen, dass LIBS eine geeignete Analysetechnik zur Untersuchung von Salzen und Salzeisen unter marsähnlichen Bedingungen darstellt und mit geeigneten Modellen Salze in verschiedenen Proben wie in Salzwassereis identifiziert werden können. Diese Ergebnisse sind nicht nur relevant für den Einsatz von LIBS zur Analyse von Salzen und Salzeisen für Missionen zum Mars, sondern können auch im Hinblick auf mögliche Missionen zu den Eismonden unseres Sonnensystems wie Europa und Enceladus herangezogen werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-02-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3623</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3623/schroeder_susanne.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
