<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:38Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3101">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3101</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: Regulation of glucose and fat metabolism in the liver by Carbohydrate Response Element Binding Protein (ChREBP) and impact of dietary influence</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Alkoholfreie Fettleber: Regulation der Glukose-und Fettstoffwechsel in der Leber durch Kohlenhydrate Response Element Binding Protein (ChREBP) und die Auswirkungen der Ernährung beeinflussen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Elkatry, Haiam Omar Mohamed</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Deregulations in hepatic lipid synthesis are often associated with obesity and type 2 diabetes, and therefore a perfect understanding of the regulation of this metabolic pathway appears essential to identify potential therapeutic targets. The liver is a major site for carbohydrate metabolism (glycolysis and glycogen synthesis) and triglyceride synthesis (lipogenesis). Carbohydrate-responsive element–binding protein (ChREBP) was implicated in the regulation by glucose of glycolytic and lipogenic genes, including those encoding l-pyruvate kinase (L-PK) and fatty acid synthase (FAS). In the last decade, increasing evidence has emerged to show that nutrients, in particular, glucose and fatty acids, are able to regulate hepatic gene expression in a transcriptional manner. Dietary polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) are potent inhibitors of hepatic glycolysis and lipogenesis. The aim of my study was to establish an assay to monitor the activation of ChREBP by analyzing cytoplasmatic – nuclear ‎translocation of a green fluorescence – ChREBP hybrid protein (ChREBP-GFP). The influence of different of sugars and ‎sweeteners (glucose, fructose, saccharin, aspartame, cyclamate, stevioside), ‎monounsaturated fatty acids [oleate (C18:1)] and polyunsaturated fatty acids [linoleate ‎‎(C18:2), eicosapentanoic acid (C20:5), docosahexaenoic acid (C22:6)] and polyphenols from ‎olive oil (oleuropein) on the activity of cloned human ChREBP was assessed by analyzing the ‎translocation of ChREBP-GFP from cytoplasm to nucleus which was monitored by an ‎automatic fluorescence microscope system. My results demonstrate that high concentration of glucose, fructose, cyclamate with insulin and saccharine with or without insulin stimulate ChREBP gene translocation from the cytosol to the nucleus, anabling increased DNA-binding and transcriptional activity of ChREBP. On the other hand, there were a suppressive effect of oleic and eicosapentanoic acids on ChREBP nuclear translocation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Deregulationen in der Leberlipidsynthese sind häufig mit Adipositas und Diabetes Typ 2 verbunden und daher ist ein detailliertes Verständnis der beteiligten, regulierenden Stoffwechselwege sehr wichtig, um künftig potentielle therapeutische Targets zu identifizieren. Die Leber ist der wichtigste Ort für den Kohlenhydratstoffwechsel (Glykolyse und Glykogen-Synthese) sowie Triglycerid-Synthese (Lipogenese). Carbohydrate-responsive element-binding protein (ChREBP) wurden in die Regulation durch Glucose der glykolytischen und lipogenen Gene einbezogen, einschließlich der codierten l-Pyruvatkinase (L-PK) und Fettsäuresynthase (FAS). In den letzten zehn Jahren konnte anhand verschiedener Untersuchungen bewiesen werden, dass Nährstoffe, vor allem Glukose und Fettsäuren in der Lage sind, hepatische Genexpressionen in einer Transkriptionsart zu regulieren. Diätetische mehrfach ungesättigte Fettsäuren (PUFAs) sind potente Inhibitoren der hepatischen Lipogenese und Glykolyse. Das Ziel unserer Untersuchungen war es, einen Test zu entwickeln , bei dem die Aktivierung von ChREBP durch die Analyse von cytoplasmatic – nuclear ‎translocation of a green fluorescence– zu ChREBP Hybrid-Protein (ChREBP-GFP) überwacht wird. Der Einfluss verschiedener Zucker und Süßstoffe (Glukose, Fruktose, Saccharin, Aspartam, Cyclamat, Steviosid), einfach ungesättigter Fettsäuren [Oleate (C18: 1)] und mehrfach ungesättigter Fettsäuren [Linoleat (C18: 2) , Eicosapentaensäure (C20: 5), Docosahexaensäure (C22: 6)] und Polyphenole aus Olivenöl (Oleuropein) wurden auf die von geklonten menschlichen ChREBP durch die Analyse der Translokation von ChREBP-GFP aus dem Zytoplasma auf den Nukleus beurteilt und durch ein automatisches Fluoreszenzmikroskop überwacht. Unsere Ergebnisse zeigen, dass hohe Konzentrationen von Glukose, Fruktose, Cyclamat mit Insulin und Saccharin mit bzw. ohne insulinstimulierenden ChREBP Gentranslokation aus dem Zytosol in den Zellkern nachgewiesen wurden und eine erhöhte DNA-Bindung und transkriptioneller Aktivität von ChREBP freisetzen. Andererseits gab es eine suppressive Wirkung von Ölsäure und Eicosapentaensäure auf ChREBP Nukleustranslokation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-10-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3101</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3101/elkatry_haiam.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
