<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:08Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1687">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1687</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Approximation of conformal mappings by circle patterns and discrete minimal surfaces</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Approximation konformer Abbildungen durch Kreismuster und diskrete Minimalflächen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bücking, Ulrike</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">To a rhombic embedding of a planar graph with quadrilateral faces and vertices colored black and white there is an associated isoradial circle pattern C_1 with centers of circles at white vertices and radii equal to the edge length. Let C_2 be another circle pattern such that the rhombi correspond to kites of intersecting circles with the same intersection angles. We consider the mapping g_C which maps the centers of circles and the intersection points to the corresponding points and which is an affine map on the rhombi. Let g be a locally injective holomorphic function. We specify the circle pattern C_2 by prescribing the radii or the angles on the boundary corresponding to values of log(g'). We show that g_C approximates g and its first derivative uniformly on compact subsets and that a suitably normalized sequence converges to g if the radii of C_1 converge to 0. In particular, we study the case that C_1 is a quasicrystallic circle pattern, that is the number of different edge directions of the rhombic embedding is bounded by a fixed constant (for the whole sequence). For a class of such circle patterns we prove the convergence of discrete partial derivatives of arbitrary order to the corresponding continuous derivatives of g. For this purpose we use a discrete version of Hölder's inequality and a discrete regularity lemma for solutions of elliptic differential equations. Furthermore, we consider the special case of regular circle patterns with the combinatorics of the square grid and two (different) intersection angles, which correspond to the two different edge directions. We show the uniqueness of the embedded infinite circle pattern (up to similarities) and prove an estimation for the quotients of radii of neighboring circles of such an (finite) circle pattern with error of order $1/$combinatorial distance of the circle to the boundary. We also carry this result over to certain classes of quasicrystallic circle patterns. In addition, we study the Z^a-circle patterns with the combinatorics of the square grid and regular intersection angles for 0&lt;a&lt;2. We prove the uniqueness (up to scaling) of such embedded circle patterns which cover a corresponding sector of the plane, subject to some conditions on the intersection angles and a. Similar results are also shown for some classes of quasicrystallic Z^a-circle patterns. For the case of orthogonal circle patterns with the combinatorics of the square grid we consider the problem to approximate an homeomorphism of a square onto a kite which is conformal in the interior and maps the corner points of the square to the corner points of the kite. We prove uniform convergence on the square and convergence of all discrete derivatives on compact sets which do not contain any of the corner points. This result is generalized for other polygonal domains and stereographic projections of spherical polygonal domains which are bounded by arcs of great circles and contained in an open half-sphere of the unit sphere. As a consequence, we prove the convergence of S-isothermic discrete minimal surfaces to the corresponding smooth minimal surfaces away from nodal points. Furthermore, we construct examples of S-isothermic discrete minimal surfaces.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Zu einer rhombischen Einbettung eines planaren Graphen mit viereckigen Flächen und schwarz-weiß gefärbten Knoten gehört ein isoradiales Kreismuster C_1 mit Mittelpunkten in den weißen Knoten und Radien gleich der Kantenlänge. Für ein weiteres Kreismuster C_2, bei dem den Rhomben Drachen von sich schneidenden Kreisen mit denselben Schnittwinkeln entsprechen, betrachten wir die Abbildung g_C, die entsprechende Mittelpunkte und Schnittpunkte der Kreismuster aufeinander abbildet und affin auf den Rhomben ist. Für eine lokal injektive holomorphe Funktion g bestimmen wir das Kreismuster C_2 durch die Vorgabe von Radien oder Winkeln am Rand mit Hilfe von log(g'). Wir zeigen, dass g_C die Abbildung g und ihre Ableitung gleichmäßig auf kompakten Teilmengen approximiert und eine geeignet normierte Folge solcher Abbildungen gegen g konvergiert, falls die Radien von C_1 gegen 0 konvergieren. Insbesondere untersuchen wir den Fall, dass C_1 ein quasikristallisches Kreismuster ist, d.h. die Anzahl der verschiedenen Kantenrichtungen der rhombischen Einbettung ist durch eine feste Konstante beschränkt (für die gesamte Folge). Für eine Klasse solcher Kreismuster beweisen wir die Konvergenz diskreter partieller Ableitungen beliebiger Ordnung gegen die entsprechenden kontinuierlichen Ableitungen von g. Dafür verwenden wir eine diskrete Hölderungleichung und ein diskretes Regularitätslemma für Lösungen elliptischer Differentialgleichungen. Außerdem betrachten wir den Spezialfall regelmäßiger Kreismuster mit Quadratgitterkombinatorik und zwei (verschiedenen) Schnittwinkeln, die den zwei Kantenrichtungen entprechen. Wir zeigen die Eindeutigkeit des eingebetteten unendlichen Kreismusters (bis auf Ähnlichkeitstransformationen) und beweisen eine Abschätzung für die Radienquotienten für benachbarte Kreise eines solchen (endlichen) Kreismuster mit Fehler der Ordnung 1/kombinatorischen Abstand der Kreise zum Rand. Dieses Ergebnis übertragen wir auch auf gewisse Klassen quasikristallischer Kreismuster. Ferner untersuchen wir die Z^a-Kreismuster mit Quadratgitterkombinatorik und regelmäßigen Schnittwinkeln für 0&lt;a&lt;2. Wir beweisen die Eindeutigkeit (bis auf Skalierung) solcher eingebetteter Kreismuster, die einen entsprechenenden Sektor der Ebene überdecken, unter bestimmten Bedingungen an die Schnittwinkel und a. Ähnliche Aussagen zeigen wir auch für einige Klassen quasikristallischer Z^a-Kreismuster. Für den Fall orthogonaler Kreismuster mit Quadratgitterkombinatorik betrachten wir das Problem, den im Inneren konformen Homeomorphismus eines Quadrates auf einen Drachen zu approximieren, der die Eckpunkte aufeinander abbildet. Wir beweisen gleichmäßige Konvergenz auf dem Quadrat und Konvergenz aller diskreter Ableitungen auf kompakten Mengen, die keinen der Eckpunkte enthalten. Dieses Ergebnis verallgemeinern wir für andere polygonale Gebiete und stereographische Projektionen sphärischer polygonaler Gebiete, die von Großkreisbögen begrenzt werden und in einer offenen Halbsphäre der Einheitssphäre liegen. Als Folgerung beweisen wir die Konvergenz von S-isothermen diskreten Minimalflächen außerhalb von Nabelpunkten gegen entsprechende glatte Minimalflächen. Des Weiteren konstruieren wir Beispiele von S-isothermen diskreten Minimalflächen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-02-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/x-empty</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1687</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17649</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17649</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1687/original_nichtvorhanden.tex</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1687/buecking_ulrike.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
