<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1872">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1872</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Sums of correlated exponentials: two types of Gaussian correlation structures</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Summen der korrelierten Exponentiale: zwei Typen der Gau√ü'schen Korrelationsstrukturen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Klymovskiy, Anton (Klimovsky, Anton)</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this thesis, we study the limiting behaviour of the large sums of strongly correlated exponentials as the number of their summands and the effective dimension of the correlation structure simultaneously tend to infinity. We consider two types of such sums which are generated by two a priori very different Gaussian correlation structures. The first type is a sum of hierarchically correlated random variables which is based on the partition function of Derrida's generalised random energy model (GREM) with external field. The second type is an infinitesimal sum of genuinely non-hierarchically strongly correlated random variables which is based on the partition function of the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick (SK) model with multidimensional spins. We consider the asymptotic behaviour (the thermodynamic limit) of these two sums on a logarithmic scale (i.e., at the level of free energy) and also at a more refined level of their fluctuations (i.e., at the level of weak limiting laws). Interestingly for the SK model with multidimensional spins, we find traces of a hierarchical organisation in the thermodynamic limit. This supports the conjectured in theoretical physics universal behaviour of the sums of such sort. Concerning the SK model with multidimensional spins, we obtain the following results. We prove upper and lower bounds on the free energy of this model in terms of variational inequalities. The bounds are based on a multidimensional extension of the Parisi functional. We generalise and unify the comparison scheme of Aizenman, Sims and Starr and the one of Guerra involving the GREM-inspired processes and Ruelle's probability cascades. For this purpose, an abstract quenched large deviations principle of the G√§rtner-Ellis type is obtained. We derive Talagrand's representation of Guerra's remainder term for the SK model with multidimensional spins. The derivation is based on well-known properties of Ruelle's probability cascades and the Bolthausen-Sznitman coalescent. We study the properties of the multidimensional Parisi functional by establishing a link with a certain class of semi-linear partial differential equations. We embed the problem of strict convexity of the Parisi functional in a more general setting and prove the convexity in some particular cases which, however, do not cover the original setup of Talagrand. Finally, we prove the Parisi formula for the local free energy in the case of multidimensional Gaussian a priori distribution of spins using Talagrand's methodology of a priori estimates. Concerning the GREM in the presence of uniform external field, we obtain the following results. We compute the fluctuations of the ground state and of the partition function in the thermodynamic limit for all admissible values of parameters. We find that the fluctuations are described by a hierarchical structure which is obtained by a certain coarse-graining of the initial hierarchical structure of the GREM with external field. We provide an explicit formula for the free energy of the model. We also derive some large deviation results providing an expression for the free energy in a class of models with Gaussian Hamiltonians and external field. Finally, we prove that the coarse-grained parts of the system emerging in the thermodynamic limit tend to have a certain optimal magnetisation, as prescribed by strength of external field and by parameters of the GREM.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Dissertation behandelt das Grenzwertverhalten der gro√üen Summen der stark korrelierten Exponenziale, w√§hrend die Anzahl ihren Summanden und die effektive Dimension der Korrelationsstruktur gleichzeitig gegen Unendlichkeit gehen. Wir betrachten zwei Arten dieser Summen, die durch die a priori sehr unterschiedliche Gau√ü'schen Korrelationsstrukturen erzeugt werden. Die erste Art ist eine Summe der hierarchisch korrelierten Zufallsvariablen, die auf der Zustandssumme von Derrida's generalised random energy model (GREM) mit externem Feld basiert. Die zweite Art ist eine infinitesimale Summe der echt nicht-hierarchisch stark korrelierten Zufallsvariablen, die auf der Zustandssumme vom Sherrington-Kirkpatrick (SK) Modell mit mehrdimensionalen Spins basiert. Wir betrachten das asymptotische Verhalten (der thermodynamische Limes) dieser Summen auf der logarithmischen Skala (d.h., auf dem Niveau der freien Energie) und au√üerdem auf dem pr√§ziseren Niveau ihrer Fluktuationen (d.h., auf dem Niveau der schwachen Grenzwertverteilungen). Interessanterweise finden wir auch im SK Modell mit mehrdimensionalen Spins Spuren der hierarchischen Organisation im thermodynamischen Limes. Dies unterst√ºtzt das hypothetische universale Verhalten dieser Summen aus der theoretischen Physik. Bez√ºglich des SK Modells mit mehrdimensionalen Spins erzielen wir die folgenden Ergebnisse. Wir beweisen die oberen und unteren Schranken f√ºr die freie Energie mittels Variationsungleichungen, die auf der mehrdimensionalen Verallgemeinerung des Parisi-Funktionals basieren. Wir setzen das Vergleichsschema von Aizenman, Sims und Starr und das von Guerra ein, die die GREM-inspirierten Prozesse und Ruell'schen Wahrscheinlichkeitskaskaden involvieren. Hierf√ºr beweisen wir ein abstraktes ‚Äúquenched‚Ä? Prinzip der gro√üen Abweichungen von G√§rtner-Ellis Art. Mittels der Eigenschaften der Ruelle'schen Wahrscheinlichkeitskaskaden und des Bolthausen-Sznitman Koaleszents leiten wir die Darstellung von Talagrand des Restterms von Guerra f√ºr das SK Modell mit mehrdimensionalen Spins ab. Wir untersuchen die Eigenschaften des mehrdimensionalen Parisi-Funktionals, indem wir eine Verbindung mit einer Kategorie semi-linearer partieller Differentialgleichungen herstellen. Wir betten das Problem der strengen Konvexit√§t des Parisi-Funktionals in einen allgemeineren Kontext ein. Wir zeigen die Konvexit√§t in einigen F√§llen, welche jedoch nicht die urspr√ºngliche Formulierung von Talagrand umfassen. Schlie√ülich beweisen wir die Parisi-Formel f√ºr die lokale freie Energie im Fall der mehrdimensionalen Gau√ü'schen a priori Verteilung der Spins mit der Methodologie der a priori Absch√§tzungen von Talagrand. Bez√ºglich des GREMs in Anwesenheit des uniformen externen Felds erzielen wir die folgenden Ergebnisse. Wir berechnen die Fluktuationen des Grundzustandes und der Zustandssumme im thermodynamischen Limes f√ºr alle zul√§ssigen Werte der Parameter. Wir finden, dass im thermodynamischen Limes die Fluktuationen durch eine hierarchische Struktur beschrieben sind. Diese Struktur ist eine Grobk√∂rnung der urspr√ºnglichen hierarchischen Struktur des GREMs mit externem Feld. Wir stellen eine explizite Formel f√ºr die freie Energie des Modells zur Verf√ºgung. Wir leiten auch einige Resultate zu den gro√üen Abweichungen, welche einen Ausdruck f√ºr die freie Energie einiger Modelle mit Gau√ü'schen Hamiltonians und externem Feld erm√∂glichen, her. Schlie√ülich beweisen wir, dass die grobk√∂rnigen Teile des Systems, die in der thermodynamischen Limes auftauchen, dazu neigen eine optimale Magnetisierung zu haben. Diese Magnetisierung ist durch die St√§rke des externen Felds und durch die Parameter des GREMs vorgeschrieben.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-08-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1872</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-19180</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-19180</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1872/klymovskiy_anton.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
