<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3396">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3396</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">On the chaotic behaviour of stochastic flows</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Über das chaotische Verhalten von stochastischen Flüssen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Biskamp, Moritz Friedrich Wilhelm Jochen Elard</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">It has been suggested that stochastic flows are used to model the spread of passive tracers in a turbulent fluid. One might think of the evolution in time of an oil spill on the surface of the ocean. Mathematically stochastic flows can be seen as solutions of certain stochastic differential equations which depend continuously on the initial value. In this thesis we are interested in the analysis of the chaotic behaviour of these objects. From Scheutzow and Steinsaltz (2002) it is known that for a broad class of stochastic flows a non-trivial bounded connected set expands linearly in time if it does not collapse. Nevertheless, upper and lower bounds for the linear growth turn out to be far from each other in some examples. A special class of stochastic flows are isotropic Brownian flows. These flows are a fairly natural class of stochastic flows and have been first introduced by Ito (1956) and Yaglom (1957). For this class of stochastic flows the image of a single point is a Brownian motion, and the covariance tensor between two different Brownian motions is an isotropic function of their positions. For planar isotropic Brownian flows with a strictly positive top-Lyapunov exponent van Bargen (2010) determined the precise linear growth rate following an idea of Dolgopyat, Kaloshin, and Koralov (2004). The first main result of this thesis extends this result to an asymptotic support thoerem for planar isotropic Brownian flows: We will show that the set of linearly time-scaled trajectories starting in a non-trivial compact connected set is asymptotically close (in the Hausdorff distance) to the set of Lipschitz continuous functions, where the Lipschitz constant is the linear growth rate mentioned above. The second main result of this thesis shows a relation between entropy of a stochastic flow and its positive Lyapunov exponents. Here, we use the notion of metric entropy introduced by Kolmogorov (1958) and Sinai (1959), which is a purely-measure theoretic way of measuring the chaotic behaviour of some evolution process. Whereas a more geometric way is given by the asymptotic exponential rate of separation of nearby trajectories. These rates of divergence are called the Lyapunov exponents of the flow. The formula relating these two objects is known as Pesin's formula and was first established by Pesin in the late 1970s for so-called deterministic dynamical systems acting on a compact Riemannian manifold. Certain stochastic flows can be seen as so-called random dynamical systems, which we will introduce in detail later. For these random dynamical systems on a compact state space Pesin's formula has been proved by Ledrappier and Young (1988) and Liu and Qian (1995). In this thesis we will show that Pesin's formula holds true even for random dynamical systems on the non-compact state space R^d. By this we will finally show that a broad class of stochastic flows on R^d satisfies Pesin's formula. In order to prove Pesin's formula for random dynamical systems on R^d we need the so-called absolute continuity theorem of local stable manifolds. These manifolds correspond to the different Lyapunov exponents and consist of those points in space whose trajectories converge to each other exponentially at least with the rate given by the Lyapunov exponent. The main consequence of the absolute continuity theorem is that the Lebesgue measure conditioned on the family of local stable manifolds and the induced Lebesgue measure on these local stable manifolds are absolutely continuous (in fact, even equivalent). Roughly speaking, this means that the local stable manifolds form a proper partition of the state space. This theorem was proved in detail for deterministic dynamical systems on a Riemannian manifold in Katok and Strelcyn (1986). The third main result of this thesis is to extend the result from Katok and Strelcyn (1986) to random dynamical systems on R^d.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Stochastische Flüsse werden häufig für die Beschreibung des Verhaltens von passiven Partikeln in einem turbulenten Fluid genutzt. Man denke etwa an die zeitliche Entwicklung eines Ölfeldes auf der Oberfläche eines Ozeans. Mathematisch können stochastische Flüsse als Lösung von stochastischen Differentialgleichungen mit stetiger Abhängigkeit vom Anfangswert gesehen werden. In dieser Arbeit wollen wir das chaotische Verhalten dieser Objekte analysieren. Scheutzow und Steinsaltz (2002) haben gezeigt, dass sich für eine große Klasse stochastischer Flüsse eine nicht triviale beschränkte zusammenhängende Menge linear ausbreitet, wenn sie nicht auf einen Punkt zusammenschrumpft. An einigen Beispielen zeigt sich, dass obere und untere Schranken für die lineare Ausbreitung weit auseinander liegen. Eine spezielle Klasse von stochastischen Flüssen sind isotrope Brownsche Flüsse. Diese Flüsse bilden eine natürliche Klasse von stochastischen Flüssen und wurden von Itô (1956) und Yaglom (1957) eingeführt. Das Bild eines Punktes unter diesen Flüssen ist eine Brownsche Bewegung und der Kovarianztensor zwischen zwei verschiedenen Brownschen Bewegungen eine isotrope Funktion allein abhängig von ihren Positionen. Einer Idee von Dolgopyat, Kaloshin und Koralov (2004) folgend, hat van Bargen (2010) für planare isotrope Brownsche Flüsse mit einem positiven Top-Lyapunov Exponenten die genaue lineare Wachstumsrate bestimmen können. Das erste Hauptresultat der vorliegenden Arbeit erweitert diese Aussage und beschreibt den asymptotischen Träger von Trajektorien eines planaren isotrope Brownsche Flüsse: Wir zeigen, dass die Menge der linear skalierten Trajektorien mit Anfangswert in einer nicht trivialen kompakten zusammenhängenden Menge gegen die Menge der Lipschitz Funktionen konvergiert, wobei die Lipschtitz Konstante durch die oben erwähnte lineare Wachstumsrate gegeben ist. Konvergenz ist hier im Sinne der Hausdorff Metrik zu verstehen. Das zweite Hauptresultat dieser Arbeit ist die Untersuchung der Entropie eines stochastischen Flusses und die Relation zu seinen positiven Lyapunov Exponenten. Wir werden hier die sogenannte metrische Entropie verwenden, die von Kolmogorov (1958) und Sinai (1959) eingeführt wurde. Diese Größe beruht auf einem rein maß-theoretischen Ansatz um das chaotische Verhalten eines Evolutionsprozesses zu messen. Demgegenüber beschreibt die asymptotische exponentielle Rate des Auseinanderstrebens von Trajektorien von nah beieinander liegenden Anfangswerten einen geometrischeren Ansatz - diese Divergenzraten werden Lyapunov Exponenten des Flusses genannt. Die Formel, die diese beiden Größen in Relation zu einander setzt, ist als Pesin Formel bekannt und wurde in den 1970er Jahren von Pesin für sogenannte deterministische dynamische Systeme zunächst gezeigt. Unter gewissen Voraussetzungen können stochastische Flüsse als sogenannte izufällige dynamische Systeme aufgefasst werden. Diese Systeme werden wir später im Detail einführen. Für zufällige dynamische Systeme auf einem kompakten Zustandsraum wurde Pesins Formel von Ledrappier und Young (1988) und Liu und Qian (1995) gezeigt. In der vorliegenden Arbeit werden wir Pesins Formel für zufällige dynamische Systeme auf dem nicht kompakten Zustandsraum R^d verallgemeinern. Im Anschluss können wir damit dann zeigen, dass Pesins Formul auch für eine große Klasse von stochastischen Flüssen auf R^d gilt. Um Pesins Formel für zufällige dynamische Systeme auf R^d zu zeigen, benötigen wir eine Aussage über die Absolutstetigkeit von Maßen auf lokalen stabilen Mannigfaltigkeiten. Diese Mannigfaltigkeiten korrespondieren zu den verschiedenen Lyapunov Exponenten und bestehen aus den Punkten des Zustandsraumes, deren Trajektorien mindestens mit exponentieller Rate, gegeben durch die Lyapunov Exponenten, zueinander konvergieren. Die Hauptfolgerung dieses Theorems ist, dass die Lebesgue Maße bedingt auf die lokalen stabilen Mannigfaltigkeiten und das auf diesen Mannigfaltigkeiten induzierte Lebesgue Maß absolut stetig (und sogar äquivalent) sind. Grob gesprochen bedeutet dies, dass die lokalen stabilen Mannigfaltigkeiten eine geeignete Partition des Raumes bilden. Dieses Resultat wurde von Katok und Strelcyn (1986) für deterministische dynamische Systeme auf einer kompakten Riemannschen Mannigfaltigkeit bewiesen. Das dritte Hauptresultat der vorliegenden Arbeit ist die Erweiterung dieser Aussage von Katok und Strelcyn (1986) auf zufällige dynamische Systeme auf dem R^d.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-07-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3396</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36149</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36149</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3396/biskamp_moritz.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
