<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:56Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2951">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2951</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:510</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Numerical analysis of PDE constrained optimal control problems with pointwise inequality constraints on the state and the control</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Numerische Analysis von Optimalsteuerungsproblemen mit partiellen Differentialgleichungen und punktweisen Ungleichungsbeschränkungen an Zustand und Steuerung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Neitzel, Ira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:510</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The purpose of this thesis is the numerical analysis of optimal control problems with partial differential equations (PDEs), whose control or state is subject to pointwise inequality constraints. We are specifically interested in nonconvex problems with semilinear state equation. It is intrinsic to the considered problem class that solutions can often only be found by numerical methods. Consequently, one is interested in estimating the error between a (local) solution of the continuous problem and an associated discrete local solution. A basic requirement for this purpose is a thorough discussion of the continuous problem. In the presence of pointwise state constraints this leads to specific difficulties of analytical and numerical nature. These difficulties have to be approached either directly or by means of regularization. With this thesis we make several new contributions to the discussion of optimal control problems with pointwise state constraints but also those with pure control constraints. After a short introduction into the field of research and providing some basic theoretical results we discuss in Chapter 3 a semiinfinite elliptic optimal control problem. Known results on necessary and sufficient optimality conditions, the comparably high regularity of solutions to elliptic PDEs, as well as the finite dimensional control space allows to address a priori discretization error estimates for this problem directly, i.e. without further regularization. Our main result in this chapter is an a priori error bound of order O(h^2|ln h|) for local solutions of a finite element discretization with mesh size h of this optimal control problem in two space dimensions. For that, we rely on certain assumptions on the structure of the active set. In Chapter 4 we address a parabolic optimal control problem with L^infty bounds on the control functions, semilinear state equation, and pointwise state constraints in the whole space-time-domain. In contrast to the elliptic problem discussed in Chapter 3, second order sufficient conditions areonly available for one-dimensional spatial domains. Moreover, the use of control functions instead of finitely many control parameters does not allow any a priori assumptions on the structure of the active sets. Therefore, we use a Lavrentiev regularization as suggested originally by Meyer, Rösch and Tröltzsch. Consequently, we can make use of available higher regularity results for the Lagrange multipliers that allow for a deeper analysis. We prove a convergence result for locally optimal solutions of the regularized problem and show local uniqueness of regularized local solutions. In Chapter 5 we analyze the finite element discretization of a control-constrained parabolic optimal control problem with semilinear state equation. We prove error estimates for discrete local solutions in the L^2-norm. We extend known results for linear-quadratic problems to the nonconvex setting. In particular, we have to prove boundedness results for the semidiscrete and discrete state functions in the L^infty-norm that hold independently of the discretization parameters. Moreover, the discussion of local solutions requires convergence results and quadratic growth conditions to be considered in the same spaces.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Gegenstand dieser Arbeit ist die numerische Analysis von Optimierungsproblemen mit partiellen Differentialgleichungen (PDEs), deren Zustand oder Steuerung punktweisen Ungleichungsbeschränkungen unterliegt. Wir interessieren uns insbesondere für nichtkonvexe Probleme mit semilinearer Zustandsgleichung. Es liegt in der Natur derartiger Probleme, dass eine Lösung oftmals nur numerisch gefunden werden kann. Man interessiert sich deshalb für den Fehler zwischen einer (lokalen) Lösung des kontinuierlichen Problems und einer zugehörigen (lokalen) diskreten Lösung. Eine umfassende Diskussion des kontinuierliche Problems ist dabei eine Grundvoraussetzung. Insbesondere bei vorhanden punktweisen Zustandsbeschränkungen treten spezifische Schwierigkeiten sowohl analytischer als auch numerischer Art auf, denen man entweder direkt oder mit Hilfe von Regularisierungsansätzen begegnen kann. Mit dieser Dissertation leisten wir auf verschiedene Weise neue Beiträge zur Diskussion von Optimalsteuerungsproblemen mit punktweisen Zustandsschranken aber auch reinen Kontrollschranken. Nach kurzer Einführung in die Thematik und Bereitstellung gewisser Grundlagen beschäftigen wir uns in Kapitel 3 mit einem elliptischen semiinfiniten Optimalsteuerungsproblem. Bekannte Resultate zu notwendigen und hinreichenden Optimalitätsbedingungen, die vergleichsweise hohe Regularität von Lösungen elliptischer PDEs und die Endlichdimensionalität des Steuerungsraumes lassen eine direkte Diskussion von a priori Diskretisierungsfehlerabschätzungen für dieses Problem zu. Unser Hauptergebnis in diesem Kapitel ist eine a priori Fehlerschranke der Ordnung O(h^2|ln h|) für lokale Lösungen einer Finite-Elemente-Diskretisierung des Optimalsteuerungsproblems mit Gitterweite h in einem zweidimensionalen Ortsgebiet. Dazu stellen wir gewisse Annahmen an die Struktur der aktiven Menge. In Kapitel 4 betrachten wir ein parabolisches Optimalsteuerungsproblem mit punktweise beschräkten Steuerungsfunktionen, semilinearer Zustandsgleichung und punktweisen Zustandsbeschränkungen im gesamten Orts-Zeit-Gebiet. Im Gegensatz zu dem in Kapitel 3 diskutierten elliptischen Problem sind hier u.a. hinreichende Bedingungen zweiter Ordnung nur für eindimensionale Ortsgebiete verfügbar. Auch läßt die Verwendung von Steuerungsfunktionen an Stelle endlich vieler Parameter keine sinnvollen a priori Annahmen an die Struktur der aktiven Menge zu. Wir regularisieren daher das Problem mit der auf Meyer, Rösch und Tröltzsch zurückgehenden Lavrentievregularisierung, und können so unter anderem auf bekannte Resultate zurückgreifen, die eine höhere Regularität der Lagrangeschen Multiplikatoren sichern und eine tiefergehende Analysis ermöglichen. Wir beweisen ein Konvergenzresultat für lokale Lösungen des regularisierten Problems und weisen die lokale Eindeutigkeit regularisierter Lösungen nach. In Kapitel 5 untersuchen wir die Finite-Element-Diskretisierung eines kontrollbeschränkten parabolischen Optimalsteuerungsproblems mit semilinearer Zustandsgleichung. Wir beweisen Fehlerordnungen für diskrete lokale Lösungen in der L^2-Norm. Dabei erweitern wir Resultate, die für linear-quadratische Probleme bekannt sind, auf den nichtkonvexen Fall. Es müssen insbesondere Beschränktheitsresultate in der L^infty-Norm der semidiskreten und diskreten Zustände gezeigt werden, die unabhängig von den Diskretisierungsparametern gelten. Außerdem erfordert die Diskussion lokal optimaler Lösungen, dass Konvergenzresultate und quadratische Wachstumsbedingungen in denselben Normen betrachtet werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-07-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2951</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2951/neitzel_ira.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
