<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3451">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3451</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-07-07</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:periodicalpart</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:720</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">MSD: Masterstudium Denkmalpflege an der TU Berlin; Jahrbuch</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">MSD: Masterprogram in Heritage Conservation Berlin Institute of Technology; annual</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sack, Dorothée</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brauchle, Antonia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gussone, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kurapkat, Dietmar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spiegel, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:720</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Das Jahrbuch des Masterstudiums Denkmalpflege der TU Berlin, kurz MSD Jahrbuch genannt, wird von dem Fachgebiet Historische Bauforschung unter der Leitung von Frau Professor Dorothée Sack herausgegeben. Es berichtet über die Aktivitäten des Fachgebiets und des angeschlossenen Masterstudium Denkmalpflege. Zudem dient das MSD Jahrbuch der Publikation von Kurzberichten über die laufenden Forschungsprojekten, die Ergebnisse der jeweiligen MSD-Jahrgangsprojekte und die Abschlussarbeiten eines jeden Studienjahrganges in Poster-Form sowie eine Kurzvorstellung von abgeschlossenen Dissertationen oder Diplomarbeiten.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The Annual of the master's program Heritage Conservation (Masterstudium Denkmalpflege) of Berlin Institute of Technology (TU Berlin) shortly called MSD Annual is published by the Department of Building Archaeology under the direction of Professor Dorothée Sack. It reports on the activities of the Department and the connected master's program Heritage Conservation. In addition, the MSD Annual serves the publication of short reports on current research projects, the results of the respective MSD project and short presentations of the master theses of each academic year in poster form. Furthermore a brief presentation of completed dissertations or diploma theses may be included.</dc:description>
          <dc:contributor>Fachgebiet  Historische Bauforschung, Masterstudium Denkmalpflege</dc:contributor>
          <dc:date>2012-09-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>periodicalpart</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:periodicalpart</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3451</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-931278-51-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3451/MSD-2007-09_Heft5.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
