<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:07Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1447">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1447</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Entwicklung und Charakterisierung von Tamoxifen-regulierbaren onkolytischen adenoviralen Vektoren zur Behandlung von Tumorerkrankungen</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">development and characterisation of tamoxifen-regulated oncolytic adenoviral vectors for treatment of tumors</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sipo, Isaac</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der vorliegenden Dissertation wurden vier Fusionsproteine ME, MEM, EM und EÔ?ÑNLSM durch Fusion des adenoviralen pRB-Bindungsdom√§ne-deletierten E1A-Mutanten (E1AÔ?ÑpRB) mit der mutierten HBD des Maus-ER (Mer) konstruiert, mit dem Ziel, ihre Aktivit√§t in Abh√§ngigkeit von Tam- bzw. OHT zu kontrollieren. Die systematische Charakterisierung der Fusionsproteine ergab, dass alle Konstrukte in Abh√§ngigkeit von Tam bzw. OHT die Funktionen des nativen adenoviralen E1A-Proteins beibehalten. Auf dieser Grundlage wurden vier lungenspezifische Tam-regulierbare oAdV (Tam-oAdV) entwickelt (Ad.ME, Ad.MEM, Ad.EM bzw. Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM), in denen die kodierenden cDNA f√ºr die Fusionsproteine ME, MEM, EM bzw. EÔ?ÑNLSM unter Kontrolle des SP-B Promotors in die E1-Region eines E1/E3-deletierten AdV-Genoms inseriert wurden. Ad.MEM und Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM wiesen die bessere Regulationskapazit√§t auf, w√§hrend Ad.EM eine niedrigere Regulationskapazit√§t im Vergleich zu Ad.MEM und Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM aber eine effizientere Replikation und Onkolyse zeigte. Das Konstrukt Ad.ME war hingegen durch eine ineffiziente Regulation und ein niedriges onkolytisches Potential gekennzeichnet. In M√§usen mit subkutanen humanen Lungen-Adenokarzinomxenograften zeigten Ad.EM und Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM, einen signifikanten Antitumoreffekt in Tam-behandelten M√§usen, aber eine ineffiziente Tam-abh√§ngige Regulation. Eine Kombination der Tam-oAdV mit dem tTS erm√∂glichte eine Steigerung der Regulationskapazit√§t der Replikation der Tam-oAdV. Des Weiteren wurde durch Trans-Komplementierung der Replikation eines FasL-exprimierenden Ad-Vektors (Ad5Tight1-FasL) durch Ad.MEM bzw. Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM in H441-Zellen einen OHT-abh√§ngigen synergistischen Effekt auf der onkolytischen Effizienz der Tam-oAdV erzielt. In der Summe wurde in dieser Arbeit eine neue Generation von pharmakologisch regulierbaren oAdV entwickelt, deren Regulationsprinzip im Gegensatz zu den bisherigen regulierbaren oAdV auf der Kontrolle der Aktivit√§t statt der Expression des essentiellen Genproduktes basiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In the present study four fusion proteins (ME, MEM, EM and EÔ?ÑNLSM) were developed by fusing a mutated hormone-binding domain (HBD) of murine estrogen receptor (Mer) with the adenoviral E1A (E1AÔ?ÑpRB) deleted in the pRB-binding site. A systematic characterisation of these fusion proteins showed that all constructs retain the functions of the native E1A in a tamoxifen (Tam) and hydroxy-tamoxifen (OHT) dependant manner. Based on these promising results four lung specific Tam-dependant oncolytic adenoviruses (Tam-oAdV) termed Ad.ME, Ad.MEM, Ad.EM and Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM were then constructed in which the coding cDNAs for ME, MEM, EM and EÔ?ÑNLSM under control of the SP-B Promotor were respectively inserted in E1-Region of E1/E3-deleted AdV-Genom. Ad.MEM and Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM showed a higher regulation capacity compared to Ad.EM. However Ad.EM displayed the best replication and oncolytic efficiency. The construct Ad.ME was less efficient for both regulation and oncolysis. In mice bearing subcutan lung adenocarcinoma xenografts and infected with Ad.EM or Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM the tumor growth was significantly reduced after treatment with Tam. However, the Tam-dependant regulation of tumor growth was inefficient in vivo. The combination of Tam-oAdV with the tTS resulted in tighter regulation of viral replication. In further investigations the trans-complementation of a FasL-expressing Ad vector (Ad5Tight1-FasL) by Ad.MEM and Ad.EÔ?ÑNLSM results in a Tam-dependant synergistic effect on the oncolytic efficient of Tam-oAdV in H441 cell. Taken together a new generation of pharmacologically controlled oAdV was developed whose principle of regulation is based on the control of viral gene products¬¥s activities and not on their expression.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-02-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-14986</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-14986</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1447/original_Entwicklung_und_Charakterisierung_von_Tamoxifen.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1447/sipo.Dissertation.2007.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
