<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:52Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2083">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2083</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Synthesis, Characterization and Catalysis of Nanostructured Vanadia Model Catalysts for Partial Oxidation of Propane</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Herbert, Rita</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Nanostructured vanadia model catalysts supported by silica were synthesized in a multi-step procedure as well as through incipient wetness impregnation. Afterwards, the samples were characterized and tested in the oxidative dehydrogenation (ODH)of propane. Silica supports used were mesoporous SBA-15 and Aerosil 300. The multi-step synthesis includes a surface functionalization and an ion exchange with decavanadate ions. One aim of this study was the investigation of the in uence between two support materials and between different synthesis methods concerning the vanadia structure and to find a correlation to their catalytic behavior. Therefore, highly dispersed vanadia species with a similar vanadium density of 0.7 V atoms/nm2 were prepared. The samples were thoroughly characterized by nitrogen adsorption-desorption, small-angle XRD, TEM, XPS, Raman- and UV-vis spectroscopy. Furthermore, reactivity was tested with TPR besides catalytic test. It could be shown that the multi-step procedure has a stabilizing effect on the mesoporous material. After mechanical, thermal and hydrothermal treatment, the sample treated with surface functionalization shows a higher stability than blank SBA-15. The blank SBA-15 shows a signiffcant decrease of the BET surface area already at a mechanical treatment already at 75 MPa, whereas a significant change of the surface area in the multi-step samples appears not until at 376 MPa. After pressure treatment at 752 MPa no mesoporous structure can be observed anymore for blank SBA-15, but for the multi-step sample it is in parts still observable. The impregnated samples show the same behavior as blank SBA-15. The enhanced stability has a positive influence on reaction behavior. The multi-step sample pressed at 752 MPa shows in the ODH of propane a higher selectivity towards propene than the impregnated sample treated in the same way. This can be explained by accessibility of active sites within the samples. In the impregnated sample are more active sites blocked than in the multi-step sample, due to the complete loss of mesoporous structure. When comparing both support materials and the different synthesis methods, an increase of the degree of polymerization can be observed in the following order: VxOy/SBA-15 multi-step - VxOy/SBA-15 impregnated - VxOy/A300 multi-step - VxOy/A300 impregnated. It can be said that the spectroscopic data show a more distinct influence on the degree of polymerization of the support materials, whereas TPR data show clear differences among the synthesis methods. In the oxidative dehydrogenation of propane, no differences could be observed concerning the selectivities at similar conversions. This leads to the assumption that the reactivity is highly influenced by the composition of the gas phase. Another issue in this study were first investigations on an SBA-15/titanium system, which can be applied as a support material for vanadia. For this purpose, several loadings of titania were impregnated on SBA-15 and characterized. Additionally, a Ti/SBA-15 sample with vanadium was synthesized, spectroscopically characterized and tested in the oxidative dehydrogenation of propane. The results show for conversion and selectivity a similar behavior at a reaction temperature of 450 °C as vanadium on blank SBA-15, but clear differences at a reaction temperature of 500 °C. For V-Ti/SBA-15 at a reaction temperature of 500 °C a signiffcant increase of conversion of propane can be observed</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Nanostrukturierte Vanadiumoxidmodellkatalysatoren, geträgert auf Siliziumdioxid, wurden sowohl mit einem mehrstufigen Verfahren als auch mit herkömmlicher Imprägnierung(incipient wetness impregnation) synthetisiert, charakterisiert und in der oxidativen Dehydrierung von Propan getestet. Als Siliziumdioxidträgermaterial wurde zum einen mesoporöses SBA-15 und zum anderen Aerosil 300 eingesetzt. Das mehrstufige Syntheseverfahren beinhaltet eine Funktionalisierung der SiO2-Oberfläche und einen Ionenaustausch mit Decavanadationen. Ein Ziel war es die Unterschiede zwischen den beiden Trägermaterialien und den Synthesemethoden hinsichtlich der Vanadiumstruktur und dem katalytischen Verhaltens zu untersuchen und einen Zusammenhang herauszuarbeiten. Um möglichst vergleichbare hochdisperse Vanadiumoxidspezies zu erhalten, wurde eine Vanadiumdichte von 0,7 V-atome/nm2 eingestellt. Die Proben wurden mit Stickstoff-Adsorption-Desorption, Kleinwinkel XRD, TEM, XPS, Raman- und UV-vis Spektroskopie charakterisiert. Die Reaktivität wurde zusätzlich mit TPR untersucht. Dabei konnte gezeigt werden, dass die mehrstufige Synthesemethode einen Stabilisierungseffekt auf das mesoporösen Material hat. Nach mechanischer, thermischer und hydrothermischer Belastung zeigte das Material nach der Oberflächenfunktionalisierung durch diese Methode eine höhere Stabilität als das reine SBA-15. Während das reine SBA-15 schon bei 75 MPa mechanischen Druckbehandlung einen deutlichen Rückgang der BET-Oberfläche aufweist, ändern sich die Proben, die mit dem mehrstufigen Verfahren hergestellt wurden, bis zu einem Druck von 376 MPa nur geringfügig. Nach einer mechanischen Druckbehandlung von 752 MPa lässt sich bei reinem SBA-15 keine mesoporöse Struktur mehr erkennen, bei den Proben des mehrstufuigen Verfahrens sind dahingegen noch Strukturen sichtbar. Die imprägnierten Proben zeigen die gleichen Stabilitätseigenschaften wie das reine SBA-15. Diese erhöhte Stabilität hat einen positiven Einfluss auf die Testreaktion. Die mit 752 MPa gepresste mehrstufig hergestellte Probe zeigt in der ODH von Propan eine höhere Selektivität zu Propen, als die imprägnierte Probe. Das ist auf die Erreichbarkeit der aktiven Zentren zurückzuführen, von denen in der imprägnierten Probe ein größerer Anteil nicht erreichbar ist. Beim Vergleich der verschieden präparierten Proben auf den unterschiedlichen Trägermaterialien kann eine Erhöhung des Polymerisierungsgrades in folgender Reihenfolge beobachtet werden: VxOy/SBA-15 mehrstufig - VxOy/SBA-15 imprägniert - VxOy/A300 mehrstufig - VxOy/A300 imprägniert. Dabei zeigen die spektroskopischen Daten einen deutlichen Einfluss der unterschiedlichen Trägermaterialien auf den Polymerisationsgrad, während die TPR Ergebnisse klare Unterschiede zwischen den Synthesemethoden aufweisen. Diese Unterschiede haben jedoch keinen signifikanten Einfluss in der oxidativen Dehydrierung (ODH) von Propan bzgl. der Selektivitäten (bei gleichen Umsätzen). Das führt zu der Annahme, dass die Zusammensetzung der Gasphase einen starken Einfluss auf die Reaktivität des Vanadiumoxids hat. Ein weiteres Thema dieser Arbeit waren erste Untersuchungen zu einem SBA-15 - Titansystem, das als Trägermaterial für Vanadiumoxid dienen kann. Dafür wurden verschiedene Beladungen von Titanoxid auf SBA-15 aufgebracht und harakterisiert. Zusätzlich wurde eine Probe Ti/SBA-15 mit Vanadium hergestellt, spektroskopisch untersucht und in der oxidativen Dehydrierung von Propan gestestet. Die Ergebnisse hier zeigen bezüglich Umsatz und Selektivität ein ähnliches Verhalten wie Vanadium auf reinem SBA-15 bei 450 °C aber ein deutlich anderes Verhalten bei 500 °C. Bei der V-Ti/SBA-15 Probe ist bei einer Reaktionstemperatur von 500 °C ein deutlicher Anstieg des Propanumsatzes zu beobachten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2083/herbert_rita.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
