<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:33Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1557">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1557</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:230</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">A Commentary on the "De predestinatione et prescientia, paradiso et inferno" by Giles of Rome on the Basis of MS Cambrai BM 487 (455)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ein Kommentar des Traktates "De predestinatione et prescientia, paradiso et inferno" von Aegidius von Rom auf Basis der Handschrift Cambrai BM 487 (455)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Holstein, Bettina Elena</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:230</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This dissertation "A Commentary on the De predestinatione et prescientia, paradiso et inferno by Giles of Rome on the basis of MS Cambrai BM 487 (455)" provides a historical commentary of the theological and philosophical treatise De predestinatione et prescientia, paradiso et inferno by Giles of Rome, written ca. 1287-90. It aims to show how Giles presents and structures his argument and how he tackles the combination of theological and philosophical questions and his viewpoints concerning predestination, paradise and hell. The commentary demonstrates the importance and standing of a single theological treatise within the context of Giles's resumed university career (1285), his particular interest in the educational organisation of his own Order and his relationship with Church or university authorities. De predestinatione is a mainly theological treatise that to date has passed by modern scholarship, which is not unusual for Giles's theological oeuvre. It covers a wide-ranging number of topics whose arrangement of questions is unique amongst contemporary works. These are related to the conditions of human existence before and after death. It is a compilation of texts, some of which Giles took from previous works such as his Sentence commentaries and his quodlibetal questions. Its style considerably varies between the three main sections and points towards prospective theology students of Giles's Order, the Hermits of St Augustine, as the audience for whom he intended the treatise. Its date of composition c. 1287-90 places it at a point of Giles's career when he received widespread recognition and respect. Although De predestinatione is only a textbook for future theology students this does not diminish Giles's achievements as a scholastic. The text is an important historical document and possibly paved the way for the 'Augustinian School' of the 14th century.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Thema der Dissertation ist "A Commentary on the De predestinatione et prescientia, paradiso et inferno by Giles of Rome on the Basis of MS Cambrai BM 487 (455)". Es handelt sich um einen historischen Kommentar des theologisch-philosophischen Traktates 'De predestinatione et prescientia, paradiso et inferno' (1287-90), der sich zum Ziel gesetzt hat, die Denkansätze von Aegidius von Rom, als auch seine Standpunkte bezüglich der Glaubenslehre auszuleuchten. Der Kommentar zeigt auf, wie ein einzelner theologischer Traktat im Kontext der 1285 wiederaufgenommenen Universitätslaufbahn von Aegidius und seinem besonderen Interesse an der Studienorganisation seines Ordens zu beurteilen ist, und in welcher Weise sein Verhältnis zu kirchlichen und universitären Amtsgewalten zu sehen ist. De predestinatione ist ein vielseitiger Traktat, der in seinen drei Hauptteilen im argumentativen Aufbau große Unterschiede aufweist. Es ist ein bis heute unerforschter Text, dessen Analyse weitere Aspekte von Aegidius' Denkstruktur und seines theologischen und philosophischen Standpunktes im Zusammenspiel mit seinen Zeitgenossen, darunter vor allem der Kirchen- und Universitätsautoritäten, aufzeigt. Sehr auffällig ist seine häufige und umfassende Bezugnahme auf Augustinus, allerdings nicht in der Art und Weise der neoaugustinischen Schule des 14. Jahrhunderts. De predestinatione entstand 1287-90 kurz nach Wiederaufnahme von Aegidius' Universitätskarriere und ist für zukünftige Theologiestudenten des Augustinereremitenordens an der Universität Paris gedacht und erfüllte sicherlich den wachsenden Bedarf seines Ordens an einem Lehrbuch. Die Auswahl der behandelten Themen ist, soweit bekannt, einzigartig. Obwohl es sich bei diesem Text nur um ein Lehrbuch für angehende Theologiestudenten handelt, schmälert dies Aegidius' Leistung als Scholastiker nicht. Der Text ist ein wichtiges Zeitdokument und ein möglicher Wegbereiter für die 'augustinische Schule' des 14. Jahrhunderts.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-07-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1557</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16141</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16141</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1557/holstein_bettina.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
