<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:20Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2602">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2602</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:900</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die Förderung historisch-politischer Urteilskompetenz. Fachdidaktische Untersuchungen zum Verhältnis zwischen einem didaktisch-theoretischen Modell und seinen unterrichtspraktischen Möglichkeiten. </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Cultivating of Historical and Political Thinking. A subject-specific didactic Enquiry into the Relationship between a theoretical didactic Model and its Implications for Teaching Practice.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kayser, Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:900</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Förderung historisch-politischer Urteilskompetenz ist Aufgabe der politischen Bildung für alle Lehrkräfte und ein Hauptanliegen des Schulunterrichts in den Fächern des gesell-schaftswissenschaftlichen Aufgabenfeldes – vor allem in Geschichte und Politikwissenschaft (Sozialkunde). Im Rahmen der Tätigkeit des Autors als Fachseminarleiter für die Fächer Geschichte, Sozialkunde und Politikwissenschaft im Berliner Vorbereitungsdienst ist ab dem Jahr 2000 ein didaktisch-theoretisches Urteilsbildungsmodell entwickelt worden, das zunächst sowohl ein Begriffsverständnis unterstützen als auch ein Handlungsmuster für die historisch-politische Urteilsbildung in der schulischen Praxis bereitstellen sollte und schließlich die historisch-politische Urteilskompetenz als Zielrichtung in den Blick nahm. Die vorliegende Arbeit hat darauf bezugnehmend drei Untersuchungsschwerpunkte. Im ersten Schwerpunkt werden Prozesse der Forschung und der Anwendung zum Modell nachgezeichnet. Hier werden (entsprechend § 2 Abs. 2 Promotionsordnung der Technischen Universität Berlin vom 23.10.2006) bereits veröffentlichte Beiträge des Autors in der Chronologie ihres Erscheinens und gemäß ihrer Bedeutung vorgestellt und einbezogen. Den zweiten Schwerpunkt bilden didaktisch-theoretische Aktualisierungen und Erweiterungen in der Abgrenzung der leitenden Begriffe (z.B. Urteilskompetenz, Domäne, Modelle, Prinzipien, Konzepte). Im dritten Schwerpunkt wird in einer qualitativen Untersuchung der Leitfrage nachgegangen, in welcher Weise durch den Einsatz des Urteilsbildungsmodells die Entwicklung der historisch-politischen Urteilskompetenz von Schülern gefördert werden kann? Dazu werden schriftliche Prüfungsarbeiten zur Zweiten Staatsprüfung für das Lehramt des Studienrats, in denen das Urteilsbildungsmodell teilweise oder vollständig Berücksichtigung fand, untersucht.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The cultivation of critical thinking skills in the fields of history and politics is the task of political education for all teachers and one of the main objectives of instruction in the curriculum of social science subjects – in particular history and political science (social studies). As a group leader for seminars on history, social studies and political science forming part of preparatory teaching practice for teachers in Berlin, in 2000 the author first began to develop a theoretical didactic model for the development of critical thinking faculties. This model was primarily designed to support an understanding of theoretical constructs and to propose an operational framework for the development of historical and political critical thinking in actual classroom practice while also considering the objectives to be achieved by inculcation of critical modes of thought in history and political science. The present work draws on this model in its three principle areas of investigation. The first area delineates research methods and their application to the model. In line with the provisions of section 2, paragraph 2 of the Rules and Regulations for PhD Candidates (Promotionsordnung) of the Technical University of Berlin dated 23 October 2006, it presents the published works of the author in chronological order and graded according to their relev-ance. The second area presents the findings of the latest theoretical research in didactics and the new and more rigorous delineation of key terms (e.g. judgment skills, domain, model, principle, concept). The third area offers a qualitative investigation of the central issue in terms of how deployment of the critical thinking promotion model can best serve to facilitate development of historical and political critical thinking in students. This involves an investigation of the written examination papers of candidates for the second state exam (Zweite Staatsprüfung) for the post of senior teacher (Studienrat) which deal, either in whole or in part, with the critical thinking model.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-08-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2602</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27449</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27449</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2602/kayser_joerg.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
