<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:38Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2440">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2440</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:900</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Judenschutz und Eigennutz. Auseinandersetzungen um Juden an der Ostgrenze des R√∂misch-Deutschen Reiches im 13. und 14. Jahrhundert.</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Patronage and Selfishness towards Jews. Disputes and Conflicts about Jews along the Eastern Border of the Roman-German Empire during the 13th and 14th Centuries.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>B√ºrstenbinder, J√ºrgen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:900</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Judenschutz und Eigennutz. Auseinandersetzungen um die Juden an der Ostgrenze des R√∂misch-Deutschen Reiches im 13. und 14. Jahrhundert J√ºrgen B√ºrstenbinder Die Publikation beschreibt und analysiert Aspekte j√ºdischen Lebens in den Gebieten von Mecklenburg, Pommern, Brandenburg, B√∂hmen, M√§hren, Schlesien und Polen im 13. und 14. Jahrhundert. Haupts√§chlich werden zeitgen√∂ssische Quellen wie Staatsschriften, Schutzbriefe, Vertr√§ge, Stadtb√ºcher, Steuerlisten, Beschriftungen von Grabsteinen und andere Mitteilungen verwendet. Bei Einzelaspekten wird auch Sekund√§rliteratur herangezogen. Besonderer Wert wurde auf die Analyse der Parallelen und der Unterschiede j√ºdischer Lebensumst√§nde zum christlichen Umfeld gelegt. In den beiden Jahrhunderten waren Juden f√ºr alle Herrschenden eine wichtige Einnahmequelle und wurden daher h√§ufig wie andere Regalien oder Verm√∂gensgegenst√§nde behandelt. In den Auseinandersetzungen zwischen Kaisern, Landesherren, St√§dten und der r√∂mischen Kirche hatten Juden keinen Kombattantenstatus, sie waren lediglich Objekte der Auseinandersetzungen. Entsprechend wurde √ºber die Menschen und deren Eigen-tum verf√ºgt. Beispiele aus der Untersuchungsregion zeigen die weitgef√§cherten Zugriffsm√∂glichkeiten. Papst Gregor IX. bestimmte 1234 namens der r√∂mischen Kirche die ‚Äûperpetua servitus‚Äú f√ºr Juden, konnte aber keine durchsetzbare Rechtsnorm schaffen. Bis zum Jahr 1236 galten Juden nach mittelalterlichem Recht als Freie. Erst Kaiser Friedrich II. √§nderte mit der Erneuerung eines Privilegs den Rechtsstatus der Juden als ‚Äûservi came-rae‚Äú. Es wird gezeigt, dass dieser Begriff in Anlehnung an Aristoteles‚Äò Definition von Sklaven und an die Begriffe der Finanzverwaltung aus dem K√∂nigreich Sizilien entstand. Eine als Privileg angesehene Feststellung des Kaisers machte Freie zu seinem s√§chlichen Eigentum. Ab dem Jahr 1244 wurden landesherrliche Judenstatuten erlassen. Herzog Friedrich II. von √ñsterreich, der im Kampf gegen den Kaiser stand, definierte eine Rechtsnorm, die Juden in das christliche Rechtssystem integrierte und einen Rechtsschutz bot. Dieses bahnbrechende Statut wurde bis in das 15. Jahrhundert in mehreren Herrschaftsbereichen an der Ostgrenze des Reiches erneuert. Daher schl√§gt der Autor vor, die gesamte Familie von Statuten als ‚ÄûCodex Iuris Fridericianum‚Äú zu bezeichnen. An einem generellen Kommunikationsmodell werden die M√∂glichkeiten zur Weiterverbreitung dieser Statuten untersucht. Im Gegensatz zu der Entwicklung auf Landesebene forderte die r√∂mische Kirche auf dem 4. Laterankonzil und auf Provinzialsynoden in Breslau und Wien eine weitgehende Ausgrenzung der Juden, was ihr nur teilweise gelang. Mehrere der dortigen Detailforderungen wurden in sp√§teren Jahrhunderten von Antisemiten erneut aufgenommen und durchgesetzt. In der Zeit zwischen 1348 und 1350 gei√üelte die gro√üe Pest Europa. Etwa 30 % der Bev√∂lkerung starben an der Seuche. Der Anteil der j√ºdischen Toten war deutlich h√∂her, aber nicht nur wegen der Pest. Die christliche Bev√∂lkerung war durch eine pseudo-religi√∂se Konditionierung darauf eingestellt, Juden als Feinde des Christentums zu sehen und als ‚ÄûGottesm√∂rder‚Äú zu vernichten. In der Arbeit wird die Ausbreitung von Judenhass und Pogromen mit den medizinischen Begriffen der Epidemie, Pandemie und Endemie verglichen. Beim Zusammentreffen von extremen Belastungen durch K√§lteeinbr√ºche, Missernten, Hungers-n√∂te und schlie√ülich der gro√üen Pest kam es zur ersten europaweiten pandemischen Ju-denvernichtung, die in ihrem schrecklichen Umfang erst wieder von den Nationalsozialisten und ihren Helfern √ºbertroffen wurde. Das j√ºdische Finanzwesen wird an einigen ausgew√§hlten Kreditvertr√§gen untersucht und in Vergleich zur christlichen Gesch√§ftspraxis gestellt. Es wird gezeigt, dass viele Aspekte dieser j√ºdischen Vertr√§ge noch heute g√§ngige Praxis von Banken sind. Die Siedlung von Juden wird f√ºr das Gebiet an der Ostgrenze untersucht, gegen√ºber der Standardliteratur vervollst√§ndigt, auf Plausibilit√§t √ºberpr√ºft und in einen Zusammenhang mit der deutschen Ostsiedlung gestellt. In vielen F√§llen folgte die Besiedlung dem gleichen Muster und verlief sehr √§hnlich. Das Resultat der Auseinandersetzungen um die Juden im 13. und 14. Jahrhundert bestand darin, dass sie aus fast ganz Europa vertrieben wurden, nach Osten wanderten, beim Aufbau Polens halfen, und dort trotz aller weiteren Verfolgungen ihr Hauptsiedlungsgebiet bis 1939 fanden. Viele Handlungen, die wie Judenschutz aussahen, dienten zugleich oder √ºberwiegend dem Eigennutz der Herrschenden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Patronage and Selfishness towards Jews. Disputes and Conflicts about Jews along the Eastern Border of the Roman-German Empire during the 13th and 14th Centuries Juergen Buerstenbinder This publication describes and analyses aspects of Jewish life in the regions of Mecklen-burg, Pomerania, Brandenburg, Bohemia, Moravia, Silesia and Poland, all located along the Eastern border of the Roman-German empire, during the 13th and 14th centuries. This work is based mainly on contemporary sources as official state papers, custodial letters and contractual papers, books from city administrations, tax lists, and inscriptions from gravestones and other types of messages. For some specific aspects only secondary literature has been referenced. Special emphasis has been given to the analysis of similar and different circumstances of Jewish life in comparison to Christian environments. During both centuries, Jews formed a significant source of income for all ruling parties. Therefore, the Jewish people have been treated as other legal ownership or treasuries. Jews did not achieve a status of full combatants during the conflicts between emperors, regional rulers, cities and the Roman Church. Jews were simply objects in the conflicts. Following this concept Jews and their possessions were in free disposition. Examples from the region investigated illustrate the wide spread of possibilities accessing the people and their properties. In 1234 pope Gregory IX decreed in the name of the Roman Church the so called ‚Äúperpetua servitus‚Ä? for Jews. But, he could not convert this attempt into a legal norm. Following medieval law Jews were free people up to the year 1236. Emperor Frederic II modified this status while renewing a ‚Äúprivilege‚Ä?. He generated the legal status for Jews as ‚Äúservi camerae‚Ä?. It has been shown that this concept is based on Aristotle‚Äôs definition of slaves and on the understanding of the financial administration in the kingdom of Sicily. Finally, an imperial letter, originally meant as a privilege, transformed free people into financial properties. From the year 1244 on, regional statutes concerning Jews have been granted. Duke Frederic II of Austria, who was in a military conflict with the emperor, was the first to define a legal normative integrating Jews into the Christian legal system and simultaneously offer-ing protection to this group. This epoch-making statute has been renewed up to the 15th century in many regions along the eastern border of the empire. Therefore the author proposes a specific term for the complete family of statues: ‚ÄúCodex Iuris Fridericianum‚Ä?. Potential paths for transfer of statutes are investigated on the basis of a general communication model. In contrary to the regional developments the Roman Church demanded on the 4th Lateran Council and at regional synods in Breslau and in Vienna a strict separation of Jews from the Christian society, which succeeded only in parts. Several of the de-tailed regulations have been adopted and applied by Anti-Semites in later centuries. From 1348 up to 1350 the great plague tortured people in Europe. More than 30 percent of the population died on the epidemic. The respective percentage of the Jewish population was significantly higher, not only because of the plague. The Christian population was conditioned by pseudo-religious argumentation to understand Jews as murderers of God and extinguish the Jews. This work discusses and compares the spread of hatred and pogroms against Jews in relation to epidemic, pandemic and endemic processes in medicine. With extreme pressure from severe coldness, crop failure, famine and finally the great plague all together the first Europe wide pandemic persecution of Jews happened. Only Nazi and their supporters raged more severely. The Jewish financial system of the period has been investigated based on several credit contracts. Furthermore, it has been related to the respective Christian business procedures. It has been shown that several details and procedures from the old Jewish contracts are still in use in our days with respect to the financial system. The settlement of Jews on the eastern border has been investigated; the description has been completed in comparison to standard literature, checked for plausibility and connected to the German settlements in the East. Frequently both migrations appeared in parallel and following the same pattern. As a result of all disputes and conflicts about Jews in the 13th and 14th centuries it can be seen that Jews have been expelled from nearly all Europe, migrated to the East, helped to build up Poland, suffered from ongoing pogroms and nonetheless kept their main settle-ments in Poland until 1939. Many actions appealing as patronage or protection of Jews were ‚Äì looking at the details ‚Äì mainly selfishness and greed from the ruling parties.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-02-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2440</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25629</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25629</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2440/buerstenbinder_juergen.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
