<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:54:08Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2097">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2097</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:900</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die sozialen und √∂konomischen Bedingungen der j√ºdischen Emigration aus Berlin/Brandenburg 1933</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The Social and Economic Conditions of Jewish Emigration from Berlin and Brandenburg in 1933</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bergmann, Armin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:900</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Arbeit untersucht die erste j√ºdische Emigrationswelle aus dem nationalsozialistischen Deutschland im Jahre 1933 am Beispiel der Emigranten aus Berlin. Dabei stehen nicht Einzelschicksale im Vordergrund, sondern die Untersuchung bezieht sich explizit auf kollektivbiographische Angaben zu fr√ºhen j√ºdischen Emigranten. Ausgehend von der √úberlegung, dass f√ºr die Emigranten die Devisenausfuhr √ºberlebenswichtig war und die Mehrzahl einen Antrag stellte, wurden Devisenantr√§ge von j√ºdischen Emigranten statistisch ausgewertet. √úber die Auswertung der sozio-demographischen Merkmale wie Alter, Geschlecht, Ausbildung und Finanzlage wird ein Sozialprofil der fr√ºhen j√ºdischen Emigranten erstellt. Die leitende Fragestellung der Untersuchung zielt auf das Herausarbeiten der verbindenden und unterscheidenden Merkmale der Frauen und M√§nner der ersten Emigrationswelle. √úber das Konvergieren und Divergieren sozialer und √∂konomischer Merkmale werden homogene und heterogene Sozialkomponenten innerhalb der Gruppe der fr√ºhen j√ºdischen Emigranten bestimmt. Die soziologische Einordnung impliziert auch die Frage, aufgrund welcher Faktoren diese Menschen bereits 1933 emigrierten, w√§hrend die meisten deutschen Juden eine Emigration ablehnten. W√§hrend die Auswertung des statistischen Materials den Hauptteil der Untersuchung ausf√ºllt, werden in einem ersten Teil einf√ºhrend verschiedene Aspekte der Emigration, die zum Verst√§ndnis der Thematik relevant sind, er√∂rtert. So wird auf die Semantik des Begriffes Emigrant ebenso eingegangen wie auf die rechtlichen Rahmenbedingungen der Emigration sowie auf die Einwanderungsgesetze der Immigrationsl√§nder. Auch wird die Problematik der tradierten Zahlen zur j√ºdischen Emigration anhand der Beispiele USA und Pal√§stina dargestellt.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Using the example of emigrants from Berlin, the dissertation examines the first wave of Jewish emigration from National Socialist Germany in 1933. The fates of individuals are not foregrounded in the study, which refers explicitly to collective-biographical information about early Jewish emigrants. Proceeding on the assumption that the ability to export foreign currency was vital to the survival of emigrants and that the majority of them therefore submitted corresponding applications, the exchange applications made by Jewish emigrants were statistically evaluated. By evaluating socio-demographic attributes like age, gender, education and financial situation, it was possible to compile a social profile of the early Jewish emigrants. The key issue addressed by the study is to work out the linking and differentiating attributes of the women and men who made up the first wave of emigration. Homogenous and heterogeneous social components within the group of early Jewish emigrants are identified over the convergence and divergence of social and economic characteristics. This sociological categorization also raises the question of the factors that led these individuals to emigrate as early as 1933, at a time when the majority of German Jews still rejected the idea of emigration. While the evaluation of the body of statistical material makes up the main section of the study, the introductory first part discusses various aspects of emigration relevant to an understanding of the topic. Thus, the first section discusses the semantics of the term ‚Äúemigrant‚Ä? and also looks at the legal framework conditions governing emigration and likewise the immigration laws of the relevant countries. At the same time, the problematical nature of the historically accepted figures relating to Jewish emigration are examined using the examples of the USA and Palestine.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/vnd.ms-excel</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2097</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21943</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21943</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2097/original_bergmann_armin.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2097/bergmann_armin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
