<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:23Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1987">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1987</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:900</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die heiligen Berge Jerusalems. Erinnerungsträger dreier Weltreligionen</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The Holy Mountains of Jerusalem. Places of Memory for three World Religions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zevallos Padilla, Kerstin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:900</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die heiligen Berge Jerusalems dienen als zentrale Erinnerungsträger der drei großen monotheistischen Weltreligionen. Judentum, Christentum und Islam belegen sie bis heute mit einer großen symbolischen Sinndichte. Die heiligen Berge sind nicht nur Zeugen der Präsenz und des Wirkens Gottes, liturgische und kultisch bedeutsame Stätten, identitätsstiftende Symbole, sondern gleichzeitig auch Kulisse und Ereignisort unzähliger historischer Begebenheiten. Die Geschichte des jüdischen Volkes ist untrennbar mit dem Tempelberg und Zion verbunden. So ist in der jüdischen Tradition der Zion nicht nur der Wohnsitz Gottes und der Ort des jüngsten Gerichts, sondern er steht für die Idee einer eigenen Staatlichkeit. Der Tempelberg, auf dem einst das Allerheiligste beheimatet war, ist das zentrale Heiligtum jüdischen Glaubens. Die Christen begreifen die Wirkstätten Jesu als heilige Orte in Jerusalem und ehren deswegen die Kreuzigungsstätte Golgatha und den Ölberg als erfahrbaren Raum in der Topographie der heiligen Stadt. Während sie die Zionstheologie in vielfältiger Weise übernahmen und der Berg Zion im Stadtbild als Erinnerungsort der Urgemeinde neu verortet wurde, galt ihnen der Tempelberg nach der Zerstörung des Heiligtums als Mahnmal der Worte des Gekreuzigten. Anders als das Christentum eignete sich der Islam nach der Eroberung Jerusalems nur einen Ort als heilige Stätte an und fand, trotz der Übernahme einer Vielfalt jüdischer und christlicher Traditionen, einen eigenen Zugriff auf den Berg, den einst der Tempel gekrönt hatte: die Himmelfahrt des Propheten. Die Arbeit untersucht die Anfänge der symbolischen Belegung der heiligen Berge in Jerusalem; die Erinnerungsorte des frühen Christentums stehen dabei im Mittelpunkt. Eine Betrachtung der jüdischen Überlieferung wird als Grundlage vorangestellt, und ein Ausblick auf die islamische Vereinnahmung eines den drei Religionen gemeinsamen Erinnerungsortes dient in einem abschließenden Teil als Vergleich.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">To this day, the holy mountains of Jerusalem are the most important sacred places for the three monotheistic world religions. For varying reasons, Jews, Christians and Muslims view them as places, which play an important role in their belief. In the Jewish tradition, Zion is not only home to Jahwe and the setting for the Last Judgement, but also symbolizes the idea of a Jewish statehood. The Temple Mount, on which the edifices of worship, housing the Holiest of Holies, once stood, is the central most sacred place of the Jewish faith. Christianity, seeing not only the Temple Mount but also the locations of Jesus‘s activities as holy places and therefore especially honouring Golgotha as a space to be experienced in the topography of the holy city, has also taken in the theology of Zion in various ways. The written tradition of the Jewish religion, and the idea of the heavenly Jerusalem with a judging God enthroned on mount Zion, is at the same time established and transcended in Christian belief. Zion became a concept which, when no longer bound to a real place, could be transferred to groups of believers and their respective countries. The Islamic religion also incorporated the holy sites of the older religions after conquering Jerusalem. Although the youngest of the abrahamitic religions borrowed many legends and characters from the Jewish tradition, it nevertheless created its own myth concerning the mountain which had once been crowned with the Temple: the ascent of Mohammed to the heavens. The holy mountains of Jerusalem unite many meanings in themselves. To this day they survive as spiritual, religious and cultural centres of three religions; to this day the conflicts survive as well, which result from the diversity of overlapping traditions of the sacred spaces. This work aims at an examination of the beginnings of the symbolic charging of the holy mountains in Jerusalem. While the Christian places of memory are the center point of this study, an analysis of the Jewish Tradition as religious and historical background will be put first and a comparison with the Islamic concept of Jerusalm will conclude it.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-11-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20839</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20839</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1987/original_zevallos_padilla_kerstin.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1987/zevallos_padilla_kerstin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
