<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:56Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3842">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3842</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-18</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Dynamics of quantum dot lasers subject to optical feedback and external optical injection</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Dynamik von Quantenpunktlasern unter dem Einfluss optischer Rückkopplung und externer optischer Injektion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Otto, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this thesis, I study the complex dynamics of different semiconductor laser structures under optical injection and under external optical feedback. In the first part of this thesis, I concentrate on nanostructured quantum dot (QD) lasers. Here, the impact of the internal nonlinear carrier dynamics -- and thus the impact of the band structure -- on the dynamics of these QD lasers is intensively studied. Therefore, a microscopically based rate equation model is used, in which the carrier scattering dynamics between the discrete energy levels of the QDs and the surrounding carrier reservoir is described by Coulomb scattering rates. These rates depend nonlinearly on the carrier densities in the carrier reservoir and thus on the pumping conditions. Further, they strongly depend on the energy spacing between the band edge of the carrier reservoir and the discrete QD levels, which permits to describe different band structures. The impact of the scattering rates on the damping of the relaxation oscillations (ROs) of the solitary laser are discussed in detail. Beside the impact of the band structure, I investigate the dependence of the complex dynamics of a QD laser under optical injection on the pump current and on the phase-amplitude coupling (alpha-factor). By means of multiscale analysis, analytical approximations are derived for the saddle-node and Hopf bifurcations bordering the region of stable continuous wave emission as well as for a codimension-2 zero-Hopf point acting as organizing center for more complex dynamics, and the minimal injection strength, below which no Hopf instability may occur. Moreover, for the QD laser subject to optical feedback, an analytic expression for the first supercritical Hopf bifurcation marking the boundary for stable continuous wave emission is obtained. The analytic expressions for the bifurcation lines and bifurcation points reveal their dependence on the RO damping, and thus on the band structure, as well as on the alpha-factor. Further, the possibility to employ the QD laser subject to feedback as an excitable optical unit is discussed. By adding white noise to the dynamic equation for the electric field in the cavity, coherence resonance is observed in the excitable regime, and its dependence on the pump current is studied. In the second part of this thesis, the response of a passively mode-locked two-section laser to external optical feedback is studied. This type of laser permits to realize compact devices that are well suited for optical telecommunication applications due to their ability to emit trains of short optical pulses with a high repetition frequency of 40 GHz, which is an upcoming IEEE standard. One major drawback of passively mode-locked lasers is their relatively large timing jitter degrading the quality of the pulse stream and thus increasing the bit-error rate. Resonant optical feedback provides an easy-to-handle way of reducing the timing jitter. I analyze the resonances of the inter-pulse interval time and the external delay time, and it is shown that the resonances can be ordered in a Farey-sequence similar to the resonances in externally driven systems, which allows for easy prediction of the laser dynamics. Further, I discuss that the timing jitter can be reduced drastically in the main resonances, where the largest stabilizing effect of the feedback is obtained, which is of relevance for applications.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In der vorliegenden Arbeit untersuche ich die komplexe Dynamik verschiedener Halbleiterlaserstrukturen unter optischer Injektion und optischer Rückkopplung. In dem ersten Teil der Arbeit stehen nanostrukturierte Quantenpunktlaser im Vordergrund. Hierbei analysiere ich den Einfluss der internen, nichtlinearen Ladungsträgerdynamik von Quantenpunktlasern -- und damit der Bandstruktur -- auf die Laserdynamik. Dafür wird ein Ratengleichungsmodell verwendet, bei dem der Ladungsträgeraustausch zwischen den diskreten Energieniveaus der Quantenpunkte und dem umgebenden Ladungsträgerreservoir durch mikroskopisch berechnete Coulomb-Streuraten beschrieben wird. Zum einen hängen diese nichtlinear von der Konzentration der Ladungsträger in dem Ladungsträgerreservoir und damit von dem Pumpstrom ab und zum anderen werden sie von dem energetischen Abstand zwischen den Bandkanten des Reservoirs und den Quantenpunktniveaus bestimmt. Letzteres ermöglicht es, den Einfluss unterschiedlicher Bandstrukturen auf die Dämpfung der Relaxationsoszillationen (ROs) des Lasers zu untersuchen. Für den optisch injizierten Quantenpunktlaser betrachte ich neben dem Einfluss der Bandstruktur zudem die Auswirkungen des Pumpstroms sowie der Phasen-Amplitudenkopplung (alpha-Faktor) auf die komplexe Laserdynamik. Mit Hilfe einer Multiskalenanalyse werden analytische Ausdrücke für die Sattel-Knoten und Hopf-Bifurkationslinien, die den Synchronisationsbereich (Arnoldzunge) begrenzen, hergeleitet. Des Weiteren werden analytische Ausdrücke für den Kodimension-2 Sattel-Knoten-Hopf-Punkt, der ein Organisationszentrum für komplexere Dynamik darstellt, sowie für die Injektionsstärke, unterhalb derer keine Hopf-Bifurkation möglich ist, hergeleitet. Auch für den Laser mit externer Rückkopplung wird ein Ausdruck für die Rückkopplungsstärke, bei der die erste Hopf Instabilität auftritt, abgeleitet. Die Formeln für die Bifurkationslinien und Bifurkationspunkte zeigen deren Abhängigkeit von der Dämpfung der ROs sowie von dem alpha-Faktor auf. Des Weiteren wird gezeigt, dass der Quantenpunktlaser unter optischer Rückkopplung in einem bestimmten Parameterbereich anregbar ist. Unter dem Einfluss additiven, weißen Rauschens weist das System in diesem Regime Kohärenzresonanz auf, deren Pumpstromabhängigkeit untersucht wird. In dem zweiten Teil der Arbeit untersuche ich den Einfluss zeitverzögerter optischer Rückkopplung auf passiv modengekoppelte Zweisektionslaser. Diese zeichnen sich durch regelmäßige Pulsemission mit einer hohen Wiederholrate von bis zu 40 GHz aus. Diese entspricht dem nächsten IEEE-Standard und ist daher von besonderem Interesse für die digitale, optische Datenübertragung. Ein gravierender Nachteil dieser Laser ist, dass der zeitliche Abstand aufeinanderfolgender Pulse (timing jitter) relativ großen Fluktuationen unterworfen ist, was zu einer erhöhten Bit-Fehlerrate führt. Optische Rückkopplung stellt eine einfache Möglichkeit dar, den timing jitter zu reduzieren. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wird gezeigt, dass sich zwischen dem zeitlichen Abstand benachbarter Pulse und der Umlaufzeit des Lichts in der externen Kavität ein ähnliches Resonanzverhalten einstellt, wie es von dynamischen Systemen mit externem periodischen Antrieb bekannt ist. Dadurch können die Resonanzen in einer Farey-Folge angeordnet werden, was eine einfache Vorhersage der Laserdynamik ermöglicht. Des Weiteren wird gezeigt, dass innerhalb der Hauptresonanzen die Pulsfolge durch die Rückkopplung stabilisiert wird, wodurch eine deutliche Verringerung des timing jitters bewirkt wird.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-06-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3842</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40730</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40730</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3842/otto_christian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
