<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:45:32Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:306">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:306</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Grass Litter Decomposition and Soil Animal Colonization: Impact of Benzo(a)pyrene and PCB 52 in Former Sewage Fields</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Wirkung von Benzo(a)pyren und PCB 52 auf Bodentiere und Streuabbau in ehemaligen Rieselfeldern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pieper, Silvia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Polyzyklische Aromatische Kohlenwasserstoffe (PAKs) und Polychlorierte Biphenyle (PCBs) sind organische Stoffverbindungen mit einer ubiquitären Umweltverbreitung. Aufgrund ihrer Toxizität für den Menschen, ihrer geringen Abbaubarkeit und ihrer hohen Persistenz in der Umwelt werden PAKs und PCBs in den Listen prioritärer Schadstoffe vieler Länder geführt. Obwohl der größte Anteil der PAKs und PCBs in terrestrischen Ökosystemen gespeichert vorliegt, sind die Kenntnisse über die Toxizität dieser organischen Verbindungen für Bodenorganismen und Bodenprozesse sehr gering. Ziel dieser Arbeit war es, die Auswirkungen einer Belastung von Streu und Boden mit den Referenzsubstanzen Benzo(a)pyren (BaP; PAK) und 2,2'-5,5'-Tetrachlorbiphenyl (PCB 52; PCB) auf die Bodenfauna zu charakterisieren und zu bewerten. Der experimentelle Ansatz wurde so gewählt, dass der Einfluss von BaP und PCB 52 auf Bodenorganismen auf verschiedenen Stufen biologischer Organisation untersucht werden konnte. Zwei Streuabbauversuche bildeten die Hauptuntersuchungen dieser Arbeit. Der erste wurde auf einer ehemaligen Rieselfeldfläche in der Nähe von Berlin mit standorttypischer Grasstreu durchgeführt. Im zweiten Versuch, der unter semi-Freiland-Bedingungen stattfand, wurde radioaktiv markiertes BaP und PCB 52 eingesetzt, im Gegensatz zu den 'kalten' Substanzen in den Freilandversuchen. Bereits nach einer kurzen Exposition im Freiland sanken in der Streu die Konzentrationen an extrahierbarem BaP und PCB 52 stark ab. Eine vollständige Verbrennung der Streu aus den Versuchen mit radioaktiven Referenzsubstanzen zeigte jedoch, dass ein großer Anteil der anfänglich applizierten 14C-Aktivität weiterhin vorhanden war. Die Ergebnisse von Dünnschichtchromatographien belegen einen hohen 'echten' Verlust von PCB 52 und seinen Metaboliten während der Exposition im Freiland. Benzo(a)pyren dagegen lag zwar zu einem höheren Anteil transformiert vor, aber stark an die organische Matrix gebunden. Die Kontamination der Streu mit bis zu 11 mg PCB 52 x kg-1 hatte keine nachweisbaren Effekte auf die Dekomposition der Grasstreu. Benzo(a)pyren bewirkte dagegen eine deutliche Steigerung der Streuabbauraten, mit maximalen Abweichungen zwischen der hochkontaminierten Variante (100 mg BaP x kg-1 Streu) und der unbelasteten Kontrolle von 18 %. Die Besiedlungsdynamik der Streu durch Mikroarthropoden belegte eine differenzierte Antwort der einzelnen Collembolen- und Oribatidenarten auf die Kontamination mit BaP und PCB 52. Es wurde keine Art gefunden, die mit verminderten Besiedlungsdichten auf Benzo(a)pyren reagierte. In den Streuabbaucontainern, die mit PCB 52 belastet wurden, wiesen dagegen einzelne Arten geringere Individuendichten auf. Der Einfluss von BaP und PCB 52 auf die Reproduktionsraten von Collembolen wurde in Labortests nach DIN-ISO-Vorschriften untersucht. Folsomia candida zeigte höhere Vermehrungsraten in den kontaminierten Böden. Die höheren Besiedlungsdichten von Mikroarthropoden in der mit BaP kontaminierten Streu, die in den Freilandcontainern nachgewiesen wurden, könnten direkt für die beobachteten höheren Streuabbauraten verantwortlich sein. In einer ersten Risikoabschätzung über die Auswirkungen einer Belastung mit BaP und PCB 52 auf Bodenorganismen konnte gezeigt werden, dass auf den untersuchten Rieselfeldflächen bereits Konzentrationen an organischen Schadstoffen erreicht sind, die als maximal für die Erhaltung schützenswerter Bodenfunktionen nach dem Bundes-Bodenschutzgesetz zu bewerten sind.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) and polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) are organic chemicals ubiquitous in the environment. Because of their toxicity to man, their recalcitrance to degradation and their persistency in the environment, PAHs and PCBs are listed in the inventory of priority pollutants compiled by several Environmental Protection Agencies. The far greatest amount of PAHs and PCBs are stored in the soil. Despite of this fact, the amount of data available on the toxicity of these organic compounds to soil animals and soil processes is very scarce. Aim of this thesis was to assess the response of soil fauna to a contamination of soil and litter with the chosen reference substances benzo(a)pyrene (BaP; PAH) and 2,2'-5,5' tetrachlorobiphenyl (PCB 52; PCB). The overall experimental approach was designed so to investigate the impact of BaP and PCB 52 on terrestrial ecosystems at different level of biological organization. Two litter decomposition experiments were the core experiments of this study. The first was carried out on a former sewage field near Berlin, Germany, employing the litter of the typical grass species of the study area. The second decomposition experiment was performed under semi-field conditions with radio-labeled compounds, in contrast to the 'cold' BaP and PCB 52 used to contaminate the litter in the field experiment. After a brief exposure in the field, the solvent extractable concentrations of BaP and PCB 52 in the litter decreased sharply. The complete combustion of the radio-labeled litter and the results of thin layer chromatographies gave evidence for 'real' PCB 52 losses during the exposure in the field, while BaP, metabolized to a higher extent, was strongly bound to the organic matrix and did not move into the soil. The contamination of the litter with PCB 52 had no detectable effect on the litter decay rates up to the tested concentration of 11 mg PCB 52 x kg-1 litter. Benzo(a)pyrene, on the contrary, enhanced markedly the decomposition process, with maximum differences in the highly contaminated variants (100 mg BaP x kg-1 litter) of 18 % compared to the uncontaminated controls. The colonization of the litter by microarthropods revealed a differentiated response of single Collembola and oribatid mite species to the grass litter contamination with BaP and PCB 52. No species was found that reacted with decreased colonization densities to a contamination with BaP. In the PCB 52 treated litter, some species with low dominance displayed reduced individual densities. When the reproductive performance of Collembola was tested according to ISO standard procedures, Folsomia candida showed higher reproduction rates in soils contaminated with PCB 52 and BaP. Summarizing the gained insight achieved within this thesis on the reaction of the decomposer community to a contamination with BaP and PCB 52, we may point to the reported higher colonization densities of soil organisms in the field BaP treatments as responsible for the higher litter decay rates. Finally, in a first risk assessment, I applied simple extrapolation methods to the achieved data on the response of soil animals and soil processes to a contamination with BaP and PCB 52. In the investigated sites the maximum soil concentrations at which the soil decomposer community may still be protected from adverse effects are reached. Concerning their loads with organic contaminants, the sewage field soils have no security margin in respect to the compliance of protection targets as defined in the German Soil Protection Act.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2004-02-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/306</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/306/pieper_silvia.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
