<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:43Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2907">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2907</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:500</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Numerical Reservoir Simulations of Multiphase Pump Operations on the Rütenbrock Sour Gas Field, Northwest-Germany </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Reservoir Numerische Simulationen von Multiphasen-Pumpe Operationen am Rütenbrock Sour Gasfeld, Nordwest-Deutschland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alwan, Abdulmalik Abdullah</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:500</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Multiphase pumping technology has evolved to become a critical component in many production schemes. A multiphase pump (MPP) field site test was conducted in Rütenbrock sour gas field, a mature carbonate reservoir (Hauptdolomit) in north-western Germany. First time this scientific study investigated an optimized recovery effect which resulted from the deployment of multiphase pumping technology on an existing sour gas reservoir with 40 years of production history. The Hauptdolomit reservoir represents a fractured dolomite of the Permian Zechstein (Ca2) with a thickness of about 30 meters. A static model with 71 x 39 x 60/60 grid cells was constructed and interactively improved by reservoir dynamic data. The final dual porosity/permeability simulation model contains 332,280 cells in total, 201,619 of which are active cells. The dual porosity/permeability model was constructed based on available reservoir properties, fluids data, and production history data. The volume of gas initially in place (GIIP) estimated on the basis of the reservoir and fluid data totalled 2.5 x 109 m³ (Vn) in the main compartment, whereas the calculated GIIP from material balance P/Z plot was around 1.9 x 109 m³ (Vn). Subsequently, dynamic simulations were performed for the purpose of history match and production forecast. The history matching process was performed by manually changing the most influential parameters in matching production data until the desired output was observed. The accurate adjustment of history match parameters, in combination with the presence of a tight zone, faults and flow barriers, ensured an excellent history match for most of the gas producers. After the completion of the history matching process, a production forecast that comprised various forecast scenarios was carried out in order to investigate the impact of the MPP operation on well RB_Z10a and the entire compartment performance, for the production period from 2004 to 2006. A second production forecast scenario was performed on the assumption that the MPP facility would utilize prior to 2004. The study results confirmed that the use of multiphase pumping technology from 2004 to 2006 resulted in optimized gas recovery for the Hauptdolomit reservoir. A positive impact on field economics is confirmed through numerical simulation by improved gas recovery and production acceleration. Two forecast scenarios were carried out for the production period 01/2004-03/2006 using either continuous deployment of the MPP facility or the conventional compression production system. The MPP forecast simulation result for the production period 01/2004-03/2006 was a total of 17.37 x 106 Sm3, representing an increase of +5.33 % over the volume of gas actually produced which was 16.49 x 106 Sm3. In contrast, the forecast simulation result of the conventional compression production system for the production period 01/2004-03/2006 was a cumulative gas volume of 5.2 x 106 Sm3 which represents a reduction of -68.3 % compared to actual production. Based on the forecast results, gas producer RB_Z10a would come to the end of its production life in 09/2004 i.e., 9 months later, if the conventional compression production system was used continuously after 01/2004. The forecast results of the assumption that the MPP facility would utilize prior to 2004 show an improvement in the ultimate gas recovery of RB_Z10a and the entire compartment of up to +3.77 % and +2.5 %, respectively, if the MPP facility was operational prior to 2004. Additionally, production acceleration would be possible i.e., it may lead to a significant saving in operation costs. Decline curve analysis techniques were used to evaluate and verify reserves, also the forecast simulation results of the analytical models to be compared with numerical reservoir simulation results. However, using all available methods will provide a comprehensive understanding and a greater degree of confidence if all techniques agree. Decline curve analysis confirmed the results and conclusions obtained from the numerical simulation. Intensive analysis of production history data identified the following observable effects as results of the MPP test operations in RB_Z10a: 1) the conventional compression gas production rates of RB_Z10a during the down-time of the MPP between 01/2004 and 03/2006 were increased compared with the previous production phase (2002-2003). 2) RB_Z10a well operational availability was evaluated for the production periods 2002 – 2007 based on actual well operation hours, and RB_Z10a turned out to be more efficient (98 %) during MPP operations compared to the prior production period (88 %). 3) A positive production response was detected in the performance of the neighbouring well (OT_Z02), which located 1.5 km in the structure crest. The MPP facility was able to pull out the reservoir fluids from the entire compartment towards the crest structure wells by creating a bigger pressure difference between the drainage areas and the crest structure area. Removing the water from the fractures (flow conduits) enhanced the gas rate, i.e., it improved the relative permeability of the gas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die voranschreitende Entwicklung der Multiphasentechnologie macht den Einsatz von Multiphasen-Pumpen zu einem wichtigen Bestandteil vieler Produktionsszenarien in der Kohlenwasserstoffindustrie. Im Rahmen eines Forschungsprojektes wurde eine Multiphasen-Pumpe im weitgehend ausgeförderten Sauergasfeld Rütenbrock (Hauptdolomit) in Nord-West Deutschland installiert. Die vorliegende wissenschaftliche Untersuchung thematisiert erstmals den erhöhten Ausbeutefaktor, der durch den Einsatz der Multiphasentechnologie in einer Gaslagerstätte mit 40 Jahren Produktionsgeschichte erzielt werden kann. Die Multiphasen-Pumpe wurde in den Jahren 2004 bis 2006 in der Förderung aus dem 30 Meter mächtigen geklüfteten Hauptdolomit im Zechstein (Perm) eingesetzt. Das erstellte duale Porositäts- /Permeabilitäts-Simulationsmodell enthält insgesamt 332.280 Zellen. Auf Basis der Daten wurde ein Wert von initiales Volumen von 2,5 x 109 m³ (Vn) Gas für das Hauptkompartment geschätzt, wohingegen sich unter Verwendung der Materialbilanz P/Z Analyse ein Wert von nur 1,9 x 109 m³ (Vn) ergab. Anschließend wurden dynamische Reservoirsimulationen vorgenommen, um ein möglichst präzises Ergebnis für das "History Matching" und die Produktionsprognosen zu erzielen. Beim "History Matching" wurden die wesentlichen Parameter so lange geändert, bis sich eine Übereinstimmung mit den Produktionsdaten ergab. Im Anschluss daran wurde eine Produktionsprognose durchgeführt, die mehrere Szenarien umfasste, um den Einfluss der Multiphasentechnologie auf die Bohrung RB_Z10a sowie das Gesamtkompartment für verschiedene Produktionsperioden zu untersuchen. Die Ergebnisse bestätigen, dass der Einsatz der Multiphasen-Pumpe von 2004 bis 2006 die Produktion beschleunigte und die Gasausbeute aus dem Hauptdolomit erhöhte. Das Ergebnis der Simulation ergab für den kontinuierlichen Einsatz der Multiphasen-Pumpe insgesamt 17,37 x 106 Sm3 Gas, was einer Steigerung von +5,33 % im Vergleich zur aktuell produzierten Gasmenge (16,49 x 106 Sm3) entspricht. Die Prognose bei Verwendung des konventionellen Produktionssystems ergab ein kumuliertes Gasvolumen von lediglich 5,2 x 106 Sm3, was einer Reduktion von -68,3 % im Vergleich zur aktuellen Produktion entspricht. Die Prognosen für einen früheren Einsatz der Multiphasen-Pumpe als 2004 zeigen eine mögliche Erhöhung der Gesamtgasausbeute für RB_Z10a (bis zu +3,77 %) und das Gesamtkompartment (bis zu +2,5 %). Zusätzlich wurde ersichtlich, dass durch den Einsatz der Multiphasentechnologie eine Beschleunigung der Produktion möglich ist. Neben der generellen Erhöhung des Ausbeutefaktors und der Beschleunigung der Produktion konnten durch das intensive Studium der Produktionsdaten weitere Auswirkungen des Einsatzes der Multiphasen-Pumpe beobachtet werden: 1) die konventionellen Gasproduktionsraten der Bohrung RB_Z10a während der Einschließzeiten der Multiphasen-Pumpe wurden im Vergleich zur vorangehenden Produktionsphase (2002-2003) verbessert; 2) es wurde ein positiver Effekt auf die Produktion der benachbarten Bohrung OT_Z02 entdeckt. Die Multiphasen-Pumpe war in der Lage, Reservoirinhaltsstoffe aus dem gesamten Kompartment zu den Bohrungen im Scheitel der Gasfeldstruktur zu fördern. Durch die Entfernung des Wassers aus den Klüften und die Verbesserung der relativen Permeabilität für das Gas resultierte eine erhöhte Gasrate.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-05-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2907</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2907/alwan_abdulmalik.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
