<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3447">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3447</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:570</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Nucleoside phosphorylases from thermophiles - Recombinant expression and biocatalytic use for modified nucleosides</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Nukleosidphosphorylasen von thermophilen Mikroorganismen - Rekombinante Expression und Nutzen für die Synthese modifizierter Nukleoside</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Szeker, Kathleen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:570</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Modified nucleosides are valuable pharmaceutical agents used in the treatment of cancer and viral infections. Moreover, they serve as building blocks in the synthesis of therapeutic oligonucleotides with advanced properties. While the chemical modification of pyrimidine nucleosides is generally well established, the synthesis of modified purine nucleosides is often rather challenging, resulting in multistage processes with low yield. Alternative synthetic routes include the chemo-enzymatic synthesis of purine nucleosides from a pyrimidine nucleoside serving as pentofuranosyl donor and a purine base functioning as pentofuranosyl acceptor. As biocatalysts, nucleoside phosphorylases (NPs) are used to catalyze the regio- and stereoselective transfer reaction, whereby natural or chemically prepared artificial precursors can be applied as substrate. Unfortunately, a number of highly interesting nucleoside analogues are hardly recognized as substrate by NPs that are currently in use. Moreover, high temperatures are desirable to increase the concentration of poorly soluble purine bases, but many enzymes are rapidly deactivated by heat. Both factors limit the scope and the efficiency of NP mediated syntheses of modified nucleosides and prompted us to study novel, thermostable nucleoside phosphorylase variants as potential biocatalysts. Therefore a set of 5 NPs from 4 different thermophilic microorganisms (Deinococcus geothermalis, Geobacillus thermoglucosidasius, Thermus thermophilus, Aeropyrum pernix) has been overexpressed in E. coli. The recombinant proteins were characterized in order to assess their potential application as biocatalysts. Thermal properties (temperature optima, stability) varied significantly and were dependent on the source microorganism and the type of enzyme. Investigations of the substrate specificities revealed striking differences in the ability to tolerate modified nucleosides as substrate. The data allowed us to select and test the most promising combinations of enzymes for enzymatic transglycosylation reactions. In focus of the present work was thereby the synthesis of 2′ fluorinated purine nucleosides as well as 2,6-dihalogenated purine nucleosides. 2′-Fluorinated nucleosides were found to have valuable pharmaceutical properties and impart favourable characteristics to synthetic oligonucleotides. On the other hand, 2,6-dihalogenated purine nucleosides are versatile precursors for a variety of purine modified nucleosides. In comparison to E. coli enzymes that are described in literature as biocatalysts for the synthesis of 2′-fluorinated purine nucleosides, the application of the novel, thermostable enzymes permits the operation at higher temperature, and appears to be more efficient in the synthesis 2′-fluorinated purine nucleosides. Furthermore, 2,6-dihalogenated purines were readily accepted as substrates and the respective (deoxy-)ribosides were rapidly produced by the novel enzyme preparations. The results corroborate the general potential of thermostable NPs in the synthesis of modified nucleosides and specifically pave the way towards improved, environmentally friendly synthetic procedures affording valuable 2′-fluorinated and 2,6-dihalogenated purine nucleoside analogues.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Modifizierte Nukleoside sind wertvolle Pharmazeutika, die für die Behandlung von Krebs und viralen Erkrankungen eingesetzt werden. Außerdem dienen sie als Bausteine für die Synthese therapeutischer Oligonukleotide mit besonderen Eigenschaften. Während es für die Herstellung chemisch modifizierter Pyrimidinnukleoside einfache und bewährte Verfahren gibt, stellt die organische Synthese modifizierter Purinnukleoside oft eine Herausforderung dar, was zu mehrstufigen Verfahren mit niedriger Ausbeute führt. Die chemisch-enzymatische Herstellung, bei der ein Pyrimidinnukleosid als Pentofuranosyl-Donor und eine Purinbase als Pentufuranosyl-Akzeptor dient, kann daher eine attraktive Alternative sein. Für den regio- und stereospezifischen Transfer der Zuckereinheit kommen Nukleosidphosphorylasen (NPs) als Biokatalysatoren zum Einsatz, wobei als Substrate sowohl natürlich vorkommende, als auch chemisch modifizierte, künstliche Vorstufen verwendet werden können. Leider ist die Substrataktivität einer Vielzahl von hochinteressanten Nukleosid-Analoga jedoch bei den gegenwärtig genutzten NPs sehr gering. Darüber hinaus ist es von Vorteil den Syntheseprozess bei hohen Temperaturen durchzuführen um die Konzentration schlecht löslicher Purinbasen zu erhöhen, doch dies führt bei vielen Enzymen zum schnellen Aktivitätsverlust. Beide Faktoren schränken den Anwendungsbereich und die Effizienz der Synthese modifizierter Nukleoside durch NPs ein. Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, neue, thermostabile Varianten von NPs und ihren potentiellen Einsatz als Biokatalysatoren zu untersuchen. Hierfür wurden 5 NPs von 4 verschiedenen thermophilen Mikroorganismen (Deinococcus geothermalis, Geobacillus thermoglucosidasius, Thermus thermophilus, Aeropyrum pernix) in E. coli überexprimiert. Die Temperaturoptima und Thermostabilität der rekombinant hergestellten Enzyme unterscheiden sich signifikant, vor allem in Abhängigkeit von Ursprungsmikroorganismus und Enzymtyp. Die Untersuchung der Substratspezifität zeigt, dass modifizierte Nukleoside in sehr unterschiedlichem Ausmaß als Substrate erkannt werden. Der Einsatz der vielversprechendsten Enzym-Kombination in enzymatischen Transglykosylierungsreaktionen wurde untersucht. Hierbei stand die Synthese 2′-fluorinierter Purinnukleoside sowie 2,6-dihalogenierte Purinnukleoside im Fokus dieser Arbeit. 2′-Fluorinierte Nukleoside haben wertvolle pharmazeutische Eigenschaften und verleihen synthetischen Oligonukleotiden günstige Eigenschaften, wohingegen 2,6-dihalogenierte Purinnukleoside hervorragende Vorstufen für die Herstellung modifizierter Purinnukleoside sind. Im Vergleich zu E. coli Enzymen, die als Biokatalysatoren für die Synthese 2′-fluorinierter Purinnukleoside bereits in der Literatur beschrieben sind, ermöglichen die hier generierten Enzyme die Durchführung der Transglykosylierung bei höherer Temperatur und scheinen dabei effizienter zu sein. Gleichzeitig werden 2,6-dihalogenierte Purine sehr gut als Substrate erkannt und die Synthese der entsprechenden (Deoxy )riboside verläuft dementsprechend schnell. Die Ergebnisse dieser Arbeit verdeutlichen generell das Potential thermostablier Enzyme als Biokatalysatoren und ebnen insbesondere den Weg für verbesserte und umweltfreundlichere Verfahren für die Synthese wertvoller 2′-fluorinierter und 2,6-dihalogenierter Purinnkleosid-Analoga.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-09-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36648</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36648</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3447/szeker_kathleen.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
