<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:57Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2747">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2747</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:610</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Design characteristics of a European Food Propensity Questionnaire in relation to Feasibility of use and Performance </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Evaluierung der Design-Charakteristika eines Europaeischen Ernaehrungshauefigkeitsfragebogen (European Food Propensity Questionnaire/EFPQ) hinsichtlich ihrer Einsetzbarkeit und Leistungsfaehigkeit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Illner, Anne-Kathrin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:610</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Background: Standardized dietary data on the individual level is needed to reliably compare and investigate diet-disease relationships in multi-centre prospective studies. A standardized long-term instrument (Food Propensity Questionnaire/FPQ) might improve the provision of comparable and valid usual dietary intake data. An evaluation of its standardized design characteristics with respect to the feasibility of use and performance is therefore warranted. Methods: The multilingual non-quantitative European FPQ (EFPQ) inquires the frequency of consumption of 116 foods and beverages during the preceding year. 80 participants from each of five ongoing European cohorts in Spain (EPIC-San Sebastian), Italy (EPIC-Florence), Germany (EPIC-Potsdam), Estonia (Estonian Genome Centre/EGC) and Norway (Norwegian Women and Cancer Study/NOWAC) were randomly selected and invited to complete either a web-based or a paper-based EFPQ (Web-EFPQ and Paper-EFPQ) in combination with three monthly telephone-administered 24-hour dietary recalls (24-HDRs) using EPIC-SOFT software. The analysis of the feasibility of use included 261 men and women aged 19-75 y (mean age: 55 y), who fully completed the EFPQ. The performance analysis was carried out in 241 subjects that responded to at least two 24-HDRs, in addition to the EFPQ. Uniform portion sizes for all centres and centre-specific portion sizes being fitted from the 24-HDRs were compared regarding their effects on the EFPQ’s performance in food intake estimation, correlational ranking and misclassification. The comparative analyses were performed in the whole study population and separately by study centre or European region using nonparametric statistics. Reference data was obtained by the means of a statistical modelling method that originally aimed to estimate individual usual intake (Multiple Source method (MSM). Furthermore, the potential of the EFPQ in identifying habitual consumers of foods and in supplementing usual intake estimates of less commonly consumed foods on repeat 24-HDRs was explored by assessing whether or not increasing EFPQ-reported frequency was associated with both the probability of consuming a given food on a 24-HDR and the ranked average amount consumed on a 24-HDR-consumption-day. Results: Response rates for the Web-EFPQ varied among the study centres from 30% in EPIC-San Sebastian to 70% in NOWAC and 93% in EGC. Web-Users rarely requested support and were in all centres younger and higher educated than those who completed the paper-format. For 67% of the included food items on the standardized food list of the EFPQ, the consumer proportion was more than 65% and 27 food items were identified to be consumed from 90% of all study participants. Although at food item level the inclusion of centre-specific portion sizes remarkably improved the ranking among all participants according to their intake, compared to the ranking in the reference data the effect seemed to cancel out at food group level. Relative to the reference data, the EFPQ with centre-specific portion sizes classified fewer subjects correctly into the same quartile of food group intake (overall: 36.7%) compared to the EFPQ with uniform portion sizes (overall: 39.7%) and extremely misclassified more (overall: 4.2% with centre-specific portion sizes versus 3.3% with uniform portion sizes). Furthermore, a differential effect of the portion sizes types on food intakes, correlations and misclassification by food group and European region was found. In general, uniform portion sizes appeared to perform slightly better in the Central and Northern European centres, whereas centre-specific portion sizes tended to be more appropriate in the Southern ones. Furthermore, for 27 out of the 74 (37%) less commonly consumed food items on the 24-HDRs there were significant positive relationships between reported frequency-category on the EFPQ and the 24-HDR-probability of consumption on a random day. Positive relationships between the frequency-category on the EFPQ and the ranked average amount consumed on a 24-HDR-consumption-day were observed for 32 of these food items (43%). Conclusion: Overall, this study supports the feasibility to use the standardized EFPQ in culturally different European study populations, including its web-based version. The moderate ability to classify individuals correctly according to their intake calls into question the stand-alone application of long-term dietary assessment instruments in prospective studies and supports approaches that combine different dietary assessment instruments.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Problemstellung: Standardisierte Ernährungsdaten auf individueller Ebene sind erforderlich, um Zusammenhänge zwischen Ernährung und Krankheiten in multizentrischen prospektiven Studien untersuchen zu können. Ein standardisierter Häufigkeitsfragebogen (Food Propensity Questionnaire/FPQ) könnte die Bereitstellung von vergleichbaren und validen Daten verbessern. Eine Evaluierung seiner Design-Charakteristika hinsichtlich ihrer Einsetzbarkeit und Leistungsfähigkeit ist daher erforderlich. Methoden: Der mehrsprachige nicht-quantitative Europaeische FPQ (EFPQ) erfragt die Verzehrshäufigkeit von 116 Lebensmitteln der letzten 12 Monate. Je 80 zufällig ausgewählte Teilnehmer von 5 Europäischen Kohortenstudien in Spanien (EPIC-San Sebastian), Italien (EPIC-Florence), Deutschland (EPIC-Potsdam), Estland (Estonian Genome Centre/EGC) und Norwegen (Norwegian Women and Cancer Study/NOWAC) wurden eingeladen, den EFPQ sowie drei monatlich telefonisch durchgeführte 24-Stunden-Erinnerungsprotokolle (24-HDRs) zu beantworten. Die Teilnehmer konnten zwischen einer web- und Papier-basierten EFPQ-Version wählen (Web- und Papier-EFPQ). Die Einsetzbarkeit dieser Administrationsmodi und der Lebensmittelliste wurden deskriptiv in 261 Männern und Frauen im Alter von 19-75 Jahren (mittleres Alter: 55 Jahre) untersucht. Die Analyse zur Leistungsfähigkeit basiert auf den Angaben von 241 Personen, die zusätzlich zum EFPQ mindestens zwei 24-HDRs beantworteten. Einheitliche Portionsgrößen und studienzentrumspezifische Portionsgrößen, abgeleitet aus den 24-HDRs-Daten, wurden hinsichtlich ihrer Effekte auf die geschätzte Lebensmittelaufnahme, Korrelationen und Missklassifizierung in allen Teilnehmern und stratifiziert nach Studienzentrum oder Europäischer Region verglichen. Referenzdaten wurden hierzu mittels statistischer Modellierung zur Schätzung der individuellen üblichen Ernährung (Multiple Source Method (MSM) generiert. Zur Überprüfung der Fähigkeit des EFPQs, wahre Konsumenten zu identifizieren und die Schätzwerte von selten konsumierten Lebensmitteln zu verbessern, wurde getestet, ob eine höhere EFPQ-Verzehrshäufigkeitsangabe eines Lebensmittels mit der Verzehrsswahrscheinlichkeit dieses Lebensmittels als auch mit der mittleren berichteten Aufnahmemenge an einem 24-HDR-Verzehrsstag assoziiert ist. Ergebnisse: Die Antwortraten für den Web-EFPQ variierten zwischen 30% in EPIC-San Sebastian, 70% in NOWAC und 93% in EGC. Web-EFPQ-Nutzer waren in allen Studienzentren jünger und höher gebildet als Papier-EFPQ-Nutzer. 67% der Items der standardisierten Lebensmittelliste hatten mehr als 65% Personen mit positiver Verzehrshäufigkeitsangabe und insgesamt wurden 27 Lebensmittel von 90% aller Teilnehmer konsumiert. Im Vergleich zu den Schätzwerten der MSM führte die Verwendung von studienzentrumspezifischen Portionsgrößen zu einer verbesserten Leistungsfähigkeit des EFPQs, die Teilnehmer hinsichtlich ihrer Lebensmittel-Aufnahme zu kategorisieren, aber dieser Effekt war für Lebensmittelgruppen nicht mehr vorhanden. Der EFPQ mit zentrumspezifischen Portionsgrößen klassifizierte weniger Personen in die gleichen Quartile (insgesamt: 36.7%) als der EFPQ mit einheitlichen Portionsgrößen (insgesamt: 39.7%) und missklassifizierte mehr (insgesamt: 4.2% mit zentrumspezifischen vs. 3.3% mit einheitlichen Portionsgrößen). Der Effekt der Portionsgrößen auf Lebensmittelaufnahme, Korrelationen und Missklassifizierung variierte in Abhängigkeit von Lebensmittelgruppe und Europäischer Region. Für 27 der 74 selten konsumierten Lebensmittel (37%) in den 24-HDRs waren signifikant positive Zusammenhänge zwischen EFPQ-Häufigkeitsangabe und Verzehrsswahrscheinlichkeit vorhanden und für 32 dieser Lebensmittel (43%) positive Zusammenhänge mit der mittleren berichteten Aufnahmemenge an einem 24-HDR-Verzehrsstag. Schlussfolgerung: Die Ergebnisse sprechen für eine gute Einsetzbarkeit des EFPQs in der multizentrischen Studienpopulationen, einschließlich seiner web-basierten Version. Die moderate Leistungsfähigkeit des EFPQs, die Teilnehmer hinsichtlich ihrer üblichen Ernährung korrekt zu klassifizieren, unterstützt neue Konzepte der Ernährungserhebung, die mehrere 24-HDRs mit einem FPQ kombinieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-01-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2747</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28675</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28675</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2747/illner_anne.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
