<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:26Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2860">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2860</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:610</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Vitamin E intake and cardiovascular diseases in the EPIC-Potsdam Study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Vitamin E Einnahme und Kardioväscular Erkrankungen in EPIC-Potsdam Studie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cordero Gonzalez, Zorabel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:610</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Cardiovascular disease is considered the leading cause of mortality world-wide and the prevention of CVD is one aim in the public health. Systematic reviews showed contradictory results about the relation between vitamin E intake and the risk of cardiovascular diseases. The characterization of the EPIC-Potsdam population across dietary vitamin E intake quintiles in this study seems to be according to other lifestyle patterns previously reported as healthy lifestyle pattern associated with supplementation usage. In this study, individuals with high vitamin E intake compared to those with low vitamin E intake were more likely to be women, to have higher education, non-smoking habits, lower and intermediate alcohol consumption, to spend more time in sport activities and to use vitamin E supplements. In contrast, the lowest intake of vitamin E was noted among subjects who had higher WHR and over normal range of blood pressure (SBP and DBP), and more likely also to report diabetes and hyperlipidaemia. Two dietary patterns were derived; one was a food pattern rich in vitamin E and another was a food pattern rich in antioxidants. Findings suggest that the healthy lifestyle at baseline in the EPIC-Potsdam study is related to a higher intake of micronutrient as vitamin E, vitamin C, β-carotenoids and flavonoids. Results of this study showed statistically significant associations between higher intake of vitamin E and increment of the risk for Myocardial Infarction. Higher intake of the food pattern rich in vitamin E is associated with a 31% reduction for all CV events and higher intake of the food pattern rich in antioxidants is associated with a 45% reduction for all CV events. Results appear to be partially justified under consideration of the paradoxical properties of vitamin E as anti- and pro-oxidant, however, those results may be a product of chance, and also bias and methodological limitations cannot be omitted.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Kardiovaskuläre Erkrankungen (CVD) werden weltweit als häufigste Todesursache angesehen, und die Vorsorge und Bekämpfung von CVD ist eines der Hauptziele der Bevölkerungsgesundheit. Systematische Forschungen haben widersprüchliche Resultate bezüglich des Zusammenhangs zwischen Vitamin E-Einnahme und dem Risiko kardiovaskulärer Erkrankungen gezeigt. Die Chakterisierung der Potsdamer EPIC-Bevölkerung mittels diätischer Einnahme von Vitamin E scheint in dieser Studie anderen im Vorfeld festgestellten gesunden Lebensstilmustern mit Ergänzungseinnahmen zu entsprechen. In dieser Studie waren Personen mit hoher Vitamin E-Einnahme im Vergleich zu denen mit niedrigerer Einnahme überwiegend Frauen, die eine höhere Bildungsstufe hatten, Nichtraucherinnen mit wenig bis mittlerem Alkoholkonsum, vermehrt sportlich aktiv und einen höherer Vitamin E-Verzehr hatten. Im Gegensatz hierzu wurde die niedrigste Vitamin-E-Einnahme bei der Gruppe mit höherer WHR und erhöhtem Blutdruck (SBP und DBP), die zudem häufiger unter Diabetis und Hyperlipodaemia litt, festgestellt. Es wurden zwei Ernährungsmuster zugrundegelegt, zum einen ein Ernährungsmuster mit reichem Vitamin E-Anteil , im Gegensatz zu einem Ernährungsmuster mit hohem Anteil an Antioxidanten. Die Forschungsergebnisse legen nahe, dass der gesündere Lebensstil gemäß der EPIC-Potsdam-Studie im Zusammenhang mit dem höheren Verzehr von Micronutrients und nicht etwa erhöhtem Verzehr von Vitamin E, Vitamin C, ß-Carotenoiden und Flavonoiden steht. Die Ergebnisse dieser Studie zeigten statistisch signifikante Zusammenhänge zwischen höherem Vitamin E-Verzehr und Erhöhung des MI-Risikos. Höherer Verzehr des an Vitamin E reichen Ernährungsmusters ist mit der Reduktion von 31 % aller kardiovaskulären Erkrankungen in Zusammenhang zu bringen. Hingegen ist mit dem höheren Verzehr des an Antioxidanten reichen Ernährungsmusters eine Reduktion aller CV von 45 % verbunden. Bei diesen Resultaten sind die paradoxen Eigenschaften von Vitamin E als Anti- und Pro-Oxidant zu berücksichtigen. Trotzdem könnten diese Resultate dem Zufall zuzuschreiben sein. Methodologische Begrenzungen können ebenfalls nicht ausgeschlossen werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-04-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2860</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26184</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26184</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2860/cordero_zorabel.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
