<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3507">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3507</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:650</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">The Management of Shareholder Relationships in Family Businesses: A Principal-Agent and Stewardship Perspective</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Das Management von Gesellschafterbeziehungen in Familienunternehmen: Eine Prinzipal-Agenten und Stewardship-Perspektive</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Siebels, Jan-Folke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:650</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The "family firm" as organizational form is a cornerstone of the economy in most countries and contributes significantly to their economic output. Family firms are characterized by a simultaneous involvement of the family in the ownership and the management of the firms, which results in specific challenges and potential areas of conflict. The dissertation at hand "The management of shareholder relationships in family businesses: A principal-agent and stewardship perspective" deals with the specific and individual shareholder structure of the family firm and the impact of this shareholder structure on the aptitude for conflict in the family firm. The study focuses especially on the roles of non-active shareholders in family firms, the relationships amongst them as well as the relationships of these shareholders with the active, managing shareholders and the possibilities to influence these complex relationships through the adequate configuration of the corporate governance structure. As a result a conceptional role model for non-active shareholders is developed which sheds light on the specific interests of this shareholder group. By integrating this role-model into the corporate governance discussion the study shows that the role-selection of non-active shareholders can be influenced and adapted through the set-up and configuration of the corporate governance structure. Therefore, corporate governance should not be perceived only as dependent variable but more as a constitutive element in context of the family firm.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Familienunternehmen sind ein integraler Bestandteil internationaler Volks-wirtschaften. Sie sind dabei durch die gleichzeitige Beteiligung der Familie am Eigentum des Unternehmens und häufig auch am Management gekennzeichnet, wodurch spezifische Spannungs- und Konfliktfelder entstehen. Die vorliegende Dissertation "The management of shareholder relationships in family businesses: A principal-agent and stewardship perspective" beschäftigt sich mit der individuellen Gesellschafterstruktur eines Familienunternehmens und deren Auswirkungen auf die Konfliktneigung in diesem Familienunternehmen. Dabei fokussiert sich die Arbeit insbesondere auf die Rollen von nicht-aktiven Gesellschafter/innen in Familienunternehmen, den Beziehungen dieser Gesellschafter untereinander sowie zu den aktiven Gesellschaftern und den Möglichkeiten diese komplexen Beziehungsgeflechte durch eine adäquate Ausgestaltung der Corporate Governance Struktur zu beeinflussen. Im Ergebnis wird ein konzeptionelles Rollen-Modell für nicht-aktive Gesellschafter entwickelt, das Aufschluss über die individuellen Interessenslagen dieser Gesellschafter gibt. Durch die Integration dieses Rollenmodells in die Corpoare Governance Diskussion wird zudem aufgezeigt, dass die Rollen-Selektion der nicht-aktiven Gesellschafter durch Ausgestaltung der Corporate Governance Struktur beeinflusst und verändert werden kann und somit nicht nur als abhängige Variable, sondern auch als gestaltendes Element verstanden werden kann.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-10-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3507</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3507/siebels_janfolke.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
