<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:45:24Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:271">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:271</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:320</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Büroflächenpolitik in Berlin 1981-99 : Akteure, Ziele, Entscheidungen</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">City Politics in Berlin 1981-99</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Altrock, Uwe Günter Hermann</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:320</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Arbeit untersucht am Beispiel von acht Fallstudien aus dem Bereich der Büroflächenplanung das Zusammenwirken der verschiedenen Akteure der Stadtentwicklungspolitik in Berlin. Dabei werden die Ziele der Akteure, deren Anpassung im Entscheidungsprozess, die entstehenden Konflikte und ihre Bewältigung, die Bündnisse zwischen den Akteuren und die Wirkung von Argumenten für die Konsensfindung analysiert. Hierauf aufbauend werden die Rolle von wirtschaftlichen Rahmenbedingungen, politischem Umfeld, Standort und grundstücksbezogenen Rahmenbedingungen, Strategien der einzelnen Akteure und dominanter städtebaulicher Leitbilder für die Entscheidungsfindung untersucht. Die Arbeit versucht dabei eine Verzahnung von Ansätzen der lokalen Politikforschung und der planungswissenschaftlichen Forschung, wobei besonderer Wert gelegt wird auf die Hintergründe des Zustandekommens baulich-räumlicher Ausprägungen von Großprojekten in der Stadtentwicklung. Mit Hilfe politikwissenschaftlicher Ansätze gelingt es dabei, die Veränderungen in der Stadtentwicklungspolitik im Untersuchungszeitraum angemessen zu interpretieren. Die Arbeit schließt mit einer umfangreichen Analyse möglicher Empfehlungen zur Qualifizierung der strategischen Planung, zu einer verbesserten Nutzung möglicher Problemlösungsspielräume sowie Durchsetzung planerischer Ordnungs- und Nachhaltigkeitsziele und integrativer Beteiligungsverfahren.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The thesis explores the interaction of various actors in city politics in Berlin focusing on eight case studies, all of them important development projects for office buildings. The author analyses the actors' goals, their adaptation throughout the decision making process, decision making in conflict, partnerships and the effects of argumentation in discussions. Building upon that the importance of the economic and political background, micro-locational factors, strategies of particular actors and dominant planning ideas for the decision process is being considered. The study tries to integrate political scientists' approaches in the field of "new urban politics" and urban planning theory. Therefore it is able to explain decision making even when it comes to planning features often neglected by political scientists. However, using political science helps understanding the changes in Berlin's city politics in the 1980s and 1990s especially considering the massive political changes as a result of the German reunification and to compare it with other greater cities in the United States and Europe. The thesis does not finish without taking a close look at possible recommendations for the improvement of strategic planning, the use of problem solving techniques, urban design, sustainable development and participation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2001-10-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/271</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-2665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-2665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/271/altrock_uwe.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
