<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:46:08Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:425">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:425</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:660</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Synthesis of silica aerogels and their application as a drug delivery system</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Herstellung von Silica Aerogelen und Ihre Anwendung als Medikamententräger</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Smirnova, Irina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:660</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit der Herstellung von Silica Aerogelen und deren potentiellen Anwendung als Medikamententräger. Die Herstellung von Silica Aerogelen ist sehr zeit- und kostenintensiv. Ein wichtiger Parameter des Herstellungsverfahrens ist die Gelierungszeit. Die Gelierungszeit kann, insbesondere bei der Synthese von Silica Aerogelen niedriger Dichte, sehr lang sein. Verschiedene Katalysatoren wurden bereits erprobt mit dem Ziel, die Gelierungszeit zu verkürzen. In dieser Arbeit wird der Gelierungsprozess in der Gegenwart von Kohlendioxid untersucht. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass die Gelierung durch die Zugabe von CO2 während des Sol-Gel Prozesses wesentlich beschleunigt wird. Der Einfluss der Prozessbedingungen, wie Temperatur, Konzentration der Reagenzien und die Art des Lösungsmittels auf die Reaktionsbeschleunigung wird untersucht. Besondere Beachtung wird auf die Abhängigkeit der für die Gelierung benötigten CO2 Konzentration von den Prozessbedingungen gelegt. Die physikalischen Eigenschaften der nach dieser Methode hergestellten Aerogele werden mit den jeweiligen Eigenschaften der konventionell hergestellten Aerogele verglichen. Anhand dieser Ergebnisse werden die Vor- und Nachteile des vorgeschlagenen Herstellungsverfahrens diskutiert. Der zweite Teil dieser Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit der Anwendung der Silica Aerogele als Wirkstoffträger. Da Silica Aerogele gesundheitlich unbedenklich sind, werden sie bereits im Bereich der Pharmazie (beispielsweise als Fliesshilfsmittel zur Tablettenherstellung) eingesetzt. Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit wird die Anwendung von hydrophilen Silica Aerogelen als Wirkstoffträger untersucht. Die Beladung der Silica Aerogele mit einem Wirkstoff erfolgt durch Adsorption aus überkritischen Gasen. Die Eigenschaften der resultierenden Wirkstoff-Aerogel Formulierungen, wie die Wirkstoffkonzentration und chemische Stabilität werden experimetell bestimmt. Auch die Freisetzungskinetiken der Wirkstoffe aus solchen Formulierungen werden untersucht. Es konnte gezeigt werden, dass die Freisetzung des Wirkstoffs aus dem Silica Aerogel wesentlich schneller als aus dessen kristalliner Form erfolgt. Die Ursache für die beschleunigte Freisetzung ist die große innere Oberfläche des auf dem Aerogel adsorbierten Wirkstoffs, sowie die augenblickliche Zerstörung des Aerogelgitters in wässrigen Medien. Aufgrund dieser experimentellen Ergebnisse wird der potentielle Einsatz von Silica Aerogelen als Medikamententräger diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work deals with the production of silica aerogels and their potential applications in the pharmaceutical industry. Synthesis of silica aerogels is rather expensive. A lot of efforts have been made to find a way to decrease the cost of aerogel production. An important factor of the synthesis of low density aerogels is gelation time. Gelation time can be very long, especially in the case of low density aerogels. Different types of catalysts were used in order to accelerate the gelation. In this work, it is suggested to use CO2 to enhance the gelation process. It is shown, that the addition of CO2 during the sol-gel process leads to the fast gelation. The influence of different factors, like temperature, component ratio, and solvent nature on this process is also described. Special attention is given to the experimental determination of the optimal CO2 concentration needed for gelation at different process conditions. For the evaluation of this process, physical properties of the aerogels synthesized by this method are determined and compared with those obtained by conventional methods. The second part of this work deals with the application of silica aerogels as a drug delivery system (DDS). Being environmentally benign and non-toxic, silica aerogels can be used in the pharmaceutical industry. Their large surface area and open pore structure make them to an ideal potential carrier material. In this work, it is suggested the use of hydrophilic silica aerogels as a carrier material for pharmaceuticals. The loading of silica aerogels with pharmaceuticals can be made by different processes, in particular by adsorption. Silica aerogel are loaded with active compounds (drugs) by the adsorption from the supercritical CO2 solution. The characteristics of the corresponding aerogel-drug formulations, like drug concentration and stability, are studied in order to prove whether the process suggested in this work is suitable for the pharmaceuticals. Also, the release of the corresponding drugs from such formulations is investigated. It is expected that the drug release from an aerogel-drug formulation is faster then that of crystalline drugs. Pharmaceuticals adsorbed on silica aerogels get a larger surface area, which should lead to faster dissolution of the compound in water. Moreover, the easily collapsing aerogel structure in water also favors a faster release. Based on these experiments, the application of silica aerogels as a drug delivery system is discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2002-12-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/425</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-4205</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-4205</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/425/smirnova_irina.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
