<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:13Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2354">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2354</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:660</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Homogeneously catalyzed hydrogenation reactions in inverse micelles with recycling of the catalyst</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Durchführung von homogen katalysierten Hydrierreaktionen in inversen Mizellen mit Katalysatorrückführung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Milano Brusco, Juan Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:660</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Microemulsion systems were designed and used as solvent systems in catalytic hydrogenation reactions catalyzed by the water soluble catalyst complex Rh‒TPPTS in order to achieve reaction rate and selectivity improvement focusing on product isolation and catalyst recycling. To find intrinsic differences between biphasic systems and microemulsions as reaction medium for catalytic reactions with the water-soluble catalyst complex Rh‒TPPTS, the kinetics of the catalytic hydrogenation of dimethyl itaconate (DMI) was studied in a biphasic cyclohexane-water system and in a [Triton X-100/1-pentanol]/cyclohexane/water microemulsion, in both cases using the water-soluble catalyst complex Rh-TPPTS. A typical profile of a zero-order reaction was observed in the case of the biphasic system. Against that the reaction order for DMI changed to 1 in a microemulsion. Based on Osborn-Wilkinson-like kinetics, the irreversible attack of free DMI at the rhodium complex was determined to be the step governing the reaction. The activation energy of the rate determining step is 53 kJ•mol-1 and is similar in both systems. Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS) and Small Angle Neutron Scattering (SANS) measurements were used to determine the structural dimensions of the commercial polyoxyethylene-based (Igepal CA-520 and Triton X-100) nonionic microemulsions, showing a linear dependence between the initial hydrogenation rate of DMI and the radius of the micelles. The initial hydrogenation rate of DMI in bulk water was exceeded in both microemulsions. Indications of deformation of the originally spherical Triton X-100 reverse micelles upon addition of the water soluble catalyst complex Rh-TPPTS were found. Microemulsion systems with the nonionic surfactant Triton X-100, the anionic surfactant AOT and the narrow range nonionic surfactant Lutensol XA 50 were also used as reaction medium in the same reaction with the catalyst Rh‒TPPTS, accomplishing product isolation and catalyst recycling. An unusual hindering effect of the surfactant on the production of elaidic acid and stearic acid as sunflower oil was hydrogenated in Triton X-100 microemulsion systems with the water-soluble catalyst complex Rh‒TPPTS was observed. When the ligand/metal ratio was higher, the reaction was slower but more selective to oleic acid. The Rh‒TPPTS catalyst could be recycled up to 3 times after hydrogenation of sunflower oil by extracting the oil phase of a three-phase microemulsion system, observing a continuous deactivation of the catalyst.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Verwendung von wasserlöslichen Katalysatoren in zweiphasigen Reaktionsmedien ermöglicht nach der Hydrierung von Substraten wie z.B. Itaconsäuredimethylester (ISDME) eine problemlose Produktabtrennung. Die Reaktionsgeschwindigkeit in diesen Systemen ist jedoch aufgrund des ungünstigen Verteilungskoeffizienten (P) oft begrenzt. Deswegen ist die Verwendung von Tensiden, d.h. die Bildung von Mikroemulsionen aus den Reaktionsgemischen eine Möglichkeit, die Limitierung der geringen Wasserlöslichkeit zu umgehen und die Kontaktfläche zwischen Katalysatorphase und Substratphase zu vergrößern und damit die Hydrierung zu beschleunigt. Am Ende der Reaktion kann die Produktabtrennung entweder durch eine temperaturabhängige Phasentrennung stattfinden. Für die Untersuchung wurde ein Katalysatorkomplex verwendet, der aus dem Rhodiumprecursor Rh2(COD)2Cl2 und dem wasserlöslichen Liganden TPPTS gebildet wurde. Die Hydrierung von ISDME wurde in zweiphasig Cyclohexan/Wasser System und in Mikroemulsionen durchgeführt. Für das Substrat ISDME ergab sich ein Verteilungskoeffizient von 0.75. Damit liegt eine ausreichende Substratkonzentration für die Reaktion in der Katalysatorphase vor. Die Reaktion verläuft nach einen Kinetik 0. Ordnung. In der Mikroemulsionen hat die Substratkonzentration einen linearen Einfluss auf die Anfangsgeschwindigkeit. Für eine kinetische Auswertung wurde das Modell von Osborn-Wilkinson benutzt und die Aktivierungsenergie der Reaktion in der Triton- Mikroemulsion (53 KJ•mol-1) ermittelt. Daraus kann geschlossen werden, dass die Reaktion in dem System ohne Stofftransportlimitierung abläuft. Für das Cyclohexan/Wasser System zeigt der Unterschied zwischen der Aktivierungsenergie im homogenen System (57.9 KJ•mol-1) und der effektive Aktivierungsenergie (11.5 KJ•mol-1) die Limitierung der Reaktion durch Stofftransport auf. Das molare Verhältnis Wasser/Tensid (ω) und das Verhältnis Pentanol/Triton (δ) sind wichtigen Einfluß der Größe der Mizellen. Bei der Hydrierung von ISDME hat die Größe der Mizellen direkten Einfluss. Die Größe der Mizellen haben wir durch SANS und DLS Messungen gewertet. In der partielle Hydrierung von Sonnenblumenöl hat der Tensidkonzentration direkten Einfluss.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-11-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2354</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-24750</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-24750</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2354/original_milano_juan.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2354/milano_juan.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
