<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:38Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3534">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3534</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:660</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Kinetic investigation for the oxidative dehydrogenation of propane (ODP) at tailored ternary (VO x) n-(TiO x) n /SBA15 catalysts</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Kinetische Untersuchung zur oxidativen Dehydrierung von Propan (ODP) an maßgeschneiderten ternären (VO x ) n-(TiO x) n /SBA15-Katalysatoren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carrero Marquez, Carlos Alberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:660</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The search for highly productive catalysts for propene production is becoming increasingly important to bridging the propene demand¬-consumption gap which is increasing every year. As a solution, the oxidative dehydrogenation of propane (ODP) is predicted to become an alternative process because of its intrinsic advantages, though its industrial application has failed so far due to the low propene productivities reached. Therefore, ODP has been investigated using different ternary (VOx)n-(TiOx)n/SBA15 catalysts for the fundamental understanding of the catalysts’ structure-reactivity relationship. In order to find a productive catalyst, a matrix of catalysts was synthesized by sequential grafting of titanium and vanadium alkoxides on a well-defined, mesoporous SBA15 support. These catalysts were prepared by Till Wolfram (Fritz Haber Institute, Berlin). Our part of the project was focused on the kinetics and thus on the performance of the catalysts. Selected catalysts were tested under ODP reaction conditions to acquire the accurate kinetic data needed to gain better insight into the ODP reaction mechanism. All catalysts studied were stable under reaction conditions. In the large catalyst set, the most productive catalysts were found to have a composition of metal loadings close to the monolayer coverage. By comparing the catalysts, it was observed that three-dimensional nanoparticles negatively influenced the propene productivity by accelerating the combustion reactions. The 4V/13Ti/SBA15 catalyst presented the highest propene productivity (5,5 gpropene/gcat/h), which invoked a detailed kinetic analysis revealing that high vanadia dispersion is required to achieve high propene selectivity. Apparently, the formation of a joint V-Ti oxide monolayer is crucial to obtaining improved reaction rates without sacrificing propene selectivity. Finally, the most promising catalysts were extensively studied using Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR) after being exposed to H2 or ODP reaction conditions. A quantitative study carried out on different binary-supported vanadia catalysts demonstrated that even under identical preparation and loading conditions, the nature of the active state would be severely influenced by the support material. This, in turn, influences the catalyst activity for propane activation to be proportional to the extent of reducibility of vanadia at the same time. Also, EPR confirmed that ODP most probably occurs via the pathway involving V4+ centers instead of V3+. EPR experiments over ternary (VOx)n-(TiOx)n/SBA15 catalysts reduced with H2 confirmed that V4+ and Ti3+ centers are simultaneously present. Under ODP conditions, rapid Ti3+ reoxidation occurs because of the presence of O2. However, Ti3+ formation and participation during ODP reaction cannot be discarded completely.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Suche nach hoch produktiven Katalysatoren wird für die Produktion von Propen zunehmend bedeutend, um die jährlich größer werdende Kluft zwischen Angebot und Nachfrage zu stillen. Wegen ihrer inhärenten Vorteile gilt die oxidative Dehydrierung von Propen (kurz: ODP) als aussichtsreicher Lösungsansatz für die Zukunft, obwohl deren industrielle Anwendung bislang an den zu niedrigen Produktionsraten von Propen scheiterte. Aus diesem Grund wurde in der vorliegenden Studie die ODP an verschiedenen ternären (VOx)n-(TiOx)n/SBA15-Katalysatoren untersucht, um die Beziehung zwischen der Struktur und der Reaktivität der Katalysatoren auf fundamentaler Ebene zu verstehen. Um einen möglichst produktiven Katalysator zu erhalten, wurde eine breite Matrix an Katalysatoren durch Grafting von Titan- und Vanadium-Alkoxiden auf hochdefinierten, mesoporösen SBA15-Träger synthetisiert. Die Katalysatoren wurden am Fritz-Haber-Institut der Max-Planck-Gesellschaft in Berlin hergestellt. Unser Anteil des Projekts konzentrierte sich auf die Untersuchung der Kinetik und somit auf das Verhalten der Katalysatoren währende der Reaktion. Anschließend wurden ausgewählte Katalysatoren ausführlicher unter ODP-Reaktionsbedingungen getestet, um exakte kinetische Daten zu erhalten. Alle Katalysatoren erwiesen sich unter Reaktionsbedingungen als stabil. In der Auswahl an Katalysatoren hoben sich die produktivsten hervor, indem sie eine hohe metallische Beladung aufweisen, die nah an einer monomolekularen Bedeckung liegen. Beim Vergleich der Katalysatoren bei gleicher Verweilzeit wurde beobachtet, dass dreidimensionale Nanopartikel die Produktivität des Propens negativ beeinflussen, indem sie die Verbrennung des Propens beschleunigen. Zugleich jedoch zeigte der hoch dispergierte Katalysator 4V/13Ti/SBA15 die höchste Produktivität für Propen (5,5 gpropene/gcat/h), während die Formierung einer Monomolekularschicht aus V-Ti-Oxid als entscheidend herausstellte, um eine bessere Reaktionsrate zu erzielen, ohne dafür die Selektivität des Propens zu beeintächtigen. Schließlich wurden die vielversprechendsten Katalysatoren, die zuvor entweder H2 oder ODP-Bedingungen ausgesetzt worden waren mit der Elektronen-Paramagnet-Resonanz (EPR) untersucht. Eine quantitative Studie, die an verschiedenen, binären Vanadiumoxid-Katalysatoren durchgeführt wurde, zeigte, dass sogar bei identischer Vorbereitung und Beladung das Verhalten der aktiven Spezies massiv vom Trägermaterial beeinflusst wird. Dies wiederum steuert die Aktivität der Katalysatoren in Bezug auf die Aktivierung des Propens und ist zugleich proportional zur Reduzierbarkeit des Vanadiums. Die EPR-Versuche bestätigten ebenfalls, dass ODP am wahrscheinlichsten über den Reaktionsweg mit V4+-Zentren anstelle von V3+ abläuft. Die EPR-Versuche über ternären, per H2 reduzierten (VOx)n-(TiOx)n/SBA15-Katalysatoren wiederum belegen, dass V4+- und Ti3+-Zentren zur gleichen Zeit anwesend sind. Unter ODP-Bedingungen tritt wegen der Gegenwart von O2 eine rasche Re-Oxidation von Ti3+ ein. Dennoch kann eine Formierung von Ti3+Ionen und deren Beteiligung an einer ODP-Reaktion nicht vollständig ausgeschlossen werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-11-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3534</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37367</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37367</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3534/carreromarquez_carlosalberto.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
