<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:04Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3404">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3404</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Biotransformation, trace analysis and effects of perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Frömel, Tobias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances are environmental contaminants with adverse properties owing to the presence of the particularly strong C-F bond. In this thesis, the biotransformation potential of fluorotelomer ethoxylates (FTEOs) was assessed under aerobic conditions. After investigation of the technical FTEO mixture by electrospray-mass spectrometry (ESI-MS) techniques, it could be shown that two pathways are possible, one involving oxidation to ω-oxidized carboxylates (FTEOCs), which can be stable under certain conditions, and another pathway releasing perfluorocarboxylates, in function of the perfluoroalkyl chain length of the FTEO. After successful synthesis of two shortchain FTEOCs, these compounds were quantified in a wastewater treatment plant (WWTP) effluent by solid phase extraction and high performance liquid chromatography coupled to ESIMS/MS. Alongside the FTEOCs, a set of perfluorocarboxylates and perfluoroalkane sulfonates was determined in seventeen WWTP effluent samples and four surface water samples. The biotransformation behavior of three building blocks of potential novel environmentally friendly fluorosurfactants was investigated. It could be shown that 6-(trifluoromethoxy)hexan-1-ol released 100% inorganic fluoride, whereas 3-(trifluoromethoxy)propan-1-ol yielded only 15% fluoride. The remainder was shown to be organically bound as the non-degradable 3-trifluoromethoxy)propanoic acid. The building block 1-(2,2,3,3,4,4,4-heptafluorobutoxy)propan-2-ol expectedly released perfluorobutanoic as the persistent transformation product. The toxicity of the dead-end transformation product PFBA towards the green algae Pseudokirchneriella subcapitata and towards the Cladoceran Chydorus sphaericus was assessed with standardized tests. The results suggested no acute toxicity of these compounds at environmental levels. Other fluorinated compounds were included in the screening suggesting a general increase of toxicity with longer perfluoroalkyl chain length. However, the functional group itself showed a major effect on toxicity. The mass spectrometric fragmentation characteristics of the compounds studied in this thesis were carefully scrutinized. Comparison of different fluorotelomerbased compounds revealed a general fragmentation pattern for these compounds after negative electrospray ionization and collision-induced dissociation, which can be utilized to screen for novel fluorotelomer-based contaminants hereafter.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Polyfluorierte und perfluorierte Verbindungen stellen eine Gruppe von Umweltkontaminanten dar, die aufgrund der starken C-F-Bindung besonders negative ökologische Eigenschaften besitzen. In dieser Arbeit wurde das Biotransformations-Potenzial von Fluortelomerethoxylaten (FTEO)unter aeroben Bedingungen untersucht. Nach Ermittlung der molekularen Zusammensetzung eines technischen FTEO-Gemischs mittels Elektrospray-Massenspektrometrie (ESI-MS) konnte aufgezeigt werden, dass zwei Transformationswege möglich sind, wobei einer dieser Wege über ω-oxidierte Carboxylate (FTEOCs), welche unter bestimmten Bedingungen nicht weiter abbaubar sind, verläuft. Ein anderer Abbauweg mündet in Perfluorcarboxylaten. Nach erfolgreicher Synthese zweier kurzkettiger FTEOCs konnten diese Verbindungen mithilfe einer Methode basierend auf Festphasenextraktion und HPLC-ESIMS/MS in einer Kläranlagenablaufprobe nachgewiesen und quantifiziert werden. Neben den FTEOCs konnten eine Reihe von Perfluorcarboxylaten und Perfluoralkansulfonaten in siebzehn Kläranlagenabläufen und vier Oberflächengewässern bestimmt werden. Die Untersuchung der Bioabbaubarkeit dreier potentieller Bausteine für neue, umweltfreundliche Fluortenside ergab, dass 6-(Trifluormethoxy)hexan-1-ol 100% anorganisches Fluorid freisetzte. Die homologe Verbindung 3(Trifluormethoxy)propan-1-ol hingegen setzte lediglich 15% Fluorid frei, wobei das verbleibende Fluor in der nicht weiter abbaubaren 3-(Trifluormethoxy)propansäure organisch gebunden blieb. Der dritte Baustein - 1-(2,2,3,3,4,4,4-Heptafluorbutoxy)propan-2-ol – führte erwartungsgemäß zur persistenten Verbindung Perfluorbutansäure. Die Toxizität der Perfluorbutansäure gegenüber der Algenspezies Pseudokirchneriella subcapitata und dem Kleinkrebs Chydorus sphaericus wurde anschließend ermittelt. Die toxikologischen Kenndaten ergaben keine akute Gefährdung dieser Organismen bei umweltrelevanten Konzentrationen. Weitere fluorierte Verbindungen wurden untersucht, wobei gezeigt werden konnte, dass die Toxizität mit zunehmender Kettenlänge im Allgemeinen zunimmt, die funktionelle Gruppe jedoch einen signifikanten Einfluss auf die Toxizität hat. Die massenspektrometrische Fragmentierung aller untersuchten Verbindungen wurde untersucht. Dabei ergab sich ein allgemeiner Fragmentierungsweg für Fluortelomer-basierte Verbindungen unter negativen Elektrospray-Bedingungen und stoßinduzierter Fragmentierung. Diese Erkenntnisse können in Zukunft zur Detektion neuer unbekannter Fluortelomerbasierter Verbindungen verwendet werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-07-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36056</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-36056</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3404/froemel_tobias.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
