<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:32Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3514">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3514</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:540</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Synthese templatiert poröser Metalloxidfilme: Von kontrollierter Einstellung der Morphologie zu maßgeschneiderten Katalysatormaterialien</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Synthesis of metal oxide films with templated porosity: from controlled morphology to tailor-made catalyst</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ortel, Erik</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:540</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Gegenstand der vorliegenden Arbeit ist die Synthese von templatiert porösen Metalloxidfilmen mit kontrolliert einstellbaren Eigenschaften in Bezug auf Porenstruktur und Materialzusammensetzung für den Einsatz als neuartige Modellkatalysatoren. Für die Schaffung von porösen Katalysatorschichten mit definierter Mesoporenstruktur wurde im Rahmen dieser Arbeit eine Serie neuer amphiphiler Polymertemplate mit der Struktur PEO-PB-PEO entwickelt. Mittels SAXS-Untersuchungen konnte nachgewiesen werden, dass die PEO-PB-PEO-Template bereits bei geringen Polymerkonzentrationen stabile Mizellen in Lösung ausbilden. Die Templatierung mit solchen „vorgeformten“ PEO-PB-PEO-Mizellen ermöglichte eine gezielte Kontrolle der Porenmorphologie. Anhand von mesoporösen TiO2-Filmen wurde demonstriert, dass i) über die Länge der Polymerblöcke der eingesetzten PEO-PB-PEO-Template die Porengröße von 7 nm bis 21 nm im Durchmesser eingestellt werden kann, ii) durch eine Variation des eingesetzten Mengenverhältnisses von Polymer-zu-Oxidvorstufen eine gezielte Einstellung der Porenwanddicke unabhängig von der templatierten Porengröße in einem weiten Wanddicke von ca. 4 nm bis 23 nm möglich ist und iii) eine Kombination aus zwei verschiedenen amphiphilen Polymertemplaten mit unterschiedlichen Blocklängen die Schaffung bimodaler Mesoporensysteme erlaubt. Ferner wurde gezeigt, dass das PEO-PB-PEO-Polymer erfolgreich TiO2-Nanokristalle zu lokal geordneten mesoporösen TiO2-Filmen templatiert mit nahezu sphärischen Mesoporenformen, wohingegen molekulare Oxid-Vorstufen zu ellipsoiden stark abgeflachten Poren führen. Desweiteren demonstriert diese Arbeit die Synthese von neuartigen geordnet mesoporösen IrO2-Katalysatorfilmen basierend auf PEO-PB-PEO-Mizellen und einer Ir-Acetat-Vorstufe. Eine systematische Untersuchung der IrO2-Filmentwicklung während der thermischen Behandlung ermöglichte die Identifizierung der optimalen Kalzinierbedingungen zur Bildung eines IrO2-Films mit intakter Mesoporenstruktur, hoher innerer Oberfläche und gleichzeitig nanokristallinen Porenwänden. Ein weiterer Schwerpunkt der Arbeit war die Synthese von porösen Katalysatorschichten mit geträgerten Edelmetall-Nanopartikeln. Basierend auf einer unkonventionellen pH-neutralen TiO2-Vorstufe, dem Titan(IV)-bis(ammoniumlactato)-dihydroxid, wurde ein Konzepte zur Präparation von Pd-NP geträgerten mesoporösen TiO2-Filmen ausgearbeitet, welche eine gezielte Einstellung von sowohl Pd-NP-Größe, Pd-Beladung als auch der Porenstruktur unabhängig voneinander erlaubt. Templatiert mesoporöse Katalysatorschichten in der Zusammensetzung Pd/TiO2, Pt/TiO2, Au/TiO2, Pd/Al2O3, Pt/Al2O3, Pd/ZrO2, Pt/ZrO2 sowie Pd/CeO2 wurden auf einen alternativen Weg synthetisiert. Damit wurde eine Toolbox von neuen Präparationswegen geschaffen, die die Synthese von mesoporösen Katalysatorfilmen mit variierter Zusammensetzung von aktivem Metall und Trägeroxid ermöglichen. Die Aktivität und Selektivität der entwickelten Katalysatoren wurde experimentell anhand einer Modellreaktion, der Gasphasenhydrierung von Butadien nachgewiesen. Der mesoporöse Katalysatorfilm der Zusammensetzung Pd/Al2O3 zeigte dabei die höchste Raum-Zeit-Ausbeute an Butenen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Aim of the present work was the development of synthesis methods for metal oxide coatings with controlled pore structure and material composition as a new type of model system for heterogeneous catalysis. To control the materials pore structure a set of new structure-directing agents was deployed, i.e. amphiphilic triblock copolymers with PEO-PB-PEO structure. SAXS studies proof that PEO-PB-PEO forms stable micelles in solution already at very low polymer concentrations. Templating of mesopores with such "pre-formed" PEO-PB-PEO micelles therefore allows precise control over the obtained pore system. Using TiO2 films as example it is demonstrated that i) the pore size is determined by the molecular mass of the template polymer (pore diameter between 7 nm and 21 nm), ii) the thickness of pore walls can be controlled independent of pore size by changing the polymer to precursor ratio (wall thickness between 4 and 23 nm) and iii) the micelle formation of the PEO-PB-PEO template polymers is sufficiently distinct from that of other commercial polymers (e.g. PPO-PEO-PPO Pluronics), so that a combination of both polymers facilitates bimodal porosity via dual micelle templating. Moreover, PEO-PB-PEO can be used in combination with different oxide building-blocks. The polymers successfully template crystalline and locally ordered mesoporous TiO2 films employing either TiCl4 or redispersed TiO2 nanocrystals as metal oxide precursors. Moreover, it is shown that the employed building block strongly influences the obtained pore shape. While TiCl4-based films exhibit elliptical pore shapes, films based on TiO2 nanocrystals feature a pore structure with mesopore shapes close-to-spherical. Furthermore, it is shown for the first time that Iridium oxide, one of the most stable OER catalysts, can be synthesized as crystalline IrO2 films with ordered mesoporosity. Analytical studies of the Iridium oxide films during their thermal treatment clearly identifies the synthesis pathways and conditions that are essential to achieve a stable IrO2 catalyst, which possesses templated mesopore structure, crystalline pore walls and a large surface area. A major focus of this work was placed on the synthesis of porous catalytic coatings containing active noble-metal nanoparticles with adjustable particle size. Colloidal synthesis methods provide access to unsupported metal nanoparticles with narrow size distribution. Hence, a new approach for the preparation of supported catalysts was developed that relies on co-assembly of preformed colloidal metal particles, pore templates and a metal-oxide precursors. The synthesis employs titanium(IV) bis(ammonium lactato) dihydroxide as unconventional water-soluble precursor. The synthesis approach is illustrated for mesoporous and hierarchical porous Pd/TiO2 catalysts prepared from colloidal solutions of palladium nanoparticles. Moreover, templated mesoporous catalyst layers with varied composition in terms of support oxide and noble metal (Pd/TiO2, Pt/TiO2, Au/TiO2, Pd/Al2O3, Pt/Al2O3, Pd/ZrO2, Pt/ZrO2 and Pd/CeO2) were synthesized by an alternative route that employs molecular metal precursors. The combination of developed synthesis methods provides a toolbox for the precise synthesis of catalyst with controlled pore structure and composition. Activity and selectivity of the developed catalysts were studied employing gas-phase hydrogenation of butadiene as test reaction. In the present investigation, mesoporous Pd/Al2O3 catalysts provided the highest space-time yield to butenes.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-11-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3514</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3514/ortel_erik.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
