<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1631">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1631</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:004</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Single trial analyses of encephalogram data.</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Single trial Analysen von Enzephalogramm Daten.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lemm, Steven</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:004</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this thesis, inspired by the development of the Brain-computer-interface (BCI) technology, we present novel methods for the analysis of macroscopically recorded brain signals. Here the focus is put on improved feature extraction methods, the detection of mental states and the analysis of variability of brain responses. Conditional event-related (de-)synchronization: The fluctuation of signal power in a narrow band induced by an event is conventionally termed event-related (de-)synchronization and is quantified as the relative deviation from the mean baseline activity. We extend the ERD terminology with respect to a generalized reference. To this end, we oppose the time course of the event-related activity against those obtained from single trials without specific stimulus processing. From this generalized approach we derive a method to determine the dependencies of the ERD response on initial cortical states. A comparative study of surrogate and real ERD data validates this approach. Spatio-spectral filters: The common-spatial-pattern algorithm (CSP) determines optimally discriminative spatial filters from multivariate broad-band signals. We extend the conventional algorithm such that it additionally obtains simple frequency filters. This enables adaptation to the individual characteristics of the power spectrum and thus improves feature extraction. An empirical comparison with the conventional CSP method reveals the advantages of our approach in the context of the classification of imaginary unilateral hand movements. Extraction of event-related potentials (ERP): Independent component analysis (ICA) is a tool for statistical data analysis that is able to linearly decompose multivariate signals into their underlying source components. We present an ICA method that uses prior knowledge about the phase-locked property of ERPs for their improved extraction from single trial EEG. The application on artificially generated and real world data validates this approach in terms of an improved signal-to-noise ratio of the extracted ERPs. Adaptive feature combination across time: Lateralized mu-rhythm ERD and lateralized movement-related potentials are the most commonly used discriminative features for the classification of imaginary hand movements. In the context of real time classification we present a method that efficiently combines these temporally differently accentuated features. To this end, we first train weak classifiers for each time instance and each feature separately. Subsequently we combine these weak classifiers in a strictly causal, probabilistic manner. The effectiveness of this approach was proven by its successful application to data from the international BCI competitions in 2003 and 2005.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Inspiriert, nicht zuletzt durch die Erforschung der Brain-computer-interface (BCI) Technologie präsentieren wir in dieser Dissertation neue Methoden zur Analyse makroskopisch gemessener Hirnsignale. Der Fokus liegt hierbei auf Methoden zur verbesserten Merkmalsextraktion, der Detektion mentaler Zustände und der Analyse der Variabilität von Reizantworten. Bedingte ereigniskorrelierte (De-)Synchronization: Die durch ein Ereignis induzierte Leistungsschwankung in einem Frequenzband wird konventionell als ERD bezeichnet und als relative Veränderung gegenüber der mittleren Grundaktivität gemessen. Wir erweitern den ERD-Begriff in Bezug auf eine verallgemeinerte Referenz. Dafür kontrastieren wir den zeitlichen Verlauf ereigniskorrelierter Aktivität mit dem gemessener single trials ohne spezifische Reizverarbeitung. Aus diesem verallgemeinerten Ansatz leiten wir eine Methode zur Bestimmung der Abhängigkeit der ERD-Antwort von initialen kortikalen Zuständen ab.Vergleichende Untersuchungen auf künstlichen und realen Daten validieren diesen Ansatz. Räumlich-spektrale Filter: Der Common-Spatial-Pattern Algorithmus (CSP) bestimmt für multivariate breitbandige Signale diskriminative räumliche Filter. Wir erweitern den klassischen Ansatz, so dass zusätzlich eine Optimierung einfacher Frequenzfilter erfolgt. Dies ermöglicht eine Adaptation an das individuelle EEG-Frequenzspektrums und somit eine verbesserte Merkmalsextraktion. Ein empirischer Vergleich mit dem klassischen CSP Algorithmus belegt die Vorteile unseres Verfahrens im Kontext der Klassifikation vorgestellter unilateraler Handbewegungen. Extraktion ereigniskorrelierter Potenziale (EKP): Independent component analysis (ICA) ist ein Werkzeug der statistischen Datenanalyse und Signalverarbeitung, welches multivariate Signale linear in ihre Quellkomponenten zerlegen kann. Wir präsentieren eine ICA Methode zur Extraktion von single trial EKP, welche unter Ausnutzung der Phasengebundenheit des EKP verbesserte räumliche Filter bestimmt. Simulationen mit künstlichen und echten Daten validieren diesen Ansatz in Bezug auf ein verbessertes SNR der extrahierten EKP. Zeitlich adaptive Merkmalskombination: Lateralisierte ERD des mu-Rhythmus und bewegungskorrelierte Potenziale sind die gebräuchlichsten diskriminativen Merkmale zur Klassifikation vorgestellter Handbewegungen. Wir präsentieren eine Methode diese zeitlich unterschiedlich ausgeprägten Merkmale für die Echtzeit-Klassifikation zu verwenden. Hierzu trainieren wir zunächst separat zu jedem Zeitpunkt einfache Klassifikatoren für jedes Merkmal und kombinieren diese anschließend adaptive in einem strikt kausalen, probabilistischen Ansatz. Die Leistungsfähigkeit dieses Algorithmus wurde durch seine erfolgreiche Anwendung in den BCI-Wettbewerbe 2003 und 2005 zur Klassifikation vorgestellter unilateraler Handbewegungen nachgewiesen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-12-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1631</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17059</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-17059</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1631/original_lemm_steven.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1631/lemm_steven.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
