<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:35Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1563">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1563</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:004</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Bayesian Learning and Regularization for Unsupervised Image Restoration and Segmentation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Bayessches Lernen und Regularisierung für unüberwachte Bildrestaurierung und Segmentierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zheng, Hongwei</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:004</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The challenge of blind image restoration is to uniquely define the restored signals from only the observed images and without any other information. It gives opportunities not only for valuable contributions in the theoretical statistics and optimization butie H also for the practical demands in image processing and computer vision. The main contribution of this thesis is in the fields of image deblurring, denoising, image reconstruction and segmentation in low level vision. The first part of this thesis is dedicated to the systematic integration of statistical model selection, Bayesian learning and regularization theory in a strictly convex optimization functional. The proposed approach is in a double regularized Bayesian estimation framework for parametric blur identification and image deconvolution. A good initial point spread function (PSF) blur kernel is estimated for convex regularization. During the iterative double regularization, the estimated PSF is prior knowledge for the next iterative estimation of the image, and vice visa. In this context, we also introduce several new ideas that improve the quality of blur identification with respect to other sources of image degradation. The second part of this thesis is devoted to improving the fidelity and quality of restored images, especially in the context of image denoising and deblurring. It is in this part that we introduce and extend several linear growth functionals to the space of functions of bounded variation (BV) for image processing. Based on these functionals, a data-driven variational image restoration functional in a Bayesian learning framework has been designed and implemented in the BV space. The performance is controlled via numeric approximation in terms of hyperbolic conservation laws, self-adjusting diffusion operators, adaptive adjustment of regularization parameters and optimal stopping time of process. The approach does not only outperform most approaches in the literature, but also allows to achieve high-fidelity and human perceptual image deblurring, denoising and image reconstruction. The third part of this thesis considers a more general blur problem in the real world, i.e., nonuniform blurred (e.g., partially-blurred) images including stationary and nonstationary blur kernels. There are numerous existing segmentation approaches that do not achieve satisfactory results for the identification and segmentation of blurred regions or objects. Inspired by spectral graph theory and their underlying connections with regularization theory, we develop a regularized spectral clustering approach on discrete graph spaces that achieves good performance. Also, the blur kernel can be identified in high-accuracy in a tractable variational Bayesian learning framework. The generalized parametric PSF prior and natural image statistics based image prior distribution are used for blur kernel estimation. As a consequence, nonuniform blur degraded images can be optimally restored without degrading unblurred regions and objects. In order to validate the proposed approaches, we demonstrate good experimental performance in a number of contexts. The results show that the proposed algorithms are robust and efficient in that they can handle images that are formed in various environments with different types of blur and noise. Furthermore, because of the flexibility of these methods, they can be easily applied to solve a number of other problems in image processing and computer vision.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Herausforderung bei der blinden Bildrestauration ist, aus einem beobachteten Bild das ursprüngliche Signal eindeutig wieder herzustellen, ohne Nutzung einer zusätzlichen Informationsquelle. Die Schwierigkeit liegt vor allem bei den notwendigen Statistiken und Optimierungen und der praktische Nutzen in Anwendungen in Bildanalyse und Bildverarbeitung. Diese Arbeit leistet drei wichtige Beiträge zur blinden Bildrestauration und Segmentierung, die im Folgenden aufgeführt sind. Der erste Teil dieser Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit der systematischen Integration von statistischer Modellselektion, Bayesschem Lernen und Regularisierungstheorie in streng konvexen Optimierungsfunktionalen. Der vorgeschlagene Ansatz der Bayesschen Schätzung basiert auf Doppelregularisierung. Er integriert globale nicht-parametrische Modellselektion, lokal parametrische Unschärfekernoptimierung für parametrische Unschärfeidentifikation und Dekonvolution. Ein guter initialer Unschärfekern wird durch eine konvexe Regularisierung geschätzt. Während der iterativen Doppelregulierung wird die geschätzte Pointspread-Funktion als Vorwissen für die nachfolgende iterative Schätzung des Bildes und umgekehrt verwendet. An dieser Stelle werden auch einige neue Ideen vorgestellt, welche die Qualität der Unschärfeerkennung in Bezug auf unterschiedliches Rauschen in den einzelnen Bildern oder in großen Videodateien verbessern. Der zweite Teil dieser Arbeit widmet sich der Verbesserung der Wiedergabetreue und Qualität von wiederhergestellten Bilder, speziell in entrauschten Bildern. Hierbei werden verschiedene lineare Wachstumsfunktionale zur Bildverarbeitung genauer behandelt und auf den Raum von Funktionen mit beschränkter Variation angewendet. Basierend auf diesen Funktionalen wird eine Bayessche Schätzung zur datengetriebenen Bildrekonstruktion durch Variationsrechnung entwickelt und implementiert. Die Performanz wird über die numerische Approximation von hyperbolischen Erhaltungssätzen, selbstregelnde Diffusionsoperatoren, adaptive Anpassung von Regularisierungsparametern und optimale Stoppzeiten des Prozesses kontrolliert. Dieser Ansatz übertrifft nicht nur die meisten bisher bekannten Ansätze, sondern erlaubt auch eine hochpräzise und nach menschlichen Kriterien exakte Bildwiederherstellung. Der dritte Teil dieser Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit dem allgemeineren Unschärfeproblem unter realen Bedingungen, beispielsweise für nur teilweis unscharfe Bilder einschließlich stationärer und nicht-stationärer Unschärfekerne. Eine Vielzahl vorhandener Segmentierungsverfahren erfüllt die Aufgabe der Identifikation und Segmentierung von unscharfen Regionen nicht zufriedenstellend. In Anlehnung an spektrale Bildsegmentierungskonzepte durch Clusteranalyse und deren zugrunde liegende Verbindung zur Regularisierungstheorie, wurde ein regularisierter spektraler Clusteringansatz auf diskreten Graphenräumen entwickelt, der gute Ergebnisse erzielt. Infolgedessen können die identifizierten und segmentierten unscharfen Regionen in einem auf Variationsrechnung basierendem Bayesschen Lernframework mit einem Prior aus natürlichen Bildstatistiken wiederhergestellt werden. Das üblicherweise nicht berechenbare inverse Lernproblem wird durch die variationale Bayessche Lernmethode berechenbar. Nicht-uniforme unscharfe Bilder können optimal rekonstruiert werden, ohne scharfe Regionen und Objekte zu zerstören. Um den vorgeschlagenen Ansatz zu validieren, wurde die Leistungtähigkeit an unterschiedlichen Bildern demonstriert. Die Resultate zeigen, dass die vorgeschlagenen Algorithmen robust und leistungsfähig gegenüber Bildern sind, die in verschiedenen Umgebungen, mit unterschiedlichen Arten von Unschärfe und Rauschen, erzeugt wurden. Außerdem können diese Methoden auf Grund ihrer Flexibilität leicht angewendet werden, um verschiedene Probleme in der Bildverarbeitung und Bildanalyse zu lösen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-07-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1563</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16236</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16236</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1563/original_zheng_hongwei.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1563/zheng_hongwei.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
