<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:20Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2831">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2831</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:004</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">User Facilitated Real-Time Inter-Operator Resource Sharing</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Benutzer Erm√∂glichte Echtzeit Inter-Betreiber Lastverteilung </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Toker, Ahmet Cihat</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:004</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">To benefit from the quickly expanding data traffic volume, the operators must make sure that the increase in traffic does not reduce the Quality of Service (QoS) offered to the users. QoS is expressed in concrete and objective technical parameters such as delay and loss rates. A newer concept, Quality of Experience (QoE) extends QoS with the subjective valuation of the user, how satisfying the service consumption over a certain network is. As the number of users in a network grows, it gets harder to satisfy the requirements of the users. One option is to combine different radio access technologies (RAT). A well-known example is the combination of WLAN Hotspot networks deployed by the network operators with the cellular networks. When one of these networks is congested, a part of the traffic destined for this network can be transferred to the alternative network. Our primary observation that lead to this work was that the limitation that the integrated networks should belong to the same operator is not theoretical or technical. The algorithms in the literature require exchange of operation information among the different radio access networks (RAN) that are managed jointly. These information are number of current users, or the congestion level in the network. This is possible if the RANs belong to the same operator. However two operators would be unwilling to share such information due to their competently status. And it is this situation that has lead to CRRM to be applied to RANs belonging to the same operator. If it were possible for operators to obtain this information indirectly over a neutral path, it would also be possible to extend the gains of CRRM to multi operator scenarios. We propose an alternative method, in which an operator can estimate the load in the RAN of another operator. This alternative method involves the cooperation of the end users. We postulate, that the users are willing to share their subjective evaluations of different networks they have access to in an open database. Naturally, we require that the storage and access to this database is anonymous and secure. If there is such a database, which stores how satisfied users are from a RAN for a specific service, we demonstrate why it is to the benefit of the users, that the operators also can query this database. When the operators have access to such a database, they can also estimate the congestion status in the foreign RANs that are co-located with their own RANs. With this estimate, they can decide when it makes sense to transfer some part of their traffic to foreign RANs in times of congestion. Our proposal is called therefore ‚Ä?User Facilitated Real-Time Inter-Operator Resource Sharing‚Ä?. For each operator in our proposal there is a single NOC-Agent, which runs in the centrally located at the Network Operations Control center(NOC). The NOC-Agent has connections to the RAN-Agents running on each and every RAN belonging to the operator. If in a particular area, a RAN goes into congestion, the NOC-Agent controlling the congested RAN obtains the details from the RAN-Agent, and contacts another NOCAgent, belonging to another operator and having an under-utilized RAN in the vicinity of the congested RAN. In Step 1, the NOC-Agents execute a negotiation protocol to agree on a percentage of the traffic that must be transferred from the congested RAN to the normal RAN. In Step 2, NOC-Agents compute a control policy for their RAN-Agents, using the agreed transfer probability and information that they obtain about the peer RANs from the open database. These policies, which are in the form of finite state controllers are sent along with the transfer rates to the RAN-Agents in Step 3. With the sharing parameters available RAN-Agents, these begin querying the QoE database to track the congestion status on their peer operators in Step 4. We assume the RAN Agents will execute these observations in time scales of minutes. Using the control policies, the RAN-Agents decide on stopping or continuing the resource sharing, depending on the observations they make on the QoE Database. Resource sharing is stopped (i) when the overloaded operator becomes normal again, or (ii) the donating operator suddenly becomes overload. These are steps 5 and 6 in the workflow. In this thesis a Processor Sharing based Queueing Network is developed to analyze the traffic exchange, and formulate optimum transfer rates. A mechanism design approach is taken to develop an incentive compatiable negotiation protocol to agree on the optimum rate. The RAN controller algorithms are developed based on POMDP abstraction. Finally the approach is validated on a testbed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Um Kapital aus der rasch zunehmenden Datenverkehrlast schlagen zu k√∂nnen, m√ºssen die Operatoren daf√ºr sorgen, dass dieser Anstieg die Qualit√§t der Dienste nicht st√∂rt, die die Benutzer empfinden. Ein neuer Begriff namens ‚Ä?Quality of Experience (QoE) ‚Ä? -Qualit√§t des Diensterlebnis- bezeichnet die subjektive Beurteilung der Benutzer, wie befriedigend die Ablieferung eines Datendienstes √ºber ein bestimmtes Operator-Netzwerk ist. Je mehr Benutzer es in einem Netzwerk gibt, desto schwieriger wird es, die Bed√ºrfnisse der Benutzer zu erf√ºllen. Eine Option dieses Problem anzugehen ist die Kombination der verschiedenen Radiozugangstechnologien. Ein sehr bekanntes Beispiel daf√ºr ist die Integration von WirelessLAN Hotspots, die Operatoren in dicht bev√∂lkerten Orten einsetzen, mit den gew√∂hnlichen Mobilfunknetzwerken. Wenn eins von dieser Netzwerke zu berlastet ist, kann ein Teil des Datenverkehrs auf das andere Netzwerk umgeleitet werden. Unsere elementare Beobachtung war, dass die Einschr√§nkung des gemeinsamen Managements der Radioressourcen (CRRM) auf Netzwerken, die alle zu einem einzigen Operator geh√∂ren, nicht technisch oder theoretisch ist. Die in der Literatur zu findenden Algorithmen machen es n√∂tig, dass die zwei Netzwerke, die Ressourcen austauschen wollen, auch Operationsdaten wie die aktuelle Last oder Benutzeranzahl austauschen. Diese Anforderung stellt keine Hindernisse dar, wenn diese zwei Netzwerke einem Operator geh√∂ren. Aber ein Operator w√§re, vermutlich aus kompetetiven Gr√ºnden nicht bereit, solche Daten einem anderen Operator zu √ºbergeben. Aber, wenn es m√∂glich w√§re,diese Informationen durch einen anderen neutralen Weg indirekt zu erfahren, w√§re es auch m√∂glich, die Gewinne der CRRM zu den Szenarien zu erweitern, in denen die kooperierenden Netzwerke verschiedenen Operatoren geh√∂ren. Diese alternative Methode, durch die ein Operator die Datenverkehrlast in einem anderen Operator absch√§tzen kann, involviert das Zusammenspiel der Benutzer. Wir postulieren, dass die Benutzer bereit sind, ihre Performanzmerkmale und Subjektive QoE-Auswertungen in einer verteilten Datenbank zu speichern. Unser Vorschlag hei√üt ‚ÄúBenutzer erm√∂glichte Echtzeit Inter-Operator Ressource Mitbenutzung‚Ä?. Der Ablauf von Interaktionen ist wie folgt. Jeder Operator hat einen Software Agent, der sich im zentralen Netzwerk Operation Zentrum (NOC) befindet. Dieser NOC-Agent hat eine Dauerverbindung zu allen Radiozugansnetze (RAN) des Operators.. Auf jeder Basisstation oder drahtlosen Zugangspunkt befinden sich weiter Software Agenten, die RAN-Agenten. NOC-Agent ist daf√ºr zust√§ndig, die mittelfristige Belastung in jedem RAN zu betrachten. Mittelfristig bedeutet f√ºr unseren Vorschlag Zeitintervalle im Stundenbereich. Wenn der NOC-Agent feststellt, dass in einem RAN der Belastung so hoch wird, dass die QoE der Benutzer gef√§hrdet sind, initiiert es ein Negotiationsverfahren mit einemanderen NOC-Agent von einem anderen Operator. Dieser Operator muss eine RAN in der N√§he des √ºberlasteteten RANs haben, damit eine Ressourcemitbenutzung stattfinden kann. Wenn das Negotiationsverfahren erfolgreich abgelaufen ist, kalkuliert jeder NOC-Agent einen Controller-Algorithmus f√ºr seinen RAN-Agent. Diese Algorithmen werden basierend auf der aktuellen Datenverkehrlast der beiden RANs berechnet. Die RAN-Agenten machen periodische Anfragen bei der von den Benutzern ausgef√ºllten Datenbank, um die kurzfristige Belastung in dem anderen RAN abzusch√§tzen. Da diese Absch√§tzung immer einen Fehleranteil hat, muss der RAN Agent eine Entscheidung mit unvollst√§ndigen Informationen treffen. F√ºr dieses Zweck benutzt der RAN-Agent den von NOC-Agent berechneten Algorithmus. RAN-Agent in den √ºberlastete RAN muss entscheiden, wann das Weiterleiten vom Datenverkehr abgebrochen werden soll. Das weiterleiten muss eingestellt werden, wenn das andere RAN,das extra Datentraffic akzeptiert, auch √ºberlastet ist. Auf der anderen Seite muss derRAN-Agent, der den datenverkehr akzeptiert, sicherstellen, dass der zuztzliche Datenverkehrnur dann angenommen wird, wenn das benachbarte RAN tatschlich berlastetist. Das akzeptieren von zus√§tzlichem Datentverkehr von einem nicht √ºberlasteten RANw√§re aus kompetitiven Gr√ºnden falsch. In dieser dissertation wird eine vollst√§ndige L√∂sung f√ºur den obengenannten Ansatz pr√§sentiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-03-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2831</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30002</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-30002</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2831/toker_ahmet.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
