<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:45:38Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:328">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:328</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:004</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Sales advisory system : a case study in applying knowledge representation systems</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Verkaufsberatungssystem : eine Fallstudie zur Anwendung als Wissensrepräsentationssystem</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Thakar, Sunil</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:004</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The presented case study establishes the relationship between the principles of knowledge representation and reasoning systems and their embodiment in working application systems. The results of the conducted study fall under two categories: one which receive everlasting scientific interest (knowledge acquisition, knowledge representation and reasoning methods, validation and man-machine interactions etc.) and one which are supposed to fulfill the business challenge (application related subjects typically include maintenance, reconfiguration, integration with legacy systems and new applications such as e-commerce) posed to them. The fact that the sales advisory domain is so highly knowledge intensive forced us to concentrate on the representation and reasoning aspects of it's application irrespective of mode/model we choose to support this process with a computer system. Further, in order to use knowledge representation and reasoning systems in real-world knowledge-intensive applications, we have tried to bridge the gap between theory and practice. A logic-oriented representation system is presented which allows the representation of the terminological knowledge of our application domain of automobile sales advisory within taxonomic reasoning. Based on our analysis, we found that the description logics BACK, FLEX and CLASSIC have sufficient expressive power to approximately represent the automobile sales advisory domain. Objects and constellations which typically describe the automobile sales advisory domain are represented in order to evaluate the method. Various complex descriptions of objects, aspects of classification and taxonomic reasoning in the sales advisory process are discussed. The investigation is illustrated by using examples from the real world and supported by various case studies in different but related fields. These examples -by virtue of their object-oriented characteristics- support an experimental mode of domain modeling and allow for a representation study on a larger scale. The resulting modeling experiences lead to an assessment of the knowledge representation and reasoning systems presented here. Further, it helped us answer: how the chosen KR&amp;R system can achieve the increased efficiency and improved quality in sales consultation. The onset of e-business, e-commerce and web-based selling are changing the practice of doing business and the expectations of the customer too. Customers not only expect instant answers to their questions, they demand instant responses to their inquiries as well. In other words they want efficient and good quality consultation as service wrapped around the product. Improving sales processes, pleasing the customers and making sales quicker simply demands more. The demand from the marketplace for customized products with a decreased quoting cycle time has lead to the introduction of configuration tools also known as interactive sales solutions or interactive sales systems or sales advisory/consultation systems. This sets the prevailing context in which the present case study was conducted.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Fallstudie stellt eine Beziehung zwischen Wissensrepräsentations- und Schlußfolgerungssystemen her und zeigt ihre Eignung für den Anwendungsbereich der Verkaufsberatung. Die Ergebnisse berücksichtigen sowohl wissenschaftliche Aspekte, wie effiziente Wissensakquisition und Wartbarkeit und Konsistenz der Wissensbasis, als auch anwendungsorientierte Aspekte, wie Flexibilität des Datenzugriffs, Stabilität und Wiederverwendbarkeit. Da die Domäne der Verkaufsberatung äußerst wissensintensiv ist, konzentriert sich die vorliegende Arbeit auf die Aspekte der Repräsentation und Schlußfolgerung unabhängig von der computerunterstützten Umsetzung des Beratungsprozesses. Es wird ein logik-orientiertes Wissensrepräsentationssystem dargestellt, in der das terminologische Wissen aus der Domäne der Verkaufsberatung in taxonomischen Strukturen repräsentierbar ist. Die Analyse von BACK, FLEX und CLASSIC hat ergeben, daß die Sprache aller drei Systeme eine ausreichende Mächtigkeit besitzt um das Domänwissen der Verkaufsberatung zu repräsentieren. Zur Bewertung dieses Vorgehens werden Objekte und Konstellationen repräsentiert die für Systeme zur Verkaufsberatung typisch sind. Beschreibung komplexer Objekte werden untersucht und unter Aspekten der Klassifikation und des taxonomischen Schlussfolgerns im Verkaufsberatungsprozess diskutiert. Die Ergebnisse der Untersuchung werden durch Beispiele aus verschiedenen verwandten Anwendungsgebieten belegt, die durch ihre objekt-basierten Charakteristika einen experimentellen Einsatz bei der Modellbildung unterstützen und damit eine Repräsentationsstudie in größerem Umfang ermöglichen; aus den Ergebnissen der Studie wiederum lassen sich Aussagen zur Ausdrucksstärke des vorgestellten Systems ableiten. E-business, e-commerce und web-basierter Verkauf verändern die Geschäftsprozesse und das Kaufverhalten der Kunden. Um diesen Bedürfnissen der Kunden gerecht zu werden müssen effiziente und qualitativ hochwertige Beratungsprozesse als Zusatzleistung angeboten werden. Die Nachfrage nach individuellen Produkten und möglichst kleiner werdender Angebotserstellungsphase führt zur Einführung computerunterstützte Konfigurations- und Beratungssystemen. Sie bieten einen neuen Kontext zur Umsetzung der Ergebnisse dieser Studie.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2001-04-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/328</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3233</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-3233</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/328/thakar_sunil.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
