<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:14Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3242">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3242</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:004</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">On the Impact of the Cellular Modem on the Security of Mobile Phones</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">On the Impact of the Cellular Modem on the Security of Mobile Phones</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mulliner, Collin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:004</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Cellular communication and especially mobile handsets are an essential part of our daily lives. Therefore, they need to be secure and work reliably. But mobile handsets and cellular networks are highly complex systems and securing them is a challenging task. Previously, most efforts concentrated on the handsets. These efforts only focused on the mobile phone operating system and applications in order to improve cellular system security. This thesis takes a new path and targets the cellular modem as the route to improve the security of mobile handsets and cellular networks. We target the modem since it is one of the essential parts of a mobile handset. It is the component that provides the radio link to the cellular network. This makes the modem a key element in the task to secure mobile phones. But cellular modems are proprietary and closed systems that cannot be easily analyzed in the full or even modified to improve security. Therefore, this thesis investigates the security of the cellular modem at its border to the mobile phone operating system. We suspect that the security of mobile handsets and cellular network strongly depends on the security of the modem interface. This is our hypothesis, which we seek to prove in this work. We solve this in three steps. In the first step, we analyze the interaction between the cellular modem and the other parts of a modern mobile phone. Based on the analysis we develop two novel vulnerability analysis methods. Using this methods we conduct vulnerability analysis of the Short Message Service implementations on various mobile phones. In the second step, we investigate the possible capabilities that malware has through unhindered access to the cellular modem. For this, we develop a cellular botnet where the bots utilize the modem for stealthy communication. In the third step, we use the results from the previous analysis steps to improve the security at the cellular modem interface. In our analysis step, we abused the cellular modem for vulnerability analysis.We discovered several security and reliability issues in the telephony softwares tack of common mobile phones. Using our cellular botnet implementation, we show how malware can abuse access to the cellular modem interface for various kinds of unwanted activities. In the final step, we show that through improving the security at the cellular modem interface the security of mobile handsets as well as the security of cellular networks can be increased. Throughout this thesis we show that the cellular modem has a significant impact on mobile phone security.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Mobile Kommunikation, Mobiltelefone und Smartphones sind ein wesentlicher Bestandteil unseres täglichen Lebens geworden. Daher ist es essentiell, dass diese sicher und zuverlässig funktionieren. Mobiltelefone und Mobilfunknetze sind hoch komplexe Systeme. Solche Systeme abzusichern ist eine anspruchsvolle Aufgabe. Vorangegangene Arbeiten haben sich meist auf die mobilen Endgeräte, im Speziellen auf die Betriebssysteme sowie Endanwendungen, konzentriert. Die vorliegende Doktorarbeit untersucht einen neuen Weg im Bereich Mobilfunksicherheit. Im Fokus steht das Modem als Schnittstelle zum Mobilfunknetz. Das Mobilfunkmodem ist die Komponente, welche die Funkverbindungzum Mobilfunknetz herstellt und ist nach unserer Auffassung eine der Schlüsselkomponenten bei der Untersuchung und Verbesserung der Mobilfunksicherheit. Mobilfunkmodems sind proprietär und können nur mit extrem hohem Aufwand untersucht werden. Für den Einbau zusätzlicher Sicherungsmaßnahmengilt dasselbe. Aus diesen Gründen analysiert diese Arbeit nicht das Innenleben eines Modems, sondern dessen Schnittstelle zum mobilen Betriebssystem. In dieser Arbeit untersuchen wir daher die folgende von uns aufgestellte These: Die Sicherheit mobiler Endgeräte sowie der Mobilfunknetze hängt direkt mit der Sicherheit der Modemschnittstelle zusammen. Diesen Zusammenhang legen wir anhand von drei Schritten dar. Im ersten Schritt führen wir eine Untersuchung der Modemschnittstelle durch. Basierend auf den Ergebnissen der Untersuchung führen wir mehrere Sicherheitsanalysen von Short-Message-Service- (SMS) Implementierungen von verschiedenen Telefontypen durch. Im zweiten Schritt untersuchen wir die Möglichkeiten, die sich Schadcode auf mobilen Endgeräten zu Nutze machen kann. Für diese Untersuchung entwickeln wir ein Proof-of-Concept-Botnetz, welches mittels des Modems verdeckt kommuniziert. Im dritten Schritt implementieren wir, basierend auf den Ergebnissen der vorangegangenen Schritte, einen Schutzmechanismus zur Absicherung des Modems gegen bösartige Zugriffe. Durch unsere Untersuchungen sind wir zu mehreren Ergebnissen gekommen. Die Software für den Empfang von SMS-Nachrichten beinhaltet oftmals (zum Teil kritische) Sicherheitsprobleme. Diese Sicherheitsprobleme haben auch Auswirkungen auf andere Komponenten der Endgeräte. Mit unserem mobilen Botnetz zeigen wir, welche Möglichkeiten Schadcode auf Mobiltelefonen grundsätzlich zur Verfügung stehen. Durch den von uns entwickelten Schutzmechanismus der Modemschnittstelle bestätigen wir unsere anfangs formulierte These. Die Absicherung der Modemschnittstelle verhindert die zuvor präsentierten Angriffe und zeigt hierdurch, dass die Modemschnittstelle einen entscheidenden Faktor der Mobilfunksicherheit darstellt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-02-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3242</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3242/mulliner_collin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
