<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:12Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3235">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3235</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">On the role of pigment-pigment and pigment-protein interaction in regulating excitation energy and electron transfer in photosynthesis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Über die Rolle der Wechselwirkungen zwischen Pigment-Pigment und Pigmentproteinen bei der Regulierung der Anregungsenergie und Elektronentransfer in der Photosynthese   </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nganou Assonkeng, Albert Collins</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The pathways of excitation energy transfer (EET) to photosynthetic reaction centres inside phycobiliprotein antenna system of Acaryochloris Marina (A. marina) were studied using time resolved absorption difference spectroscopy with a resolution time of 200 fs. The results revealed a new pathway of 14 ps inside the phycocyanin spectral band in addition to the previously known EET-equilibration pathway of all phycocyanins to allophycocyanin. This EET funnelling is faster than the previous kinetic found in phycobilisomes of 17 ps inside the phycocyanin (spectral range 600-630 nm) to allophycocyanin (640-650 nm). In addition, we present the result that excitonic coupling does not contribute to the EET inside the phycobiliprotein antenna system at room temperature. Anisotropy of the EET pathway was calculated to determine the contribution of excitonic coupling, which originated from the strong interaction between adjacent chromophores. This band is located between 624 nm to the final emitter 675 nm. In order to compare the results with those of the cyanobacterium containing phycobilisome and to address the functional role of the linker protein, further femtosecond flash induced transient absorption changes were monitored. This was done to obtain a time-resolved view of the excitation energy transfer in intact phycobilisomes of Thermosynechococcus vulcanus (T. vulcanus) having different linker proteins at room temperature. Ultrafast excitation energy transfer in phycobilisomes occurs along the phycocyanin rod shaped domain to the allophycocyanin core domain in two channels (i.e. 890 fs and 17 ps). The phycocyanin is assembly in the form of a rod of two PC hexamers separated by a distinct linker protein along the symmetry axis of the hexameric units, and an additional rod–core linker. In comparison to the absorbance of the phycobiliprotein antenna system of A. marina, the presence of the rod-core linker induces a 5 nm red shift on the rod spectrum. The kinetic component of 890 fs indicates that the presence of the linker proteins induces ultrafast EET inside the phycobilisome (PBS). Thus, we suggest that the PBP rod structure (with APC in the rod involving less pigment) of A. marina is not the reason of the ultrafast EET in comparison to the phycobilisomes. Furthermore, the absorbance of the phycocyanin rod (PC rod) sub-domain of phycobilisomes and PBP indicate that the high-energy sub-aggregate state of the PBP is likely to be influenced by different conformations. Further comparative study at low temperature by spectral hole burning (SHB) and fluorescence narrowing (FLN) revealed the existence of the inhomogeneous broadened distribution of local vibrational mode along the PBP antenna system of A. marina. In addition to the inhomogeneous broadened distribution of pure electronic frequencies in the spectra of the PBP antenna system, the presence of a blue shifted delocalized satellite hole along the rod is originated from different vibrations. The low amount of local vibrational frequencies in the PBS T. vulcanus leads to a high strength of pigment coupling which enhanced the ultrafast energy transfer. Thus, it is a coupling with the downhill energy transfer of the upper state towards a lower state. Additional information through FLN and SHB reveal the existence of new pigment absorbing at 635 nm in the PBP rod and 645 nm in the PBS as well as some similarity and difference on the terminal emitter spectral band. The similarity leads to an identification of two different pigments absorbing between 660 – 665 nm and 670 nm. The 660 – 665 nm pigment is an allophycocyanin (APC) pigments indentified by a 40 cm-1 energy gap between α84 and β84, while the difference between the first vibrational mode and the red shift of wing supports the suggestion of a different APC gene. Due to the wavelength of the latter, it might be the apcB of the LCM. A further difference leads to excitonic contribution on the all-spectral band of the PBS T. vulcanus instead of the 624 nm to the final emitter 675 nm in the PBP of it case. In addition to the excitation energy transfer in cyanobacteria, time resolved absorption changes in the light harvesting complex II of higher plants (LHC II) were monitored. Aggregation state size was controlled by specific ß-DM concentration. The equilibrium time in each aggregation state was complemented by findings from the literature. Some information sources are listed as follows: • The aggregation state was observed where dependence of the relative maximum of the absorption state in time domain. • No significant change in the excited states was observed Further femto-second transient absorption spectroscopy at room temperature (RT) was applied to investigate the charge transfer process. This was done by photo-exciting ligand chlorine dendrone (PaCD) in different concentrated solutions of oxidant horse heart cytochrome c (Hccox) at 620 nm. After the HccoxPaCD was photo-excited, a delayed-bleach recovery signal at 550 nm was observed. This was due to the charge transfer from the excited state of the donor ligand PaCD to the acceptor state within about 30 ps. In the longer wavelength region above 620 nm, an excited state absorption signal originating from the PaCD was observed while a flash induced transient absorption signal was also observed at 667 nm. This was due to the excitation energy transfer (EET) produced from the 620 nm excitation to the 667 nm. The latter was followed by a red shift bleaching at 667 nm. The detailed analysis of the red shift bleaching at 667 nm indicates the quenching of excess EET originating from the ligand excited state band.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wurden die komplementären Techniken der Grundzustands Absorptionsspektroskopie, Messungen zeitaufgelöster fs Absorptionsänderungen, Lochbrennspektroskopie und Fluoreszenz line Narrowing Spektroskopie angewendet, um Anregungsenergietransfer- (EET) prozesse in den Phycobiliprotein (PBP) Antennensystemen des Cyanobakteriums Acaryochloris marina im Verleich zu Thermosynechococcus vulcan7us zu untersuchen. Die Ergebnisse zeigten, dass in A.marina ein neuer Pfad des EET vom Phycocyanin (PC) zum Allophycocyanin (APC) mit einer charakteristischen zeitkonstante von 14 ps existiert. Ein weiterer Einblick in das System offenbarte, dass das Exziton unterhalb von 624 nm lokalisiert ist, während der Anistropie Faktor Delokalisationseffekte oberhalb von 625 nm zeigt. Es wurde gezeigt, dass ein rotverschobenes Pigment bei 635 nm, welches den energetisch niedrigsten Zustand im PC darstellt, stark mit dem β84 Pigment im PC gekoppelt ist, um den effizienten Energietransfer zum APC sicherzustellen. Das APC transportiert seine Anregungsenergie in den höchsten Zustand in der Linkermembran bei 657 – 665 nm. Es wurde gezeigt, dass das Linkerprotein ein APC Gen an der Bindungsstelle des APC_E aufweist und dieses ist stark gekoppelt an APC im letzten Heterohexamer. Der untere Zustand der Linkermembran ist vornehmlich ein APC_B gemäß seiner Spektralposition. Eine Studie der vibronischen zustände des PBP wird für spätere Vergleiche mit theoretischen Modellen gezeigt. In Thermosynechococcus vulcanus wurde ein ultrasschneller Energietransfer vom rod PC zum Kern APC gefunden, der mit einer Zeitkonstante von ~ 900 fs abläuft. Dieser ultraschnelle EET wird durch die Anwesenheit des Linkerproteins im rod PC und durch weitere Pigmente wie die beiden rotverschobenen Pigmente bei 635 nm und 645 nm induziert. Der Anteil dieser Arbeit besteht darin, dass gezeigt wurde, dass das beste Modell für das Phycobilisom (PBS) dasjenige von Adir 2008 ist. Um dieses Modell zu bestätigen zeigen wir, dass gegenüberstehende rod PCs parallel angeordnet sind, was zur exzitonischen Kopplung der β155 Pigmente führt. Die starke Kopplung zwischen den Piugmenten entlang des rod PCs und des Kern APCs zeigt die steuernde Rolle des 645 nm Pigments und des 660 nm Pigments. Der niedrigste Zustand des PC wird bei 645 nm gefunden. Ein klares Ende der Wechselwirkung zwischen dem höchsten Zustand und dem niedrigeren Zustand der Linker Kern Membran zeigt sich mit typischen Zeitkonstanten von 450 fs und 13 ps, was einen schnelleren Pfad zum RC des PS II zeigt, als vorher angenommen wurde. In weiteren Untersuchungen wurde der EET im großen Lichtsammelkomplex LHC II höherer Pflanzen in Abhängigkeit vom Aggregationszustand untersucht, indem Beta-DM benutzt wurde. Es wurde gefunden, dass die schwache Aggregation der Trimerbildung im LHC II benötigt wird, um effizienten EET und Photoprotektion zu garantieren. Die exakte Psoition des löschenden Zentrums bleibt eine offene Frage. Die Studie wurde abgeschlossen durch die Analyse eines künstlichen photosynthetischen Systems, das aus der elektrostatischen Assemblierung von Chlorin dendrone (PaCD) mit dem Cytochrom C des Pferdeherzens (HCC) besteht. Es wurde gezeigt, dass das Design dieses künstlichen photosynthetischen Systems ein guter Kandidat für einen effizienten Energieztransfer in 30 ps und gleichzeitige Photoprotektion ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-02-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3235</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33956</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-33956</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3235/nganouassonkeng_albert.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
