<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:18Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2374">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2374</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Raman studies on individual nanotubes and nanotube ensembles - vibrational properties and scattering efficiencies </dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ramanstudien an einzelnen Nanoröhren und Nanoröhrenensemble - Schwingungseigenschaften und Streueffizienzen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Telg, Hagen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this work we present Raman scattering experiments on ensembles of nanotubes in solution and individual suspended nanotubes. In the first part of this work we study the maximum Raman intensities for a large number of (n1, n2) including semiconducting and metallic nanotubes. We show that the strong differences between the RBM Raman intensities of the first and second optical transition of semiconducting nanotubes can be related to a larger broadening parameter of the second transition compared to the first transition. This is in accordance with a shorter live times of carriers excited into the second optical transition compared to carriers in the first transition. Also intensity differences between metallic and semiconducting nanotubes can be related to a stronger broadening of metallic transitions rather than differences in the electron-phonon coupling. On the other hand intensity variations as a function of nanotube family, chiral angle and diameter are related to variations in the Raman matrix elements, primarily the electron-phonon coupling. The dependence of the RBM intensity on the family and the chiral angle can be correlated to the position of the electronic transition with respect to the K point. We find a small maximum of the electron-phonon coupling for tubes with the transition close to K-Gamma symmetry line and a large maximum for tubes with the transition close to the K-M direction. Close to K-K line we find a minimum, where the electron-phonon coupling is close to zero. Due to the trigonal warping of the graphene bandstructure the minimum electron-phonon coupling is obtained for nanotubes with a chiral angle of ≈ 20° and with a family index of either ν = +1 or ν = −1 depending on the electronic transition. The dependence of the RBM Raman intensity on the nanotube diameter is related to three effects. First, with increasing diameter the broadening of the electronic transitions decreases which causes the intensity to rise. Second, with increasing diameter the RBM frequency decreases, which reduces the distance between incoming and outgoing resonance. This again causes the intensity to rise with diameter. The observed overall decrease of the intensities with diameter can therefore only be explained by a decrease of the electron phonon coupling. In the second part of this work we study the lineshape of the high-energy mode. From experiments on a tiny bundle of one metallic and one semiconducting nanotube we conclude that the broad and downshifted G− peak is related to the LO phonon in metallic nanotubes. We show that the observation of a sharp peak at 1590 cm−1 indicates the presence of an additional semiconducting nanotube. The peak at 1590 cm−1 in semiconducting nanotubes is again related to the LO phonon. The energy of the LO phonon in metallic nanotubes is broadened and downshifted in comparison to the LO in semiconducting nanotubes due to the effect of a Kohn anomaly. The fact that we see the downshifted and broadened G− peak of metallic nanotubes in the tiny bundle as well as in the nanotube separated in solution clarifies that this peak is an intrinsic feature of metallic carbon nanotubes. On nanotube ensembles dispersed in solution we observe several features in addition to the major G− and G+ features. We can assign a serious of peaks on the low energy side of the HEM to particular (n1, n2) or groups of nanotubes. This leads to a diameter dependence of this feature. By comparison to theoretical prediction we assign this peak to the TO phonon in semiconducting nanotubes. In order to strengthen this assignment the measurements should be extended to higher and lower excitation energies. Furthermore we find peaks on the high energy side of the HEM which we tentatively assign to the second-order Raman modes of the infrared-active phonon. To clarify this assignment a detailed study of this feature and the intermediate frequency modes is necessary. The frequency of the first-order phonon falls into this region and might be visible due to imperfections in the nanotubes.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorgelegte Dissertationsschrift befasst sich mit den optischen Eigenschaften von Kohlenstoffnanoröhren. Kohlenstoffnanoröhren (KNR) sind Nanometer dicke hohle Zylinder, deren Wände aus Kohlenstoffatomen aufgebaut sind. Das große Interesse an KNRs beruht unter anderem auf den vielversprechenden elektronischen Eigenschaften wie etwa dem ballistischem Transport und einer großen Anzahl möglicher Bandlücken. Die Charakterisierung von KNRs geschieht meist mithilfe der Raman-Spektroskopie. So lässt sich anhand der radialen Atmungsmode (RAM) die atomare Struktur – gegeben durch die chiralen Indices (n1, n2) – der in einer Probe vorhanden Röhren bestimmen. Anhand der hochenergetischen Moden lässt sich überprüfen, ob eine Probe metallische Röhren enthält. Die Arbeit besteht aus zwei Teilen. Im ersten Teil wird die maximale Raman-Intensität der RAM für unterschiedliche (n1, n2) untersucht. Diese Intensitäten lassen Rückschlüsse auf die Elektron-Phonon-Kopplung zu, welche wiederum relevant für das Verständnis von Transporteigenschaften ist. Außerdem verspricht man sich, die Häufigkeiten der einzelnen (n1, n2) in einer Probe mithilfe der RAM-Intensitäten bestimmen zu können. Wir beobachten große Unterschiede zwischen den Raman-Intensitäten der verschiedenen (n1, n2), welche wir entweder auf Unterschiede der natürlichen Linienbreiten oder auf Variationen der Elektron-Phonon-Kopplung zurückführen können. Der zweite Teil der Arbeit behandelt die Form und den Ursprung der Moden im hochenergetischen Bereich des Raman-Spektrums von KNRs. Wie oben erwähnt, kann dieser Bereich des Spektrums zum Nachweis von metallischen Röhren in einer Probe benutzt werden. Entspricht die Anregungsenergie der Resonanzenergie einer metallischen Röhre, so verschiebt und verbreitert sich der sogenannte G− Peak. Hierzu gibt es zwei Theorien, welche das Phänomen auf sehr unterschiedliche physikalische Prozesse zurückführen. Gewöhnliche Nanoröhrenproben enthalten viele verschieden Röhrensorten, metallische sowie halbleitende, sodass sich die Raman-Signale überlagern und daher keine der genannten Theorien zu favorisieren ist. In den letzten Jahren sind zunehmend Experimente an scheinbar einzelnen Röhren durchgeführt worden, deren Interpretationen sich je nach zurate gezogener Theorie widersprachen. In dieser Arbeit werden Raman-Experimente an einem winzigen Bündel von einer metallischen und einer halbleitenden Nanoröhre präsentiert. Wir zeigen, dass der verbreiterte und verschobene Peak in metallischen Röhren dem durch eine sehr starke Elektron- Phonon-Kopplung verschobenen und verbreitert LO Phonon zuzuordnen ist. Die Beobachtung eines weiteren Peaks bei der unveränderten Frequenz des LO Phonons ist folglich nur durch die Anwesenheit einer halbleitenden Röhre zu erklären. Außerdem bestätigen unsere Messungen, dass der verschobene und verbreiterte Peak ein intrinsisches Merkmal von metallischen KNRs ist, er resultiert also nicht aus der Bündelung von Röhren. Des Weiteren können wir durch Raman-Experimente an Proben, die alle denkbaren (n1, n2) enthalten, die Durchmesserabhängigkeit der TO Phononen in halbleitenden Röhren zu kleineren Röhrendurchmessern erweitern.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-12-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/x-gzip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-24740</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-24740</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2374/original_telg_hagen_sources.tar.gz</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2374/telg_hagen.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-SA: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, Weitergabe zu gleichen Bedingungen</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
