<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2963">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2963</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Structural, electronic and transport properties of amorphous/crystalline silicon heterojunctions</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Strukturelle, elektronische und Transport-Eigenschaften von amorph-/kristallinen Silizium-Heterostrukturen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schulze, Tim Ferdinand</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Solar cells based on heterojunctions between hydrogenated amorphous (a-Si:H) and crystalline silicon (c-Si) are an active field of research. a-Si:H/c-Si heterojunction solar cells combine the high efficiency potential of wafer-based photovoltaics (PV) with simple and low-temperature processing using thin-film deposition with PECVD. The company Sanyo has reached a conversion efficiency of 23 % with this concept, which is considerably more than delivered by typical 'classical' c-Si based homo-junction solar cells (&lt; 19 %), with a potentially simplified processing. Also from a scientific point of view, a-Si:H/c-Si heterojunctions are of great interest, as fundamental properties of the heterojunction remain under dispute. This e.g. concerns the lineup of the electronic bands, the charge carrier transport across the heterojunction, or the outstandingly effective passivation of c-Si surface defects by a-Si:H. The present dissertation is concerned with the physical aspects of the a-Si:H/c-Si heterojunction in the context of PV research. In a first step, the technological development which took place in the framework of the thesis is summarized. Its main constituent was the development and implementation of ultrathin (10 nm) undoped a-Si:H [(i)a-Si:H] layers to improve the passivation of the c-Si surface with the goal of increasing the open-circuit voltage of the solar cell. It is shown that the effect of (i)a-Si:H interlayers depends on the c-Si substrate doping type, and that challenges exist particularly on the technologically more relevant (n)c-Si substrate. A precise optimization of (i)a-Si:H thickness and the doping level of the following a-Si:H top layers is required to realize an efficiency gain in the solar cell. In this chapter, the key scientific questions to be tackled in the main part of the thesis are brought up by the technological development. In the next chapter, the charge carrier transport through a-Si:H/c-Si heterojunctions is investigated making use of current-voltage (I/V) characteristics taken at different temperatures. The dominant transport mechanisms in a-Si:H/c-Si heterojunctions are identified, and the relevance for solar cell operation is discussed. It is found that in the bias regime relevant for solar cell operation, the theoretical framework for the description of carrier transport in classical c-Si solar cells applies as well, which enables to use I/V curves for a simple characterization of a-Si:H/c-Si structures. The next chapter deals with the microscopic characterization of ultrathin a-Si:H layers. Employing infrared spectroscopy, spectroscopic ellipsometry, photoelectron spectroscopy and secondary ion mass spectroscopy, the structural, electronic and optical properties of (i)a-Si:H are analyzed. It is found that ultrathin a-Si:H essentially behaves like layers of 10...100 times the thickness. This represents the basis for the application of established concepts for the physical description of a-Si:H in the following chapters. Further, the impact of the PECVD deposition parameters on the properties of the resulting layers is explored and discussed. Next, the lineup of the electronic bands at the heterojunction is elucidated in device-relevant a-Si:H/c-Si heterostructures. To this end, a novel method combining photoelectron spectroscopy and surface photovoltage measurements is developed and employed. It is found that upon widening the a-Si:H optical band gap by controlling its hydrogen content, predominantly the valence band offset is increasing while the conduction band offset stays constant. This result is consistent with established theories on the a-Si:H electronic structure, but was not experimentally observed to date to the author's knowledge. The significance of the valence band offset for solar cell operation and possible pathways for tailoring the electronic properties of the heterojunction are discussed. In the last chapter, the microscopic properties of the a-Si:H layers are linked with the resulting passivation of c-Si surface states, which limit the obtainable open-circuit-voltage in a heterojunction solar cell. It is found that in case of ideal processing, the heterojunction does not possess particular properties but can be described by the a-Si:H bulk properties projected onto the actual heterojunction. Based on this conclusion it is possible to comprehend the complex phenomenology of c-Si surface passivation by a-Si:H from the properties of the amorphous silicon passivation layer. The principal limit of c-Si surface passivation follows naturally, as does the explanation of passivation degradation effects from the metastability inherent to a-Si:H. The amorphous network has the propensity to adapt upon changes in externally controllable parameters like the Fermi energy, which was seldom taken into account so far when interpreting phenomena of the a-Si:H/c-Si heterojunction.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Solarzellen auf der Basis von Heterostrukturen aus hydrogeniertem amorphem (a-Si:H) und kristallinem Silizium (c-Si) sind ein aktuelles Forschungsfeld in der Photovoltaik (PV). Sie vereinen das hohe Wirkungsgrad-Potential von c-Si Wafern mit einfacher Prozessierung bei niedrigen Temperaturen durch die Gasphasendeposition von a-Si:H mittels PECVD. Die Firma Sanyo hat mit diesem Konzept einen Wandlungs-Wirkungsgrad von 23 % erreicht, der deutlich über dem aktueller 'klassischer' c-Si-Solarzellen liegt (&lt; 19 %), bei potentiell vereinfachter Herstellung. Auch wissenschaftlich ist das Feld von großem Interesse, da fundamentale Eigenschaften der Heterostruktur bislang unverstanden sind. Unter anderem betrifft dies die genaue Anordnung der elektronischen Bänder, den elektronischen Transport, und die höchst effektive Absättigung der c-Si-Oberflächendefekte ('Passivierung') durch a-Si:H. Die vorliegende Dissertation befasst sich mit den physikalischen Fragen zum amorph-kristallinen Silizium-Heteroübergang im Kontext der PV. Zunächst wird die technologische Weiterentwicklung der Heterosolarzellen, die im Rahmen der Dissertation stattfand, zusammengefasst. Diese bestand aus der Entwicklung und dem Einsatz sehr dünner (10 nm) undotierter a-Si:H Schichten [(i)a-Si:H], um die Passivierung des c-Si weiter zu verbessern und somit die offene-Klemmen-Spannung der Solarzelle zu vergrößern. Es zeigt sich, dass die Wirkung des (i)a-Si:H je nach Dotiertyp des c-Si-Substrats unterschiedlich ist, und vor allem auf dem (technologisch wichtigeren) n-dotierten c-Si-Substrat Herausforderungen bestehen. Eine genaue Einstellung der (i)a-Si:H Dicke und der Dotierung der weiteren a-Si:H-Schichten ist vonnöten, um das Verbesserungspotential in der Solarzelle umzusetzen. In diesem Kapitel werden aus der technologischen Optimierung heraus die wesentlichen physikalischen Fragen gesammelt, die im weiteren Verlauf der Arbeit als Leitlinie für die Grundlagen-Untersuchungen dienen. Im nächsten Kapitel wird der elektronische Transport durch a-Si:H/c-Si Heterostrukturen mit Hilfe von Strom-Spannungs-Kennlinien (I/V) bei verschiedenen Temperaturen untersucht. Die elektronischen Transportmechanismen in a-Si:H/c-Si Heterostrukturen werden identifiziert, und deren Bedeutung für die Funktion der Solarzelle diskutiert. Es zeigt sich, dass im für den Betrieb der Zelle relevanten Regime die Beschreibung von klassischen c-Si-Solarzellen angewandt werden kann, was eine einfache Charakterisierung von Zellstrukturen mittels I/V-Messungen ermöglicht. Das nächste Kapitel beschäftigt sich mit der mikroskopischen Charakterisierung von ultradünnen (i)a-Si:H-Schichten. Mit Hilfe von Infrarotspektroskopie, Spektralellipsometrie, Photoelektronenspektroskopie und Sekundärionen-Massenspektroskopie werden die strukturellen, elektronischen und optischen Eigenschaften des a-Si:H untersucht. In der Gesamtschau zeigt sich, dass auch ultradünne a-Si:H Schichten sich ähnlich wie 10…100-fach dickere Schichten verhalten. Dies ist die Grundlage für die Anwendbarkeit etablierter Konzepte der physikalischen Beschreibung von a-Si:H in den folgenden Kapiteln. Im Weiteren wird die Wirkung verschiedener Parameter der Herstellung der a-Si:H-Schichten auf ihre Eigenschaften untersucht und diskutiert. Im nächsten Kapitel wird die relative Anordnung der elektronischen Bänder in der a-Si:H/c-Si-Heterostruktur an Bauteil-relevanten Proben untersucht. Hierzu wird ein neuartiges Verfahren entwickelt, welches Photoelektronen-Spektroskopie und die Messung der Oberflächen-Photospannung kombiniert. Es zeigt sich, dass bei einer Aufweitung der a-Si:H-Bandlücke durch Kontrolle des Wasserstoff-Gehalts nur der Sprung im Valenzband variiert, während derselbe im Leitungsband konstant bleibt. Dieses Ergebnis ist konsistent mit etablierten Theorien, wurde jedoch noch nie experimentell nachgewiesen. Die Bedeutung des Valenzband-Sprungs für die Heterosolarzelle und die Möglichkeit dessen gezielter Kontrolle werden diskutiert. Im letzten Kapitel wird die Verbindung zwischen mikroskopischen Eigenschaften der a-Si:H-Schichten und der resultierenden Passivierung von c-Si-Oberflächendefekten gezogen, welche die realisierbare Spannung in Heterosolarzellen bestimmt. Es zeigt sich, dass im Falle einer idealen Prozessierung die Heterogrenzfläche keine ausgezeichneten Eigenschaften besitzt, sondern sich als Projektion des a-Si:H-Volumens auf die Hetero-Grenzfläche beschreiben lässt. Auf dieser Grundlage lässt sich die komplexe Phänomenologie der c-Si-Passivierung durch a-Si:H verstehen. Die Bestimmung der maximal möglichen Defekt-Absättigung folgt daraus ebenso wie die Erklärung von Degradationseffekten aus der inhärenten Metastabilität des amorphen Siliziums. Dessen Eigenschaften können sich als Reaktion auf externe Parameter wie z.B. die Fermi-Energie verändern, was bislang in der Analyse der a-Si:H/c-Si Heterostruktur nur selten berücksichtigt wurde.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-07-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2963</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2963/schulze_tim.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
