<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:14Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1956">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1956</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Many-particle theory of optical properties in low-dimensional nanostructures</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Vielteilchentheorie optischer Eigenschaften in niederdimensionalen Nanostrukturen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Malic, Ermin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work focuses on the theoretical investigation of optical properties of low-dimensional nanostructures, specifically single-walled carbon nanotubes (CNTs) and self-assembled InAs/GaAs quantum dots (QDs). The density-matrix formalism, an established technique for a quantum-mechanical description of many-particle systems,is applied to explain recent experimental results and to give insight into the underlying physics. CNTs are ideal model systems to study the physics of one-dimensional structures. Due to their unique electronic and optical properties, they also attract great technological interest. However, the problems of the characterization of specific CNTs and their low luminescence efficiency are still substantial challenges in current research. A microscopic calculation of the absorption coefficient and the Rayleigh scattering cross section is performed by a novel approach combining the density-matrix formalism with the tight-binding wave functions. The derived excitonic Bloch equations allow the study of CNTs of arbitrary chiral index. In agreement with experiment, the calculated spectra of metallic nanotubes show a double-peaked structure resulting from the trigonal warping effect. The intensity ratios of the four lowest-lying transitions in both absorption and Rayleigh spectra can be explained by the different behavior of the optical matrix elements along the high-symmetry lines K-Gamma and K-M. Also in agreement with experiment, the Rayleigh line shape is predicted to be asymmetric, with an enhanced cross section for lower photon energies arising from non-resonant contributions of the optical susceptibility. Furthermore, the Coulomb interaction is shown to be maximal when the momentum transfer is low. For intersubband processes with a perpendicular momentum transfer, the coupling strength is reduced to less than 5%. Due to their reduced dimensionality, CNTs have a strong Coulomb interaction that considerably changes their optical spectra. While the electron-electron interaction renormalizes the band gap, the electron-hole coupling leads in both semiconducting and metallic CNTs to the formation of excitons with binding energies of up to 1 eV. The chirality and diameter dependence of the excitonic binding energy and the transition frequency are presented in Kataura plots. Furthermore, the influence of the surrounding environment on the optical properties of CNTs is investigated. Extending the confinement to all three spatial dimensions, semiconductor Bloch equation are derived to describe the dynamics in QD semiconductor lasers and amplifiers. A detailed microscopic analysis of the nonlinear turn-on dynamics of electrically pumped InAs/GaAs QD lasers is performed, showing the generation of relaxation oscillations on a nanosecond time scale in both the photon and charge carrier density. The complex interplay between strongly nonlinear Coulomb scattering rates and radiative processes gives rise to these oscillations, which are generated after a characteristic delay time of approximately 1 ns. In agreement with experiments, the theory predicts a strong damping of relaxation oscillations indicating the crucial importance of the Coulomb interaction between the bound QD and continuous wetting-layer states for a fast dynamical response of the laser. Moreover, the ultrafast gain dynamics in QD semiconductor optical amplifiers has been investigated. It is found to be affected by the strength of the Coulomb scattering rates as well as by temperature, dephasing time, and pump power. Furthermore, the so called coherent artifact is shown to be a result of interference effects between the pump and the probe pulse rather than a consequence of two-photon absorption processes as often claimed in literature. The obtained results contribute to a better understanding of the limiting mechanisms for the ultrafast gain recovery in QD amplifiers.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorgelegte Dissertationsarbeit beschäftigt sich mit optischen Eigenschaften von niederdimensionalen Nanostrukturen am Beispiel von Kohlenstoff-Nanoröhren und Quantenpunkten. Die Kohlenstoff-Nanoröhren sind quasi-eindimensionale Nanostrukuren, deren einzigartige Eigenschaften sie sowohl für die Grundlagenforschung als auch für die Industrie attraktiv machen. In dieser Arbeit wurden mikroskopische Berechnungen des Absorptionskoeffizienten und des Rayleigh-Streuwirkungsquerschnitts im Rahmen eines neuen Ansatzes, der die Dichtematrixtheorie mit Tight-Binding Wellenfunktionen kombiniert, präsentiert. Im Gegensatz zu Ab-Initio-Berechnungen ermöglichen die so hergeleiteten Blochgleichungen die Untersuchung von Nanoröhren beliebiger Chiralität. In Übereinstimmung mit experimentellen Ergebnissen zeigen die berechneten Absorptions- und Rayleigh-Spektra eine Doppelpeak-Struktur bei metallischen Nanoröhren, die sich auf den Trigonal-Warping-Effekt zurückführen läßt. Die Intensitätsverhältnisse der energetisch niedrigsten Anregungen können durch das unterschiedliche Verhalten des optischen Matrixelements entlang der hochsymmetrischen Richtungen K-Gamma und K-M erklärt werden. Die Asymmetrie der Lininenform in Rayleighspektra hin zu niedrigeren Energien wurde bestätigt und mit dem Einfluß der nicht-resonanten Beiträge des Brechungsindex begründet. Außerdem konnte gezeigt werden, dass die Coulomb Wechselwirkung dann maximal ist, wenn der Impulsübertrag gering ist, wobei die Kopplungsstärke für Intersubbandübergänge mit einem senkrechten Impulstransfer auf weniger als 5% abnimmt. Wegen ihrer Eindimensionalität ist die Coulomb Wechselwirkung in Kohlenstoff-Nanoröhren besonders ausgeprägt. Die Elektron - Elektron - Abstoßung führt zu einer Renormierung der Bandlückenenergie, während die anziehende Elektron - Loch - Wechselwirkung zur Ausbildung von Exzitonen mit Bindungsenergien von bis zu 1 eV führt. Die exzitonischen Übergangs- und Bindungsenergien wurden auf ihre Abhängigkeit von der Chiralität, dem Durchmesser und ihrer Familienzugehörigkeit untersucht. Außerdem wurde der Einfluß des die Nanoröhren umgebenden Mediums im Detail studiert. Das aufgestellte theoretische Modell wurde weiterhin am Beispiel der quasi-nulldimensionalen Quantenpunkte und ihrer Anwendungen als Laser und Verstärker ausgewertet. Eine detaillierte mikroskopische Analyse der nichtlinearen Einschaltdynamik in elektrisch gepumpten InAs/GaAs Quantenpunkt-Lasern zeigt die Ausbildung von Relaxationsoszillationen, die als Folge eines komplexen Zusammenspiels zwischen nichtlinearen Coulomb-Streuprozessen (zwischen gebundenen Quantenpunkt-Zuständen und den sie umgebenden kontinuierlichen Wetting-Layer-Zuständen) und der radiativen Prozesse entstehen. In Übereinstimmung mit experimentellen Ergebnissen sagt die Theorie eine starke Dämpfung dieser Oszillationen für Quantenpunkt-Laser vorher und stellt dabei die entscheidende Bedeutung der Coulomb-induzierten Augerprozesse heraus. Schließlich wurde die ultraschnelle Gain-Dynamik von quantenpunktbasierten optischen Verstärkern mikroskopisch untersucht. Dabei wurde diese insbesondere auf ihre Abhängigkeit von der Stärke der Coulomb-Streuung, der Temperatur, der Dephasierungszeit und der Pulsintensität untersucht. Die erhaltenen Ergebnisse tragen zu einem besseren Verständnis sowohl des sogenannten kohärenten Artefakts als auch der limitierenden Mechnismen für eine ultraschnelle Gainerholung in quantenpunktbasierten Verstärkern bei.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-10-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>text/plain</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1956</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-20584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1956/original_main.tex</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1956/malic_ermin.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
