<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:33Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2013">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2013</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Pd und Au Nanoteilchen auf verschiedenen Oxidträgern - Stabilität und CO-Adsorptionseigenschaften</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Pd and Au nanoparticles on different oxide supports - stability and CO adsorption properties</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Höbel, Frank</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit wurde das Adsorptionsverhalten von Molekülen an Modellkatalysatoroberflächen in einem weiten Druck- und Temperaturbereich mit unterschiedlichen, sich ergänzenden, oberflächenphysikalischen Messmethoden untersucht. Die Ergebnisse wurden benutzt, um von den Adsorptionseigenschaften auf die Oberflächenmorphologie zu schließen. Zur schwingungsspektroskopischen Charakterisierung der Oberflächen wurde die oberflächensensitive summenfrequenzgenerierte Schwingungsspektroskopie (SFG) mit CO als Sondenmolekül verwendet. SFG erlaubt in-situ-Messungen von UHV- bis Atmosphärendruckbedingungen. Des Weiteren wurden die Systeme mit Temperatur-programmierte Desorptionsspektroskopie (TPD), niederenergetische Elektronenbeugung (LEED) und Augerelektronenspektroskopie (AES) untersucht. SFG-Untersuchungen des Pd-Nb2O5-Systems mit CO zeigten eine thermisch induzierte Ausbildung einer Pd-NbxOy-Mischphase bei Temperaturen oberhalb von 300 K. Bei Temperaturen bis 300 K konnten bis zu einem CO Druck von 100 mbar keine signifikanten Modifikationen des Systems beobachtet werden. Pd-Fe3O4-Systeme wurden mit CO in TPD- und SFG-Experimenten auf ihre thermische Stabilität (bis 600 K) getestet. Während der Heizexperimente konnte ein bei ~ 300 K beginnender Sinterprozess beobachtet werden, der unter anderem eine besser geordnete Oberflächenstruktur der Palladiumpartikel bewirkte. Im Gegensatz zu Pd-Nb2O5 sind Pd-Partikel auf der Fe3O4-Oberfläche auch bei höheren Temperaturen stabil und es kommt zu keiner Mischphasenbildung. Während stabilisierte Proben bei 450 K keine nennenswerten Unterschiede in der CO-Adsorptionscharakteristik aufwiesen, konnte bei einer Stabilisierungstemperatur von 500 K eine stark abweichende SFG-Signatur detektiert werden, die auf eine veränderte Oberflächenmorphologie hindeutet. Weiterhin wurde das Fe3O4-System mit unterschiedlichen Goldbelegungen SFG- und TPD-Messungen mit CO als Sondenmolekül unterzogen und auf thermisch induzierte Modifikationen untersucht. Für Au-Bedeckungen von 1 Å und 6 Å wurde hauptsächlich eine Abnahme der Au-Adsorptionsplätze beobachtet, ausgelöst durch Sintern. Bei kleineren Au-Bedeckungen (≤ 1 Å) konnten zusätzlich zu den regulären Au-Partikeln ungeordnete Au-Cluster in den SFG-Spektren anhand weiterer CO-Banden beobachtet werden. Bei Heizversuchen stand bei niedrigeren Temperaturen die Agglomeration von Au-Clustern im Vordergrund und der Sinterprozess begann erst bei 200 K. Auf Fe3O4-Proben mit 0.1 Å Gold konnten geladene Auδ+-Teilchen beobachtet werden, die bei höheren Temperaturen zu größeren Partikeln sintern. Vanadium- und Vanadyl-terminierte V2O3(0001)-Oberflächen wurden auf ihr CO-, Propan- und Propen-Desorptionsverhalten mit TPD untersucht. Vanadium-terminierte Filme wiesen die höchste Adsorptionskapazität bei einer gleichzeitig stärkeren Bindung der Sondenmoleküle an der Oberfläche auf. Domänengrenzen, Sauerstofffehlstellen oder Stufenkanten konnten durch Desorptionsmerkmale im Hochtemperaturbereich identifiziert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this study, the structure and adsorption properties of oxide supported model catalyst surfaces were investigated on a microscopic level using a comprehensive set of surface science techniques. Specifically, molecular CO adsorption on well-defined model catalyst surfaces has been studied in a broad temperature and pressure regime. As a result, the study enabled one to gain a fundamental understanding on the relation between the microscopic structure of the model catalyst and its adsorption properties. SFG (sum frequency generation) vibrational spectroscopy, being a surface sensitive technique, has been used to investigate the adsorption of CO on the model catalysts from UHV to atmospheric pressure. The experiments have been supplemented by temperature programmed desorption (TPD), low energy electron diffraction (LEED) and Auger electron spectroscopy (AES) to obtain complementary information on adsorption sites and surface composition. CO adsorption studies on a Nb2O5 supported Pd model catalyst have shown the formation of mixed Pd–NbxOy sites at temperatures above 300 K. The formation of this mixed metal oxide structure is connected with significant modifications of the adsorption properties of the model catalyst. In contrast, for Fe3O4 supported Pd model catalysts a relatively high thermal stability of the model surface and no formation of mixed metal oxide sites have been observed below 600 K by combined TPD- and SFG-experiments of adsorbed CO. However, annealing of the model catalyst was shown to be connected with a sintering of the Pd resulting in the formation of large, well-ordered Pd-particles. After a stabilization procedure at 450 K, no significant changes in CO adsorption behavior could be observed. High stabilization temperature (500 K) results, however, in a strong deviation of the SFG-signature pointing to a modification of the surface morphology. Thermal induced changes of Fe3O4 supported Au particles were also investigated by SFG- and TPD-experiments using CO as probe molecule. While larger Au-particles (1 Å and 6 Å Au exposure) mainly show reduction of Au-adsorption sites due to sintering, SFG-spectra of smaller Au-particles (≤ 1 Å) show additional CO-features. These features can be assigned to adsorption sites of crystalline particles as well of less ordered clusters. At the beginning of the annealing process at lower temperature an agglomeration of the particles was observed, followed by sintering at temperatures higher than 200 K. For very small Fe3O4 supported Au particles (0.1 Å), charged Auδ+-clusters and sintering to larger particles at higher temperatures have been observed. Finally, V2O3(0001) surfaces, terminated by vanadium and vanadyl were probed with CO, propane and propene to determine their desorption properties by TPD. Vanadium terminated surfaces demonstrated the highest adsorption capacity in combination with concurrently strongest bonded molecules on the surface. Contributions of high temperature desorption features were assigned to various kinds of surface defects (domain boundaries, step sites and oxygen vacancies).</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-01-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2013</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2013/original_hoebel_frank.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2013/hoebel_frank.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
