<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:43Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3558">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3558</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Ultrafast processes in molecules visualized with femtosecond pump-probe photoelectron spectroscopy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Ultraschnelle Prozesse in Molek√ºlen visualisiert mit Femtosekunden Anregungs-Abfrage Photoelektronenspektroskopie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Leitner, Torsten</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">One of the grand challenges in modern science is understanding chemistry on a fundamental inter- and intra-molecular scale. The principal player in chemical reactions is the electron and therefore, the fundamental scales to address are the sub to few nanometer length scale and the femto- to picosecond time scale. A widely occurring trigger for chemical reactions in nature is photo-excitation ‚Äì without the ability of harvesting sunlight and using it for further chemical processes, life as we know it would not be possible. Therefore, in order to contribute to understanding chemistry on a fundamental level, methods for visualizing the interaction of light with the electronic structure of molecules and the dynamics in the electronic structure after photo-excitation are investigated in this thesis. The method of choice to address the function of the electron was time-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy (TRPES). The thesis is divided into two major parts: Part I ‚ÄúMethods and Instruments‚Ä? where experimental setups and tools used for ultrafast photoelectron spectroscopy are introduced and Part II ‚ÄúExperiments‚Ä?, presenting and discussing three concrete experiments on electronic molecular structures. In Part I, the implementation and operation of a TRPES setup for investigating ultrafast electronic structure dynamics, based on laser high-harmonic generation, is discussed in detail. Furthermore, a high-temperature molecular evaporation source developed within the framework of this thesis is introduced and the TRPES setups used for this thesis at the Max-Born-Institute in Berlin and the free electron laser FLASH on the DESY site in Hamburg are detailed. The challenges and solutions for performing TRPES at FLASH are addressed in detail, especially a scheme for accurate pump‚Äìprobe timing, which at FLASH underlies a large shot-to-shot arrival-time jitter. Part II demonstrates the usability of photoelectron spectroscopy for visualizing the dynamics of the electronic structure in molecules. The possibility of drawing conclusions on symmetry properties of the electron density distribution is explored by comparing the polarization dependence of a two-color two-photon ionization process to an approximative theoretical model. The visualization of coherent nuclear and electronic wave packet oscillations in excited state NaI molecules by means of TRPES with sub 100 fs time resolution is demonstrated, revealing quantum mechanical effects like coherent superposition of wave packets reflected in the co-existence of a single molecule in several intra-molecular distances. Furthermore, a transfer of the molecular wave packet population between intra-molecular potentials, hence between molecular states, is visualized. Lastly, an experiment on revealing the transient electronic structure during the step-wise photo-dissociation of Fe(CO)5 molecules in gas-phase is presented, with a focus on how to disentangle the complex TRPES data set and separate the overlapping photoelectron spectra arising from the different molecular species occurring during the photo-dissociation process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Eine der gro√üen Herausforderungen der modernen Wissenschaft ist es, die Chemie auf ihrer fundamentalen inter- und intra-molekularen Ebene zu verstehen. Das Elektron ist der Hauptakteur in chemischen Reaktionen und erfordert Untersuchungen auf fundamentalen L√§ngen- und Zeitskalen im Nanometer- bzw. Femto- bis Picosekundenbereich. Photoanregung ist ein vielfach in der Natur vorkommender Ausl√∂ser f√ºr chemische Prozesse ‚Äì ohne die M√∂glichkeit, das Sonnenlicht als Energiequelle zu nutzen, w√§re Leben wie wir es kennen nicht m√∂glich. Diese Arbeit untersucht Methoden zur Visualisierung der Interaktion von Licht mit der elektronischen Struktur von Molek√ºÃàlen sowie der Dynamik in der elektronsichen Struktur nach Photoanregung. Die Methode, um die Funktion des Elektrons zu untersuchen, war zeitaufgel√∂ste Photoelektronenspektroskopie (TRPES ‚Äì time-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy). Die Arbeit gliedert sich in zwei Hauptteile: Teil I ‚ÄúMethoden und Instrumente‚Ä?, in dem experimentelle Aufbauten und Werkzeuge vorgestellt werden, die in der ultraschnellen Photoelektronenspektroskopie zum Einsatz kommen, und Teil II ‚ÄúExperimente‚Ä?, in dem drei konkrete Experimente zur elektronischen Struktur von Molek√ºlen vorgestellt und diskutiert werden. In Teil I wird die Implementierung und der Betrieb eines TRPES Aufbaus zur Untersuchung ultraschneller Dynamik in elektronischen Strukturen detailliert dargestellt, der auf der Erzeugung Hoher Harmonischer eines Lasers basiert. Desweiteren wird eine Hochtemperatur-Molek√ºl-Verdampfungsquelle vorgestellt, die im Rahmen dieser Arbeit entwickelt wurde, und die TRPES Experimentieraufbauten werden erl√§utert, die f√ºr diese Arbeit am Max-Born-Institut in Berlin und am Freie Elektronen Laser FLASH in Hamburg, verwendet wurden. Die Herausforderungen und L√∂sungen zur Durchf√ºhrung eines TRPES Experiments bei FLASH werden detailliert geschildert, insbesondere wird ein Schema zur pr√§zisen Bestimmung der Pump‚ÄìProbe Zeiten vorgestellt, die bei FLASH von einer gro√üen Schuss-zu-Schuss Schwankung der Lichtpulsankuftszeiten beinflusst sind. Teil II demonstriert die Verwendbarkeit von Photoelektronenspektroskopie zur Visualisierung der Dynamik der elektronischen Struktur von Molek√ºlen. Die M√∂glichkeit Schlussfolgerungen √ºber die Symmetrieeigenschaften der Elektronendichteverteilung zu ziehen wird untersucht, indem die Polarisationsabh√§ngigkeit eines zwei-Farben zwei-Photonen Ionisierungsprozesses mit einem theoretischen Modell verglichen wird. Die Visualisierung koh√§renter Kern- und Elektronenwellenpaketoszillationen von NaI Molekl√ºen im angeregten Zustand mittels TRPES mit sub 100 fs Zeitaufl√∂sung wird demonstriert und zeigt quantenmechanische Effekte, wie z.B. koh√§rente √úberlagerung von Wellenpaketen auf, die sich in der Koexistenz eines einzelnen Molek√ºls in verschiedenen intra-molekularen Abst√§nden widerspiegelt. Weiterhin wird ein Transfer des Wellenpakets zwischen verschiedenen intra-molekularen Potenzialen, folglich molekularen Zustanden, visualisiert. Zuletzt wird ein Experiment zur Offenlegung der transienten elektronischen Struktur w√§hrend der schrittweisen Photo-Dissoziation von Fe(CO)5 Molek√ºÃàlen in der Gas-Phase vorgestellt, Der Schwerpunkt liegt hierbei auf der Entflechtung des komplexen TRPES Datensatzes bzw. der Trennung der √ºberlappenden Photoelektronenspektren, die von den im Laufe des Photo-Dissoziations-Prozesses auftretenden verschiedenen molekularen Spezies stammen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-12-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3558</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37436</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-37436</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3558/leitner_torsten.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
