<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:00:20Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3467">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3467</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Influence of defects, phonons and strain on the luminescence properties of nitride- and arsenide-based quantum dots</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Einfluss von Defekten von Phononen und von Verspannung auf die Lumineszenzeigenschaften der nitrid- und arsenidbasierten Quantenpunkte</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ostapenko, Irina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work presents the results of experimental investigations of the luminescence properties of two important quantum dot (QD) material systems by means of cathodoluminescence (CL) spectroscopy. Nitride-based QDs are prospective for quantum-communication applications at elevated temperatures due to their large localization energies. Site-controlled InGaAs/GaAs QDs present an example of a novel ‚Äúbottom-up‚Ä? approach for deterministic QD alignment. This method, based on strain-modulation controlled QD nucleation, is generally applicable to lateral positioning of nanostructures. The experimental results are substantiated with numerical calculations, some of which are presented for the first time within the frame of this work. Different manifestations of the so-called spectral diffusion (SD) - the variation of the single QD luminescence under influence of stochastic fluctuations of electric fields in the QD environment - were investigated. The dependence of SD on various excitation conditions and sample fabrication methods was analyzed for nitride-based QDs. The origin of different components of SD is discussed in terms of different defect types. For the spectral jitter of QD emission lines, which can be resolved in the spectroscopic experiments, a model of a moving charge is proposed. The analysis of the spectral jitter of the QD emission lines allows to conclude about the QD excitonic dipole-moment, induced by piezo- and pyroelectric fields. It is shown, that a large emission linewidth appears to be intrinsic property of the nitride material system using current fabrication methods and is present even in case of resonant excitation of the QD. From the spectral jitter of the emission lines, stemming from the excitonic transitions of the same QD, the ratio of the built-in dipole moments of the respective excitonic complexes can be determined quantitatively. Built-in dipole moments of various excitonic complexes from the same dot are shown to differ significantly. A special type of spectral jitter, reported for the first time in this work, allows to estimate the absolute value of the excitonic built-in dipole moment without applying external electric field. Interaction of excitons and acoustic phonons is investigated in detail in a combined experimental and theoretical survey for the first time for GaN/AlN QDs, where the impact of vertical and lateral charge-carrier confinement on the coupling mechanisms is analyzed. The independent Boson model using realistic wave-functions from 8-band k ¬∑ p theory accounts very well for the experimental observations of the shape and position of the phonon side-bands. The intensity ratio of the zero-phonon line and phonon side-band as obtained from the numerical results matches measured data only when SD-induced line broadening is superimposed. The importance of taking SD into account in case of nitride-based QDs is again emphasized and its major impact on the inhomogeneous line broadening is proven. The analysis of temperature dependence of the emission linewidth shows a major role of acoustic phonon scattering for broadening of the linewidth, while the contribution of optical phonons can be neglected here. Spatially-resolved CL showed itself as a very useful technique for the investigation of the first test-structures of positioned QD. The feasibility of the growth concept is proven on the example of InGaAs/GaAs QD material system. The unambiguous influence of the strain from the buried stressor structure on luminescence properties, such as spectral diffusion and ensemble polarization, is evidenced. CL experiments reveal the formation of different QD luminescence bands, which can be clearly distinguished spectrally and spatially in strong correlation with the stressor position. The possibility to control properties of QD and their formation by means of strain from a buried stressor structure, appears an important step on the way to tailoring single-QD-based devices with desirable properties.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit stellt die Ergebnisse der experimentellen Untersuchungen der Lumineszenzeigenschaften von Halbleiterquantenpunkten (QP) vor. Zwei wichtige Materialsysteme stehen im Mittelpunkt dieser Arbeit. Beide Systeme sind f√ºr die Entwicklung von Anwendungen im Bereich der Quantenkryptografie und Quantencomputer von gro√üer Bedeutung: Nitrid-basierte QP sind wichtige Kandidaten f√ºr die Anwendbarkeit bei Raumtemperatur. Am Beispiel des Materialsystems InGaAs/GaAs wurde ein neuer Ansatz der Herstellung positionierter QP untersucht. F√ºr die optische Charakterisierung wurde Kathodolumineszenzspektroskopie (KL) benutzt, da sie eine hohe Orts- und Spektralaufl√∂sung bietet. Um die experimentellen Beobachtungen einzuordnen, wurden verschiedene Modellrechnungen durchgef√ºhrt und deren Ergebnisse werden zum ersten Mal im Rahmen dieser Arbeit pr√§sentiert. Dabei vermittelt die gesamte Analyse ein besseres Verst√§ndnis der untersuchten Prozesse. Stochastische Fluktuationen lokaler elektrischer Felder in der Umgebung von QP beeinflussen die Lumineszenzenergie, dieser Effekt ist als spektrale Diffusion (SD) bekannt. Die Auswirkungen der SD auf die Lumineszenz Nitrid-basierter QP wurden untersucht. Die vorliegende Arbeit liefert umfangreiche Ergebnisse und Diskussionen zu unterschiedlichen Typen von SD und f√ºhrt deren m√∂glichen Ursprung auf bestimmte Arten von Defekten zur√ºck. Es wurde festgestellt, dass die gro√üen Linienbreiten auch bei resonanter Anregung auftreten und f√ºr die Nitrid-basierten QP, die mittels heutigen Verfahren gewachsen werden, eine charakteristische Eigenschaft darstellen. Ein spezielles Muster im zeitlichen Verlauf der Lumineszenz einzelner QP wird zum ersten Mal beschrieben, ein Model als Erkl√§rung f√ºr diese √Ñnderung der Linienlage wird vorgestellt und durch Simulationsrechnungen verifiziert. Pyro- und piezoelektrische Felder in den Nitrid-basierten Heterostrukturen verursachen eine r√§umliche Trennung der Wellenfunktionen der Ladungstr√§ger in den QP. F√ºr die resultierenden Dipolmomente exzitonischer Komplexe in einzelnen QP wurde aus den Experimenten anhand der SD sowohl die Gr√∂√üe als auch das relative Verh√§ltnis identifiziert. Die Wechselwirkungen zwischen Exzitonen, eingeschlossen in AlN/GaN QP, und elementaren Gitterschwingungen wurden untersucht. Temperaturabh√§ngige Messungen und spezielle Modelrechnungen zeigen die verst√§rkte Kopplung an akustische Phononen. Eine detaillierte Analyse der Kopplungsmechanismen in Abh√§ngigkeit von Gr√∂√üe und Form eines QPs wurde mit Hilfe des Independent Boson Modells durchgef√ºhrt. Diese Rechnungen benutzen realistische Wellenfunktionen aus 8-Band k ¬∑ p Rechnungen in der Hartree-Fock N√§herung als Eingangsparameter und ber√ºcksichtigen au√üerdem die durch die SD verursachte inhomogene Linienverbreiterung. Die Simulationsergebnisse zeigen eine sehr gute √úbereinstimmung mit dem Experiment. KL Untersuchungen haben best√§tigt, dass der Einsatz vergrabener Stressor-Strukturen unter einer QP-Schicht das Wachstum der QP steuern kann. Die Ergebnisse deuten darauf hin, dass sich die QP in starker Korrelation mit der Position des Stressors bilden. Die durch den Stressor erzeugte Verspannung im Material beeinflusst auch die optischen Eigenschaften der positionierten QP. So wurden ortsabh√§ngige systematische Variationen der QP nachgewiesen, die sich in der Emissionsenergie, der SD und der Polarisation zeigen. Da die in dieser Arbeit untersuchte Methode des kontrollierten Wachstums von QP auch in anderen Materialsystemen anwendbar ist, erscheint dieses Verfahren ein bedeutender Schritt f√ºr die Entwicklung von Anwendungen, die auf einzelnen positionierten QP basieren, die bestimmte optische Eigenschaften aufweisen sollen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-09-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3467</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35422</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-35422</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3467/ostapenko_irina.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
