<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:14Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2810">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2810</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Theory for strongly coupled quantum dot cavity quantum electrodynamics - Photon statistics and phonon signatures in quantum light emission</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Theorie der stark gekoppelten Quantenpunkt-Resonator Quantenelektrodynamik - Photonstatistik und Phononsignaturen in der Quantenlichtemission</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carmele, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Advances in semiconductor technology constitute a new physical system to investigate quantum optics in a solid state environment: a quantum dot strongly coupled to a single cavity mode. In the strong coupling regime, the electron-photon coupling dominates over dissipation processes and Rabi oscillations occur. This thesis focuses on the theoretical investigation of the strong coupling regime in the single-photon limit, in which few photons interact with a single quantum dot and the combined electron and photon dynamics is strongly correlated. Typical theoretical frameworks rely on factorization approaches, such as the cluster expansion scheme. However, for strongly correlated dynamics, standard factorization schemes fail and new theoretical frameworks become necessary. The work in hand develops two novel methods within the equation of motion approach to solve the complete quantum kinetics without a factorization of the electron-photon interaction, including non-Markovian features, and hereby bridges this gap in the theoretical description of semiconductor quantum optics. First, for quantum dots with a fixed number of electrons, a mathematical induction method for the combined electron, photon and phonon dynamics is introduced. This method is numerically solvable up to an arbitrary accuracy. Surprisingly, for an initial thermal photon distribution in the cavity the electron-phonon interaction leads to a counter-intuitive reduction in the intensity-intensity correlation function. The classical photon distribution evolves into a nonclassical one. In addition to the well-known anti-crossing for zero detuning, more anti-crossings and signatures for strong coupling are found for detunings of a multiple of the LO-phonon energy below and above the band gap energy. Within this LO-phonon cavity feeding, modified Rabi oscillations exhibit anharmonicities for elevated temperatures. Assuming two electrons in the quantum dot, the polarization entanglement of photons generated by a biexciton cascade is theoretically investigated in the weak and strong coupling regime. Via an effective multi-phonon Hamiltonian approach, temperature dependent relaxation rates from the QD to the wetting layer states are taken into account. For elevated temperatures $T \ge 120~$K, these LO-phonon relaxation rates in GaAs result in a vanishing degree of entanglement. This calculation is in agreement with recent experiments. Focusing on quantum dots, in which the number of electrons and holes is not fixed due to the presence of a wetting layer/carrier reservoir, many-particle correlations occur and are treated within the photon-probability cluster expansion approach. This generalized cluster expansion is a reliable theoretical framework to study the optical emission in the single photon regime. Vacuum Rabi flopping is discussed. The oscillation amplitude of vacuum Rabi flopping is interestingly determined by the number of electrons in the quantum dot. Furthermore, the dynamics of an electrically pumped single quantum dot is described and the full photon statistics of the quantum light emission for different pump rates is investigated. Including semiconductor specific Pauli-blocking effects in the polarization dynamics, a parameter study of an electrically driven single photon emitter is provided.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Aktuelle Fortschritte in der Halbleitertechnologie etablieren ein neues physikalisches System, um quantenoptische Eigenschaften auf Nanoskalen zu untersuchen: ein Quantenpunkt in einem Mikroresonator. Im Falle einer starken Kopplung übertrifft die Stärke der Elektron-Licht Wechselwirkung die auftretenden Verluste und Rabi Oszillationen treten auf. Diese Arbeit befasst sich mit der theoretischen Beschreibung solcher Systeme für den Fall, dass wenige Photonen mit einem einzelnen Quantenpunkt wechselwirken und die Dynamik der Photonen und Elektronen stark korreliert ist. Typische theoretische Zugänge basieren auf Faktorisierungsansätzen, die im Falle einer stark korrelierten Dynamik ihre Gültigkeit einbüßen. Neue theoretische Zugänge sind zwingend erforderlich und werden mit dieser Arbeit vorgestellt, die im Bewegungsgleichungsansatz eine Faktorisierung der Elektron-Licht Wechselwirkung vermeiden und eine vollständige Beschreibung der Vielteilchenkinetik im Falle stark korrelierter Dynamiken gewährleisten, inklusive der Berücksichtigung von Gedächtniseffekten. Für atomähnliche Quantenpunkte kann die Zahl der Elektronen und Löcher als konstant angenommen werden. Mittels der vollständigen Induktion wird ein numerisch lösbares Modell eingeführt, das die ineinanderspielende Elektron-, Photon- und Phonondynamik bis auf beliebige Genauigkeit auswertet. Überraschenderweise wird ein anfängliches thermisches Lichtfeld im Resonator aufgrund der stark wechselwirkenden Phononen- und Photonendynamik in den Zustand eines nichtklassischen Lichtfeld gebracht. Neben dem üblichen spektralen Anti-crossing, falls sich die Resonatormode in Resonanz mit der Bandlückenfrequenz des Quantenpunktes befindet, treten weitere Anti-crossings auf, sobald die Kavitätsmode von der Bandlückenfrequenz um ein ganzzahliges Vielfaches der LO-Phononenfrequenz verstimmt ist. Diese von den Phononen herbeigeführte starke Kopplung führt zu anharmonischen Rabi Oszillationen bei Raumtemperatur. In einem nächsten Schritt wird das induktive Modell auf eine Biexziton-Kaskade in einem Quantenpunkt angewendet und für starke und schwache Kopplung ein temperaturabhängiges Maß für Polarisationsverschränkung der abgestrahlten Photonen bestimmt. Ab einer Temperatur von 120K dominiert der Einfluss der Halbleiterumgebung in GaAs und die Polarisationsverschränkung verschwindet. Dieses Ergebnis stimmt mit aktuellen Messergebnissen überein. In flachen Quantenpunkten ist die Zahl der Elektronen und der Löcher nicht mehr konstant und die Vielteilchenkorrelationen der Ladungsträger können nicht mehr vernachlässigt werden. Im Rahmen einer Photonwahrscheinlichkeitsentwicklung, die die starke Korrelation zwischen Elektronen und Photonen berücksichtigt, wird eine modifizierte Hartree-Fock Faktorisierung eingeführt. Das erhöhte Pauli-Blocking in Halbleiterumgebungen führt zu modizifierten Rabi Oszillationen, an deren Amplitude die Zahl der Ladungsträger im Quantenpunkt bestimmt werden kann. Zudem wird die Photonenstatistik eines elektrisch gepumpten Quantenpunktes berechnet und auf diese Weise eine Parameterstudie für elektrisch gepumpte Einzelphotonenemitter erstellt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-02-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2810</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2810/carmele_alexander.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
