<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:52Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2727">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2727</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Fundamental properties of excitons and phonons in ZnO: A spectroscopic study of the dynamics, polarity, and effects of external fields</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Grundlegende Eigenschaften von Exzitonen und Phononen in ZnO: Eine spektroskopische Studie der Dynamik, der Polarität und der Effekte externer Felder</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wagner, Markus Raphael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The work in hand presents a spectroscopic study of optical transitions and lattice dynamics of ZnO under the influence of external fields. A comparative study of different ZnO single crystals and homoepitaxial ZnO films reveals pronounced differences in the free and bound exciton luminescence which can be related to different impurity centers and strain levels. The charge state and donor or acceptor character of all observed shallow bound exciton centers is identified by photoluminescence spectroscopy in external magnetic fields. A correlation between the localization energies of excitons bound to the same chemical element in the neutral and ionized charge state is reported. Furthermore, different excited states of the free and bound excitons are investigated and identified by photoluminescence excitation spectroscopy and temperature dependent photoluminescence spectroscopy. The properties of the shallow impurity bound excitons are compared to defect related deeply bound excitons. Not much was known about the defect centers of these deeply bound excitons. By the combination of different experimental techniques, a multitude of new information is obtained including the defect type and charge state of the binding centers, the temperature dependence of the localization energies, the strength of the exciton-phonon coupling of the deeply bound excitons, the recombination dynamics of shallow and deeply bound excitons, the influence of uniaxial pressure on the electronic energy levels, and the spatial distribution of the luminescence centers. Based on these data, a defect model for deeply bound excitons in ZnO is developed which is capable of explaining all experimental results and provides a theoretical estimation of the extend of the defect complexes. Another part of this work is dedicated to the study of the valence band ordering in ZnO which has been debated controversially for almost half a century. High resolution magneto-PL measurements of bound excitons are presented which allow to resolve this long lasting disagreement in the literature. A previously undetected hole fine splitting could be resolved which provides, in combination with polarization and angular resolved measurements, conclusive evidence for a reversed valence band ordering in ZnO compared to other wurtzite II-VI and III-V compound semiconductors. The lattice dynamics of ZnO crystals are studied by Raman spectroscopy under the influence of external pressure. A variety of important material parameters is derived including high precision values of the hydrostatic pressure coefficients and Grüneisen parameters of all Raman active modes. The accuracy of the here reported values exceeds those of previously published values in the literature. For Born's transverse effective charge, an incorrect pressure dependence in the literature is discovered and revised. Raman measurements of ZnO single crystals under uniaxial pressure are reported for the first time. In combination with the hydrostatic pressure measurements on the same samples, the first experimental determination of the phonon deformation potentials of all Raman active modes in ZnO is achieved. Furthermore, a study of the resonant Raman scattering at bound exciton states is presented. The influence of the excitation energy and temperature on the decay dynamics of phonon replicas and Raman modes is investigated. The dissociation of the bound excitons at elevated temperatures is found to alter the lifetimes of the LO modes under resonant excitation which are directly determined by time resolved measurements on the picosecond time scale.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die vorliegende Arbeit präsentiert spektroskopische Untersuchungen der optischen Übergänge und Gitterdynamik von ZnO unter dem Einfluss von externen Feldern. Eine vergleichende Studie von verschiedenen ZnO-Einkristallen und homoepitaktisch gewachsenen ZnO Filmen zeigt deutliche Unterschiede in der Lumineszenz freier und gebundener Exzitonen, die auf Verunreinigungen und Verzerrungen zurückgeführt werden können. Der Ladungszustand und Donator- oder Akzeptor-Charakter aller flachen Exzitonen-Bindungszentren wird durch Photolumineszenz-Spektroskopie (PL) in externen Magnetfeldern identifiziert. Eine Korrelation zwischen den Lokalisierungsenergien der Exzitonen, die an Fremdatomen des gleichen chemischen Elementes in unterschiedlichen Ladungszuständen gebunden sind, wird dargelegt. Des Weiteren werden die angeregten Zustände der gebundenen Exzitonen untersucht und durch Anregungsspektroskopie und temperaturabhängige PL identifiziert. Die Eigenschaften flach gebundener Exzitonen an Fremdatomen werden mit denen tief gebundener Exzitonen an Defekten verglichen. Durch die Kombination verschiedener experimenteller Techniken kann eine Vielzahl neuer Erkenntnisse abgeleitet werden. Diese umfassen die Defektart und den Ladungszustand der Bindungszentren, die Temperaturabhängigkeit der Lokalisierungsenergien, die Stärke der Exziton-Phonon-Kopplung der tief gebundenen Exzitonen, die Rekombinationsdynamik flach und tief gebundenen Exzitonen, den Einfluss von uniaxialem Druck auf die elektronischen Energieniveaus sowie die räumliche Verteilung der Lumineszenz-Zentren. Basierend auf diesen Daten wird ein Defektmodell für tief gebundene Exzitonen in ZnO entwickelt, das alle experimentellen Ergebnisse erklärt und eine theoretische Abschätzung der Ausdehnung der Defektkomplexe ermöglicht. Ein weiterer Teil dieser Arbeit ist der Untersuchung der Valenzbandordnung in ZnO gewidmet, die seit fast einem halben Jahrhundert kontrovers diskutiert wird. Die hier vorgestellten hochaufgelösten Magneto-PL-Messungen gebundener Exzitonen ermöglichen eine eindeutige Identifizierung der Valenzbandordnung und tragen somit zur Beendigung dieser Debatte bei. Durch die Auflösung einer bisher unerkannten Feinaufspaltung der Lochzustände in Kombination mit polarisations- und winkelaufgelösten Messungen werden schlüssige Beweise für eine umgekehrte Valenzbandordnung in ZnO im Vergleich zu anderen Wurtzit II-VI und III-V Verbindungshalbleitern präsentiert. Die Gitterdynamik von ZnO-Kristallen unter dem Einfluss von äußerem Druck wird mittels der Raman-Spektroskopie untersucht. Eine Vielzahl wichtiger Materialparameter einschließlich präziser Werte der hydrostatischen Druck-Koeffizienten und Grüneisen Parametern aller Raman-aktiven Moden wird bestimmt. Für die transversale effektive Ladung nach Born wird eine fehlerhafte Druckabhängigkeit in der Literatur aufgezeigt und korrigiert. Außerdem werden zum ersten Mal Raman-Messungen an ZnO-Einkristallen unter uniaxialem Druck durchgeführt. In Kombination mit hydrostatischen Druckmessungen an denselben Proben wird erstmalig eine experimentelle Bestimmung der Phonon-Deformationspotentiale aller Raman-aktiven Moden in ZnO erreicht. Darüber hinaus wird die resonante Raman-Streuung an gebundenen Exzitonen in ZnO untersucht. Der Einfluss der Anregungsenergie und der Temperatur auf die Dynamik der Phonon-Repliken und Raman-Moden wird analysiert. Die Dissoziation der Exzitonen bei erhöhten Temperaturen beeinflusst die Lebensdauer der LO-Phononen unter resonanter Anregung, die durch zeitaufgelöste Messungen im Pikosekundenbereich bestimmt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-12-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28766</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28766</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2727/wagner_markus.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
