<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:08Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3645">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3645</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Nonequilibrium dynamics and self-organization in field-driven dipolar colloidal particles</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Nichtgleichgewichtsdynamik und Selbstorganisation feldgetriebener dipolarer kolloidaler Teilchen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jäger, Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">In this thesis, we investigate the dynamics and pattern formation behavior of systems of spherical colloidal particles with permanent dipole moments in external time-dependent fields on the basis of computer simulations and theoretical considerations. The computer simulation techniques that we use are molecular dynamics simulations, Langevin dynamics simulations, Wang-Landau Monte Carlo simulations, and Brownian dynamics simulations that include hydrodynamic interactions. First, we focus on rotating fields in a three-dimensional geometry. Performing simulations at a fixed packing fraction and dipolar coupling parameter, we construct a full nonequilibrium phase diagram as function of the driving frequency and field strength. This diagram contains both synchronized states, where the individual particles follow the field with (on average) constant phase difference, and asynchronous states. The synchronization is accompanied by layer formation, which breaks down at too large driving frequencies. During the transition from layered to unlayered states, complex changes in the single-particle rotational dynamics from synchronous to asynchronous behavior appear. We investigate this dynamic behavior in detail and show that the limit frequencies can be well described as a bifurcation in the nonlinear equation of motion of a single particle rotating in a viscous medium. We also present a density functional theory, which describes the emergence of layers in perfectly synchronized states as an equilibrium phase transition. Finally, we investigate the influence of hydrodynamic interactions on these three-dimensional systems. In a next step, we consider monolayers of dipolar particles that are driven by rotating external in-plane fields. In these system, two-dimensional cluster formation can occur. We investigate at which field strengths and frequencies these clusters form and explore the influence of hydrodynamic interactions in depth. In particular, we focus on their interplay with the permanent dipolar interactions of the particles. We also examine the phase behavior of the equilibrium system resulting from a time-average of the colloidal interactions in the rotating field. In this way we demonstrate that the clustering in the driven system arises from a first-order phase transition between a vapor and a condensed phase. Lastly, we report results on the rotational ratchet effect in systems of three-dimensional dipolar particles. The ratchet effect consists of directed rotations of particles in an oscillating magnetic field, which lacks a net rotating component. We investigate the influence of both the random and deterministic contributions to the equations of motion on the ratchet effect. As a main result, we show that dipolar interactions can have an enhancing as well as a dampening effect on the ratchet behavior depending on the dipolar coupling strength of the system under consideration. The enhancement is shown to be caused by an increase in the effective field on a particle generated by neighboring magnetic particles, while the dampening is due to restricted rotational motion in the effective field. Moreover, we find a non-trivial influence of the short-range, repulsive interaction between the particles.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In dieser Arbeit untersuchen wir die Dynamik und das Strukturbildungsverhalten in Systemen aus dipolaren kolloidalen Teilchen mit permanenten Dipolmomenten in externen zeitabhängigen Feldern mittels Computersimulationen und theoretischen Überlegungen. Die verwendeten Computersimulationstechniken sind Molekulardynamik, Langevindynamik und Brownsche Dynamik mit hydrodynamischen Wechselwirkungen. Zuerst untersuchen wir den Einfluss rotierender Felder auf dipolare kolloidale Systeme in dreidimensionalen Geometrien. Wir konstruieren ein Nichtgleichgewichtsdiagramm, in dem sich sowohl synchronisierte Zustände, in denen die Teilchen dem Feld folgen, als auch nichtsynchronisierte Zustände finden. Die Synchronisation ist von Schichtenbildung begleitet, die bei zu hohen Feldfrequenzen zusammenbricht. Der Zusammenbruch geht mit einem Übergang des System in einen asynchronen Zustand einher. Wir untersuchen das damit verbundene dynamische Verhalten und zeigen, dass die Grenzfrequenz durch eine Bifurkation der nichtlinearen Bewegungsgleichung eines isolierten Teilchens, das in einem viskosen Medium rotiert, beschrieben werden kann. Weiterhin konstruieren wir eine Dichtefunktionaltheorie, die das Auftreten der Schichtenbildung in perfekt synchronisierten Systemen beschreibt. Zuletzt untersuchen wir den Einfluss hydrodynamischer Wechselwirkungen auf das System. Im nächsten Schritt diskutieren wir quasi-zweidimensionale Systeme aus dipolaren Teilchen, die von einem rotierenden Feld getrieben werden. In solchen Systemen können sich zweidimensionale Cluster bilden. Wir studieren das Auftreten der Cluster in Abhängigkeit von den Feldparametern und analysieren den Einfluss hydrodynamischer Wechselwirkungen auf das Verhalten des Systems. Insbesondere das Wechselspiel zwischen den dipolaren und hydrodynamischen Wechselwirkungen untersuchen wir im Detail. Außerdem untersuchen wir das Phasenverhalten des Gleichgewichtssystems, das aus der Mittelung der dipolaren Wechselwirkung im rotierenden Feld hervorgeht. Zusammen mit einer Analyse des Clusterwachstums können wir so zeigen, dass Clusterbildung in einem Phasenübergang zwischen einer gasförmigen und einer kondensierten Phase begründet ist. Zuletzt untersuchen wir den rotatorischen Ratscheneffekt in dreidimensonalen Systemen aus dipolaren Teilchen. In diesem Effekt kann gerichtete rotatorische Bewegung aus oszillierenden Feldern, die keine Nettorotationskomponente besitzen, gewonnen werden. Wir analysieren den Einfluss sowohl der zufälligen als auch der deterministischen Beiträge in den Bewegungsgleichungen auf den Ratscheneffekt. Als Hauptresultat zeigen wir, dass dipolare Wechselwirkungen einen verstärkenden als auch einen unterdrückenden Effekt auf den Ratscheneffekt haben können. Die Verstärkung des Effekts kann durch einen Anstieg des lokalen Feldes in der Umgebung der dipolaren Teilchen begründet werden. Dieser Anstieg tritt auf, da die Teilchenwechselwirkung das effektiv wirkende Feld verstärkt. Die Unterdrückung ist durch die Einschränkung der rotatorischen Freiheit aufgrund der Dipolwechselwirkungen zu erklären. Außerdem finden wir einen nichttrivialen Einfluss der kurzreichweitigen und abstoßenden Wechselwirkung auf den Ratscheneffekt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-03-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3645</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38847</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38847</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3645/jaeger_sebastian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
