<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:51:32Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1549">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1549</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Electronic Properties of Self-Organized Quantum Dots</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Elektronische Eigenschaften von Selbstorganisierten Quantenpunkten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schliwa, Andrei</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die elektronischen und optischen Eigenschaften von verspannten und unverspannten Halbleiterquantenpunkten realistischer Geometrie und chemischer Zusammensetzung werden theoretisch untersucht, d.h. des um Verspannungseffekte erweiterten 8-band-k.p-Modells unter Einbeziehung piezoelektrischer Effekte erster und zweiter Ordnung berechnet. Basierend auf den so erhaltenen Einteilchenzuständen werden mittels der Konfigurations-Wechselwirkungs-Methode die Energien von Mehrteilchenzuständen, wie dem Exziton, Biexziton und positiv, wie negativ geladenen Trion ermittelt und mit experimentellen Ergebnissen verglichen. Im Hauptteil der Arbeit wird eine breite Palette von verschiedenartigen InGaAs/GaAs Quantenpunkten untersucht, die sich in Geometrie und der Art ihrer chemischen Komposition unterscheiden. Die sich ergebenden spektroskopischen Signaturen können somit dazu dienen - ohne aufwändige strukturelle Untersuchungen anzustellen - aus optischen Daten, wie Übergangsenergien oder/und Mehrteilchenbindungsenergien, Schlüsse über die Struktur der involvierten Quantenpunkte zu ziehen. Besonderer Wert wurde bei den Untersuchungen darauf gelegt, wie sich die inhomogene Verspannung vermittels der QP-Geometrie auf die elektronischen Zustände auswirkt. Eine Schlüsselrolle spielt dabei die Piezoelektrizität. Erstmals wurde im Detail untersucht, wie sich erste und zweite Ordnung in Abhängigkeit von QP-Form und Komposition verhalten und wie sich die Symmetrie des Einschlusspotentials ändert. Piezoelektrische Effekte und Verspannung spielen ebenfalls eine große Rolle bei Stapeln von Quantenpunkten. In dieser Arbeit wurden Paare identischer und solche unterschiedlicher Größe in Hinsicht auf das Kopplungsverhalten von Elektron- und Lochzuständen untersucht. Im ersten Fall identischer Quantenpunkte führt die inhomogene Verspannung zur Einführung einer vertikalen 'Confinement'-Asymmetrie. Diese führt dazu, dass der Lochgrundzustand immer im unteren QP gebunden ist, egal, ob es sich um einen Zweifach-, Dreifach-, oder Fünffachstapel handelt. Piezoelektrische Effekte können diesen Trend im Einzelfall noch verstärken. Im Fall von Paaren unterschiedlich großer QPte, ist erstmals das Kopplungsverhalten von Elektronenniveaus unterschiedlicher Schalen untersucht worden. Mittels vertikal angelegter elektrischer Felder wurde die Resonanzbedingung variiert: Nur solche Einzel-QP-Zustände bilden gekoppelte Hybridzustände, die zur selben Irreduziblen Darstellung der entsprechenden Symmetriegruppe gehören. Das Stapeln von Quantenpunkten wird auch im Zusammenhang mit dem Design von Halbleiterverstärkern und speziell ihrer Polarisationsunabhängigkeit benutzt. Die dabei zum Tragen kommenden physikalischen Mechanismen wurden aufgeklärt, und die sich mit der Stapelung ändernde Biaxialverspannung als Schlüsselelement identifiziert. Damit einher geht eine Änderung des Schwerloch/Leichtlochverhältnisses der Lochzustände, welche schlussendlich in eine Umkehrung der Absorption der TE -Mode im Verhältnis zur TM-Mode mündet. InAs Quantenpunkte, gewachsen auf InP anstatt auf GaAs, zeigen bei gleicher Geometrie eine ins Rote verschobenen Lumineszenz. Ursache dieses Verhaltens ist der vergleichsweise kleinere Unterschied in der Gitterkonstante und die daraus resultierende verminderte Verspannung. In dieser Arbeit wurden, angelehnt an experimentellen Arbeiten, flache kegelförmige Quantenpunkte in Abhängigkeit ihrer Höhe untersucht. Dabei wurde auch die Substratorientierung zwischen (100) und (311) variiert. Für den letzteren Fall führt das piezoelektrische Feld zur Aufhebung jeglicher Symmetrie des Einschlusspotentials und somit zur deutlichen Aktivierung vormals nahezu verbotener Übergänge. Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit wurde der Hamiltonoperator um die Möglichkeit erweitert, Magnetfelder beliebiger Ausrichtung zu berücksichtigen. Anhand von invertierten GaAs/AlGaAs QPten, wurden ausgiebige Testrechnungen durchgeführt, in denen zudem auch die Interfacerauhigkeit variiert wurde. Die Ergebnisse wurden mit Hochfeldmagnetmessungen verglichen und exzellente Übereinstimmung festgestellt.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Semiconductor quantum dots (QD) are fascinating physical subjects exhibiting electronic properties close to hydrogen in a dielectric cage, thus merging semiconductor with atomic physics. Their electronic properties, exciton and biexciton binding energies, exciton fine-structure splitting are strongly geometry dependent. Varying size, shape and composition are attractive and practical means to control the electronic and optical properties. Many applications are based on this discovery. Despite the tremendous advances in structural characterization techniques the real shape and composition of capped quantum dots (QD), which present the decisive input parameters for all modeling, are often only poorly known. Even the most sophisticated STM techniques either provide only cross sections of capped or surface images of uncapped QDs despite their atomic resolution. Therefore the purpose of this work is to identify those spectroscopic quantities that serve as a fingerprint for a specific QD structure, thus, addressing the inverse problem of fitting the spectroscopic data to the model and deriving the size, shape and composition as adjustable parameters. Eight band kp theory enables us to obtain the electronic structure thus taking into account arbitrary QD-shapes, as well as strain, piezoelectricity, and band mixing effects. The model provides, at reasonable computational cost, a fast and transparent relation between the electronic structure of QDs and bulk properties of the constituent materials. We present here systematic calculations of the single- and few-particle properties of many types of QDs, varying size, shape (square/circular/rhomboid base, different vertical/lateral aspect ratios) and composition (homogeneous/peaked and isotropic interdiffusion). Despite strain, first and second order piezoelectric effects are taken into account. Most of the recent work has been focused on single QDs. However, QD structures for applications are usually prepared as multi-layer, vertically stacked systems, since they have some advantageous properties such as a better homogeneity and higher active volume. Therefore, one chapter of this work is dedicated to the study of vertically stacked QDs. Their actual and potential applications are numerous, ranging from the mere increase of active media volume, over the creation of entangled photon pairs, for quantum information processing, the tailoring of the TE/TM mode intensity ratio of QD based semiconductur optical amplifiers, to the quantum dot cascade laser. The stacking of QDs can lead to the coupling of electronic states with the formation of binding and anti-binding states. The main parameters, that determine the onset of electronic coupling, are the inter-QD distance, the relative QD size, the symmetry of the overlapping single QD wavefunctions, and strain and piezoelectricity. To quantify the impact of these parameters, pairs of structurally identical and nonidentical QDs with varying spacer thickness and QD-shape are considered. Furthermore, external electric fields are applied to tune the resonance energies of the adjacent QDs. One of the biggest challenges for QD-laser-devices is to reach the 1.55 micrometer (0.8 eV) wavelength used for long-haul telecommunications. In the past the large efforts to push the InGaAs/GaAs system to this wavelength have been hampered by the large strain that accumulates in- and outside the QD-structure during the Stranski-Krastanow growth leading to a large increase of the local InAs band gap. Therefore, the most recent developments aimed at the reduction of strain in the system which can be achieved by introducing metamorphic buffers and thus replacing GaAs by InGaAs as matrix material close to the QD, or by turning to InP as a completely different host material which is employed in this case. Both approaches reduce the lattice mismatch and limit the strain in the QD-system. The smaller lattice mismatch, however, carries the danger of creating too large QDs during the epitaxy resulting in a small QD density and insufficient gain. This can be circumvented by using the (311)B substrate orientation, resulting in high QDs densities and low size dispersion permitting the development of low-thresholds QD lasers. In this work we theoretically investigate the impact of substrate orientation on the QDs optical properties, using the eight-band kp model including strain and piezoelectric effects, and demonstrate that the use of the (311)B substrate breaks the initial symmetry of the (100) system, thus modifying the optical properties of the QDs. Recently, unstrained GaAs/AlGaAs QDs were fabricated through an ingenious multistep approach based on a combination of hierarchical self-assembly and in situ etching. Photoluminescence (PL) of an ensemble of such QDs revealed an appreciably smaller inhomogeneous broadening, in the range between 8 to 15 meV depending on the growth conditions, indicating a good size homogenity. The QDs have a typical lateral size of \backsim 35nm and a thickness of about 6nm. We extend the previous theoretical studies based on eight-band kp theory taking into account the Zeeman effect. Single particle states, exciton binding energies and its diamagnetic shift are calculated for magnetic fields applied in growth direction as well as in the direction perpendicular to the growth direction. The calculations are based on a realistic confinement potential based on STM data. Furthermore, recent cross section scanning tunneling microscopy (X-STM) experiments demonstrate,that the interfaces between GaAs and AlGaAs layers are not abrupt as previously observed for quantum wells. Since the size and shape of the dots are known, the previously not discussed effect of this roughness on the electronic properties of the dots is investigated in detail. The overall intention of this work is to link the structural properties of QDs to their electronic and optical properties. Thus, as will be demonstrated in various examples, it becomes possible to derive the true 3D QD-morphology by their spectroscopic signature alone.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2007-07-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1549</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16070</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-16070</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1549/schliwa_andrei.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
