<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:57:21Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2838">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2838</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:530</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Structure and Reactivity of Diesel Soot Particles from Advanced Motor Technologies</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Struktur und Reaktivität von Ruß-Partikeln fortschrittlicher Dieselmotoren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schuster, Manfred Erwin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:530</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Diesel engine soot and other fine dust particles have been shown to be hazardous if they enter the human body, penetrate the lungs, and irritate lung tissue. These particles have been linked to the possible causes of lung cancer. Particle size and reactivity are important factors in this process. The smaller the particles, the further they can enter the lung system. More crucially, reactivity determines the environmental accessibility of such soot particles. This reactivity is defined by the microstructure of the system and the functionalization of carbon atoms, which is mainly determined by carbon-oxygen and carbon-hydrogen bonds. A systematic study of both bulk and surface characterization is missing in literature. The aim of this work is to determine the microstructure and reactivity of two soot models, namely two Emission Standards, Euro IV and Euro VI, by combining these surface and bulk sensitive techniques. As reference samples, soot, generated by spark discharge of graphite electrodes, served as model for atmospheric particles, Highly Ordered Pyrolytic Graphite (HOPG), Nanotubes (NC 3100) and Flammruss were used. HRTEM, SEM and EELS were used in this study for the bulk characterization of the microstructure and electronic structure of carbonaceous samples. Surface sensitive methods such as NEXAFS spectroscopy and XPS were applied to probe the surface species which affect the reactivity and toxicity of the particles. The Euro IV and Euro VI samples were subsequently subject to TPO, in which oxidation and heat experiment simulates a possible treatment in the exhaust system. The result of this treatment was compared to results for untreated samples in order to visualize the changes, to elucidate the structure-reactivity correlation, and establish a reaction scheme for the different soot samples. The main results obtained in this work are the following: 1. The microstructure of the Euro IV and VI samples is determined by an onion-like arrangement of the graphene layers, building up a "core-shell structure", with additional molecular-carbon units present on the surface of the Euro IV sample. 2. The microstructure of the Euro IV sample is altered by the oxidation treatment, resulting in a loss of this "disordered" carbon units on the surface, approaching a similar microstructure as the Euro VI sample, which did not alter its structural state as a result of the oxidation treatment. 3. The oxygen-surface functionalization differs significantly in amount and heterogeneity between the two samples. Additionally, the modifications of the oxygen-carbon bonds due to the oxidation treatment are also quite different. 4. The reactivity of the carbons shows a different starting point for combustion of the two samples and and a different combustion rate, which can be explained by the results obtained by the data gathered during this project. Two factors, much higher functionalization of the Euro VI sample and the conversion of less stable oxygen-functional groups to highly stable oxygen-functional groups during the oxidation treatment, explain the higher reactivity of this sample as well as its higher accessibility to the environment and subsequently a higher reactivity in the human body. Furthermore, oxidation and heat treatment have to occur in a much faster and higher temperature regime to ensure that soot particles undergo complete combustion before a restructuring of the soot samples can occur, thus hindering further combustion.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Dieselruße und andere Feinstaubpartikel können im Lungengewebe gesundheitsschädlich wirken. Rußpartikel im Lungenbereich sind ein möglicher Grund für Lungenkrebs. Teilchengröße und Reaktivität sind wichtige Faktoren für die Gesundheitsschädlichkeit dieser Partikel. Je kleiner die Teilchen sind, desto weiter können sie ins Lungengewebe eindringen. Die Oberflächenfunktionalisierung dieser Teilchen entscheidet dann wie stark die Reaktivität im Lungenbereich ist. In der vorgelegten Arbeit, wurde eine systematische Studie durchgeführt, um sowohl die Partikel als Ganzes, also auch die Oberflächenbeschaffenheit von zwei Standards, Euro IV und Euro VI, zu charakterisieren. Die Bindungszustände wurden mittels EELS untersucht, während die strukturelle Ordnung mittels HRTEM und SEM untersucht wurden. NEXAFS und XPS Untersuchungen gaben Aufschluss über die Oberflächenfunktionalisierung der Proben. Die Proben wurden weiters einer Testreaktion unterzogen, in der eine Behandlung im Auspuffsystem simuliert wurde. Danach wurden die Proben mit den unbehandelten verglichen und eine Struktur-Reaktivitätskorrelation hergestellt. Die Ergebnisse der Euro IV und Euro VI Proben wurden mit Referenzproben verglichen. Die grundlegenden Erkenntnisse dieser Studie sind: 1. Die Mikrostruktur der beiden Dieselruße ist durch eine Zwiebel-Struktur charakterisiert, wobei sich auf der Oberfläche der Euro IV Probe Oberfläche molekulare Kohlenstoffe befinden. 2. Die thermische Behandlung entfernt die molekularen Kohlenstoffe von der Euro IV Oberfläche und führt des weiteren zu einer höheren strukturellen Ordnung der Probe. 3. Die Euro VI Probe weist im Vergleich zu Euro IV eine signifikant höhere und heterogenere Sauerstoff-Funktionalisierung auf. 4. Die Reaktivitätsmessungen der beiden Proben mittels TPO zeigen ein unterschiedliches Verbrennungsverhalten, mit einer höheren Verbrennungstemperatur für die Euro VI Probe. Sobald der Verbrennungsprozess eingesetzt hat, verbrennt die Euro VI Probe stärker als die Euro IV Probe. Die höhere Reaktivität der Euro VI Probe erklärt sich durch die höhere Funktionalisierung mit Sauerstoff und durch die Umwandlung dieser Sauerstoffe während der Testreaktion von weniger stabilen zu thermisch stabileren Sauerstoffgruppen. Diese Studie hat auch gezeigt, dass eine Oxidations- und Hitzebehandlung mit höherer Temperatur notwendig ist, um eine Restrukturierung der Proben zu verhindern und damit komplette Verbrennung zu ermöglichen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-03-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2838</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29972</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-29972</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2838/schuster_manfred.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
