<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:05Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3629">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3629</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:520</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Search for Planetary Transits and Stellar Variability with BEST II and ASTEP</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Suche nach planetaren Transits und stellarer Variabilität mit BEST II und ASTEP</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fruth, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:520</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Two decades ago, the first evidence of planets orbiting stars other than our Sun opened a new field of astronomy and astrophysics. Today, more than 850 such extrasolar planets are known, and their detections have revealed a wide diversity regarding, e.g., the planetary size, mass, density, or orbital distance. As a result, more and more intriguing scientific questions can now be investigated quantitatively, while all previous knowledge was solely based upon our Solar System. The space mission CoRoT successfully applies the transit method to find new planets; it is supported, e.g., by the two Berlin Exoplanet Search Telescopes (BEST and BEST II) with ground-based photometric observations. The main aim of this thesis is to search for new exoplanets. Within this work, the first BEST II transit survey was planned, realized, and analyzed scientifically: During 138 nights in 2009/2010, three target fields were monitored. Optimizations of their selection, observations, the data pipeline, and transit search improved the expected detection yield significantly compared to previous BEST II surveys, and simulations suggest a reasonable chance for a detection. The sensitivity of the optimized BEST II system is competitive with leading ground-based surveys such as SuperWASP. Furthermore, this work aims to probe the potential for transit search from Antarctica. While previous studies indicate excellent conditions, it was yet to be shown whether a real transit survey can benefit from these in practice. In this work, first data from the ASTEP 400 telescope (Dome C) were analyzed, and parallel observations were obtained with BEST II (Chile) for a direct comparison. These show that ASTEP 400 achieves sub-mmag precision on favorable nights, but systematic effects still limit the overall photometric quality. However, within two weeks, ASTEP yields an observational coverage of planetary transits that is comparable to a whole season in Chile. An optimal performance is achieved when data from both sites are combined, which increases the detection yield by up to ~30%. Overall, 256,026 low-noise light curves have been analyzed for transiting planets. Using state-of-the-art procedures for detection and false alarm exclusion, 20 high-quality "hot Jupiter" candidates were identified (14 in BEST II, four in ASTEP, and two in combined time series). Eleven host stars were characterized spectroscopically, and radial velocity analyses were proposed to eventually confirm the planetary nature and derive masses of the two best candidates. These are important findings since they orbit early F-type dwarf stars, which are expected to host giant exoplanets more frequently than later types, but very few such systems are currently known. In addition, photometric data allow the study of stellar variability. New detections enable new and/or more detailed astrophysical studies (e.g., stellar interior models). This thesis presents a new method to decrease the false alarm rate in variable star searches significantly. It was recently published (Fruth et al. 2012) and applied successfully to five BEST II data sets: Out of 329,660 light curves analyzed here, 2,791 new and 806 suspected variable stars were found and classified, thus increasing the yield of BEST/BEST II by 258%. Where possible, the results were compared with other surveys such as CoRoT, and were found to be in excellent overall agreement.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Während vor etwa zwanzig Jahren der erste Planet außerhalb des Sonnensystems nachgewiesen wurde, so sind mittlerweile mehr als 850 solcher extrasolaren Planeten bekannt. Sie unterscheiden sich z.B. hinsichtlich ihrer Radien, Massen, Dichten und Bahneigenschaften sowohl untereinander als auch von den bisher bekannten Begleitern unserer Sonne und ermöglichen nun die quantitative Untersuchung einer Vielzahl alter und neuer wissenschaftlicher Fragestellungen. Die Weltraummission CoRoT sucht mithilfe der Transitmethode nach extrasolaren Planeten. Sie wird u.a. von den beiden "Berlin Exoplanet Search Telescopes" (BEST und BEST II) mit bodengebundenen photometrischen Beobachtungen unterstützt. Die Suche nach Exoplaneten stellt auch das primäre Ziel dieser Dissertation dar. In einer eigens geplanten BEST II Transitsuchkampagne wurden drei Sternfelder 2009/2010 insgesamt 138 Nächte lang beobachtet. Im Vergleich zu vorangegangenen BEST II Studien steigerten Verbesserungen in der Feldauswahl, der Datenauswertung, sowie des Beobachtungsumfangs die Leistungsfähigkeit des Systems erheblich. Simulationen zeigen, dass die Empfindlichkeit von BEST II vergleichbar mit führenden Projekten wie SuperWASP und eine erste Planetenentdeckung realistisch ist. Einen weiteren Schwerpunkt bildet eine Studie zu den Bedingungen der Transitsuche in der Antarktis. In dieser Arbeit wurden erste Daten des ASTEP 400 Teleskops (Dome C) analysiert und mit BEST II (Chile) verglichen. Die Analyse zeigt, dass ASTEP in einzelnen Nächten sub-mmag Präzision erzielt, aber systematische Effekte die photometrische Genauigkeit über die gesamte Kampagne limitieren. Die Polarnacht bewirkt während eines zweiwöchigen Beobachtungszeitraums eine gute Abdeckung kurzperiodischer Planeten, die in Chile nur während einer kompletten Saison erzielt wird. Optimal ist eine Kombination beider Standorte, wodurch bis zu ~30% mehr Entdeckungen erzielt werden können. Insgesamt wurden 256.026 hochpräzise Lichtkurven auf extrasolare Transitplaneten untersucht. Mithilfe aktueller Techniken zur Detektion konnten 20 sehr gute "heiße Jupiter" Kandidaten (14 in BEST II, vier in ASTEP und zwei in kombinierten Daten) identifiziert und von falsch-positiven Signalen abgegrenzt werden. Elf Sterne wurden bereits spektroskopisch klassifiziert, und die besten zwei Kandidaten wurden für Nachfolgebeobachtungen vorgeschlagen, um ihre Masse zu bestimmen und den Planetenstatus zu bestätigen bzw. zu widerlegen. Dies sind wichtige Entdeckungen, da die Sterne frühe F-Zwerge sind: Bei diesen erwartet man häufiger Riesenplaneten als bei sonnenähnlichen Sternen, kennt aber bisher nur sehr wenige solcher Systeme. Photometrische Zeitreihen werden zudem auf Variabilität untersucht, da die Entdeckung variabler Sterne neue bzw. genauere astrophysikalische Studien ermöglicht. Diese Arbeit präsentiert eine Methode, die die Suche nach variablen Sternen in photometrischen Daten signifikant verbessert. Sie wurde bereits veröffentlicht (Fruth et al. 2012) und erfolgreich auf fünf BEST II Datensätze angewandt: In 329.660 Lichtkurven wurden 2.791 variable und 806 mutmaßlich variable Sterne entdeckt und klassifiziert, wodurch die Anzahl der mit BEST/BEST II identifizierten Variablen um 258% ansteigt. Die Ergebnisse stimmen sehr gut mit vergleichbaren Studien überein.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-02-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3629</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38623</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-38623</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3629/fruth_thomas.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
