<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:53Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2087">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2087</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Integration and Management of Multiple Radio Access Technologies in Converged Wireless Networks</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Integration und Verwaltung verschiedener Funkzugangstechniken in konvergierten Mobilfunknetzen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sachs, Joachim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Wireless communication networks enable customers to use communication services – like telephony or Internet services – at anytime and anywhere. A multitude of varying radio access technologies has been developed or is currently being developed. Those access technologies have different characteristics: they differ in their radio coverage, their spectral efficiency, cell capacity, and peak data rate; they can support different services; some support user mobility; they differ in their complexity and costs. For a network operator different radio access technologies may best be suited in different parts of the network, depending on the radio environment, the expected traffic pattern, and the anticipated services. The dynamic selection of access technology according to the communication requirements and network characteristics enable end users to be always best connected. Therefore, it is desirable to allow various access technologies to be combined in a common network and to allow interworking of different networks to be possible, even when they deploy different access technologies. The integration of multiple heterogeneous access technologies into a common network is referred to as network convergence. In this work we investigate technical solutions for integrating and managing different access technologies in a converged network and derive suitable network architectures. We define three types of functionality that are required for multi-access management: access monitoring, access selection and access handover. Access selection is the functionality that evaluates different accesses in order to determine which one is best suited for a certain communication session. This decision can be based on a number of parameters, like the characteristics of the radio link, the availability of resources in the different access systems, the requirements of the service, or policies of the user or network operator, which may depend on the business arrangement that the user has agreed to with the network operator. Access selection is performed by one or more multi-radio resource management functions which are typically located in multiple network nodes. Based on system simulations we evaluate the gain that can be achieved by access selection for different types of radio access technologies, radio network layouts, user distributions, and access selection algorithms. We show that the capacity gain of the system depends strongly on the considered scenario; in most cases significant gain can be achieved by access selection. We furthermore develop a model of a multi-access system that allows the system capacity to be derived analytically. Access monitoring it is the process of deriving useful information about accesses; it is a prerequisite for access selection. We present generic access abstractions that provide information about different accesses in a generic and comparable form. A generic link layer derives such abstracted information from access technology specific parameters. The generic abstractions provide information about the performance, as well as the resource situation for each access. The process of access monitoring depends on the connectivity state of a user terminal. Some types of information about an access system can be derived by making local measurements and observing access system information that is broadcasted in beacon signals; other types of information require that first a connection is established to the access system and the user terminal is attached to the network. We present different solutions on how suitable information about access systems can be obtained by the user terminal in different connectivity states. We develop a new network attachment mechanism that allows embedding access system information in the connectivity setup and network attachment procedure. We analyse this integrated network attachment procedure in a scenario where users evaluate surrounding WLAN networks; we show that the amount of signalling overhead and the time spent to evaluate the WLAN network can be significantly reduced. Once the available accesses are evaluated and a best suited access has been determined an access handover may be required, that redirects the service data flow of a session to the new access. We present several different solutions how an access handover can be performed. Generic link layer functions enable to establish a required communication context quickly in the new access system in order to avoid data distortion and service degradation. We evaluate and compare several access handover schemes based on alternative forms of context transfer for services based on the transmission control protocol (TCP). We show that context transfer schemes can provide a significant performance gain during access handover; this gain depends on the link layer characteristics of the old and new access system.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Drahtlose Kommunikationsnetze erlauben Endnutzern jeder Zeit und an jedem Ort von Kommunikationsdiensten Gebrauch zu machen. Dabei existiert eine Vielzahl von Funkzugangstechniken, weitere werden entwickelt. Funkzugangstechniken unterscheiden sich beispielsweise in Reichweite und Abdeckung, ihrer spektralen Effizienz, Kapazität und maximalen Datenrate, in ihrer Komplexität und ihren Kosten, zudem unterstützen sie verschiedene Dienste und gestatten dem Nutzer Mobilität in unterschiedlichem Umfang. Je nach Funkumgebung, erwartetem Verkehrsaufkommen und den in Anspruch genommenen Diensten sind für den Netzbetreiber lokal unterschiedliche Funkzugangstechniken jeweils die geeignetsten. Eine dynamische Auswahl des Funkzugangssystems anhand der Kommunikationsanforderungen und des Netzzustands ermöglicht gleichzeitig, dass Endnutzer allzeit bestmöglich angebunden sind. Deshalb ist es erstrebenswert, mehrere Funkzugangstechniken in ein einheitliches Kommunikationsnetz zu integrieren (sogenannte Netzkonvergenz) und ein Zusammenspiel verschiedener Kommunikationsnetze mit unterschiedlichen Funkzugangstechniken zu ermöglichen. Diese Arbeit untersucht technische Lösungen der Netzkonvergenz einschliesslich der dazu erforderlichen Verwaltungsaufgaben und geeigneter Netzarchitekturen. Sie definiert dabei drei grundlegende Funktionen zur Verwaltung mehrerer Funkzugangstechniken: die Funkzugangswahl, die Funkzugangsüberwachung und den Funkzugangswechsel. Die Funkzugangswahl beurteilt und vergleicht verschiedene Funkzugangssysteme und bestimmt, welches als geeignetstes für die jeweilige Kommunikationsverbindung zu nutzen ist. Die Entscheidung kann auf einer Vielfalt von Parametern beruhen, wie z.B. Eigenschaften der Funkverbindung, Verfügbarkeit von Ressourcen in den einzelnen Funkzugangssystemen oder Dienstanforderungen. Durchgeführt wird die Funkzugangswahl von einer oder mehreren Multifunkverwaltungsfunktionen (multi-radio resource management). Anhand von Systemsimulationen wurde gezeigt, dass durch eine dynamische Funkzugangswahl in den meisten Szenarien ein deutlicher Mehrwert erzielt werden kann. Die entscheidenden Systemparameter sind dabei die vorhandenen Funkzugangstechniken, der Funknetzplan, die geographischen Nutzerverteilung und verschiedene Algorithmen der Funknetzwahl. Eine Funkzugangswahl erfordert eine Funkzugangsüberwachung, um Informationen über die vorhandenen Funkzugangssysteme zu erhalten. Voraussetzung hierzu ist zunächst, verschiedene Funkzugangssysteme in einer generischen und vergleichbaren Form bewerten zu können. Dies leistet eine generische Verbindungsschicht (generic link layer), die aufgrund von funkzugangsspezifischen Metriken eine allgemeine Beschreibungsform liefert. Wie welche der erforderlichen Informationen nun erlangt werden, hängt von dem Verbindungszustand des Endgerätes ab. Ohne Netzverbindung kann ein Endgerät bereits lokale Messungen durchführen oder diese vom Zugangsnetz in Pilotkanälen erhalten. Andere Arten von Information erfordern, dass das Endgerät eine Verbindung zu dem Funkzugangssystem aufgebaut hat und dort angemeldet ist. In der Arbeit werden verschiedene Lösungen aufgezeigt, wie Informationen über ein Funkzugangssystem in verschiedenen Verbindungszuständen von einem Endgerät ermittelt werden können. Ein neues Anschlussverfahren erlaubt, unterschiedliche Informationen über das Zugangssystem in die Prozeduren des Verbindungsaufbaus und anschlusses zu integrieren. Dieses Anschlussverfahren wird in einem Szenario untersucht, in dem die Endgeräte der Nutzer umliegende WLAN-Funkzugangssysteme bewerten. Demnach kann sowohl der Aufwand an Signalisierung als auch die Zeit, die benötigt ist, um eine WLAN-Funkzugangssystem zu bewerten, deutlich reduziert werden. Die Zugangswahl kann bestimmen, eine Datenverbindung auf ein neues Zugangssystem zu übertragen. Ein solcher Funkzugangswechsel ist auf verschiedene Arten zu realisieren. Ein mögliches Problem dabei kann die Verzerrung der übertragenen Daten darstellen. Für Dienste, die auf dem Übertragungssteuerungsprotokoll (TCP) basieren, wurde dies gezeigt und die Abhängigkeit von den Eigenschaften der Verbindungsschicht des alten und neuen Zugangs untersucht. Durch verschiedene Methoden der Kontextübertragung kann ein größerer Verlust an Dienstgüte verhindert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/zip</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2087</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2087/original_sachs_joachim.zip</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2087/sachs_joachim.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
