<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:43Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2453">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2453</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">On the Wake of an Inclined Circular Cylinder</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Über den Nachlauf eines angestellten Kreiszylinders</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Taubert, Lutz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">This work evolved from a feasibility study targeted at a specific application: the control of a refuelling boom. Presently, the attitude of the refuelling boom on tanker airplanes, basically a finite cylinder with pitch and yaw, is adjusted by means of control surfaces extending from the boom. These control surfaces are bulky and very sensitive to damage by unintended contact with the tanker itself or the refuelling airplanes. Preliminary experiments were carried out on a relative simple model to evaluate the potential to alternatively control the attitude of the refuelling boom by altering lift and drag of this finite inclined cylinder by means of active flow control. The results were very promising. Based on these findings, a detailed investigation was carried out to improve the understanding of the general problem of the flow past an inclined cylinder, in particular with application of active flow control. The forces on the cylinder were determined by pressure measurements on the surface and in the far wake to obtain easily comparable quantitative results. To gain a better insight into the vortex dynamics in this complex three-dimensional flow, focus was put on the coherent structures in the near wake of an infinite inclined cylinder and their interaction with it. Substantial lift was generated by applying periodic zero-mass-flux excitation asymmetrically from a single slot running along the span of the cylinder. Excitation from two slots located symmetrically on the circumference of the cylinder reduced the form drag significantly. Lift and drag were altered independently of each other by adjusting the level of excitation differently on both sides of the cylinder. This proves that the full control of a refuelling boom by active flow control is possible, eliminating the necessity of protruding control surfaces that are easily damaged. A POD based technique was developed for the dynamic analysis of the flow field in the near wake. It revealed the complexity of the coherent structures and their dynamics close to the cylinder. Considerable fluctuations of the positions of the coherent structures were identified, in radial as well as in azimuthal direction. These fluctuations were suppressed at higher levels of excitation, reducing the unsteady loads significantly. As inclined circular cylinders are found in many engineering applications the so enabled active damping of flow induced oscillations could prove to be very useful to greatly reduce the risks of structural failure due to fatigue.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Diese Arbeit begann mit einer Machbarkeitsstudie über die potentielle Nutzung aktiver Strömungskontrolle für die Lagekontrolle eines Tankrüssels für die Luftbetankung, der vereinfachend als angestellter Kreiszylinder betrachtet werden kann. Die Vorversuche an einem einfachen Modell wurden sehr erfolgreich abgeschlossen. Daran anschließend wurde eine grundlegende Untersuchung der Umströmung eines unendlichen angestellten Kreiszylinders mit aktiver Strömungskontrolle durchgeführt. Druckverteilungen um den Zylinder und im fernen Nachlauf wurden zur Bestimmung der auf den Zylinder wirkenden Kräfte aufgenommen, der Schwerpunkt dieser Arbeit lag allerdings auf den kohärenten Strukturen im nahen Nachlauf. Die Analyse dieser Strukturen ermöglichte ein tieferes Verständnis der Wirbeldynamik in dieser komplexen dreidimensionalen Strömung. Die Anwendung von asymmetrischer periodischer zero-mass-flux Anregung durch einen einzelnen Schlitz entlang des Zylinders erzeugte deutlichen Auftrieb, die Anregung über zwei symmetrisch auf dem Umfang angeordnete Schlitze reduzierte den Formwiderstand merklich. Auftrieb und Widerstand konnten durch Anregung mit unterschiedlicher Stärke auf beiden Seiten des Zylinders unabhängig voneinander variiert werden. Dies beweist, dass die Kontrolle eines Tankrüssels mittels aktiver Strömungskontrolle möglich wäre und dadurch der Einsatz von hervorstehenden und deshalb leicht zu beschädigenden Kontrollflächen vermieden werden könnte. Die im Laufe dieser Arbeit entwickelte POD-basierte dynamische Analyse des Strömungsfeldes im nahen Nachlauf enthüllte die Komplexität der kohärenten Strukturen und ihrer Dynamik nahe des Zylinders. Deutliche Fluktuationen der Positionen der kohärenten Strukturen konnten sowohl in radialer als auch in Umfangsrichtung nachgewiesen werden. Diese Fluktuationen wurden bei grösserer Anregungsstärke unterdrückt und damit die auf den Zylinder wirkenden Wechselbelastungen deutlich reduziert. Da angestellte runde Zylinder in vielen technischen Anwendungen vorkommen, könnte sich die so mögliche aktive Dämpfung strömungsinduzierter Schwingungen als sehr nützlich für die Reduzierung von Strukturversagen durch Ermüdung erweisen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-03-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2453</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25773</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25773</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2453/taubert_lutz.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
