<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:32Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3744">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3744</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Quantitative Evaluation of Ultrasonic Wave Propagation in Inhomogeneous Anisotropic Austenitic Welds using 3D Ray Tracing Method : Numerical and Experimental Validation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Quantitative Betrachtung der Ausbreitung von Ultraschallwellen in inhomogen anisotropen austenitischen Schweißnähten unter Verwendung eines 3D Ray Tracing Verfahrens : numerische und experimentelle Validierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kolkoori, Sanjeevareddy</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Austenitic welds and dissimilar welds are extensively used in primary circuit pipes and pressure vessels in nuclear power plants, chemical industries and fossil fuelled power plants because of their high fracture toughness, resistance to corrosion and creep at elevated temperatures. However, cracks may initiate in these weld materials during fabrication process or stress operations in service. Thus, it is very important to evaluate the structural integrity of these materials using highly reliable non-destructive testing (NDT) methods. Ultrasonic non-destructive inspection of austenitic welds and dissimilar weld components is complicated because of anisotropic columnar grain structure leading to beam splitting and beam deflection. Simulation tools play an important role in developing advanced reliable ultrasonic testing (UT) techniques and optimizing experimental parameters for inspection of austenitic welds and dissimilar weld components. The main aim of the thesis is to develop a 3D ray tracing model for quantitative evaluation of ultrasonic wave propagation in an inhomogeneous anisotropic austenitic weld material. Inhomogenity in the anisotropic weld material is represented by discretizing into several homogeneous layers. According to ray tracing model, ultrasonic ray paths are traced during its energy propagation through various discretized layers of the material and at each interface the problem of reflection and transmission is solved. The influence of anisotropy on ultrasonic reflection and transmission behaviour in an anisotropic austenitic weld material are quantitatively analyzed in three dimensions. The ultrasonic beam directivity in columnar grained austenitic steel material is determined three dimensionally using Lamb’s reciprocity theorem. The developed ray tracing model evaluates the transducer excited ultrasonic fields accurately by taking into account the directivity of the transducer, divergence of the ray bundle, density of rays and phase relations as well as transmission coefficients. The ray tracing model is able to determine the ultrasonic wave fields generated by a point source as well as finite dimension array transducers. The influence of inhomogenity on ultrasonic ray propagation and its interaction with defects in inhomogeneous austenitic welds is presented. The applications of 3D ray tracing model for optimizing experimental parameters during the ultrasonic non-destructive testing of transversal cracks in austenitic welds are presented. An ultrasonic C-scan image in homogeneous and multi-layered anisotropic austenitic steel materials is quantitatively evaluated using a novel 3D ray tracing method. The influence of the columnar grain orientation and the layback orientation on an ultrasonic C-scan image is presented. The ray tracing model results are validated first time quantitatively with the results obtained from 2D Elastodynamic Finite Integration Technique (EFIT) on several important configurations such as anisotropic and homogeneous austenitic steel material, layered austenitic steel material and austenitic weld material which are generally occurring in the ultrasonic non-destructive testing of anisotropic materials. Quantitatively a deviation of 8.6% was observed in the point source generated ultrasonic fields whereas in the case of array source ultrasound fields a deviation of 10.2% was observed. The predicted ultrasonic fields for array transducers in an inhomogeneous austenitic weld material with spatially varying columnar grain orientation using ray tracing method are validated against the results of a commercially available NDT simulation tool (CIVA). The result shows that an accuracy of 89.5% was achieved in the presented ray tracing model in this thesis. Experiments have been conducted on 32 mm thick inhomogeneous austenitic weld material, 62 mm thick austenitic clad material and quantitatively measured the ultrasound beam distortion and field profiles using electrodynamical probes. The inhomogenity in the weld material is modeled based on the Ogilvy’s empirical relation. The weld parameters are optimized in the empirical relation such a way that to match with the macrograph of the real life austenitic weld specimen. The ultrasound beam propagation and field profiles are accurately computed using ray tracing model. The simulated ultrasound field profiles using ray tracing model along the back wall of an austenitic weld component and clad material are compared quantitatively with the experimental results. It turned out that the deviation between simulation and experiments was about 5.2% in the isotropic austenitic material, 16.5% in the austenitic weld material and 5.46% in the austenitic clad material. Finally, the reasons for differences between simulation and experimental results are explored.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Austenitische Schweißnähte und Mischnähte werden aufgrund ihrer hohen Bruchfestigkeit und ihres Widerstands gegen Korrosion und Risswachstum bei hohen Temperaturen bevorzugt in Rohrleitungen und Druckbehältern von Kernkraftwerken, Anlagen der chemischen Industrie und Kohlekraftwerken eingesetzt. Während des Herstellungsprozesses oder durch im Betrieb auftretende mechanische Spannungen können sich jedoch Risse bilden, weshalb die Überwachung des Zustandes dieser Materialien unter Einsatz zuverlässiger zerstörungsfreier Prüfmethoden von großer Wichtigkeit ist. Die zerstörungsfreie Ultraschallprüfung austenitischer Schweißnähte und Mischnähte wird durch anisotrope Stängelkristallstrukturen erschwert, welche zur Teilung und Ablenkung des Schallbündels führen können. Simulationsprogramme spielen in der Entwicklung fortschrittlicher Prüfverfahren und der Optimierung der Parameter für die Prüfung derartiger Schweißnähte eine bedeutende Rolle. Das Hauptziel dieser Dissertation besteht in der Entwicklung eines 3D Ray-Tracing Modells zur quantitativen Auswertung der Ultraschallwellenausbreitung in inhomogenen anisotropen Füllmaterialien von Schweißnähten. Die Inhomogenität der Schweißnähte wird durch eine Diskretisierung in mehrere homogene Schichten abgebildet. Gemäß des Ray-Tracing Modells, werden die Strahlverläufe des Ultraschalls im Sinne der Energieausbreitung durch die verschiedenen Schichten verfolgt und an jeder Grenzfläche Reflexion und Transmission berechnet. Der Einfluss der Anisotropie auf das Reflexions- und Transmissionsverhalten von Ultraschall in austenitischen Schweißnähten wird quantitativ in allen drei Raumrichtungen untersucht. Die Richtcharakteristik von Ultraschallquellen in der Stängelkristallstruktur austenitischer Stähle, wird dabei im dreidimensionalen Fall durch das Lamb'sche Reziprozitätsgesetz bestimmt. Das Ray-Tracing Modell ist im Stande sowohl die von einer Punktquelle, als auch die von einem ausgedehntem Phased-Array Prüfkopf erzeugten Schallfelder zu bestimmen. Der Einfluss der Inhomogenität auf die Ultraschallausbreitung und die Wechselwirkung des Schallfeldes mit Materialfehlern in austenitischen Schweißnähten sowie die Anwendung des 3D-Ray-Tracing Modells zur Optimierung experimenteller Parameter während der zerstörungsfreien Ultraschallprüfung auf Querfehler in austenitischen Schweißnähten werden dargestellt. Der Einfluss der Stängelkristallstruktur und des Layback-Winkels auf Ultraschall-C-Bilder in der praktischen Prüfung anisotroper Materialen wird dargestellt. Die Ergebnisse des Ray-Tracing Modells werden quantitativ gegen Ergebnisse validiert, die mit der 2D Elastodynamic Finite Integration Technique (EFIT) an verschiedenen wichtigen Testfällen, wie anisotropem und homogenem austenitischen Stahl, Schichtstrukturen aus austenitischen Stählen und Schweißnahtstrukturen gewonnen wurden, welche in der Praxis der zerstörungsfreien Ultraschallprüfung anisotroper Materialien auftreten. Dabei wird festgestellt, dass die Abweichungen von der Ultraschallquelle abhängen. Quantitative betragen diese 8,6% für die punktquelle und 10,2% für die Phased-Array Prüfköpfe. Die unter Verwendung des Ray-Tracing Verfahrens gewonnenen Vorhersagen über Schallfelder für Phased-Array Prüfköpfe in einem inhomogenem, anisotropen Schweißnahtmaterial mit räumlich veränderlicher Stängelkristallstruktur, werden gegen die Ergebnisse einer kommerziellen Simulationssoftware (CIVA) validiert. Mit dem Ray-Tracing Model wird eine Übereinstimmung von 89,5% erzielt. Experimente wurden an 32 mm hohen austenitischen Schweißnähten und 62 mm dicken plattierten Testkörpern durchgeführt, wobei die Verzerrung und das Profil der Ultraschallfelder mit Hilfe einer elektrodynamischen Sonde quantitativ bestimmt wurden. Die Inhomogenität der Schweißnahtstruktur wurde basierend auf den von Ogilvy gefundenen empirischen Formeln modelliert. Die Modellparameter wurden dabei dahingehend optimiert, dass die Modellstruktur eine möglichst gute Übereinstimmung mit dem Schliffbild der realen Schweißnaht im verwendeten Testkörper liefert. Die mittels Ray-Tracing Verfahren entlang der Unterseite eines Testkörpers mit austenitischer Schweißnaht und austenitischer Pufferung simulierten Profile der Ultraschallfelder, werden quantitativ mit den experimentellen Daten verglichen. Für die Simulation ergib sich eine Abweichung von 5,2% für das isotropische austenitische Material, 16,5% für die austenitische Schweißnaht und 5,46% für das austenitische plattierte Material gegenüber den experimentellen Ergebnissen. Abschließend werden die Unterschiede zwischen der Simulation und den experimentellen Ergebnissen erläutert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-05-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3744</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40065</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-40065</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3744/kolkoori_sanjeevareddy.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
