<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3283">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3283</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Electronic Properties of ALD Zinc Oxide Interfaces and its Implication for Chalcopyrite Absorber Materials</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Elektronische Eigenschaften von ALD Zinkoxid Grenzflächen und deren Auswirkungen auf Chalkopyrit Absorber Materialien</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Janocha, Eike</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">With its capacity as a transparent conductive oxide (TCO), zinc oxide (ZnO) is currently used in a wide field of applications, for instance as the front contact in thin-film solar cells. Nowadays, in thin-film chalcopyrite solar cells the heterojunction with the p-doped chalcopyrite absorber is formed by a thin n-type cadmium sulfide buffer layer. Due to environmental considerations and due to disadvantages in the deposition process, it is desirable to replace the cadmium sulfide layer by an alternative Cd-free buffer material. To understand the processes at the interface in detail, well-defined single-crystalline chalcopyrite absorber films in the technologically relevant (112) orientation are used. Onto these absorber layers, ZnO was then grown onto the layers by atomic layer deposition (ALD). Due to its unique self-limiting growth mode, ALD allows a controlled deposition of single ZnO monolayers. In this work a UHV-compatible ALD deposition chamber was designed, assembled and commissioned. A constant deposition rate of 3.0 Å/cycle was determined in a temperature regime between 200 − 225 °C, the so-called ALD window. The electronic and chemical properties of the interfaces were investigated by means of X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS), ultraviolet photoelectron spectroscopy (UPS) and synchrotron-radiation photoelectron spectroscopy (SR-PES) at the BESSY II facility. Auger parameter analysis of the initial growth of ALD-ZnO on CuInSe2 (112) and comparison to reference samples indicates the formation of an intrinsic ZnIn2Se4 (ZISe) boundary layer having a thickness of only one monolayer. Combined XPS and UPS analysis allows the investigation of the electronic properties of the CuInSe2|ZnIn2Se4|ZnO heterostructure, resulting in a detailed picture of the band alignment at the interfaces. Furthermore, this thesis presents a new water-free ALD process for ZnO deposition using metal-organic diethylzinc (DEZn) and molecular oxygen (O2) as reacting precursors. Zinc oxide films usually show significant n-type doping and it is commonly stated that intrinsic point defects as well as interstitial hydrogen atoms play a major role in the doping mechanism. To reduce the amount of hydrogen in the ZnO, an alternative oxygen precursor to H2O was introduced and successful atomic layer deposition was demonstrated. The ALD window of the water-free ALD process is shifted slightly towards lower temperatures, located between 185 − 210 °C and a growth rate of 5.0 Å/cycle was observed. This significant increase indicates a completely different reaction mechanism not limited by steric hindrance effects of the ethyl ligands as in case of standard ALD of ZnO. A detailed comparison of two ZnO films deposited with both, water-free ALD and the standard precursor combination is presented. Both show an additional oxygen photoemission peak that is assigned to a surface hydroxide in the case of H2O-ALD and a O22- dumbbell defect in the case of water-free ALD. Additional non-destructive photoemission depth-profiling and annealing experiments do not show further significant differences in the chemical and electronic properties of both ZnO films.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Zinkoxid (ZnO) in seiner Eigenschaft als transparenter elektrischer Leiter wird heute in vielen Anwendungen eingesetzt, beispielsweise als Frontkontakt für Dünnschicht-Solarzellen. Dort wird der Heteroübergang zwischen dem p-dotierten Chalkopyrit Absorber heutzutage noch mit einer dünnen Schicht aus n-CdS erzeugt. Da es wünschenswert wäre das Schwermetall Cadmium sowohl aus Umweltaspekten, als auch aufgrund unvorteilhafter Produktionsbedingungen zu vermeiden, sind in den letzten Jahren starke Forschungsanstrengungen in dem Feld sogenannter alternativer Pufferschichten zu vermerken. Um die Prozesse an der Grenzfläche des Absorbers im Detail zu verstehen werden in dieser Arbeit einkristalline Chalkopyrit Absorber in der technologisch relevanten (112) Kristallorientierung hergestellt und verwendet. Auf diese Absorber wurde ZnO mittels Atomic Layer Deposition (ALD) gewachsen. ALD hat den Vorteil, dass durch sein selbstlimitierenden Wachstumsmodus einzelne ZnO Monolagen definiert abgeschieden werden können. Dafür wurde eine UHV-kompatible ALD Anlage aufgebaut und in Betrieb genommen. In einem Temperaturbereich zwischen 200 − 225 °C, dem sogenannten ALD Fenster, wurde eine konstante Wachstumsrate von 3,0 Å/Zyklus bestimmt. Untersucht wurden die chemischen und elektrischen Eigenschaften der Grenzfläche mittels Röntgen-, Ultraviolett- und und Synchrotron-Photoelektronenspektroskopie am BESSY II. Eine Analyse des Auger Parameters während des initiellen Wachstums von ALD-ZnO auf CuInSe2 (112) und der Vergleich mit Referenzproben deutet auf die Bildung einer intrinsischen ZnIn2Se4 Grenzschicht hin, welche eine Dicke von nur einer Monolage aufweist. Die Kombination aus XPS und UPS erlaubt die Untersuchung der elektronischen Eigenschaften der CuInSe2|ZnIn2Se4|ZnO Heterostruktur und liefert ein detailliertes Bild der elektronischen Bandanpassung an den jeweiligen Grenzflächen. Zudem wird in dieser Arbeit ein neuer wasserfreier ALD Prozess zur ZnO Abscheidung mittels Diethylzink (DEZn) und molekularem Sauerstoff (O2) präsentiert. ZnO zeigt üblicherweise eine starke n-Dotierung, hervorgerufen durch intrinsische Punktdefekte, sowie von Wasserstoff-Zwischengitteratomen. Um den Wasserstoff-Anteil im ZnO zu reduzieren wurde ein alternativer Sauerstoff-Lieferant zum H2O benutzt und der erfolgreiche ALD Prozess gezeigt. Das ALD Fenster der wasserfreien ALD ist leicht zu niederigeren Temperaturen verschoben (185 − 210 °C) und zeigt eine Wachstumsrate von 5,0 Å/Zyklus. Der Anstieg deutet auf einen grundlegend unterschiedlichen Reaktionsprozess hin, der nicht durch sterische Hinderung der Ethyl-Liganden limitiert wird. Im Vergleich beider Methoden zeigt sich, dass beide ZnO Filme jeweils eine zusätzliche Sauerstoff-Komponenten aufweisen. Im H2O-ALD Prozess wird diese durch eine Hydroxid-Oberflächenkomponente erzeugt, wohingegen der Ursprung beim wasserfreien ALD Prozess ein O22− dumbbell Defekt ist. Zerstörungsfreie Photoemissions-Tiefenprofilierung zeigen keine weiteren wesentlichen Unterschiede der chemischen und elektronischen Eigenschaften beider ZnO Schichten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-04-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3283</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34818</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34818</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3283/janocha_eike.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
