<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:05Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2987">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2987</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Driver Mental States Monitoring Based on Brain Signals</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Fahrerzustandserkennung Basierend auf Signalen des Gehirns</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lei, Shengguang</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Research of automotive human factors becomes increasingly important for improving the traffic safety. In light of human-centred design, a newly proposed concept, adaptive task allocation (ATA), is supposed. The ATA suggests an adaptive regulation of the task demands upon human operators according to their workload states, which can be assessed using various psychophysiological signals. This dissertation focuses on driver adaptive task allocation, based on the Electroencephalogram (EEG) signals. However, for such a concept, three basic issues should be addressed. Firstly, more theoretical frameworks for ATA should be developed. Although there is a widely accepted theoretical models existing, such a model fails to provide a solution when workload and task demand are dissociated. Secondly, a fundamental issue is how to reliably assess driver’s workload in real-time. Although various methods have been applied to evaluate workload, there is still a lack of a well-accepted approach for online workload detection. Thirdly, the EEG-based adaptive task allocation is actually a new topic. So far, there is still a lack of evidence supporting the feasibility of such a concept in driving context. This dissertation focuses intensively on these three research questions. Firstly, a theoretical model, demand-workload-matched ATA (DWM-ATA), is proposed in the chapter 2. As an extension of the existing model, DWM-ATA suggests to use workload and task demand to determine the regulation of task allocation. Secondly, in order to develop a computational model for workload quantification, two laboratory studies were conducted to investigate workload associated variation of EEG parameters, including both ERPs components (e.g. P300) and band powers (e.g. theta power and alpha power). The motivation of the first study (chapter 3) is to find out which kind of parameters (ERPs or band powers) is more robust for workload assessment. The second study (chapter 4) is to investigate the changes of band powers with task combination, since in reality driver’s workload is frequently contributed by the combined effect of different subtasks. Based on the results from these two studies, a logistic function model (LFM) was proposed in chapter 5. This model enables to combine EEG theta power and alpha power into a unified workload score with a range of [0 1]. Finally, a study investigating the feasibility of ATA in driving context was conducted in a simulated driving environment (chapter 6). The DWM-ATA model and LFM were applied in this study. The results from these experiments demonstrated that EEG is a useful tool for workload assessment. Both ERPs and band powers could be used for workload assessment. For instance, the amplitude of P300 decreased with workload; the frontal theta power increased and parietal alpha decreased as the workload increased. However, band powers showed higher robustness for continuous workload assessment. The investigation of band powers with two combined workload dimensions indicated that workload variation in different dimension may contribute to the changes of theta power and alpha power differently and therefore it was concluded that single theta and alpha power could not represent workload completely, which raised the needs of a method to combine both parameters for workload assessment. The results applying LFM showed that LFM is efficient for workload quantification and beneficial for the application of ATA. Finally, the final validation study indicates that the EEG-based ATA is beneficial for reducing the driver’s workload and improving driver’s performance in high task demand condition. Results from this study also addressed the needs of the theoretical DWM-ATA model. In this dissertation, the topic of driver adaptive task allocation underwent multifaceted investigations which ranged from theory to methodology to validation. Such a research would be beneficial for solving the human factors issues associating with the new in-vehicle technologies. The significance of this dissertation lies also on its potential application in the human-centred design of intelligent vehicle in the future.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Erforschung der menschlichen Faktoren in Fahrzeug wird immer wichtiger für die Verbesserung der Sicherheit im Straßenverkehr. 'Adaptive Task Allocation' (ATA) ist ein neu entwickeltes Konzept aus dem Bereich des Mensch-zentrierten Designs und stellt eine Lösung für wichtige Problemstellungen des menschlichen Faktors dar. Die ATA schlägt eine adaptive Regulierung der Aufgabenanforderungen basierend auf dem mentalen Zustand des Menschen vor. Dieser kann anhand verschiedener psychophysiologischer Signale bewertet werden. Die vorliegende Dissertation konzentriert sich auf die Erkennung von mentaler Beanspruchung und die adaptive Aufgabenzuweisung bei Autofahrern mit Hilfe des Elektroenzephalogramms (EEG). Zunächst müssen für solch ein Konzept drei grundlegende Fragen gestellt werden. Erstens sollte eine umfassendere Theorie für ATA entwickelt werden. Zweitens ist eine grundlegende Frage wie die mentale Beanspruchung zuverlässig beurteilen werden sollte. Drittens ist die ATA mittels EEG im Fahrzeug ein neues Forschungsfeld. Daher gibt es bislang immer noch einen mangelhafte Evidenz für die Umsetzbarkeit eines solchen Konzepts. Diese Dissertation konzentriert sich intensiv auf die drei beschriebenen Fragestellungen. In Kapitel 2 wird ein theoretisches Modell, Demand-Workload-Matched ATA (DWM-ATA), aufgestellt. Als Erweiterung des bestehenden ATA- Modells schlägt DWM-ATA vor, die Bestimmung der Aufgabenzuweisung der Aufgabenanforderung und der mentalen Beanspruchung anzupassen. Zweitens wurden zwei Studien durchgeführt, um ein Berechnungsmodell zur Quantifizierung der mentalen Beanspruchung zu entwickeln. Sowohl Event-Related-Potentials (ERP) Komponenten (Z.B., P300) als auch EEG-Frequenzbänder (z.B., Theta, Alpha und Beta) wurden erforscht. Die Motivation der ersten Studie (Kapitel 3) ist es herauszufinden, welcher Parameter (ERPs vs Frequenzbänder) robuster bei der Bewertung der mentalen Beanspruchung ist. Die zweite Studie (Kapitel 4) untersuchte die Veränderungen der Frequenzbänder bei der Kombination zweier unterschiedlicher Aufgaben. Auf der Grundlage der Ergebnisse dieser beiden Studien wird in Kapitel 5 ein Modell der logistischen Funktion (LFM) vorgeschlagen. Dieses Modell ermöglicht die Kombination der EEG Frequenzbänder zu einer einheitlichen Bewertung der mentalen Beanspruchung mit einer Spanne von [0-1]. Schließlich wurde eine Studie zur Beurteilung der Umsetzbarkeit der ATA in einer Fahrsimulation durchgeführt (Kapitel 6). Das DWM-ATA Modell und LFM wird dieser Studie zu Grunde gelegt. Die Ergebnisse dieser Experimente haben gezeigt, dass EEG ein nützliches Tool zur Bewertung der mentalen Beanspruchung ist. ERPs- zum Beispiel, die Amplitude der P300- sowie Frequenzbänder können hierzu verwendet werden. Bezüglich der Frequenzbänder hat sich gezeigt, dass sich bei einer Erhöhung der mentalen Beanspruchung die frontale Theta-Aktivität erhöht und die parietale Alpha-Aktivität verringert. Die Frequenzbänder zeigten höhere Robustheit für die kontinuierliche Bewertung der mentalen Beanspruchung. Die Untersuchung der Frequenzbänder mit zwei kombinierten Aufgaben hat gezeigt, dass die Veränderung der mentalen Beanspruchung bezüglich verschiedener kognitiver Ressourcen zu unterschiedlichen Veränderungen in der Theta- und Alpha-Aktivität führt. Diese Unterschiede können nicht durch Theta- oder Alpha-Aktivität alleine repräsentiert werden. Die Ergebnisse des LFM zeigen, dass das LFM effizient für die Quantifizierung der mentalen Beanspruchung und vorteilhaft für die Anwendung in ATA ist. Zudem zeigt die Validierung auf, dass die EEG-basierte ATA vorteilhaft ist für die Verringerung der mentalen Beanspruchung und die Verbesserung der Leistung des Fahrers bei zu hoher Aufgabenanforderung ist. Ergebnisse aus dieser Studie haben auch die Bedürfnisse des theoretischen DWM-ATA Modell adressiert. In dieser Dissertation wird ATA im Fahrkontext in vielfältigen Untersuchungen beleuchtet, die von der Theorie zur Validierung der Methodik reichen. Dies ist vorteilhaft für die Lösung von Fragen der menschlichen Faktoren assoziiert mit neuen Fachzeugtechnologien. Die Bedeutung der Dissertation liegt auch im ihrer möglichen Anwendung im Mensch-zentrierten Design vom intelligenten Fahrzeug der Zukunft.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-08-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31852</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-31852</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2987/lei_shengguang.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
