<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3287">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3287</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Process development for nanostructuring and 3D micro/nanointegration</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Prozessentwicklung für Nanostrukturierung und 3D Mikro/Nanointegration</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Senn, Tobias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Micro- and nanostructures significantly influence the physical and chemical properties of surfaces. Therefore, such structures can be used to functionalize surfaces and adjust the surface properties to the specific requirements of a certain application. A typical surface effect based on topological patterning is the self-cleaning surface, similar to the well-known lotus effect based on micro- and nano roughness. Other examples are the effect of the moth eye to create an anti-reflective effect, based on sub-wavelength gratings; the enhancement of surface adhesion similar to the Gecko’s ability to climb on smooth surfaces due to large hairy nanostructures; or the effect of the shark skin where a microstructure influences the flow resistance and spore settlement. These properties as well as many others can have an impact on industrial applications in different fields. Many approaches have been proposed for the fabrication of such structures to imitate the effects of nature and use them in industrial applications. For economical use of these structure effects, fabrication processes are needed that meet the standard set by industry: the production of robust structures with a high lifetime in an easily reproducible and cost efficient way. Typical replication processes to fulfil these requirements are Injection Molding or Imprint processes. A remaining challenge is the integration of functional structures into microdevices to achieve e.g. patterning in 3D, 3D surface structures and sidewall patterning. The goal of this work is to fabricate and replicate functional surface structures using Imprint technologies and to integrate them into polymer parts to obtain a higher functionality of polymer based microdevices. For this purpose, a Nanoimprint Lithography (NIL) process was developed to replicate nanostructures in the sub 100 nm range. The potential of this technology is demonstrated in various applications including the replication of photonic crystal structures for the fabrication of novel optical devices and the structuring of functional materials for applications in the fields of solar cells and magnetic sensors. For the integration of functional surface structures into polymer based microparts, a process chain was developed based on Thermoforming and Soft Lithography. In this process chain a 3D structured elastomer stamp is produced from which replications can be made. This process chain was applied to various industrial fields like optics and micro fluidics. Functionalized micro lenses were produced by the integration of moth eye structures; in the field of micro fluidics, a hydrophobic surface structure was molded into micro channels to create a fluidic system for a micro fuel cell. The results of these investigations have shown that the integration of surface structures into polymer parts can be used to improve the performance of a system and to reduce production costs.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Mikro- und Nanostrukturen haben Einfluss auf die physikalisch-chemischen Eigenschaften von Oberflächen. Dadurch ist es möglich die Oberflächeneigenschaften durch eine Strukturierung an spezifische Anforderungen einer Anwendungen anzupassen. Ein typischer durch Strukturen hervorgerufener Oberflächeneffekt ist eine selbstreinigende Oberfläche, ähnlich dem bekannten Lotuseffekt basierend auf einer Mikro- und Nanorauhigkeit. Andere Beispiele sind der Effekt der Mottenaugen um Antireflektionseigenschaften basierend auf einem Subwellenlängengitter zu erzeugen, die Erhöhung der Oberflächenadhäsion durch langhaarige Nanostrukturen (Gekko-Effekt), oder der Effekt der Haifischhaut, bei der eine Mikrostruktur den Strömungswiderstand und die Anlagerung von Bakterien beeinflusst. Für die Herstellung und das Design künstlicher Strukturen, die diese aus der Natur bekannten Eigenschaften imitieren, wurden unterschiedliche Ansätze entwickelt. Um das wirtschaftliche Potential dieser Effekte zu nutzen, benötigt man Herstellungsprozesse, welche die Anforderungen der Industrie erfüllen: Die reproduzierbare und kosteneffiziente Produktion robuster Strukturen mit hoher Lebenszeit. Typische Replikationsprozesse, die diese Anforderungen erfüllen sind Spritzgieß- und Prägeprozesse. Eine weiterhin bestehende Herausforderung ist die Integration dieser Strukturen in Mikrobauteile. Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es funktionale Oberflächenstrukturen mittels Imprint Prozessen zu replizieren und sie in Polymerbauteile zu integrieren, um hoch funktionalisierte Mikroteile herzustellen. Hierzu wurde zunächst ein Nanoimprint Lithographieprozess entwickelt, um Nanostrukturen im sub 100 nm Bereich zu replizieren. Das Potential dieses Verfahrens wird in mehreren Anwendungen demonstriert, unter anderem die Replikation photonischer Kristalle für die Herstellung neuartiger optischer Anwendungen und die Strukturierung funktionaler Materialien für Anwendungen im Bereich der Solarzellen- und Magnetsensorforschung. Für die Integration funktionaler Oberflächenstrukturen in Polymerbauteile wurde eine Prozesskette entwickelt, basierend auf einem Thermoform- und Softlithographieprozess. Hierbei wird ein dreidimensional strukturierter Elastomerstempel hergestellt, welcher in einem Gießprozess verwendet wird um Polymerbauteile zu produzieren. Mit Hilfe der entwickelten Prozesskette wurden mehrere Bauteile für optische und mikrofluidische Anwendungen gefertigt. Durch die Integration einer Mottenaugenstruktur in ein Linsenarray konnten funktionalisierte Linsen hergestellt werden. In einer mikrofluidischen Anwendung wurden hydrophobe Oberflächenstrukturen in Mikrokanäle integriert, um so ein Befüllungs- und Abgassystem für eine Mikrobrennstoffzelle herzustellen. Die Ergebnisse dieser Untersuchungen haben gezeigt, dass die Integration von funktionalen Oberflächenstrukturen in Polymerbauteile dazu genutzt werden kann, die Eigenschaften eines Systems zu verbessern und die Kosten im Herstellungsprozess zu reduzieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-04-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3287</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34713</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34713</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3287/senn_tobias.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-SA: Creative Commons Lizenz: Namensnennung, Weitergabe zu gleichen Bedingungen</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
