<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:59:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3288">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3288</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Solvent-free chemo-enzymatic epoxidation: Experimental and kinetic modelling studies</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Lösemittelfreie Chemo-enzymatische Epoxidierung: Experimentelle Untersuchungen und kinetische Modellierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bhattacharya, Subhamoy</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">A promising route to sustainable epoxide synthesis involves in situ peracid formation biocatalysed by Novozym®435 (NZ435), using hydrogen peroxide (H2O2) as oxidant and organic acids as acyl donors. The peracid can be used for epoxidation of unsaturated compounds. In this work, a leach proof and mechanically stable silicone-coated variant of NZ435 (silcoat-NZ435) was used for epoxidation of model terminal alkene 1-dodecene (Dod) under solvent-free conditions. Using a modified Lewis cell, the complex three-phase system could be operated in complete absence of mass transfer limitations (both film and pore diffusions). Subsequently the effect of varying individual chemical concentrations as well as reaction conditions like temperature were tested. Two rate laws were proposed for two different ranges of octanoic acid (OA) concentrations. H2O2 concentration was found to be pivotal in determining the reaction rates. Non-integer orders obtained from the rate laws indicated a complex reaction mechanism compounded by the multiphase system. Issues like enzyme stability and re-usability were investigated in detail to further characterize the biocatalyst in the system. Thermodynamic feasibility of the reaction was also proven. Pseudo Michaelis-Menten models indicated that OA inhibited the enzymatic reaction. A semi-empirical kinetic model was also devised to fit reaction rate dependency on Dod levels. Finally, a more comprehensive kinetic model was proposed which indicated substrate inhibition by both OA and H2O2 and also accounted for parallel peracid hydrolysis reactions. The semi-empirical model provided best agreement with experimental results from maximum conversion runs. Based on the information collected, a simple process setup was attempted where the silcoat-NZ435 beads were physically separated and prevented from coming in direct contact with the H2O2.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Einen viel versprechenden, nachhaltigen Syntheseweg von Epoxiden stellt die in-situ Persäuresynthese dar, die Novozym®435 (NZ435) als Biokatalysator, Wasserstoffperoxid (H2O2) als Oxidationsmittel und organische Säuren als Acylquelle nutzt. Die Persäure kann für die Epoxidierung von ungesättigten Verbindungen genutzt werden. In dieser Arbeit wurde eine gegen Auslaugung und mechanische Belastung stabilisierte Variante des NZ435 (silcoat-NZ435) für die Epoxidierung des endständigen Modellalkenes 1-Dodecen (Dod) ohne Verwendung von Lösungsmitteln eingesetzt. Das komplexe Dreiphasensystem konnte in einer modifizierten Lewiszelle ohne Stofftransportlimitierung durch Film- und Porendiffusion betrieben werden. Anschließend wurde sowohl der Einfluss der Konzentration von einzelnen Substanzen als auch der Reaktionsbedingungen wie der Temperatur untersucht. Diese Informationen wurden genutzt, um zwei Reaktiongeschwindigkeitsänsatze für zwei verschiedene Oktansäurekonzentrationenen (OA) zu formulieren, die zentral von der H2O2-Konzentration abhängen. Die nicht ganzzahlige Reaktionsordnung lässt den komplexen Reaktionsmechanismus, der durch das Multiphasensystem bedingt ist, erkennen. Um den Biokatalysator besser zu charakterisieren, wurden im Anschluss die Enzymstabiltät, die Wiederverwendbarkeit und Inaktivierungskinetik in diesem System betrachtet. Außerdem wurde die thermodynamische Plausibilität der Reaktion bewiesen. Pseudo-Michaelis-Menten-Modelle zeigten, dass OA die enzymatische Reaktion inhibiert. Ein semi-empirisches Modell wurde entwickelt, um die Abhängigkeit der Reaktionsrate von der Dod-Menge zu beschreiben. Schließlich wurde ein umfassenderes kinetisches Modell vorgeschlagen, das Substratinhibierung durch sowohl OA als auch H2O2 zeigt und auch die parallele Persäurehydrolyse mit einbezieht. Das semiempirische Modell erzielte die beste Übereinstimmung mit experimentellen Ergebnissen. Schließlich wurde unter Verwendung der Kinetikdaten und der Ergebnisse aus den Deaktivierungsversuchen eine einfache, geregelte Prozessanordnung aufgebaut. In dieser Anordnung wurden die silcoat-NZ435-Perlen physisch vom H2O2 getrennt, so dass einer Inaktivierung durch direkten Kontakt vorgebeugt wurde.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2012-04-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3288</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34677</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-34677</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3288/bhattacharya_subhamoy.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
