<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:53:51Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2080">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2080</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Characterization of Gate Controlled Diodes for IGCT Applications</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Die Charakterisierung der Gate Controlled Dioden für die Anwendung von IGCTs </dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bhalerao, Prasad</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The scope of the research work is to characterize and evaluate prototypes of a newly devloped device called 'Gate Controlled Diode' (GCD), manufactured and preliminary tested by ABB, Semiconductor for steady state operating conditions-forward conducting and reverse blocking mode and transient operation-turn-off mode. The experimental test results are analyzed and evaluated. Furthermore, the prime application of the GCD- the series connection of IGCTs is investigated. In medium voltage applications, to achieve higher output voltages on the basis of a three level NPC voltage source converter, the series connection of IGCTs is a simple solution. For the effective series connection of IGCTs, the voltage balancing has to be maintained during the blocking mode as well as during the turn-on and turn-off transients. Presently simple RC or RCD snubbers offer a straight forward solution to maintain the voltage symmetry between the series connected ICTs and its anti-parallel diodes. However these conventional snubber networks lead to unwanted effects such as increases losses, space and costs. The contents of this thesis is the introduction of a new device called 'Gate Controlled Diode', which offers an effective solution for the voltage balancing of a series connected IGCTs without passive snubber network. In this p+nn+ diode, with an additional gate terminal a positive gate current injection can adjust the voltage balancing between IGCTs and its anti-parallel diodes by changing the resulting the leakage current distribution among the series connected devices. First time it has been experimentally analyzed in this thesis that a small of some mA is required to maintain the static voltage balancing while for dynamic voltage balancing a sufficient amount of gate charge, which has to be impressed during the turn-off transient of the IGCT is necessary. Due to press pack case of the GCD, it offers advantages regarding space and mounting compared to passive networks. The reverse recovery behavior of the GCD can be influenced by impressing a positive gate current. This feature could also be applied in fast medium voltage diodes (e.g. 10 kV diodes). In normal converter operation the GCD, which is connected anti-parallel to the IGCT can operate as a normal free-wheeling diode. By injecting a gate current into the GCD in its blocking mode the turn-off current of the IGCT can be reduced. This application of the GCD has also been experimentally investigated. The experimental results and analysis show that GCD can be a promising solution for an IGCT series connection in voltage source converters.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Gegenstand dieser Arbeit ist die Charakterisierung des Durchlassverhaltens, des Blockierverhaltens und des Ausschaltverhaltens von Prototypen neu entwickelter Bauelemente, die als "Gate-Gesteuerte Diode" (Gate Controlled Diode, GCD) bezeichnet werden. Diese Bauelemente wurden hergestellt und vorab getestet bei ABB, Schweiz. Die experimentellen Resultate werden beschrieben und bewertet. Weiterhin wird die Hauptapplikation der GCD, die Reihenschaltung von IGCTs, untersucht. In Applikationen von Mittelspannungsstromrichtern ist die Reihenschaltung von IGCTs eine einfache Lösung zur Erhöhung der Ausgangsspannung in Dreipunkt Spannungswechselrichtern. Für eine sinnvolle Reihenschaltung von IGCTs muss eine symmetrische Spannungsaufteilung während des Blockierens sowie beim Ein- und Ausschalten gewährleistet sein. In aktuellen Anwendungen sind RC-Snubber eine einfacher Ansatz zur Spannungssymmetrierung zwischen den in Reihe geschalteten IGCTs und Dioden. Diese Snubberbeschaltungen haben unerwünschte Effekte wie erhöhte Schaltverluste, Platzbedarf und erhöhte Kosten zur Folge. Der Inhalt der vorliegenden Dissertationsschrift ist die Einführung des neu entwickelten Bauelements, der Gate-Gesteuerten Diode als kostengünstige Möglichkeit zur Spannungssymmetrierung von in Reihe geschalteten IGCTs ohne passive Snubber. In dieser p+nn+-Diode wird durch einen über einen zusätzlichen Gate-Anschluss zugeführten positiven Gate-Strom eine Spannungssymmetrierung zwischen den in Reihe geschalteten IGCTs und Dioden durch Veränderung des entsprechenden Blockierstromes erreicht. In dieser Arbeit wird erstmalig gezeigt, dass ein kleiner Gate-Strom im Bereich einiger Milliampere benötigt wird, um eine statische symmetrische Spannungsaufteilung zu erreichen während für eine dynamische symmetrische Spannungsaufteilung während des Ausschaltens des IGCTs eine ausreichende Gate-Ladung notwendig ist. Das Press-Pack-Gehäuse der GCD bietet Vorteile hinsichtlich Platzbedarf und Montageaufwand verglichen mit der Anwendung von passiven Netzwerken. Das Rückwärtserholverhalten der GCD kann durch einen eingebrachten Gate-Strom positiv beeinflusst werden. Diese Eigenschaft kann in Dioden für den Mittelspannungsbereich (10-kV-Dioden) angewendet werden. In normalem Umrichterbetrieb kann die Gate-Gesteuerte Diode, die antiparallel zum IGCT geschaltet ist, als normale Freilaufdiode arbeiten. Durch die Injektion eines Gate-Stromes während des Blockierens kann der Ausschaltstrom des abschaltenden IGCTs reduziert werden. Diese Anwendung wurde ebenfalls experimentell untersucht.Die Resultate der experimentellen Untersuchungen zeigen, dass die Gate-Gesteuerte Diode eine viel versprechende Lösung in der Anwendung von in Reihe geschalteten IGCTs in Mittelspannungsstromrichtern ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2009-03-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2080</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21409</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-21409</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2080/bhalerao_prasad.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
