<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:56Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2510">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2510</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Growth mechanisms of CuInS2 formed by the sulfurization of thin metallic films</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Wachstumsmechanismen von CuInS2 während der Sulfurisierung von metallischen Schichten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rodriguez Alvarez, Humberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The focus of this thesis is the growth of CuInS2 films from a rapid thermal sulfurization process. This material is used as the absorber layer in thin-film solar cells. The rapid thermal sulfurization of thin Cu-In films is a technology that represents a low cost alternative to other chalcopyrite thin-film fabrication technologies. This technology has evolved to industrial maturity thanks to the optimization of the resulting solar cell devices. However, the knowledge concerning the formation of the film microstructure during this kind of processing is scarce. This knowledge is necessary for further optimization and future process design. This thesis makes two contributions to the sulfurization technology. First, it presents an experimental method to monitor in real-time the microstructural changes of a thin-film during solid-solid or solid-gas reactions. This in situ method was developed on the basis of the energy-dispersive X-ray diffraction. It is used to follow and quantify isolated solid state mechanisms and complete rapid thermal sulfurizations. Second, it divides the sulfurization process into five independent growth mechanisms. The microstructure formation can be clarified by the analysis of their interaction. The mechanisms are: 1) the alloying of the metals, 2) the sulfurization of the metallic alloy, 3) the reaction of the sulfides, 4) the thin-film recrystallization and 5) the sulfide interdiffusion. These growth mechanisms are investigated by means of the in situ and complementary characterization methods. The experimental results reveal the impact that each mechanism has on the film microstructure. Detailed attention is firstly given to the sulfide layered stack formation during the sulfurization of a Cu16In9 alloy. The layer sequence and the morphology are functions of the temperature and the sulfur pressure. The second focus concerns the kinetics of the reaction between CuIn5S8 and Cu(2-x)S. This reaction consumes the secondary CuIn5S8 phase that may segregate during sulfurization. The thin-film recrystallization is the third central point of these investigations. This mechanism ensures grain sizes of the order of the thickness of the films, low structural defect densities and the chalcopyrite ordering of the Cu and In cations. This mechanism is monitored in situ for the first time. A model is presented that describes the thin-film recrystallization together with its prerequisites and enhancement factors. The rapid thermal sulfurization of thin metallic Cu-In films is investigated by means of the in situ method developed in this thesis. The investigations concentrate on the growth mechanisms during the formation of the CuInS2 films. The impact of each mechanism on the film microstructure is xemplified. Paths to control the growth mechanisms are proposed. These paths support the further development of the sulfurization technology and enable the design of innovative fabrication processes.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Gegenstand dieser Arbeit ist das Wachstum von dünnen CuInS2-Schichten mittels eines schnellen thermischen Syntheseprozesses. CuInS2 dient als absorbierende Schicht in Dünnschichtsolarzellen. Die Herstellung erfolgt durch eine Sulfurisierung von Cu und In Vorläuferschichten. Dieses Verfahren stellt eine kostengünstigere und ertragreichere Möglichkeit zu anderen Herstellungstechnologien dar und wird, dank iterativer Optimierung der resultierenden Solarzellen, in der großflächigen Massenherstellung von Solarmodulen benutzt. Die Mikrostrukturentwicklung während eines solchen Herstellungsverfahrens ist bisher allerdings unbekannt. Dieses Wissen ist notwendig für die weitere Optimierung und für die zukünftige Gestaltung neuartiger Prozesse. Diese Dissertation liefert zwei Beiträge zur Sulfurisierungstechnologie. Erstens zeigt sie eine in situ Methode zur Überwachung der Dünnschichtmikrostruktur während Festkörperumwandlungen und Reaktionen mit einer Gasphase. Diese Methode basiert auf der energiedispersiven Röntgenbeugung. Sie eignet sich sowohl für die Untersuchung von isolierten Festkörpermechanismen als auch für die Analyse von kompletten schnellen thermischen Sulfurisierungen. Zweitens schlägt die Arbeit eine Zerlegung des komplizierten Sulfurisierungsprozesses in fünf unabhängige Wachstumsmechanismen vor. Die Analyse von deren Interaktion erlaubt eine nachvollziehbare Beschreibung der Mikrostrukturbildung in Abhängigkeit von den Prozesseinflussgrößen. Die Wachstumsmechanismen sind: 1) die Bildung einer Metalllegierung, 2) die Sulfurisierung einer Metalllegierung, 3) die Reaktion zwischen den Sulfiden, 4) die Rekristallisation der Dünnschicht und, 5) die Interdiffusion der Sulfide. Jeder Mechanismus wirkt sich anders auf die Schichtmikrostruktur aus und wird in dieser Dissertation in situ und mit anderen Charakterisierungsmethoden untersucht. Der erste Schwerpunkt der Untersuchungen betrifft die Bildung von Schichtsytemen während der Sulfurisierung einer Cu16In9-Legierung. Die Temperatur und der Schwefeldruck bestimmen sowohl die Sulfidschichtreihenfolge als auch deren Morphologie. Als Zweites studiert diese Arbeit die Kinetik der Reaktion zwischen Cu(2-x)S und CuIn5S8 Dünnschichten. Diese Reaktion verbraucht die Fremdphase CuIn5S8, die zusammen mit der Hauptphase CuInS2 koexistieren kann. Die Rekristallisation der Dünnschicht ist das dritte Schwerpunktthema. Dieser Mechanismus bewirkt strukturell defektarme Körner, die eine Größe von einigen Mikrometern im Durchmesser aufweisen. In diesen Körnern befinden sich die Kupfer- und Indiumkationen in der Chalkopyritordnung. Die Rekristallisation von CuInS2-Schichten wurde das erste Mal in situ beobachtet. Diese Arbeit schlägt ein Modell zur Beschreibung dieses Mechanismus vor. Die neue in situ Methode erlaubt die Erforschung schneller thermischer Sulfurisierungen. Anhand der untersuchten Wachstumsmechanismen kann die Mikrostrukturbildung der CuInS2-Schicht erklärt werden. Die vorgeschlagenen Pfade zur Kontrolle aller Mechanismen unterstützen die Weiterentwicklung der Sulfurisierungstechnologie und ermöglichen die Entstehung von neuartigen Herstellungsprozessen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-04-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2510</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2510/rodriguezalvarez_humberto.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-ND: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, keine Bearbeitung</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
