<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:52:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1777">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:1777</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Inactivation mechanisms of Geobacillus and Bacillus spores during high pressure thermal sterilization</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Inaktivierungsmechanismen von Geobacillus und Bacillus Sporen w√§hrend der thermischen Hochdrucksterilisation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mathys, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">High pressure thermal sterilization is an emerging technology that can produce uniform, minimally processed foods of high quality, better than heat treatment alone. At present, it has not yet been successfully introduced into the food industry, possibly due to the less known inactivation mechanism of high resistant bacterial spores. This study developed and used new analytical tools, to improve the understanding of spore mechanisms at high pressures and temperatures. Biophysical analyses showed that the lag phase often found in thermal spore inactivation (‚Äúshoulder formation‚Ä?) can sufficiently be described by first-order inactivation kinetics, when the spore agglomeration size is considered. Two limiting cases have been discriminated in mathematical modeling: three-dimensional, spherical packing for maximum spore count and two dimensional, circular packing for minimum spore count of a particular agglomerate. Physiological analyses using flow cytometry detected four distinct sub-populations for pressure treated spores, which could be described by a three step model of inactivation. The model involves a germination step following hydrolysis of the spore cortex, an unknown step, and finally an inactivation step with physical compromise of the spore‚Äôs inner membrane. Chemical and thermodynamical analyses of commonly used buffer solutions resulted in different shifts of the dissociation equilibrium under pressure and temperature. Heat and pressure inactivation of bacterial spores at different initial pH-values in ACES and phosphate buffer confirmed the data modeled. The development of a temperature control system for an innovative high pressure unit allowed ideal adiabatic process conditions and isothermal dwell times, which provided an excellent tool to study the spore inactivation mechanisms at ultra-high pressures in detail. Highest inactivation rates were found within 700 - 800 MPa. Spore stabilization at 1100 MPa was explained by using a cumulative lethal effect distribution, which was hypothetically produced by different germination reaction pathways at various pressure levels. The generated data were exemplarily incorporated into analyses of industrial sterilization processes. An improved understanding of the mechanisms of spore inactivation will aid in the food safety assessment of high pressure thermal sterilization in particular, and also assist in the commercialization of this novel process, facilitating adoption by industry.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Hochdrucksterilisation als neuartige Technologie kann minimal behandelte Produkte h√∂chster Qualit√§t im Vergleich zur thermischen Konservierung erzeugen. Bisher gelang keine erfolgreiche Einf√ºhrung in die Lebensmittelindustrie, oft begr√ºndet durch die wenig bekannten Inaktivierungsmechanismen hoch resistenter bakterieller Sporen. Diese Studie entwickelt und verwendet neue analytische Werkzeuge zur wesentlichen Verbesserung des Verst√§ndnisses dieser Mechanismen unter Druck- und Temperaturbedingungen. Biophysikalische Analysen zeigten, dass die oft gefundene lag-Phase (‚ÄûSchulterformation‚Äú) bei thermischer Inaktivierung durch Kinetiken erster Ordnung mit Ber√ºcksichtigung der Sporenagglomerationsgr√∂√üe beschrieben werden kann. Zwei limitierende F√§lle der mathematischen Modellierung wurden unterschieden: dreidimensionale Kugelpackung f√ºr maximale und zweidimensionale Kreispackung f√ºr minimale Sporenanzahl bei einem bestimmten Agglomerat. Physiologische Analysen detektierten f√ºr druckbehandelte Sporen vier Sub-Populationen durch Durchflusszytometrie, f√ºr welche ein Drei-Schritt-Model der Inaktivierung vorgeschlagen wurde. Das Model beinhaltet die Keimung und nachfolgender Hydrolyse des Sporencortex, einen unbekannten Schritt und letztendlich die Inaktivierung mit Abbau der inneren Membran. Chemische und thermodynamische Analysen von verwendeten Puffersystemen lieferten unterschiedliche Verschiebungen des Dissoziationsgleichgewichtes unter Druck- und Temperaturbedingungen. Hitze- und Druckinaktivierung bakterieller Sporen bei verschiedenen pH-Werten in ACES- und Phosphatpuffer best√§tigten die modellierten Daten. Die Entwicklung einer Temperaturregelung f√ºr eine innovative Hochdruckanlage erm√∂glichte ideal adiabatische Prozessbedingungen und isotherme Haltezeiten, optimal f√ºr die Untersuchung des detaillierten Inaktivierungsmechanismus bei Ultra-Hochdruckbehandlung. Maximale Inaktivierungsraten wurden bei 700 - 800 MPa erreicht, wobei die beobachtete Sporenstabilisierung bei 1100 MPa mit einer kumulativen Verteilung der letalen Effekte, hypothetisch hervorgerufen durch unterschiedliche Keimungsreaktionen, beschrieben wurde. Exemplarisch wurden die generierten Daten zur Analyse industrieller Sterilisationsprozesse verwendet. Ein erweitertes Verst√§ndnis der mechanistischen Sporeninaktivierung verbessert die M√∂glichkeiten einer Kommerzialisierung des vorgestellten Prozesses.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2008-05-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/msword</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/1777</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-18731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1777/original_mathys_alexander.doc</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/1777/mathys_alexander.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
