<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:55:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2463">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2463</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-08-20</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Substance flow analysis of the recycling of small waste electrical and electronic equipment - An assessment of the recovery of gold and palladium</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Stoffstromanalyse für das Recycling von kleinen Elektro(nik)-Altgeräten - Eine Bewertung der Verwertung von Gold und Palladium</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chancerel, Perrine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The demand for precious metals by manufacturers of electrical and electronic equipment has increased significantly over the past few years. Although precious metal concentrations in appliances are very low, these metals have a high economic and environmental relevance compared to other substances present at much higher levels (for example iron, copper, plastics). This thesis aims at describing and quantifying the flows of small waste electrical and electronic equipment (sWEEE) in Germany and in the USA for the year 2007, as well as the flows of gold and palladium associated with the sWEEE. Although collection systems have been set up, in many cases sWEEE is not collected separately for recycling but instead is disposed of. Regarding treatment of sWEEE, the model differentiates between reuse and treatments carried out by the formal and informal sector (including illegal export of sWEEE). The material flows were quantified based on a combination of expansive experimental investigations and a review of the relevant literature. The results revealed that, in 2007, 370 000 to 430 000 tonnes of sWEEE were generated in Germany, containing 1.9 to 2.4 tonnes of gold and 580 to 720 kg of palladium. In the USA, 26 to 36 tonnes of gold and 9 to 12 tonnes of palladium were contained in the 3.1 to 4.3 million tonnes of sWEEE generated in 2007. In Germany, the collection rates are much higher (77% of the generated sWEEE is collected) than in the USA (30%). In the USA, 6% of the generated sWEEE is reused, whereas in Germany the reuse rate amounts to 3%. 72% of the gold contained in the sWEEE was discarded in Germany and therefore lost for the recycling economy. The discarding rate is around 75% for the USA. The economic value of the discarded gold and palladium in 2007 amounted to 34 to 44 million US-dollars in Germany and 466 to 714 million US-dollars in the USA. In conclusion, the recycling infrastructures in Germany and in the USA do not allow an efficient recovery of the precious metals. The losses are caused by the non-separated collection of sWEEE and by inappropriate treatment, for instance during pre-processing. The characteristics of the different types of sWEEE considerably influence the recovery of precious metals. This has to be considered by developing strategies to improve it. Besides the recommendations how to improve the system, some suggestions to improve the data collection for the conduction of further substance flow analyses were formulated. The applied methodology can be used to assess waste management systems and develop improvement strategies. The method is not only useful for assessing the recovery of valuable substances as presented in this thesis, but in a more general way allows a quantitative analysis of the destination of substances fed into a waste management system.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Nachfrage nach Edelmetallen von Herstellern elektrischer und elektronischer Geräte ist in den letzten Jahren bedeutsam gestiegen. Obwohl die Edelmetallkonzentrationen in den Geräten sehr niedrig sind, sind diese Metalle wirtschaftlich und ökologisch relevant, verglichen mit anderen in höheren Konzentrationen enthaltenen Stoffen (z.B. Eisen, Kupfer, Kunststoffe). Das Ziel dieser Dissertation ist es, die Stoffflüsse von kleinen elektrischen und elektronischen Altgeräten (Kleingeräten) in Deutschland und in den USA bezogen auf das Jahr 2007 zu beschreiben, sowie die mit den Kleingeräten verbundenen Flüsse von Gold und Palladium zu quantifizieren. Obwohl Sammelsysteme für Kleingeräte existieren, werden Kleingeräte häufig nicht erfasst sondern im Restabfall entsorgt. Bezüglich der Verwertung von Kleingeräten unterscheidet das Modell Wiederverwendung und Behandlung durch den formellen und den informellen Sektor (inklusive illegalen Export von Kleingeräten). Die Stoffströme wurden, basierend auf einer Kombination von aufwendigen experimentellen Untersuchungen und Literaturauswertung, quantifiziert. Die Ergebnisse zeigen, dass 370 000 bis 430 000 Tonnen von Kleingeräten 2007 in Deutschland angefallen sind. Sie beinhalteten 1,9 bis 2,4 Tonnen Gold und 580 bis 720 kg Palladium. In den USA befanden sich in den 2007 angefallenen 3,1 bis 4,3 Million Tonnen Altgeräten 26 bis 36 Tonnen Gold und 9 bis 12 Tonnen Palladium. In Deutschland sind die Sammelquoten deutlich höher (77%) als in den USA (30%). In den USA wurden 6% der angefallenen Kleingeräte wieder verwendet, während die Wiederverwendungsquote in Deutschland 3% beträgt. 72% des in den Kleingeräten beinhalteten Goldes ging deshalb für die Kreislaufwirtschaft verloren. Die Verlustquote beträgt in den USA ca. 75%. Der wirtschaftliche Wert des verlorenen Goldes und Palladium betrug 2007 34 bis 44 Million US-Dollar in Deutschland und 466 bis 714 Million US-Dollar in den USA. Die Recyclinginfrastrukturen in Deutschland und in den USA ermöglichen keine effiziente Rückgewinnung der Edelmetalle. Die Verluste werden durch die nicht-getrennte Erfassung der Kleingeräte und durch die ungeeignete Behandlung, insbesondere bei der Aufbereitung, verursacht. Die Charakteristika der Kleingeräte beeinflussen stark die Rückgewinnung der Edelmetalle. Das soll bei der Entwicklung von Verbesserungsstrategien betrachtet werden. Neben Empfehlungen zur Systemverbesserung wurden Vorschläge zur Verbesserung der Datenerfassung zur Durchführung weiterer Stoffflussanalysen formuliert. Die angewandte Methode kann benutzt werden, um Abfallwirtschaftsysteme zu bewerten und Verbesserungsstrategien zu entwickeln. Die Methode ist nicht nur für die Bewertung der Verwertung von Wertstoffen nützlich, sondern ermöglicht im Allgemeinen eine quantitative Analyse des Verbleibs der in einem Abfallmanagementsystem behandelten Stoffe.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-03-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2463</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-25903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>978-3-89720-555-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2463/chancerel_perrine.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
