<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:58:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3108">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3108</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Escaping the Tsunami: Evacuation Strategies for Large Urban Areas Concepts and Implementation of a Multi-Agent Based Approach</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Flucht vor dem Tsunami: Evakuierungsstrategien für große Urbane Gebiete Konzepte und Implementierung eine Multi-Agenten basierden Ansatzes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lämmel, Gregor</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The evacuation of whole cities or even regions represents a complex problem for traffic planning. Congruent with the importance of the topic, there is a large body of research regarding emergency evacuations. Many dynamic aspects of an evacuation such as congestion can be handled adequately only if the evacuation process is modeled on a microscopic level. This is also true for large-scale scenarios. Most existing models are either not microscopic, or not capable to deal with large scenarios. This thesis discusses an approach that deals with large-scale evacuations on the microscopic level. Whereas existing models tend to neglect essential aspects like the time-dependent expansion of hazards, a comprehensive evacuation simulation framework has been developed in order to consider such aspects. The simulation framework has been tested on a real-world scenario for the city of Padang, Indonesia. Padang is located on the Mentawai segment at the West Coast of Sumatra, Indonesia. Padang is a low-lying city with approximately 850 000 inhabitants and is characterized by its net of urban waterways. The West Coast of Sumatra is a region of high tectonic activity and has been hit by tsunamis in the past. The city has been indicated as one of the most plausible locations for a tsunami of disastrous proportions in near future. Various evacuation strategies have been tested on the Padang scenario.Detailed analyses of the results are given for each evacuation strategy. Some important findings that are obtained from the simulation results are: • The shortest path solution, being a straightforward one, is not suitable for the evacuation planning. • Other routing strategies like the Nash equilibrium approach or the marginal social cost based approach are considering congestion effects and therefore leading to better evacuation results. However, as long as time-dependent aspects of the hazard are not explicitly modeled, those solutions are also unsuitable. • Usually there are a lot of uncertain factors when it comes to evacuations. One uncertain factor is the advance warning time. The risk that not all evacuees manage to escape increases with the uncertainty in the advanced warning time. Risk should be explicitly modeled, which calls for a risk reducing evacuation strategy. • Even if the time-dependent aspects and risks are explicitly considered by the model, situations are still possible, when the available time is still to short. In those situations safe places (so-called shelters) have to be build inside the evacuation area. However, the locations for the shelters have to be considered carefully because a shelter at the wrong location could also worsen the situation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Evakuierung von Städten oder sogar ganzen Regionen ist eine große Herausforderung. Nicht zuletzt aufgrund der Bedeutung dieser Thematik gibt es bereits ein großes Spektrum an Forschungsergebnissen auf dem Gebiet der Notfallevakuierung. Viele dynamischen Aspekte einer Evakuierung, wie z.B. entstehender Stau, kann nur adäquat erfasst werden wenn der Evakuierungsprozess auf einer mikroskopischen Ebene modelliert wird. Die meisten existierenden Modelle sind entweder nicht mikroskopisch oder nicht in der Lage mit großen Szenarien umzugehen. Diese Arbeit präsentiert einen Ansatz, der sowohl mikroskopisch ist als auch mit großen Szenarien umgehen kann. Des Weiteren werden in den meisten existierenden Modellen wichtige Aspekte, wie z.B. die zeitabhängige Ausbreitung der Bedrohung, nicht abgebildet. Aus diesem Grund wird in dieser Arbeit ein umfassendes Simulations-Framework erforscht, welches diese Aspekte berücksichtigt. Das Simulations-Framework wird an einem reale Szenario für die Stadt Padang in Indonesien getestet. Padang befindet sich auf dem Mentawai Segment an der Westküste von Sumatra in Indonesien. Die Stadt hat etwa 850 000 Einwohner und ist von einem Netz von Kanälen und Flüssen durchzogen. Padang liegt in einer Region starker tektonischer Aktivität und wurde bereits in der Vergangenheit von Tsunamis überflutet. Es wird erwartet, dass die Stadt in absehbarer Zukunft von einem gewaltigen Tsunami betroffen sein wird. Verschiedene Evakuierungsstrategien wurden am Padang Beispiel erforscht. Die Simulations-ergebnisse der einzelnen Evakuierungsstrategien werden in der Arbeit detailliert diskutiert. Einige wichtige Ergebnisse sind: • Die kürzeste Wege Lösung ist für die Evakuierungsplanung ungeeignet. • Besser optimierende Strategien wie der Nash-Gleichgewicht Ansatz und der marginale soziale Kosten basierende Ansatz sind so lange die zeitabhängigen Gegebenheiten der Gefahr nicht berücksichtigt werden auch ungeeignet. • In der Regel gibt es diverse Unsicherheiten im Fall einer Evakuierung. Eine unsichere Gegebenheit ist die Länge der vorhandenen Vorwarnzeit. Es besteht ein Zusammenhang zwischen unsicherer Vorwarnzeit und dem Risiko, dass es nicht alle Flüchtlinge entkommen. Das Risiko sollte explizit modelliert werden, d.h. eine risikoreduzierende Evakuierungsstrategie wird benötigt. • Auch wenn die zeitabhängigen Aspekte und das Risiko explizit modelliert werden, kann es Situationen geben wo die Zeit für eine Evakuierung ins sichere Hinterland nicht ausreicht. In solchen Situation können sichere Orte (Fluchtburgen) innerhalb des Evakuierungs-gebiets errichtet werden. Die Plätze an denen Fluchtburgen errichtet werden, müssen jedoch sorgfälltig ausgewählt werden, da eine Fluchtburg an der falschen Stelle die Situation auch verschlechtern kann.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2011-10-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32701</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-32701</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3108/laemmel_gregor.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
