<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2623">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2623</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Analysis of Hierarchical Structures for Hybrid Control Systems</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Analyse hierarchischer Strukturen für hybride Regelungssysteme</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gromov, Dmitry</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Hybrid systems arise from nontrivial interaction between discrete-event subsystems (usually modelled by finite automata) and continuous subsystems (described by differential or difference equations). Therefore, neither methods from discrete-event systems theory nor methods from continuous systems theory alone can be used to adequately analyse and control systems of this kind. An additional difficulty is that the restrictions imposed on the system often refer to different aspects of the system dynamics and, hence, cannot be addressed in a uniform way. There are two widely used approaches aimed at overcoming this problem. The first one, called continuation, is based on the conversion of a hybrid system into a purely continuous dynamical system. This approach has several drawbacks, among which is increased complexity of the resulting system dynamics. The second approach is to approximate continuous dynamics by a discrete event system. In this way, the hybrid control problem is transformed into a purely discrete one. In particular, Moor and Raisch proposed an approximation-based approach set within Willems' behavioural system theory framework. This approach allows to approximate hybrid system by a nondeterministic finite automaton which can be effectively treated by the Ramadge-Wonham supervisory control theory. As many other approximation-based approaches, it also suffers from the curse of complexity''. The state set of the approximating automata can grow enormously even for comparatively simple systems. Hence, complexity becomes a key problem in control design for hybrid systems. A hierarchical control approach could be a way out of this problem. Obviously, a decomposition of the controller into several levels can substantially reduce the complexity. Moreover, it allows an engineer to introduce some intuition into the control systems design. A theoretical basis for the hierarchical control synthesis was developed within the behavioural systems theory framework. Unfortunately, there are still only few practical applications of this approach. Moreover, the proposed conditions are not always easy to check in practice. The dissertation is intended to close this gap between theory and practice. Its main contribution consists in the following: 1. A unified framework which allows for a constructive description and analysis of all levels of a hierarchical control structure is described. We show that most practically relevant classes of control systems can be described as input/output state machines and give a classification of such state machines. 2. Developing the results obtained bz Raisch and Moor, we formulate a set of constructively verifiable conditions which guarantee a non-conflicting interaction of all control levels. 3. Two particularly useful classes of intermediate control layers are described and analysed with respect to the non-conflictingness property. 4. We consider two cases where the developed approach is applied to practically relevant control problems. In the first case, we consider an optimisation problem for a hybrid system under safety and liveness conditions. It is shown that this problem can be efficiently solved in a hierarchic way: the low-level controller enforces safety and liveness constraints while the high-level controller performs optimisation. In the second case, the low-level controller is designed to render the plant monotone.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">In hybriden dynamischen Systemen wirken ereignisdiskrete und kontinuierliche Komponenten in nichttrivialer Weise zusammen. Deswegen können weder Methoden der klassischen kontinuierlichen noch der ereignisdiskreten Regelungstheorie auf hybride Systeme übertragen werden. Eine zusätzliche Schwierigkeit besteht in dem nichthomogenen Charakter der Spezifikation, die nicht unbedingt eine einheitliche Darstellung zulässt. Ansätze, die sich mit dem Entwurf hybrider Regler befassen, sind zum großen Teil approximationsbasiert. Um die aus der Heterogenität der Systemstruktur folgenden Schwierigkeiten zu umgehen, approximiert man den kontinuierlichen Anteil der Prozeßdynamik durch ein ereignisdiskretes System und ersetzt so das ursprüngliche hybride Regelungsproblem durch ein rein ereignisdiskretes. Das resultierende diskrete Regelungsproblem kann mit Standardmethoden der ereignisdiskreten Systemtheorie, wie beispielsweise der auf Ramadge und Wonham zurückgehenden supervisory control theory behandelt werden. Diese Vorgehensweise kann aber zur einer Explosion'' der Komplexität auf diskreter Ebene führen, so dass sich viele technisch relevante Aufgabestellungen auf diese Art und Weise nicht mehr behandeln lassen. In solchen Fällen kann man das regelungstechnische Problem durch (heuristisches) Dekomponieren handhabbar zu machen. Hierarchische Ansätze stellen eine besonders attraktive Möglichkeit der Dekomposition dar, da sie auf sehr intuitive Reglerarchitekturen führen. In einer Reihe von Papers wurde eine systematische Methode zur Entwicklung hierarchischer Strukturen vorgeschlagen. Dieser Ansatz ermöglicht die Einbettung kontinuierlicher, hybrider und ereignisdiskreter Entscheidungsebenen in eine konsistente Reglerarchitektur, in der jede einzelne Ebene leichter zu entwerfen ist als ein unstrukturierter monolithischer'' Regler. Bedauerlicherweise fand diese Methode bis jetzt nur wenige praktische Anwendungen. Ein weiteres Problem besteht darin, dass die vorgeschlagene Bedingungen sich nicht in allen Fällen konstruktiv überprüfen lassen. Im Rahmen dieser Dissertation soll die Lücke zwischen dem formulierten verhaltensbasierten Ansatz und der praktischen Anwendung geschlossen werden. Wir verfolgen hauptsächlich drei Ziele: 1. Entwicklung eines einheitlichen Frameworks für konstruktive Beschreibung und Analyse von allen Hierarchie-Ebenen. 2. Analyse und Klassifizierung von hierarchischen Strukturen, in denen ein konfliktfreies Zusammenwirken zwischen allen Reglerschichten garantiert werden kann. 3. Demonstration und praktische Anwendung der obengenannten Strukturen anhand einiger praktisch relevanter Beispiele.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-09-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2623</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27712</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-27712</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2623/gromov_dmitry.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
