<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2675">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2675</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Modeling, Analysis, and Control of Thermoacoustic Instabilities</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Modellierung, Analyse und Kontrolle von thermoakustischen Instabilitäten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Moeck, Jonas Pablo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Modern gas turbine technology relies on lean premixed combustion to comply with low-emission standards. However, combustion systems operating in the lean premixed mode are highly susceptible to the excitation of high-amplitude pressure fluctuations commonly referred to as thermoacoustic instability. These self-excited oscillations are a result of the interaction between unsteady heat release in the flame and the acoustic modes of the combustion chamber. The main consequences of thermoacoustic instabilities are increased noise, reduced system performance, and reduced system durability. The capability to predict and to control combustion-driven oscillations, therefore, is of utmost importance for a further advance in gas turbine technology. The present work contributes to the knowledge on thermoacoustic instabilities and their control in a number of ways. Combustion oscillations are investigated in an atmospheric single-burner test-rig. A multiple actuator scheme is developed that allows for efficient control of unstable acoustic modes, which is an important aspect in view of current actuator limitations. Model-free adaptive control is shown to be capable of mitigating strong pressure pulsations at varying operating conditions with peak amplitude reductions up to 40 dB. Subcritical instabilities, which are particularly dangerous because they are not accounted for in linear stability tools, are investigated in a detailed experimental study. Triggering of limit-cycle oscillations and hysteresis in operating parameter variations are demonstrated. To exploit the separation of length scales inherent to flame-acoustic interactions in gas turbine combustors, a modeling approach based on separate descriptions of the hydrodynamic and the acoustic field is developed. This coupled method is demonstrated to be extremely efficient, and the computational results are validated with corresponding experiments in an elementary thermoacoustic configuration. It is shown that more complex cases can be handled as well and that active control schemes can be incorporated in this framework. Thermoacoustic instabilities observed in modern gas turbines often exhibit a dominant circumferential variation of the fluctuating pressure field due to the ring-shaped geometry of the combustion chamber. In order to study these unstable azimuthal modes on a fundamental level, we devise a simplified surrogate system on the basis of the well-known Rijke tube. This mock-up mimics the multitude of flames in an annular combustor by simple heating grids; both feature a similar dynamic response to acoustic perturbations. The thermoacoustic dynamics in this set-up are investigated experimentally and by using a low-order, network-type model. Different unstable azimuthal modes are observed and characterized in detail. The effect of circumferential asymmetries in the heat sources is investigated and shown to be strongly related to the symmetry-induced degeneracy of the modes. A feedback control scheme, based on a modal decomposition of the measured pressure field, is set up and applied to the experimental configuration. This scheme is shown to be capable of controlling all unstable modes leading to a complete stabilization of the system.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Moderne Gasturbinen werden mit magerer Vormischverbrennung betrieben, um niedrige Emissionsstandards zu erfüllen. Diese Art der Verbrennung ist jedoch äußerst anfällig gegenüber Störungen der Flamme durch akustische Schwankungen. Hierdurch entstehen sogenannte thermoakustische Instabilitäten, die sich durch außerordentlich hohe Druckpulsationen manifestieren. Diese selbsterregten Schwingungen werden durch die Interaktion der instationären Wärmefreisetzung in der Flamme mit den akustischen Moden der Brennkammer angetrieben. Neben erhöhtem Lärm führt dieses unerwünschte Phänomen zu einer Einschränkung des Betriebsbereiches der Maschine, so dass der angestrebte Wirkungsgrad und die niedrigst möglichen Schadstoffemissionen oft nicht erreicht werden können. Die Entwicklung von Methoden zur Voraussage und zur Kontrolle von Verbrennungsinstabilitäten ist daher für die Weiterentwicklung der Gasturbinentechnologie von enormer Wichtigkeit. Die vorliegende Arbeit trägt zu diesem Ziel bei. Zuerst werden thermoakustische Instabilitäten in einem atmosphärischen Brennkammerprüfstand untersucht. Es wird ein Regelansatz vorgestellt, der unter Zuhilfenahme von verschiedenen Aktuationsmechanismen eine effiziente Kontrolle von thermoakustisch instabilen Moden erlaubt. Ein modellfreies, adaptives Regelungsverfahren wird im Prüfstand bei festen und variierenden Betriebsbedingungen eingesetzt und erreicht eine Reduktion der Schwingungsamplituden um nahezu zwei Größenordnungen. Subkritische Instabilitäten, die durch lineare Analysen nicht erfasst werden können und daher besonders schwer voherzusagen sind, werden im Experiment detailliert untersucht. Die Anregung von Grenzzyklusschwingungen in einem linear stabilen System sowie Hysterese bei einer Variation der Betriebsparameter werden demonstriert. Eine effiziente Darstellung thermoakustischer Phänomene ist möglich, wenn man die Separation der Längenskalen in der Flamme-Akustik Interaktion ausnutzt. Hierauf basierend wird ein Modellierungsansatz vorgestellt, bei dem unterschiedliche Methoden zur Berechnung des hydrodynamischen und des akustischen Feldes verwendet werden. Dieser auf einer konsistenten Kopplung der beiden Berechnungsverfahren beruhende Ansatz wird anhand von einer einfachen Konfiguration vorgestellt und anschließend durch experimentelle Untersuchungen validiert. Komplexere Fälle einschließlich Regelung können ebenfalls simuliert werden. Heutige Gasturbinen sind in den häufigsten Fällen mit Ringbrennkammern ausgestattet, in denen eine Vielzahl von Brennern in eine annulare Kammer feuert. Die akustischen Moden in diesen Geometrien weisen eine dominante Variation in Umfangsrichtung auf. Da sich die Großzahl an experimentellen und numerischen Untersuchungen an Einzelbrennerkonfigurationen, in denen nur rein longitudinale akustische Schwankungen auftreten, orientiert, sind an Umfangsmoden gekoppelte thermoakustische Instabilitäten weitaus weniger gut verstanden. Aus diesem Grund wird ein vereinfachtes, auf dem bekannten Rijke Rohr basierendes Ersatzsystem entwickelt, das eine grundlegende Untersuchung dieser Art von Schwingung im Detail erlaubt. Verschiedene instabile Umfangsmoden werden im Experiment beobachtet und durch ein Netzwerkmodell berechnet. Der Einfluss von Asymmetrien im System wird untersucht und ein modales Regelungsverfahren zur Kontrolle der Schwingungen angewandt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-10-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2675</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28153</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28153</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2675/moeck_jonas.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
