<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2697">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2697</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Nonlinear Effects in Ultralong Semiconductor Optical Amplifiers for Optical Communications: Physics and Applications</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Nichtlineare Effekte in sehr langen Halbleiterlaserverstärkern für die optische Nachrichtentechnik: Physik und Anwendungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Runge, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">The presented work discusses physical properties of ultralong semiconductor optical amplifiers (UL-SOAs) and some of their possible applications in optical communication systems. At the beginning of this thesis the analytical framework for the optical properties of UL-SOAs is presented. Based on this theoretical description, a numerical simulation model is derived used for the investigation of this thesis. To obtain from the simulation model realistic results the important properties of UL-SOAs have to be included, e.g., being the saturation of the main part of the device. In this saturated part of the device, fast intraband effects dominate over the slow interband effects. The intention of UL-SOAs is to make use of these pronounced fast intraband effects in applications. Due to the short relaxation times of the fast intraband effects, they can be used for high-speed signal processing (&gt;20GBaud). With the help of an additional continuous wave (CW) signal propagating with the data signal in the UL-SOA, the capability for all-optical signal processing with 100Gbit/s on-off keying RZ-50% pseudo random bit sequence signals has been demonstrated in this thesis. With an optimised device under proper driving conditions, bit pattern effects are negligible compared to the degradation due to amplified spontaneous emission. The suppression of the bit pattern effects can be ascribed to the additional CW signal operating as a holding beam. Investigations of the UL-SOA's driving condition showed that the data signal's extinction ratio (ER) can be regenerated if the two input signals are co-polarised and the data signal has a shorter wavelength than the CW signal. These two and other driving conditions have indicated, that parametric amplification due to four-wave mixing (FWM) (Bogatov-like effect) is the reason for the ER improvement. Moreover, due to the additional CW signal, all-optical wavelength conversion (AOWC) is possible which can be combined with the ER improvement and the ability for high-speed signal processing to high-speed AOWC with ER improvement. Numerically an ER improvement of 7dB could be demonstrated while the signal has been converted over 4nm to a shorter wavelength. Another property of UL-SOAs is the tremendous FWM efficiency being also caused by the fast intraband effects of the saturated section. Hence, a possible application of UL-SOAs is the generation of short pulses if two co-polarised phase-locked CW laser sources inject their light into an UL-SOA. When the CW laser sources are tuneable, the generated pulses at the output of the UL-SOA are also tuneable in the repetition rate and the carrier frequency of the pulses. According to simulations, a strong dependence of the pulsewidth on the CW signals mode spacing could be observed. With increasing mode spacing the repetition rate of the pulses increases and also the pulsewidth shortens. For a pulse repetition rate of 20GHz pulses with a pulsewidth of less than 2ps could be obtained. Within the framework of the propagation of short pulses, the influence of chromatic dispersion has been calculated. Compared to the waveguide dispersion, composite material dispersion (CMD) dominates the chromatic dispersion in SOAs over a wavelength region of 400nm around the band gap. In turn, CMD itself is dominated by the material dispersion of the active region. The chromatic dispersion has been estimated with 30fs/mm/nm around the band gap wavelength for typical SOA waveguide structures.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Doktorarbeit befasst sich mit den physikalischen Eigenschaften von sehr langen Halbleiterlaserverstärkern (UL-SOAs) und ihren Anwendungsmöglichkeiten in der optischen Nachrichtentechnik. Am Anfang der Arbeit werden die analytischen Grundlagen für die optischen Eigenschaften von UL-SOAs vorgestellt. Anhand dieser theoretischen Beschreibung wird ein numerisches Simulationsmodell hergeleitet, mit dem die Untersuchungen in dieser Arbeit durchgeführt werden. Damit das Simulationsmodell realitätsnahe Ergebnisse liefert, werden wichtige Eigenschaften von UL-SOAs berücksichtigt, zu denen unteranderen die überwiegende Sättigung des Bauteils zählt. In diesem gesättigten Teil des UL-SOAs, dominieren schnelle Intraband Effekte gegenüber den langsamen Interband Effekten. In Anwendungen mit UL-SOAs sollen von diese schnellen Intraband Effekte profitiert werden. Aufgrund der kurzen Relaxationszeiten können die schnellen Intraband Effekte für sehr schnelle rein-optische Signalverarbeitung genutzt werden (&gt;20GBaud). Mit einem zusätzlich zu dem Datensignal in den UL-SOA eingestrahlten Dauerstrich (CW)-Signal, konnte die Machbarkeit für rein-optisch Signalverarbeitung mit 100Gbit/s OOK RZ-50% pseudo Zufallsbitsequenzen gezeigt werden. Wenn ein optimierter UL-SOA im passenden Arbeitspunkt betrieben wird, sind Störungen durch Bitmustereffekte im Vergleich zum Rauschen vernachlässigbar. Das Nichtvorhandensein von Bitmustereffekten kann auf das zusätzliche CW-Signal zurückgeführt werden, dass als Fixierungssignal wirkt. Des Weiteren besteht die Möglichkeit die Extinktion des Datensignals zu verbessern, wenn das CW-Signal parallel zum Datensignal polarisiert ist und das Datensignal auf der kürzeren Wellenlänge des CW-Signals liegt. Diese und andere Betriebsparameter weisen darauf hin, dass parametrische Verstärkung aufgrund von Vierwellenmischung (FWM) (Bogatov-ähnlicher Effekt) die Ursache für die Extinktionsverbesserung ist. Mit dem zusätzlichen CW-Signal besteht auch die Möglichkeit rein-optische Wellenlängenumsätzung (AOWC) zu betreiben, was mit der Extinktionsverbesserung zu hochgeschwindig-keits-AOWC mit Extinktionsverbesserung kombiniert werden kann. Nummerisch konnte eine Extinktionsverbesserung von 7dB erzielt werden, während das Signal über 4nm zu einer kürzeren Wellenlänge umgesetzt wurde. Eine andere besondere Eigenschaft von UL-SOAs sind die exzellenten FWM-Effizienzen, die ebenfalls auf die schnellen Intraband Effekte des gesättigten Bereichs zurückgeführt werden können. Daher besteht eine mögliche Anwendung von UL-SOAs in der Erzeugung von kurzen Pulsen wenn zwei phasengelockte CW-Laser ihr Licht in den UL-SOA einstrahlen. Wenn die CW-Laserquellen abstimmbar sind, können die erzeugten Pulse am Ausgang des UL-SOAs in der Wiederholfrequenz und der Trägerfrequenz auch abgestimmt werden. Simulationen zeigten eine starke Abhängigkeit der Pulsweite von dem Modenabstand der CW-Signale. Mit zunehmendem Modenabstand erhöht sich die Wiederholfrequenz der Pulse und die Pulsweite nimmt ab. Für eine Wiederholfrequenz von 20GHz konnten Pulse mit einer Pulsbreite von kleiner 2ps erzeugt werden. Im Rahmen der Ausbreitung kurzer Pulse ist auch der Einfluss von chromatischer Dispersion abgeschätzt worden. Im Vergleich zur Wellenleiterdispersion dominiert die effektive Materialdispersion (CMD) die chromatische Dispersion in SOAs in einem Wellenlängenbereich von 400nm um die Bandkantenwellenlänge. Die CMD wiederum wird von der Materialdispersion der aktiven Schicht dominiert. In dieser Arbeit wurde ein Wert von 30fs/mm/nm für die chromatische Dispersion im Bereich der Bandkantenwellenlänge ermittelt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-11-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28386</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-28386</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2697/runge_patrick.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
