<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:56:00Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2526">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:2526</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:620</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">On the Multiscale, Mechanical Behaviors of Mineralized Bone</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Über Multiscale, mechanisches Verhalten des mineralisierten Knochens</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Seto, Jong</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:620</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Nature has fashioned mineralized tissues into every imaginable morphology—possessing abilities that allow either for tremendous toughness, extreme extensibility, or superior strength— enabling organisms use of these devices to endure in ever-changing environments. The origins of these extraordinary properties in these materials are an outcome of the composition and organization of constituent elements into an integrated, functional tissue. The prevailing theme of this work is to delineate these structure-function relationships across multiple length-scales in mineralized tissues, specifically in the hierarchically structured bone. Through use of in situ micro-mechanical characterization coupled with X-ray scattering and diffraction techniques, processes that occur during mechanical deformation, from the molecular scale to the tissue level, are investigated in bone. The material bone is a biological composite structured in a hierarchical manner to provide ever so distinct materials properties at every length-scale. In its arrangement, weak elements are shielded from high loads by organizing weak elements within stronger elements. Bone compartmentalizes weak components of the material such that mechanical loads are distributed disproportionately throughout the tissue, enabling stronger elements to assume more mechanical stress than its weaker counterparts. Specifically, the distribution of stress from the tissue to the mineral platelets is found in this work to be highly dependent on the various hierarchical structuring schemes employed at these different length-scales. A vital component of this hierarchical structuring is the inclusion of oriented, weak interfaces at every length-scale, serving to increase the amount of compliance between the hard and soft elements. The orientation of these weak interfaces is crucial in regulating excess strains especially at the micro-scale, where weak interfaces contribute to large degrees of mechanical anisotropy found in the elastic modulus and strength. These design schemes enable bone to minimize tissue density while retaining its characteristic materials properties. In utilizing genetically modified mice models, localized dysfunction are introduced and studied to determine the mechanisms in which skeletal disease affects the normal strengthening schemes in bone. In investigating the micro- and the nano- structural properties of these genetically modified samples, the mineral, cellular components, or organic matrix are probed and comparatively studied with non-diseased analogs. Specifically, this work examines Schnurri (Shn3), Neurofibromatosis-1 (NF1), and α-HS glycoprotein (Ahsg) mice models—models that have disrupted mineralization phenotypes. By investigating the structural properties of murine bone under conditions of disease, the mechanisms of degeneration in bone can be elucidated. Bone is a complex tissue—undergoing growth and development as well as maintaining homeostasis in an environment that is constantly under mechanical loading. Whether it is in tension or compression, Nature has developed strategies to distribute excess mechanical stress to the diverse structures that are found throughout the hierarchical structured tissue, from the level of the tissue- to the nano- scales. By elucidating these mechanisms that prevent catastrophic material failure in bone tissue, insights into the structural origins of properties in the material bone like strength and toughness can be revealed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Natur bildet eine Reihe von mineralisierten Geweben mit verschiedenster Morphologie. Diese Materialien weisen eine enorme Zähigkeit, große Dehnbarkeit oder große Festigkeit auf und behalten diese auch bei veränderlichen Umgebungsbedingungen. Diese außergewöhnlichen Eigenschaften sind ein Ergebnis der Zusammensetzung und der Organisation von Elementen in ein einheitliches, funktionelles Gewebe. Das Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, Beziehungen von Struktur und Funktion über mehrere Längenskalen in mineralisierten Geweben -speziell im hierarchisch aufgebauten Knochenaufzeigen. Durch Kombination von Röntgenstreuung mit mikromechanischen in-situ Charakterisierungsmethoden werden Prozesse untersucht, die während der mechanischen Deformation im Knochen ablaufen. Knochen ist ein hierarchisch strukturierter, biologischer Verbundwerkstoff, der verschiedene Materialeigenschaften auf unterschiedlichen Längenskalen aufweist. Durch die spezielle Anordnung von Elementen mit geringerer und hoher Festigkeit, können weichere Elemente gegenüber hohen Lasten abgeschirmt werden. Diese Anordnung ermöglicht es, mechanische Lasten ungleichmäßig im Gewebe zu verteilen, d.h. festere Elemente nehmen eine höhere mechanische Belastung auf als die weniger festen Elemente. Besonders die Lastübertragung von der organischen Matrix auf die Mineralplättchen ist stark von den verschiedenen Charakteristiken der hierarchischen Strukturierung abhängig. Ein grundlegender Bestandteil dieser hierarchischen Strukturierung sind orientierte, schwache Schnittstellen auf jeder Stufe der Längenskala, die die Nachgiebigkeit zwischen den harten und weichen Elementen vergrößern. In der Arbeit konnte gezeigt werden, dass die Orientierung dieser schwachen Schnittstellen bei der Regulierung von Überbeanspruchungen insbesondere auf der Mikroskala entscheidend ist. Dort tragen diese schwachen Schnittstellen zu großer mechanischer Anisotropie bei, die im Elastizitätsmodul und der Kraft repräsentiert ist. Ein andere Untersuchung zeigt, dass sich bei makroskopischer Deformation die jeweiligen Dehnungswerte nacheinander in Richtung kleinerer Längenskalen im Knochen (Gewebe → organische Matrix → Mineralplättchen) vermindern. Dieses Designprinzip ermöglicht Knochen die Gewebedichte zu minimieren während die charakteristischen Materialeigenschaften unverändert bleiben. In dieser Arbeit werden auch genetisch veränderte Maus-Modelle mit Funktionsstörungen untersucht um die Mechanismen der Mineralisierung und die Ausbildung der Knochenfestigkeit bei Skelett-Krankheiten zu verstehen. Es werden die Mikro- und Nano- Strukturen dieser genetisch veränderten Proben untersucht, wobei die Mineral- und Zellbestandteile sowie die organische Matrix mit gesunden Referenzproben verglichen werden. In der vorliegenden Arbeit werden Schnurri (Shn3), Neurofibromatosis-1 (NF1), und α-HS Glycoprotein (Ahsg) Maus-Modelle untersucht, bei denen der Prozess der Mineralisation gestört ist. Auf der Materialebene zeigen sich keine signifikanten Unterschiede in den Eigenschaften, was zum Schluss führt dass diese Mechanismen der Mineralisierung und die Ausbildung der Knochenfestigkeit sehr komplex sind. Knochen ist ein komplexes Gewebe, unterliegt ständigem Wachstum und muss die Mineralhomöostase in einer Umgebung aufrecht erhalten, die sich unter dauerhafter mechanischer Belastung befindet. Die Natur hat Strategien entwickelt, um mechanische Überbelastung auf verschiedenen Sub-Strukturen zu verteilen, die überall im hierarchisch strukturierten Gewebe wiedergefunden werden können. Durch ein besseres Verständnis dieses Prinzips kann aufgeklärt werden, in welchen Strukturelementen die Ursprünge für die vielseitigen Knocheneigenschaften liegen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2010-05-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2526</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-26599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/2526/seto_jong.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights> CC BY-NC-SA: Creative Commons-Lizenz: Namensnennung, nicht kommerziell, Weitergabe zu gleichen Bedingungen</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
