<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T06:46:42Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:567">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:567</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-07-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:600</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Waldzustandserfassung und -monitoring mit hochauflösenden Satellitenbilddaten</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Forest mapping and monitoring using high-resolution satellite data</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Coenradie, Bodo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:600</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Die Forstwirtschaft ist traditionell eines der wichtigsten Anwendungsgebiete der Fernerkundung. Im Gegensatz zur operationellen Nutzung analoger Luftbilder bleibt jedoch im mitteleuropäischen Raum der Praxiseinsatz von Satellitenfernerkundung hinter den technischen Möglichkeiten zurück. Es gilt, die Lücke zwischen Technologieentwicklung und praktischer Anwendung (Praxisreife) weiter zu schließen. Die Eigenschaften moderner Sensoren wecken zudem Hoffnungen, Satellitenbilddaten bald auch zur Informationsgewinnung für großmaßstäbige Planungsebenen zu nutzen (v.a. Forsteinrichtung, 1 : 10 000). In dieser Arbeit werden planungsrelevante Anwendungsmöglichkeiten sowie (gegenwärtige) Grenzen der Satellitenfernerkundung für forstliche Zwecke aufgezeigt. Im Mittelpunkt stehen die Anforderungen des Nutzers. Es werden kommerzielle Softwareprodukte, Standardverfahren sowie Daten operationeller Aufnahmesysteme hoher und mittlerer Auflösung genutzt. Zur besseren Nutzbarmachung von fernerkundeten Informationen wird ein fernerkundungs- und planungsrelevanter Systematisierungsansatz für forstliche Objektarten vorgeschlagen, der eine disziplinübergreifende und dabei weitgehend sensorunabhängige Lösung darstellt. Um praktikable und effiziente Lösungen für große Teile des Auswertungsprozesses zu erreichen, wird die wechselseitige Nutzung von Fachplanungs-, Geo- und Fernerkundungsdaten angestrebt. Als besonders vielversprechend, sowohl für die visuelle Interpretation als auch für die digitale Bildanalyse, erweist sich die Kombination von räumlich hochauflösenden panchromatischen und spektral hochauflösenden multispektralen Satellitenbilddaten. Hochaufgelöste Bildprodukte fusionierter Daten erweisen sich für den praktischen Einsatz als sehr hilfreich, da waldstrukturelle Informationen in einer hohen Detailerkennbarkeit abgebildet werden. Anwendungsbeispiele unterstreichen das große Nutzungspotenzial hochauflösender Satellitenbilder für Inventur- und Monitoringaufgaben, die zukünftig unter Kosten-Nutzen-Aspekten eine Alternative zu Luftbildern darstellen können. Mit einem multisensoralen Auswertungskonzept (u.a. Segmentierung panchromatischer Szenen, pixelbasierte Klassifizierung von Multispektraldaten) wird eine im Vergleich zu herkömmlichen Klassifizierungen deutlich verbesserte Differenzierung (Baumart, Wuchs-, Dichteklasse usw.) erzielt. Der Ansatz zielt auf eine möglichst uneingeschränkte Auswahlmöglichkeit von optischen Satellitensensoren hoher und mittlerer Auflösung ab. Die multispektrale Waldschadenskartierung (Fichte) basiert auf der Erfassung der Schadmerkmale Nadelverlust und Beschirmungsgrad. Eine zuverlässige Kartierung wird für letzteren erreicht. Das Nutzungspotenzial der Satellitenfernerkundung wird vor allem bei der Abgrenzung von größeren Schadregionen und dem Monitoring gesehen. Zur Erfassung von Veränderungen wird ein automatisiertes multitemporales Verfahren vorgestellt, das speziell für Waldgebiete ausgelegt ist und eine rasche großräumige Kartierung von Verdachtsflächen ermöglicht.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Forestry is traditionally regarded as one of the most promising fields of application of remote sensing. In contrast to aerial photography, however, which is already operational, the practical usage of satellite remote sensing in forestry is a long way behind in the development of its technical capabilities. This is particularly true for forest inventories to be carried out in European regions. The aim is therefore to better transfer new technical developments in the field of sensor technology into the operational use of satellite remote sensing. The characteristics of new sensor types justify the hope that in the nearest future satellite remote sensing will serve as an operational tool for the assessment of high-scale information for use in manifold forestry planning purposes (e.g. forest management maps, 1 : 10 000). The task of the thesis was on the one hand to demonstrate to what extent satellite remote sensing can support planning tasks in forestry. On the other hand, current limitations of remote sensing based methods are demonstrated and discussed. Distinct emphasis is laid on the analysis of user requirements. Commercial software products, standard procedures, high- and medium-resolution data from operational sensor systems were used in the study. The processing chain developed makes use of the complementary information of forest management data, GIS data and remote sensing data in order to obtain practicable and effective solutions. In order to make better use of remote sensing data, an interdisciplinary approach for systematisation of forestal object-classes was set up which can be applied to different sensor types. The investigation has shown that the combined use of panchromatic data with its high spatial resolution and multi-spectral data with its high spectral resolution is particularly promising. This is true both for the visual interpretation and the digital classification of the satellite remote sensing data. Thus high-resolution image products derived from the fusion of panchromatic and multi-spectral data have been shown to be very powerful for practical applications, since detailed information on forest structures can be easily recognised. Forest managers can use these image products as a cost-effective, comprehensive planning tool and can integrate them into their current GIS work. Manifold application examples underline the enormous potential of high-resolution satellite data for inventory and monitoring purposes, which can thus be regarded as a thoroughly viable alternative to methods based on aerial photography in terms of cost/benefit. The application of a multi-sensor interpretation concept (segmentation of panchromatic images, pixel-based classification of multi-spectral images, rule-based postclassification) results in a significant improvement in the classification of forest parameters such as tree age, stage of development or density classes, in comparison to conventional classification concepts. The method developed aims at maximum flexibility in the selection of different high and medium-resolution satellite remote sensing data. In addition to this, a method for the classification of forest damage based on multi-spectral data was developed allowing the determination of needle loss and degradation of spruce forests. Verification of the classification results by means of terrestrially selected reference areas has shown that the different deforestation stages can be classified precisely on the basis of satellite remote sensing data. The classification of needle symptoms, however, has turned out to be far more difficult. The potential of satellite remote sensing can thus be seen in particular for the classification of the forest condition on a small scale and for the monitoring of changes in forests in general. An automated procedure based on multi-temporal data is introduced for the detection of changes, which is especially adapted to forest areas and allows a rapid large-area assessment of potential plots of changes.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2003-11-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/567</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-5627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus-5627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/567/coenradie_bodo.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. für Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
