<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/oai2.xsl"?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2014-10-15T07:01:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" identifier="oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3936">http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/oai</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:kobv.de-opus4-tuberlin:3936</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-08-08</datestamp>
        <setSpec>doc-type:doctoralthesis</setSpec>
        <setSpec>bibliography:false</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>ddc:610</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="eng">Analysis of the derivation phase  of human adipose tissue-derived  multipotent mesenchymal stromal cells</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="deu">Analyse der Derivationsphase humaner Fettgewebe-abgeleiteter multipotenter mesenchymaler Stromazellen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Braun, Julian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ddc:610</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="eng">Mesenchymal stromal cells (MSC) are characterized in vitro by plastic-adherent proliferation, a specific immunophenotype and multipotency. The in vivo cell types giving rise to MSC, referred to as MSC progenitors, have been recently described as perivascular cells. However, further characterization of these MSC progenitors is necessary and it remains to be elucidated whether the in vitro characteristics of MSC are intrinsic to MSC progenitors in vivo or are acquired upon in vitro culture. We addressed this question by analyzing morphology, proliferation, immunophenotype and transcriptome of human MSC progenitors during the early in vitro culture phase, the ‚ÄúMSC derivation phase‚Ä?. &#13;
To identify potential human adipose tissue-derived MSC (AT-MSC) progenitors, stromal vascular cell subsets were characterized by multi-parametric flow cytometry using diverse MSC progenitor markers, such as CD34, CD105, CD146 and CD271. Further, MSC progenitor subsets were monitored during early culture in tight kinetic analyses to determine changes in morphology, proliferation, and immunophenotype. We identified two AT-MSC progenitor subsets: CD34+CD146-CD271+/- adventitial stromal cells (AdSC) and CD34-CD146+CD271+/- pericytes (PC). During early in vitro culture, AdSC exhibited high proliferative capacity, also under MSC culture conditions, whereas proliferation of PC was restricted to endothelial culture conditions. The kinetic analysis revealed that MSC progenitors became fibroblastoid as early as day 4 and upregulated CD105, CD146 and CD271. Accompanying this phenotypic transition, AdSC commenced proliferation and downregulated CD34. &#13;
Comparing transcriptomes of ex vivo sorted and 14-days-cultured AdSC by microarray and Gene Set Enrichment Analysis revealed that ex vivo AdSC were quiescent and that activation was induced in vitro probably by early inflammatory responses triggered by cell isolation and  that proliferation was regulated by PDGF and FGF signaling and, most importantly, inhibition of WNT signaling by Dickkopf-1. &#13;
In this study, we provide the first detailed analyses of early culture-mediated changes in the properties of human MSC progenitors. Comparing AdSC and PC during early in vitro culture demonstrated not only that MSC derivation from different progenitor subsets is culture-dependent, but also that AdSC are the most clonogenic AT-MSC progenitors. Moreover, we identified a highly reproducible sequence of phenotypic changes during the MSC derivation process which is associated with inflammation-induced activation and proliferation and is necessary for AdSC to acquire the typical MSC phenotype. </dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="deu">Mesenchymale Stromazellen (MSC) sind in vitro gekennzeichnet durch plastik-adh√§rente Proliferation, einen spezifischen Immunph√§notyp und Multipotenz. Die in vivo Zelltypen, die zu MSC werden (MSC-Vorl√§ufer), wurden k√ºrzlich als perivaskul√§re Zellen beschrieben. Allerdings m√ºssen diese MSC-Vorl√§ufer besser charakterisiert und gekl√§rt werden, ob die MSC-Vorl√§ufer bereits in vivo die in vitro-Eigenschaften von MSC aufweisen, oder diese erst w√§hrend der in vitro Kultur annehmen. Um diese Frage zu beantworten, haben wir Morphologie, Proliferation und Immunph√§notyp sowie Trankriptom von humanen MSC-Vorl√§ufern w√§hrend der fr√ºhen in-vitro-Kultur Phase, der "MSC-Ableitungsphase" analysiert.&#13;
Potenzielle human MSC-Vorl√§ufer aus dem Fettgewebe (AT-MSC) wurden mittels multi-parametrischer Durchflusszytometrie charakterisiert, unter Verwendung diverser MSC-Vorl√§ufer-Marker, z.B. CD34, CD105, CD146 und CD271. Die MSC-Vorl√§ufer wurden in engen Kinetiken w√§hrend der fr√ºhen Kultur √ºberwacht. Zwei AT-MSC-Vorl√§ufertypen wurden identifiziert: CD34+ CD146- CD271+/- adventitielle Stromazellen (AdSC) und CD34- CD146+ CD271+/- Perizyten (PC). AdSC proliferierten schneller, auch unter MSC-Kulturbedingungen, w√§hrend die ex-vivo-Expansion von PC auf Endothelzell-typische Kulturbedingungen beschr√§nkt war. Am Tag 4 der fr√ºhen In-vitro-Kultur wurden MSC-Vorl√§ufer fibroblastoid und regulierten CD105, CD146 und CD271 hoch. Gleichzeitig begannen die AdSC zu proliferieren und CD34 herunterzuregulieren.&#13;
Der Vergleich der Transkriptome von ex vivo sortierten und 14-Tage-kultivierten AdSC mittels Microarray und ‚ÄûGene Set Enrichment Analysis‚Äú ergab, dass ex vivo AdSC quieszent waren, und dass die Aktivierung in vitro wahrscheinlich durch fr√ºhe Entz√ºndungsreaktionen, ausgel√∂st durch Zellisolation, induziert und durch PDGF und FGF-Signale und, vorallem durch Dickkopf-1-vermittelte Hemmung des Wnt-Signalwegs reguliert wurden.&#13;
Diese Studie stellt die erste detaillierte Analyse der Ver√§nderungen in den Eigenschaften der MSC-Vorl√§ufer w√§hrend der fr√ºhen Kultur dar. Der Vergleich von AdSC und PC ergab nicht nur, dass MSC-Ableitung aus unterschiedlichen Vorl√§ufern kulturabh√§ngig ist, sondern auch, dass AdSC die klonogensten AT-MSC-Vorl√§ufer sind. Desweiteren haben wir eine reproduzierbare Abfolge ph√§notypischer Ver√§nderungen w√§hrend des MSC-Ableitungsprozesses entdeckt, die mit inflammationsbedingter Aktivierung und Proliferation korreliert und f√ºr den Erwerb des MSC-typischen Ph√§notyps durch AdSC essentiell ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2013-07-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:doctoralthesis</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/frontdoor/index/index/docId/3936</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-39365</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn/resolver.pl?urn:nbn:de:kobv:83-opus4-39365</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-tuberlin/files/3936/Braun_Julian.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Deutsches Urheberrecht mit Print on Demand (u.a. f√ºr Dissertationen empfohlen)</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
